<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">F1000Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">F1000Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">F1000Research</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>F1000Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2046-1402</issn><publisher><publisher-name>F1000Research</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5325067</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28299201</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12688/f1000research.10416.1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Articles</subject><subj-group><subject>Epidemiology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Global Health</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Tropical &#x00026; Travel-Associated Diseases</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Viral Infections (without HIV)</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Virology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Lyssaviruses and rabies: current conundrums, concerns, contradictions and controversies</article-title><fn-group content-type="pub-status"><fn><p>[version 1; referees: 2 approved]</p></fn></fn-group></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rupprecht</surname><given-names>Charles</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kuzmin</surname><given-names>Ivan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Meslin</surname><given-names>Francois</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="a1">
<label>1</label>Wistar Institute, Philadelphia, PA, 19104, USA</aff><aff id="a2">
<label>2</label>University of Texas Medical Branch at Galveston, Galveston, TX, 77555, USA</aff><aff id="a3">
<label>3</label>DVM, former Team Leader, Neglected Zoonotic Diseases, WHO Headquarters, Geneva, Switzerland</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>a</label><email xlink:href="mailto:charleserupprechtii@gmail.com">charleserupprechtii@gmail.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>All authors were involved in the writing of the manuscript and agreed to the final content.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>
<bold>Competing interests: </bold>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>2</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>184</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>2</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; 2017 Rupprecht C et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Licence, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="f1000research-6-11223.pdf"/><abstract><p>Lyssaviruses are bullet-shaped, single-stranded, negative-sense RNA viruses and the causative agents of the ancient zoonosis rabies. Africa is the likely home to the ancestors of taxa residing within the Genus
<italic>Lyssavirus</italic>, Family
<italic>Rhabdoviridae</italic>. Diverse lyssaviruses are envisioned as co-evolving with bats, as the ultimate reservoirs, over seemingly millions of years. In terms of relative distribution, overt abundance, and resulting progeny, rabies virus is the most successful lyssavirus species today, but for unknown reasons. All mammals are believed to be susceptible to rabies virus infection. Besides reservoirs among the Chiroptera, meso-carnivores also serve as major historical hosts and are represented among the canids, raccoons, skunks, mongooses, and ferret badgers. &#x000a0;Perpetuating as a disease of nature with the mammalian central nervous system as niche, host breadth alone precludes any candidacy for true eradication. Despite having the highest case fatality of any infectious disease and a burden in excess of or comparative to other major zoonoses, rabies remains neglected. Once illness appears, no treatment is proven to prevent death. Paradoxically, vaccines were developed more than a century ago, but the clear majority of human cases are unvaccinated. Tens of millions of people are exposed to suspect rabid animals and tens of thousands succumb annually, primarily children in developing countries, where canine rabies is enzootic. Rather than culling animal populations, one of the most cost-effective strategies to curbing human fatalities is the mass vaccination of dogs. Building on considerable progress to date, several complementary actions are needed in the near future, including a more harmonized approach to viral taxonomy, enhanced de-centralized laboratory-based surveillance, focal pathogen discovery and characterization, applied pathobiological research for therapeutics, improved estimates of canine populations at risk, actual production of required vaccines and related biologics, strategies to maximize prevention but minimize unnecessary human prophylaxis, and a long-term, realistic plan for sustained global program support to achieve success in disease control, prevention, and elimination.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>lyssaviruses</kwd><kwd>rabies</kwd><kwd>rabies vaccine</kwd><kwd>zoonoses</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declared that no grants were involved in supporting this work.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta><notes><sec sec-type="editor-note"><title>Editorial Note on the Review Process</title><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://f1000research.com/browse/f1000-faculty-reviews">F1000 Faculty Reviews</ext-link> are commissioned from members of the prestigious
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://f1000.com/prime/thefaculty">F1000 Faculty</ext-link> and are edited as a service to readers. In order to make these reviews as comprehensive and accessible as possible, the referees provide input before publication and only the final, revised version is published. The referees who approved the final version are listed with their names and affiliations but without their reports on earlier versions (any comments will already have been addressed in the published version).</p><p>The referees who approved this article are: </p><list list-type="simple" list-content="reviewer-list"><list-item><p>
<named-content content-type="reviewer-name">James Childs</named-content>, Yale School of Public Health, New Haven, CT, USA
<fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>No competing interests were disclosed.</p></fn>
</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<named-content content-type="reviewer-name">Nicholas Johnson</named-content>, Animal and Plant Health Agency, Surrey, Surrey, UK
<fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>No competing interests were disclosed.</p></fn>
</p></list-item></list></sec></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Rabies is not a simple long-ago vestige, nightmarish myth, or literary allegory but rather a significant viral encephalitis with the highest case fatality of any conventional infectious disease. Who else, besides those afflicted and affected, should care about rabies today? Legions&#x02014;including the true animal lover, anthropologist, administrator, caver, educator, environmentalist, farmer, medical professional, traveler, health economist, hiker, historian, humanist, industrialist, legislator, modeler, philanthropist, sociologist, student, conservation biologist, and life scientist, to name a few by vocation or avocation&#x02014;curious for elevated self and situational awareness, caring for the common good, intrigued by this view of life from an applied microbiological and ecological perspective or challenged by the allure for professional intervention in nature, represented by the less-than-apparent &#x0201c;
<italic>non</italic>-low-hanging fruit&#x0201d;.</p><p>To simplify the infectious cycle of rabies, exposure is direct, not by environmental deposition, but rather individual-to-individual intra- and inter-specific transmission, usually occurring via bite. Millions of highly neurotropic virions are excreted intermittently in the saliva of a rabid host, days to weeks before overt morbidity and eventual demise, entering the peripheral nervous system of a bite recipient.
<italic>In vivo</italic>, from local depots and centripetal transit in the axoplasm, primary replication occurs within neurons of the central nervous system (CNS). Thereafter, centrifugal passage occurs from the CNS to a number of highly innervated sites, including the salivary glands. Oral, mucosal, or transdermal delivery of virions occurs by normal daily mammalian interactions. Failing these routine modus operandi pathways, altered unusual behaviors offer a variety of options for secondary contacts. These may range from mania to paresis and paralysis, with deliberate transmission options of agonistic encounters and biting, increased movement outside of normal home range/territories, or acute death, with predation by others upon virion-laden tissues and organs of the affected host. If a productive infection ensues, the entry-reproduction-exit cycle is poised to begin anew after initiation, taking days, weeks, months, or (rarely) years of incubation before excretion or obvious clinical manifestation. Such obligate, parasitic virions ensure elegant self-transfer by exploitation of the normal through to the bizarre. Relatively distant viral familial relatives hail among invertebrates and plants, but warm-blooded vertebrates are the rabies-prone hosts. Although these agents predated
<italic>Homo sapiens</italic>, their current distribution, abundance, and diversity likely exceed pre-historic comparisons, especially mediated during the Anthropocene period.</p><p>Among warm-blooded vertebrates, birds are susceptible to infection, but rabies predominates naturally among various mammalian populations. Within the Mammalia, a virtual alphabet soup of cases has been recorded, from the armadillo to the zebra. Rabies is a significant disease of domestic and wild mammals alike, yet its zoonotic aspect is the cause of major historical infamy. Few and privileged were the civilizations that did not describe the ravages of an entity akin to rabies, such that this infection has impacted art, literature, and cultural practices for millennia. By one small measure, during the time taken by a typical reader to peruse this article, more than 1,300 people will have been exposed to rabies virus (RABV). Annually, tens of thousands of persons will succumb, the majority children. Most are poor, have no access to modern medical care, and will die unreported, frequently at home in a rural village. If among other scales&#x02014;on the basis of disability-adjusted life-year scores or health economic measures&#x02014;rabies ranks within the top-ten list of neglected viral zoonoses, one would anticipate that the degree of philanthropic input would be roughly equivalent among such pathogens. Unfortunately, such is not the case. For example, several other neglected viral diseases may have a somewhat smaller presumed impact yet receive far greater attention for international support (
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Not rooted entirely in science, a more holistic transdisciplinary philosophy assists in a better partial understanding of why such biomedical disparities persist between need and assistance, provoking a bootstraps approach in the field out of frustrated necessity in the face of apparent contradictions.</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Table 1. </label><caption><title>Comparison of associated health parameters of two vector-borne diseases and human rabies transmitted by dogs
<sup><xref ref-type="other" rid="note-1">a</xref></sup>.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" content-type="article-table"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yellow fever</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japanese encephalitis</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rabies</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disease</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild to acute viral hemorrhagic
<break/>syndrome</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild to severe viral encephalitis</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acute progressive viral encephalitis</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Etiology</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flavivirus</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flavivirus</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lyssavirus</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distribution</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Endemic in tropics of about
<break/>34 African and about 13 Latin
<break/>American countries</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Endemic in about 24 Southeast
<break/>Asian and Western Pacific
<break/>countries</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Endemic within about 150 developing
<break/>countries in the Americas, Africa, and
<break/>Asia</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transmission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mosquito</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mosquito</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dog bite</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case fatality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">About 20&#x02013;50% in severe cases</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">About 30%</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;99.9%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Burden</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">About 84,000&#x02013;170,000 severe
<break/>cases</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">About 68,000 cases</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;15 million exposures annually</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annual fatalities</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">About 29,000&#x02013;60,000 estimated
<break/>deaths in Africa alone</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">About 13,600&#x02013;20,400 estimated
<break/>deaths</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">About 25,000&#x02013;159,000 estimated
<break/>deaths</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epidemiological
<break/>occurrence</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sylvatic cycle and urban
<break/>outbreaks</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major outbreaks about 2&#x02013;15 years,
<break/>intensified during the rainy season</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primarily individual human cases in
<break/>rural, underserved areas</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vaccination</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">One dose may be effective, with
<break/>long-term to lifelong immunity in
<break/>about 99% of people</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary and booster doses for
<break/>childhood Expanded Programme
<break/>on Immunization incorporation</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Currently, requires three or more doses
<break/>in pre- or post-exposure vaccination</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Supportive care only</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Supportive care only</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No specific treatment, comfort care
<break/>only before death</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospect for elimination</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vaccination protects humans at
<break/>risk, but Yellow fever cannot be
<break/>eliminated in nature.</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vaccination protects humans at
<break/>risk, but Japanese encephalitis is
<break/>not a candidate for elimination.</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human rabies can be prevented by
<break/>vaccination and canine rabies can be
<break/>eliminated by mass dog vaccination.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Global Alliance
<break/>for Vaccines and
<break/>Immunization (GAVI)
<break/>support (by 2015)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;$264 million USD</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">About $105 million USD forecast for
<break/>2015&#x02013;2020</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">$0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="note-1"><p>
<sup>a</sup>World Health Organization (
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/mediacentre/en/">http://www.who.int/mediacentre/en/</ext-link>).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In light of meaningful global action for the public good, at what level should one come to terms with rabies in the 21st century? Management, control, prevention, elimination, eradication, and so on are often freely bandied about together in today&#x02019;s lexicon of disease deliberations but are not synonymous terms. Unlike smallpox or rinderpest, rabies is not a candidate for actual eradication today, given the extent of host breadth and diversity. However, rabies has at least three major attributes in common with those other two extinct viral pathogens: validated diagnostic protocols, safe and effective vaccines, and the epidemiological insight to apply those laboratory tools and licensed biologics for sound prevention and control practices. Somewhat paradoxically, based upon a century of experience, modern rabies management accomplishes, in a truly One Health capacity, what no other comparable zoonosis program can achieve in tandem: human cases prevented by avoiding defined exposure and seeking prophylaxis after exposure; primary canine and secondary species infections eliminated, by mass immunization; and significantly, wild carnivore viral perpetuation interrupted via oral vaccination efforts on a landscape scale. Building upon such apparent progress, this review aims to provoke renewed discussions on several of the current issues and challenges related to modern lyssavirus taxonomy, phylogeny, surveillance, prevention, treatment, control, and elimination, based in part upon the opinions of the authors, representing more than a century of collective person-years of introspective knowledge, skills, and abilities in the field&#x02014;not as an historical aside alone, but rather within the context of evidence from the peer-reviewed literature, focusing upon relevant publications primarily within the past few years
<sup><xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#x02013;
<xref rid="ref-115" ref-type="bibr">115</xref></sup>. Our hope is, in some small manner, to educate, enlighten, engage, and enable others to participate meaningfully in these remaining endeavors, within the realm of a &#x02018;science of conviction&#x02019;.</p></sec><sec><title>An evolving viral taxonomy: what is in a name?</title><p>Taxonomy, a formal attempt at objective, systematic classification and naming of entities in the complex milieu of life on earth, represented by plants, animals, and so on, also extends to the microbiological arena. Both RABV and a group of phylogenetically related viruses (all of which cause the acute progressive encephalomyelitis known as rabies) belong to the genus
<italic>Lyssavirus</italic>, within the family
<italic>Rhabdoviridae</italic> and the order Mononegavirales, the single-stranded, non-segmented, negative-sense RNA viruses. With active surveillance and technical advances offered by next-generation sequencing, the taxonomy of the
<italic>Rhabdoviridae</italic> is developing with increased complexity and new rhabdoviruses are being characterized
<sup><xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>. However, although new lyssaviruses are also being described, the genus forms a well-delineated cluster within the family and does not have any close relationships with other rhabdoviruses.</p><p>Recently, the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses (ICTV) moved toward a partial appropriation of binomial species nomenclature, which exists in other fields of taxonomy. However, the ICTV applied such naming inversely, so the genus name appears after the species name
<sup><xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. An objective rationale for this change is somewhat difficult to fathom unless the ICTV is trying to underline the fact that &#x0201c;real&#x0201d; virions and the concept of viruses and viral species are totally different entities. Although virions are observed by electron microscopy, no one has ever seen a &#x0201c;virus&#x0201d;. Virions are particulate, whereas viruses are conceptual populations of microorganisms, and more so virus species are &#x0201c;polythetic classes&#x0201d; (or fabricated &#x0201c;containers&#x0201d;) in which certain agents are placed artificially on the basis of their genetic, morphological, and physio-chemical properties
<sup><xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>. In other fields of biology, one would use the scientific name of an organism as the synonym for its species, but in virus taxonomy this is not the case. For example, now RABV belongs to the type species of the
<italic>Lyssavirus</italic> genus, termed
<italic>Rabies lyssavirus</italic>. So speaking in general of the virus as an organism, one still uses the former, whereas the latter is employed in a taxonomic context only. Inherited operational difficulties of use&#x02014;for example, RABV (a virus) but
<italic>Rabies lyssavirus</italic> (a species); Mokola virus (a virus) but
<italic>Mokola lyssavirus</italic> (a species) and so on, also noting that virus names, but not species names, can be abbreviated&#x02014;may lead to further changes of this binomial nomenclature in future years
<sup><xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>.</p><p>Other species in the genus include
<italic>Aravan lyssavirus</italic>,
<italic>Australian bat lyssavirus</italic>,
<italic>Bokeloh lyssavirus</italic>,
<italic>Duvenhage lyssavirus</italic>,
<italic>European bat lyssaviruses</italic>,
<italic>type 1</italic> and
<italic>type 2</italic>,
<italic>Ikoma lyssavirus</italic>,
<italic>Irkut lyssavirus</italic>,
<italic>Khujand lyssavirus</italic>,
<italic>Lagos bat lyssavirus</italic>,
<italic>Mokola lyssavirus</italic>,
<italic>Shimoni bat lyssavirus</italic>, and
<italic>West Caucasian bat lyssavirus</italic>
<sup><xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. Two other putative lyssaviruses do not yet have taxonomic status. One is Lleida bat lyssavirus (LLEBV), identified previously by only a partial genome sequence, while isolation attempts continue
<sup><xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>. The other, soon to be submitted to the ICTV for review, is the most recently described Gannoruwa bat lyssavirus
<sup><xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>. Lyssavirus phylogeny is depicted in
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref> (with colors of the branches applicable to
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="f1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1. </label><caption><title>Extant lyssavirus phylogeny.</title><p>Unrooted phylogenetic tree of currently recognized and putative lyssaviruses (neighbor-joining method, p-distances matrix). Lineage colors correspond to the same lyssaviruses depicted in
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref>. ABLV, Australian bay lyssavirus; ARAV, Aravan virus; BBLV, Bokeloh bat lyssavirus; DUVV, Duvenhage virus; EBLV-1, EBLV-2, European bat lyssaviruses, type 1 and 2; GBLV, Gannoruwa bat lyssavirus; IKOV, Ikoma lyssavirus; IRKV, Irkut virus; KHUV, Khujand virus; LBV, Lagos bat virus; LLEBV, Lleida bat lyssavirus; MOKV, Mokola virus; RABV, Rabies virus; SHIBV, Shimoni bat virus; WCBV, West Caucasian bat virus.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="f1000research-6-11223-g0000"/></fig><fig fig-type="figure" id="f2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2. </label><caption><title>Proposed lyssavirus radiations.</title><p>Highly speculative schematic depiction of the ancient spread of proto-lyssaviruses on a proposed map of the continents as they were present during the late Cretaceous period. Solid lines show hypothetical directions of lyssavirus ancestor distribution at that time, and dashed lines show further spread thereafter with additional continental drift. Although the &#x0201c;out of Africa&#x0201d; hypothesis dominates the scheme, this does not discount the potential role of Antarctica in biogeographic dispersal with bat-virus links to both Australia and South America as suggested for other pathogens
<sup><xref rid="ref-93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref></sup>. ABLV, Australian bay lyssavirus; ARAV, Aravan virus; BBLV, Bokeloh bat lyssavirus; DUVV, Duvenhage virus; EBLV-1, EBLV-2, European bat lyssaviruses, type 1 and 2; GBLV, Gannoruwa bat lyssavirus; IKOV, Ikoma lyssavirus; IRKV, Irkut virus; KHUV, Khujand virus; LBV, Lagos bat virus; LLEBV, Lleida bat lyssavirus; MOKV, Mokola virus; RABV, rabies virus; RABV(IA), rabies virus, &#x0201c;indigenous American&#x0201d; lineage; RABV(C), rabies virus, &#x0201c;carnivore&#x0201d; strain (further shifted to other host mammals); SHIBV, Shimoni bat virus; WCBV, West Caucasian bat virus. 
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="f1000research-6-11223-g0001"/></fig><p>Globally, lyssaviruses have been subdivided into two phylogroups on the basis of genetic distances within their G-protein ectodomains and serologic cross-reactivity
<sup><xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>. Phylogroup I includes
<italic>Rabies lyssavirus</italic>,
<italic>Aravan lyssavirus</italic>,
<italic>Australian bat lyssavirus</italic>,
<italic>Bokeloh lyssavirus</italic>,
<italic>Duvenhage lyssavirus</italic>,
<italic>European bat lyssaviruses</italic>,
<italic>type 1</italic> and
<italic>type 2</italic>,
<italic>Irkut lyssavirus</italic>,
<italic>Khujand lyssavirus</italic>, and the new Gannoruwa bat lyssavirus. Phylogroup II includes
<italic>Lagos bat lyssavirus</italic>,
<italic>Mokola lyssavirus</italic>, and
<italic>Shimoni bat lyssavirus</italic>. The remaining
<italic>West Caucasian bat lyssavirus</italic>,
<italic>Ikoma lyssavirus</italic>, and Lleida bat lyssavirus are not included in either phylogroup. Although phylogenetically they do appear related, the amount of genetic divergence and absence of cross-neutralization do not allow placement in a single phylogroup on the basis of existing demarcation criteria
<sup><xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>. Genetic distances between lyssaviruses from different species are significantly shorter than those in other rhabdovirus genera. Therefore, other characters, such as antigenic reactivity patterns with monoclonal antibodies and ecologic properties (including distribution and host range), are used imperfectly for demarcation between the viral species
<sup><xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>. This demarcation is based on expert opinion of a well-qualified taxonomic study group. With increasing ICTV debate toward unification of virus taxonomy based on genetic distances, in the near future there may be a re-classification attempt, in which all phylogroup I viruses are segregated into one species (for example,
<italic>Rabies lyssavirus</italic>?) and all phylogroup II viruses are segregated into another. Of course, such re-classification would miss important characteristics used for species demarcation at present and may have potential socio-economic or bio-political consequences for certain areas. For example, some places where RABV is not thought to circulate, such as in Australia or Western Europe (but where other lyssaviruses are present among bats), might lose their self-defined &#x0201c;rabies-free&#x0201d; status, on the basis of viral taxonomic re-organization, creating greater confusion, with potential public health, veterinary, or economic repercussions, if suddenly recast into the same disease status as Africa, Asia and the New World. Arguably, the term &#x0201c;rabies&#x0201d; appears to garner greater weight and seriousness than the less familiar designation &#x0201c;bat lyssavirus&#x0201d;.</p></sec><sec><title>A conundrum over lyssavirus origins, emergence, perpetuation&#x02014;and extinctions?</title><p>All phylogroup I lyssaviruses circulate in bats. Among these, only RABV is also adapted to perpetuation in carnivores. Within phylogroup II, both Lagos bat virus (LBV) and Shimoni bat virus are bat-borne whereas the reservoir of Mokola virus (MOKV) remains unknown
<sup><xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>. MOKV was isolated on a few occasions from shrews and from spill-over infections to cats and a dog
<sup><xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>. The West Caucasian bat virus (WCBV) was isolated from a bat, and LLEBV genetic material was identified in a bat as well. Ikoma lyssavirus (IKOV) was isolated from an African civet, but phylogenetic relatedness of this virus to WCBV and LLEBV suggests that it might be a spill-over infection, such that IKOV is actually a bat-borne virus as well
<sup><xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>. Enhanced surveillance activities may help to resolve this point.</p><p>The evolutionary history of the lyssaviruses is very poorly understood. Common observations include strong purifying selection and neutral evolution of viral genomes
<sup><xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>&#x02013;
<xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup>. The substitution rates along lyssavirus genomes are similar between viruses from different species and between different viral genes, approximating 3.8 &#x000d7; 10
<sup>&#x02212;5</sup> to 2.1 &#x000d7; 10
<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> substitutions per site per year
<sup><xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
<xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
<xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>. An episodic diversifying selection was suggested in some studies, under a mixed effects model of episodic (MEME) selection. However, such endeavors failed to identify specific amino acid substitutions involved in host shifts with subsequent virus adaptation to a new host species (with increased fitness and fixation of favorable mutations) and as such should be interpreted cautiously
<sup><xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
<xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>. This is not too surprising given that only the current sequences (sampled during the past 30 to 40 years from well-established reservoir species) were available for the analysis whereas the natural history of lyssavirus speciation is set in several orders of magnitude longer.</p><p>Extant lyssaviruses appear well adapted to their reservoir hosts. Comparison of LBV gene sequences sampled in South Africa over the past several decades revealed over 95% genome conservation
<sup><xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>. In another study, the genome of LBV isolated in Kenya was 99% identical to the genome of another LBV isolate obtained in Senegal 22 years earlier
<sup><xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>. Recent host shifts might help to elucidate the mechanisms of lyssavirus evolution but are not common. Spill-over infections usually result in dead-end events
<sup><xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>. An empirical observation from several short-term host shifts of bat RABV to carnivores suggested that S
<sub>242</sub> substitution in the viral G protein might warrant fitness to bat hosts but that A/T
<sub>242</sub> substitution is typical for carnivore-associated RABVs
<sup><xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>. However, no further studies in the development of this hypothesis have been performed.</p><p>Early attempts to create a timescale for the natural history of lyssaviruses on the basis of substitution rates (molecular clocks) suggested that the most recent common ancestor (MRCA) of lyssaviruses existed 7,000 to 11,000 years ago but that the MRCA of the present RABV existed 900 to 1,500 years ago
<sup><xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>. In line with this, the MRCA age of North American bat RABVs was estimated to be 118 to 233 years
<sup><xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> to 220 to 750 years
<sup><xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
<xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>.</p><p>Other studies that used essentially the same approaches and similar or slightly larger datasets extended the MRCA of bat RABVs to 436 to 1,107 years
<sup><xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> or to 500 years for one of the bat-associated RABV lineages
<sup><xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup>. However, an increasing amount of evidence suggests that timescale estimation performed on a limited set of recently sampled sequences cannot provide realistic inferences for viruses evolving under constraints of purifying selection
<sup><xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup>. For example, an alternative approach with improved substitution saturation increased the MRCA of coronaviruses for several orders of magnitude compared with previous molecular clock estimates, and the resulting timescale was comparable to that of the coronavirus reservoir hosts
<sup><xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>. In general, evolutionary rates observed in a set of sequences exhibit time dependency and are increased toward the present because of the transient mutations yet to be removed by purifying selection. Therefore, substitution rates estimated during long time frames will be lower systematically than those obtained during short time frames. This effect is as strong as, or stronger than, purifying selection, which shapes virus evolution
<sup><xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
<xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
<xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup>. In other words, timescale estimations based on substitution rates are useful only for the time frame encompassed by the sampling period but cannot be extrapolated easily for longer periods of time.</p><p>Present distributions, diversity and compartmentalization of lyssaviruses, and the empiric observation of viral genome conservation reveal great contrast to the suggested recent age of their MRCA. If one entertains that the published suggested timescale estimates of lyssaviruses are fallacious, restricted by analysis of limited sets of available isolates, one can use several other lines of evidence to hypothesize their origin and longer-term evolution. All the diversity of lyssaviruses is represented in bats (except for MOKV and IKOV, for which the reservoir hosts are yet to be established definitively), whereas carnivores maintain perpetuation of several lineages of RABV only. As such, it is commonly accepted that bats are the primary evolutionary hosts of lyssaviruses
<sup><xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
<xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
<xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup>. Lyssaviruses of multiple species (with the notable exception of RABV) circulate in Old World bats, but only RABV circulates in New World bats. Furthermore, RABV lineages present in New World bats, along with a few lineages circulating in skunks and raccoons (the so-called &#x0201c;indigenous American&#x0201d; RABV), are paraphyletic to the RABV lineages circulating in carnivores in the Old World and to the &#x0201c;cosmopolitan&#x0201d; canine lineage, which (as believed) was dispersed worldwide with human migrations across the globe
<sup><xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup>. Nevertheless, all RABV lineages are monophyletic when compared with lyssaviruses of other species and demonstrate a greater sequence identity between each other than to lyssaviruses of other species
<sup><xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup>. From this evidence, it is tempting to speculate that an ancient RABV ancestor (already distinct from lyssaviruses of other species) circulated in early bats in the territory of Gondwana, as bats presumably originated in the region of modern Africa
<sup><xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup>. A bat morphologically similar to extant bats,
<italic>Onychonycteris</italic>, lived about 52.5 million years ago
<sup><xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup>. Other related species might have existed earlier. Molecular inferences suggested that the MRCA of present bats existed at least 80 million years ago, potentially pushing bat origins into the Cretaceous period
<sup><xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
<xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup>. Such an ancient chiropteran origin of RABV might explain the existence of the independently evolved &#x0201c;indigenous American&#x0201d; virus lineage and the absence of similar RABVs in related bat species between the Americas and the Old World (for example, in
<italic>Myotis</italic> spp. and
<italic>Eptesicus</italic> spp.). South America and Africa split from each other between 100 and 84 million years ago and were separated by the South Atlantic Ocean. Ancient bats are hypothesized to have spread from Africa to South America slightly later, via island hopping or direct intercontinental flight
<sup><xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup>. Perhaps, at that time, bats were already infected with a progenitor of the &#x0201c;indigenous American&#x0201d; RABV (
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref>). This virus might be well adapted to bat hosts (for example, owing to substitutions such as S
<sub>242</sub> in the viral G protein) and compartmentalized in numerous bat species, such as the indigenous phyllostomatids, across the Americas, with a later host shift to other bat species, skunks, and raccoons. Phylogenetic analysis suggested rapid diversification of bats, with all families having evolved before the late Eocene epoch
<sup><xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup>, and the same might be true for the viruses that co-evolved with their hosts, followed by millions of years characterized by stasis and slow genetic drift under constraints of purifying selection. Possibly, RABV lineages that continued to evolve in the Old World did not obtain such favorable substitutions and could not colonize multiple bat species as in the Americas but rather switched to carnivores as a comparatively recent event. Of course, this hypothesis does not explain the absence of RABV in Old World bats. However, given the less-than-ideal level of surveillance in the Old World tropics, it is possible that bat RABV does exist there but is undiscovered. Considering that four new lyssaviruses were described during the last decade (including Bokeloh bat lyssavirus in Western Europe, where surveillance is quite adequate) and that the most recent of these, Gannoruwa bat lyssavirus, was described in Sri Lanka in 2016 only
<sup><xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>, one should expect further discoveries of lyssaviruses in the Old World. The absence of non-RABV lyssaviruses in the Americas can be explained at least in part by the fact that even at present these viruses have a limited geographic distribution and host ranges compared with RABV. If these characteristics were similar in the past, such viruses might not spread to the territory of the present Americas once Africa and South America drifted further apart (
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref>).</p><p>Alternatively, one can speculate that many viruses (including multiple bat RABVs in the Old World and non-RABV lyssaviruses in the New World) became extinct during the Cretaceous-Paleocene event 65 million years ago which, as estimated, wiped out 75% of all biologic species
<sup><xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup>. As major reservoirs went extinct, so too the viral species adapted to them. Though lacking to date for lyssaviruses, progress in the field of paleovirology and applications to other members of the Mononegavirales support the contention of time scales for some ancient viruses in excess of tens of millions of years in age, co-evolving with their hosts
<sup><xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>Neglect of laboratory-based surveillance systems</title><p>In an applied One Health context, rabies diagnosis is the only routine procedure applied to a suspect animal that will directly determine the need for specific, life-saving medical intervention in a human at risk (
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/rabies/pdf/rabiesdfaspv2.pdf">http://www.cdc.gov/rabies/pdf/rabiesdfaspv2.pdf</ext-link>). Laboratory diagnosis is critical to confirm the status of a suspect case, in part, to justify prophylaxis in exposed persons or animals, to measure objectively the impact of disease prevention programs, and to support certification of a country as free of disease.</p><p>Sensitive, specific, economical, and timely diagnostic tests have been available for more than 50 years, and there has been increasing augmentation by molecular methods for routine rabies diagnosis
<sup><xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
<xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
<xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup>. Yet despite the innumerable rabies cases that occur in wildlife, domestic animals, and humans on a daily basis, only a very small fraction are diagnosed. Few resources are provided, because no cases are diagnosed, owing to a lack of support, producing a cycle of neglect that minimizes the true understanding of disease burden. Those at highest risk are often of lowest priority, such as the poor, the disenfranchised, and the non-agricultural commodities represented by free-ranging wildlife or community dogs.</p><p>Misdiagnosis may result with the presentation of fever and coma in children because of confusion with other diseases, such as cerebral malaria
<sup><xref rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup>. Conversely, in some situations, a history of animal bite may be missing because the patient does not realize that exposure has occurred, such that rabies does not enter the original differential diagnosis of encephalitis
<sup><xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup>. The relationship between exposure and illness may be forgotten, and patient recall may be disconnected because of the lag from the incubation period, which can extend beyond weeks to months or even years
<sup><xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup>. Moreover, the national laboratory may be located centrally in an urban capital, far from case occurrence in rural areas.</p><p>The consequences of neglect are obvious. For example, when juveniles contact rabid puppies, the diagnostic event is missed, the prophylaxis opportunity is gone, and the child dies
<sup><xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup>. If rabies is not suspected in an infected donor, organs may be transplanted from a patient that dies acutely, producing additional fatal cases in the recipients
<sup><xref rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup>. Beyond the individual, at a global level, the frequent lack of inclusion of wildlife in surveillance efforts may mean the difference between a misjudged, rabies-free locality and a newly appreciated enzootic area
<sup><xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup>. Similarly, translocation of a rabid dog from a canine-enzootic area can threaten the status of another area that has eliminated canine RABV circulation, after great cost and years of effort
<sup><xref rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup>. Such reports of importation are not uncommon in the literature, online sources such as ProMED, or communication in the daily news (
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.animals24-7.org/2014/06/08/dog-meat-traffic-still-spreads-rabies-in-vietnam/">http://www.animals24-7.org/2014/06/08/dog-meat-traffic-still-spreads-rabies-in-vietnam/</ext-link>).</p><p>Although it is highly desirable to document the presence of new lyssaviruses during pathogen discovery, the basic surveillance information needed to prevent and control what is already known about RABV and its impact upon public health, agriculture, and conservation biology, using available, practical diagnostic tools, is more important (
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Table 2. </label><caption><title>Problems and options for improved lyssavirus laboratory-based surveillance.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" content-type="article-table"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apparent issues</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proposed resolution</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">References</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Few reported suspect cases</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Improved enhanced or active
<break/>surveillance</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confusion over which test to use
<break/>for primary case confirmation</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Direct fluorescent antibody test
<break/>implementation on central nervous
<break/>system (CNS) tissue (gold standard)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limited budget for fluorescent
<break/>microscopic equipment</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Direct rapid immunohistochemistry
<break/>test</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-95" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biosafety concerns of animal
<break/>CNS removal</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Focus upon brainstem collection</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-96" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Few trained field staff for
<break/>de-centralized surveys</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linear flow assay (LFA) screening
<break/>with confirmatory testing</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-97" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insensitivity of existing LFA tests</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Improved commercial lot release
<break/>and licensing</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-98" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Need for basic virus variant
<break/>identification</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monoclonal antibody typing</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-99" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cultural sensitivity over human
<break/>autopsy performance</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antemortem collection of skin
<break/>biopsy, serum, cerebrospinal fluid
<break/>(CSF), and saliva swabs</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Requirement for rapid, sensitive,
<break/>and specific identification of
<break/>suspect human cases</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Real-time polymerase chain reaction
<break/>of human saliva and biopsy samples</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-101" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inability for virus neutralization
<break/>tests of clinical samples</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enzyme-linked immunosorbent
<break/>assay-based tests of serum and
<break/>CSF</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Desire for greater epidemiological
<break/>investigation of confirmed cases</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whole genome sequencing</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Need for deep identification of
<break/>viral quasispecies</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Next-generation sequencing</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-104" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Prophylaxis concerns</title><p>Often forgotten, rabies qualifies as a vaccine-preventable disease. Effective rabies biologics have been available for over a century
<sup><xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup>. Pre-exposure vaccination is highly efficacious for those at risk of exposure, such as veterinarians, laboratory workers, and certain travelers
<sup><xref rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
<xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup>. After exposure, the prompt and proper application of post-exposure prophylaxis (PEP)&#x02014;consisting of wound care, infiltration of rabies immune globulin (RIG), and administration of modern rabies vaccines&#x02014;virtually ensures survival
<sup><xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup>. Nevertheless, the majority of persons at risk do not receive pre-exposure vaccination and most RABV-exposed patients are never provided adequate PEP. This discrepancy between Advisory Committee on Immunization Practices/World Health Organization (ACIP/WHO) recommendations and reality has sparked strong debate and translational research for more novel, less expensive products; simplified schedules; and improved ease of use
<sup><xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>&#x02013;
<xref rid="ref-58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></sup>. Outstanding questions for resolution include the following: Can PEP be performed safely without RIG (given that limited availability means more than 90% of persons do not receive it)? Are heterologous (for example, equine) RIG products equivalent to human RIG in regard to safety and effectiveness? If so, how should their production be increased? Is the dose of RIG critical in terms of international units per kilograms or is local infiltration more important, regardless of absolute dose? Does administration of vaccine directly into exposure sites improve survivorship if RIG is not available? Could PEP completion be reduced to one week or less? What is the role for rabies pre-exposure vaccine inclusion into childhood schedules? When will GAVI add human rabies vaccine to its portfolio? Will monoclonal antibodies help to resolve the issues with RIG availability and distribution? Should new biologics be developed to increase the breadth of reactivity against non-phylogroup I lyssaviruses? Is there a role for new adjuvants or attenuated RABV vaccines to obviate the need for RIG? Should genes involved in the innate immune response (for example, interferons) be incorporated into genomes of recombinant RABV vaccine strains? Although the field will always profit from relevant advances, much attention is often spent on academic research on new biologics and less on translational research for the appropriate use of existing products and protocols to prevent rabies now (
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Table 3. </label><caption><title>Risk assessment to maximize the utility of rabies prophylaxis after human exposure
<sup><xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
<xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
<xref rid="ref-75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref></sup>.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" content-type="article-table"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Category</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Issue</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outcome</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Is the mammal a reservoir?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-reservoirs or non-vectors are less likely to be rabid.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exposure</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Was the exposure due to a bite?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-bite exposures are less likely to cause rabies.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Does the animal show compatible clinical
<break/>signs with an encephalitis or other behavioral
<break/>abnormalities suggestive of rabies?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">In general, apparently healthy animals (even near the end
<break/>of the incubation period) are less likely than ill animals to
<break/>excrete virus.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epidemiological
<break/>status</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">What is the occurrence of rabies in the area?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unless an epizootic or enzootic status is apparent, rabies
<break/>is less frequent in areas without cases for several years,
<break/>assuming adequate laboratory-based surveillance.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Event
<break/>circumstances</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Was the exposure provoked?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Often animals may bite if provoked (for example, protecting
<break/>young, sleeping, or eating).</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Observation</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Can the dog, cat, or ferret be observed?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">If the animal stays apparently healthy during at least 10
<break/>days after the bite, no post-exposure prophylaxis (PEP) is
<break/>needed (or initiated PEP can be discontinued).</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vaccination
<break/>status</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Is the animal up to date on rabies vaccination?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vaccine failures are possible, but rare, with modern
<break/>veterinary biologics.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnosis</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Is the brain available for a timely examination?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">If no rabies virus antigens are detected by a qualified
<break/>laboratory using an approved test, no PEP is needed.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First aid</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Were all wounds washed well?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proper cleansing with soap and water reduces the viral
<break/>load in local wounds.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Injury</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Does the injury require sutures?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">If at all practical, suturing should be postponed, to avoid
<break/>the opportunity to further contaminate the locality and drive
<break/>virus deeper in tissues.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biologics</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Are modern vaccines and rabies immune globulin
<break/>(RIG) available?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">If the diagnosis is positive or (under the worst conditions
<break/>when rabies is strongly suspected) if an unprovoked bite is
<break/>from an ill, unavailable dog or other reservoir in an enzootic
<break/>area, begin PEP per current World Health Organization
<break/>recommendations to the extent possible or support
<break/>transport to the nearest suitable facility immediately.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient health</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Is the person immune-competent?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">In the severely immune-suppressed patient, such as
<break/>someone with AIDS, passive immunization with rabies
<break/>immune globulin (RIG) becomes an even more critical part
<break/>of PEP.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Controversy on the horizon: a paradigm shift to treating the &#x0201c;incurable wound&#x0201d;?</title><p>Today, as in the past, a diagnosis of a rabies case is, in a statistical sense (&#x0003e;99.9%), synonymous with fatality. There is no proven treatment once clinical signs appear. This presents a huge dilemma to the clinician faced with a rabies patient, with few options
<sup><xref rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></sup>. For a veterinarian, the animal is euthanized. For a physician, the patient may be placed in isolation, and at a minimum palliative care needs to be provided.</p><p>Alternatively, the person may be sent home to die. Cumulatively, since the 1970s, reports of very rare, non-fatal human cases (most with a history of vaccination) and the occasional spontaneous &#x0201c;survivor&#x0201d; during animal rabies studies suggested that clinical rabies may not always end in death, prompting the administration of aggressive anti-viral therapy
<sup><xref rid="ref-60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></sup>. As a case in point, in 2004, a Wisconsin teenager bitten by a bat became the first unvaccinated survivor after intensive medical care, coma induction, and administration of anti-viral drugs
<sup><xref rid="ref-61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></sup>. Over the next decade, few additional survivors who received the &#x0201c;Milwaukee protocol&#x0201d; were added to the registry (
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mcw.edu/Pediatrics/InfectiousDiseases/PatientCare/Rabies.htm">http://www.mcw.edu/Pediatrics/InfectiousDiseases/PatientCare/Rabies.htm</ext-link>). Nevertheless, the drive to act is understandable; such undertakings are compassionate and heroic attempts at treating the incurable. Who can witness the face of pathos in a Manila rabies ward and not be sensitized (
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aljazeera.com/programmes/lifelines/2013/09/rabies-lifelines-isolation-patient-2013923164345829402.html">http://www.aljazeera.com/programmes/lifelines/2013/09/rabies-lifelines-isolation-patient-2013923164345829402.html</ext-link>)? Who can listen to the heart-breaking personal impact of rabies on a family and not feel moved (
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u8o1tOuyghk">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u8o1tOuyghk</ext-link>)? Who can watch &#x0201c;The Girl Who Survived Rabies&#x0201d; and not feel compelled (
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qdPuXHhEwDk">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qdPuXHhEwDk</ext-link>)? Although there has been sharp debate over the dangers of therapeutic coma and the merits of the Milwaukee protocol, the often-heated discussion has reinvigorated the field in a direction toward consideration of potential treatment administered to the patient with rabies
<sup><xref rid="ref-62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></sup>. Asklepios is but one example of such a renaissance by a consortium of scientists whose focal research aims include the following: the identification of drugs that would inhibit RABV replication, the testing of molecules that may minimize detrimental host responses during RABV infection, the determination of whether alteration of the blood-brain barrier (BBB) permeability could improve treatment effectiveness, and validation of the potential success for such an approach
<italic>in vivo</italic> (
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://asklepiosfp7.eu/">http://asklepiosfp7.eu/</ext-link>). Regardless of technical insights, required expertise, the associated expense and related ethics of effort issues, there is also the prospect of survivorship with sequelae and the need for lengthy, potentially lifelong, rehabilitation and quality-of-life considerations
<sup><xref rid="ref-63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref></sup>. To make progress, whether in veterinary or human medicine, a more complete approach to rabies treatment should be taken, combining insights on rabies pathobiology gleaned from both experimental animal research and individual human case studies
<sup><xref rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref></sup>. Excellent clinical care by a dream team of specialists, anti-viral drugs incorporated from other RNA virus research, targeted immune modulation, the tincture of time, and a healthy dose of luck for appreciable self-cure in a patient with the ideal age, genetic pre-disposition, and clinical staging parameters may offer future hope to a more prescriptive treatment of rabies (
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">Table 4</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T4" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Table 4. </label><caption><title>Consideration for a strategic combination approach to the management and treatment of clinical rabies.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" content-type="article-table"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proposed need</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suggested consideration</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">References</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Management of the dying rabies
<break/>patient?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Responsible palliative care, toward death with dignity</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intensive care of acute progressive
<break/>rabies encephalitis?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventilation, sedation, cardiac monitoring, body
<break/>temperature regulation, parenteral nutrition,
<break/>management of vasospasm, and so on</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Real-time diagnostic support?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rapid antemortem confirmation, viral characterization,
<break/>and continued patient monitoring, including serology,
<break/>amplicons, antigens, and so on</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Active immunization?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recombinant vaccines</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Passive immunization?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rabies immune globulin or monoclonal antibodies</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-109" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Administration of immunostimulatory
<break/>oligonucleotides?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Use of PyNTTTTGT compounds, such as IMT504</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anti-viral drugs?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Use of known ssRNA virus inhibitors, such as
<break/>favipiravir (T-705)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-111" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Targeted host-catalyzed biochemical
<break/>pathways?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Selection of specific small-molecular-weight
<break/>compounds</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-112" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood-brain barrier permeability
<break/>enhancement?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Induction of pro-inflammatory chemokines and
<break/>cytokines</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-113" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Associated pathological decrease
<break/>of dopaminergic and serotoninergic
<break/>neurotransmission?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Supplementation with biotin</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-114" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mitochondrial dysfunction and
<break/>degenerative changes in neuronal
<break/>processes?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relief of potential oxidative stress</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref-115" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Concerns over vaccine needs to achieve global human and dog rabies elimination&#x02014;by 2030</title><p>Throughout the late-20th and early-21st centuries, target dates for the elimination of human-dog-mediated rabies were set by the WHO, the Pan American Health Organization, and other international governmental and non-governmental organizations for Africa, Asia, and Latin America (
<xref rid="ref-65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>&#x02013;
<xref rid="ref-68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.paho.org/hq/index.php?option=com_content&#x00026;view=article&#x00026;id=11243%3Astep-up-action-toward-rabieselimination&#x00026;Itemid=1926&#x00026;lang=en">http://www.paho.org/hq/index.php?option=com_content&#x00026;view=article&#x00026;id=11243%3Astep-up-action-toward-rabieselimination&#x00026;Itemid=1926&#x00026;lang=en</ext-link>). These recent end dates were endorsed by the World Health Assembly in May 2013
<sup><xref rid="ref-69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref></sup>.</p><p>The main components of this human rabies elimination program are control, prevention, and eventual elimination of rabies in dogs by mass immunization. Successive annual vaccination campaigns, reaching at least 70% of the dog population, led to progressive disease control and ultimately elimination in both dogs and humans
<sup><xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
<xref rid="ref-68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></sup>. Estimating the number of canine vaccine doses needed by country, WHO region, and finally globally over time to achieve these goals is of upmost importance. Understandably, dog rabies vaccine production and access have not received the same attention as human rabies biologics, even though the latter are still in somewhat limited availability, particularly in rural areas. Today, overall dog vaccination coverage is estimated to be less than 20% in canine rabies-endemic countries outside of the Americas (
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5a">Table 5</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T5a" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Table 5a. </label><caption><title>Estimated dog populations, annual dog vaccine coverage and number of dog vaccine doses used per WHO region, including China (WPR) and India (SEAR).</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" content-type="article-table"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elimination
<break/>target date</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO region</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimated dog
<break/>population (
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">Table 6</xref>)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimated
<break/>vaccination coverage
<break/>(see source below)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dog vaccine doses
<break/>used annually (in
<break/>millions of doses)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of total
<break/>vaccine doses
<break/>applied</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="7" valign="top" colspan="1">2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EUR (Eurasia)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85,612,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26,547,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEAR, without
<break/>India</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72,631,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">India (72% rural)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38,109,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WPR, without
<break/>China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38,847,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China (55%
<break/>rural)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71,785,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Totals for EMR,
<break/>EUR, SEAR, and
<break/>WPR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">333,531,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">2030</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77,417,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grand total
<break/>WHO regions
<break/>(but AMR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">411,000,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>AFR, African Region; AMR, Region of the Americas; EMR, East Mediterranean Region; EUR, European Region; SEAR, South East Asia Region; WHO, World Health Organization; WPR, West Pacific Region.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T5b" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Table 5b.</label><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" content-type="article-table"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Region</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Supportive notes and references</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eurasia (EUR)</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22%
<sup><xref rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eastern Mediterranean Region
<break/>(EMR)</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32%
<sup><xref rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South East Asia Region (SEAR),
<break/>without India</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sum of number of dogs vaccinated in SEAR countries belonging to clusters Asia 2, 3, and 4
<break/>plus Indonesia according to estimated vaccination coverages (respectively 9, 5, 36, and 24%
<break/>in
<xref rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>) divided by an estimated total dog population of about 72.6 million</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">India</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15% (from
<xref rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>) applied to estimated rural dog population of India (
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">Table 6</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">West Pacific Region (WPR), without
<break/>China</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sum of number of dogs vaccinated in WPR countries belonging to clusters Asia 2, 3, and 4
<break/>plus Mongolia according to vaccination coverage (5.9% from
<xref rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>) divided by estimated total
<break/>dog population of 38.8 million (
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">Table 6</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coverage 14%
<sup><xref rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></sup> applied to estimated rural dog population of China (
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">Table 6</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">African region</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North Africa dog immunization coverage 10%, Southern Africa Development Community
<break/>(SADC) coverage 23%, West Africa coverage 10%, and rest of Africa 9%
<sup><xref rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></sup> applied to
<break/>estimated dog population of relevant geographical clusters (
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">Table 6</xref>), giving for North Africa:
<break/>0.7 million dogs vaccinated, for SADC: 7 million, West Africa: 2 million and rest of Africa:
<break/>2.5 million. Total Africa: 12.2 million. Dog vaccination coverage Africa: 16%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T6" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Table 6. </label><caption><title>Numbers of dogs per human and estimated dog populations per geographical areas, countries and World Health Organization regions.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" content-type="article-table"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geographic
<break/>area</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO
<break/>region</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human
<break/>population
<break/>(estimated)</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage
<break/>rural</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human/
<break/>dog ratio</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dog population
<break/>(estimated)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asia and
<break/>Eurasian</td><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asia 2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WPR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cambodia</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,135,169</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80%</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.60</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,293,207</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WPR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Laos</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,769,727</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66%</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.60</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,025,716</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEAR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North Korea</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24,895,480</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40%</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.60</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,772,042</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WPR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Korea</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50,219,669</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17%</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.60</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,609,041</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEAR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myanmar</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53,259,018</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63%</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.60</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,069,548</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WPR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vietnam</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89,708,900</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69%</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.60</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,592,258</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" valign="top" colspan="1">Asia 3</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEAR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bangladesh</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156,594,962</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72%</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.70</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,652,719</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEAR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bhutan</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">753,947</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64%</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.70</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51,289</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pakistan</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">182,142,594</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64%</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.70</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,390,653</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEAR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nepal</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27,797,457</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83%</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.70</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,890,983</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" valign="top" colspan="1">Asia 4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WPR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Philippines</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98,393,574</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51%</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.00</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,056,225</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEAR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sri Lanka</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,483,000</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85%</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.00</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,926,143</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEAR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thailand</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67,010,502</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66%</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.00</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,572,929</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Asia
<break/>2, 3, 4</td><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87,902,753</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other Asia</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEAR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indonesia</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">249,865,631</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49%</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.00</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35,695,090</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WPR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mongolia</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,839,073</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31%</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">270,388</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEAR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">India</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,252,139,596</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72%</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.0</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38,108,596a</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WPR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,357,380,000</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55%</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71,784,519
<sup>a</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total other
<break/>Asia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">145,858,593</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Asia
<break/>excluding
<break/>Pakistan.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>221,370,693</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eurasia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EUR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kazakhstan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EUR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kyrgyzstan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EUR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Russian
<break/>Federation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EUR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Turkmenistan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EUR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tajikistan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EUR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uzbekistan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total
<break/>Eurasia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">898,926,561</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>85,612,053</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Africa</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SADC</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Democratic
<break/>Republic of
<break/>the Congo</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67,513,677</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66%</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Angola</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21,471,618</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41%</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zambia</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,538,640</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Malawi</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,362,567</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tanzania</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49,253,126</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mozambique</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25,833,752</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zimbabwe</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,149,648</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Botswana</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,021,144</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Namibia</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,303,315</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Africa</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52,981,991</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Swaziland</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,249,514</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Madagascar</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,924,851</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lesotho</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,074,465</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total
<break/>SADC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>292,678,308</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>9.5</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>30,808,243</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>North Africa</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Morocco</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33,008,150</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Algeria</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39,208,194</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tunesia</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,886,500</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Libya</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,201,521</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Egypt</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82,056,378</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Western
<break/>Sahara</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">500,000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sudan (+
<break/>south)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37,964,306</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total North
<break/>Africa</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>209,825,049</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>31.2</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>6,725,162</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>West Africa</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benin</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,323,474</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Burkina Faso</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,934,839</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cape Verde</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">498,897</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ivory Coast</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,316,086</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gambia</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,849,285</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ghana</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25,904,598</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guinea</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,745,189</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guinea-Bissau</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,704,255</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liberia</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,294,077</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,301,650</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,831,270</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nigeria</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">173,615,345</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senegal</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,133,280</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sierra Leone</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,092,075</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Togo</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,816,982</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total West
<break/>Africa</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>327,361,302</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold/>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>16.8</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>19,485,792</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Other Africa</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uganda</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37,578,876</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,955,671</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gabon</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,671,711</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99,507</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nigeria</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">173,615,345</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,334,247</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Equatorial
<break/>Guinea</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">757,014</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45,060</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chad</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,825,314</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">763,412</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rwanda</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,776,522</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,239,634</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Burundi</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,162,532</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">604,913</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Republic of
<break/>Congo</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,447,632</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">468,172</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethiopia</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94,100,756</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,016,050</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mauretania</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,889,880</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124,676</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kenya</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44,353,691</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,668,810</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Somalia</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,495,583</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">336,397</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Central
<break/>African
<break/>Republic</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,616,417</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">274,787</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eritrea</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,333,135</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">202,985</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cameroon</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,253,959</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,324,640</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total other
<break/>Africa</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>27,458,959</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Total Africa</bold>
<break/>
<bold>excluding</bold>
<break/>
<bold>North</bold>
<break/>
<bold>Africa and</bold>
<break/>
<bold>Somalia</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77,416,599</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Other</bold>
<break/>
<bold>EMRO</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Afghanistan</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30,551,674</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">863,042</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bahrain</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,332,171</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37,632</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Djibouti</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">872,932</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24,659</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77,447,168</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,187,773</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iraq</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33,417,476</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">943,996</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jordan</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,459,000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">182,458</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kuwait</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,368,572</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95,157</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lebanon</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,467,390</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126,197</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Palestine</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,169,506</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117,783</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oman</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,632,444</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102,611</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saudi Arabia</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28,828,870</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">814,375</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syrian Arab
<break/>Republic</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,845,550</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">645,355</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United Arab
<break/>Emirates</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,346,129</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">264,015</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yemen</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24,407,381</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">689,474</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total EMR
<break/>including
<break/>North Africa,
<break/>Pakistan,
<break/>Somalia
<break/>and other EMR
<break/>countries</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>26,546,739</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Grand total</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>410,946,084</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Adapted from K. Hampson (personal communication, 2014) using World population statistics 2010 at
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldpopulationstatistiscs.com/">www.worldpopulationstatistiscs.com</ext-link> and expanding on the list of countries eligible for GAVI support, 2014 (
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gavi.org/supportapply/countries-eligible-for-support/">www.gavi.org/supportapply/countries-eligible-for-support/</ext-link>). AFR, African region; EMR, East Mediterranean region; EMRO, Eastern Mediterranean Regional Office; EUR, European (Asian portion) Region; SADC, Southern Africa Development Community; SEAR, South East Asia Region; WHO, World Health Organization; WPR, West Pacific Region.
</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>There is relatively little production, technology development or transfer, import, and subsequent use of canine vaccines in dog rabies-enzootic countries. To prevent rabies in humans, manufacturers from the Northern Hemisphere and an increasing number of producers from emerging markets (for example, China and India) produce enough vaccine annually to deliver approximately 28 million rabies PEP courses in dog rabies-enzootic countries of Africa, Asia, and the Eastern Mediterranean region, preventing nearly 98% of human rabies deaths. Unfortunately, easier access to rabies vaccine, particularly in urban centers of Africa and Asia, has been accompanied by an increasing proportion of PEP (sometimes up to 70%) administered to people who are not at high risk of developing rabies, necessitating greater education and outreach to the public and professionals alike
<sup><xref rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></sup>. Such issues are not uncommon in Europe and North America, where human rabies caused by dogs has been eliminated.</p><p>A canine rabies vaccine bank was established in 2012 by the World Animal Health Organization (OIE), with multi-donor support to assist Asian countries initiating (for example, Afghanistan, Laos, and Myanmar) or strengthening (for example, the Philippines, Sri Lanka, and Vietnam) their immunization campaigns
<sup><xref rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>,
<xref rid="ref-72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref></sup>. Though certainly useful, the quantities provided (about 3.7 million doses from 2012 to April 2015) have remained limited in comparison with annual requirements of full-fledged national programs in 10 Asian beneficiary countries. For example, over 3 years, Vietnam received a total of about 1 million doses, but nearly 10 million local dogs need to be vaccinated annually. Similarly, the WHO has expressed an intention of constructing a human rabies vaccine stockpile to rapidly provide quality-ensured vaccines upon request
<sup><xref rid="ref-73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref></sup>. Globally, human rabies vaccine quantities produced seem close to adequate, but at a country level, major challenges include the following: assessing unnecessary or inappropriately applied PEP, particularly in urban centers; bringing appropriately staffed &#x0201c;bite treatment centers&#x0201d; to needed communities; providing free or low-cost rabies biologics; and applying economical and easier-to-use PEP regimens to exposed patients
<sup><xref rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></sup>.</p><p>A meeting was held at the WHO in 2015 on human and dog rabies vaccines and RIG. Objectives were to discuss forecasting needs, vaccine and RIG quality, and funding and procurement issues, and to estimate quantities of human and dog vaccines needed in the medium and long term at both the country and regional level
<sup><xref rid="ref-74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref></sup>. During this meeting, manufacturers of canine rabies vaccines stated that production capacity shortages were not an issue and that output could be increased easily should accurate, financially supported, medium-term vaccine forecasts become available. However, current annual production capacities of major manufacturers are estimated to be near 100 million doses, and maximum capacity is about 150 million doses
<sup><xref rid="ref-75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref></sup>. This rabies vaccine production is meant to satisfy the most profitable Northern Hemisphere (for example, USA, Canada, and Western and Eastern Europe) markets, where there are about 170 million owned dogs, whereas only a small share of the 411 million owned and community dogs are vaccinated each year in the defined WHO African, Asian, Eurasian, and Middle Eastern regions (
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5a">Table 5</xref>). The vaccine requirements of Latin American countries, where dog-mediated human rabies has almost been eliminated (mostly through dog rabies immunization), are estimated at about 42 million doses annually and often are covered largely by local manufacturers based in Mexico and Brazil
<sup><xref rid="ref-76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>,
<xref rid="ref-77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref></sup>. Together, dog rabies-enzootic countries of Central Asia belonging to the European (EU), South-East-Asian (SEA), and Western Pacific (WP) WHO regions account in nearly equal proportions for almost 74% of the total number of canine vaccine doses used. Africa and Eastern Mediterranean regions account for the remaining 15% and 11%, respectively.</p><p>The number of vaccine doses needed in canine rabies-enzootic countries of the defined WHO Africa, Asia, Eurasia, and East Mediterranean regions were estimated in the medium (2015&#x02013;2020) and longer (2020&#x02013;2029) terms to achieve the goal of human and dog rabies elimination. As a given, these vaccines should comply with all international norms and standards
<sup><xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
<xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
<xref rid="ref-78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref></sup>. In the computing of estimates, one of the most sensitive figures is the human/dog ratio by geographical areas/WHO regions and large countries (China and India). Numbers of dogs per human and country clustering have been used from earlier publications
<sup><xref rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>,
<xref rid="ref-79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref></sup>. Some dog rabies-enzootic countries were added to existing lists. When country-specific data were unavailable, the average estimate from countries within the cluster was applied.
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">Table 6</xref> provides a list of more than 85 dog rabies-enzootic countries with their human and dog populations and dogs-per-human ratio in Africa, Asia, and East Mediterranean regions on the basis of prior work
<sup><xref rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>,
<xref rid="ref-80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>,
<xref rid="ref-81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref></sup>.</p><p>Using the above population estimates to compute canine vaccine needs over time, we used a conservative 10-year country-based dog rabies elimination model divided into a 5-year attack phase, a 3-year consolidation phase, and a 2-year maintenance phase (with vaccination coverages decreasing from 70% to 20% and finally to 5% as the program moved from one phase to another). This model is based on both theoretical and field experiences
<sup><xref rid="ref-82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>&#x02013;
<xref rid="ref-86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref></sup>. Understandably, national programs will progress at various paces. Some may need shorter or longer attack, consolidation, or maintenance phases than others. Ten years of sustained dog rabies immunization activities were considered long enough to bring human rabies cases down toward zero in most places, if carried out with the joint leadership of the countries and major international organizations
<sup><xref rid="ref-87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref></sup>.</p><p>Dog vaccine requirements per country were aggregated by WHO regions and time periods. The results of estimated dog vaccine requirements by WHO regions and large countries (for example, China and India) are presented in
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T7">Table 7</xref>. For the European (Eurasia cluster), East Mediterranean, Asian, and Western Pacific WHO regions, the attack phase extends from 2015 to 2019; the consolidation phase from 2020 to 2022; and the maintenance phase from 2023 to 2024, as the target date for human rabies elimination here is 2020. Many countries in the above listed WHO regions particularly the Southeast Asia and Western Pacific regions which carry a large part of the global human rabies burden have committed themselves to achieve the goal of human rabies elimination by 2020 and already scaled-up their dog and human rabies control activities (e.g Philippines, Sri Lanka, Thailand, Vietnam and parts of Indonesia, India &#x00026; China). For the African Region, the attack phase extends from 2020 to 2024; the consolidation phase from 2025 to 2027; and the maintenance phase from 2028 to 2029, as the target date for human rabies elimination here is 2030. The African region particularly sub-Saharan Africa will benefit from the full 10 year program plus preparatory time as the number of countries with experience of large-scale dog rabies immunization campaigns is comparatively small.</p><table-wrap id="T7" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Table 7. </label><caption><title>Estimated dog vaccine requirements in 2014&#x02013;2030 to achieve human and dog rabies elimination target dates in World Health Organization regions.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" content-type="article-table"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Program phase</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Attack
<break/>phase
<break/>(5 years)</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Consolidation
<break/>phase
<break/>(3 years)</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Totals
<break/>(phases 1
<break/>and 2)</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maintenance
<break/>phase
<break/>(2 years)</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total
<break/>(phases 1, 2,
<break/>and 3)</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number
<break/>of dogs
<break/>vaccinated
<break/>per
<break/>region in
<break/>percentage
<break/>total</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grand total</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time lines</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015&#x02013;2019</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2020&#x02013;2022</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015&#x02013;2022</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2023&#x02013;2024</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015&#x02013;2024</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015&#x02013;2024</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015&#x02013;2029</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annual dog vaccination coverage (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70%</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20, 20, 20%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5, 5%</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elimination
<break/>target</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO region</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimated
<break/>dog
<break/>population
<break/>(millions)</td><td align="left" colspan="7" valign="top" rowspan="1">Total doses in millions (per year)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6" valign="top" colspan="1">2020</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EURO
<break/>(Eurasia)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85,612,000</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300 (60, 60,
<break/>60, 60, 60)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (17, 17, 17)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">351</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (4, 4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">359</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMRO</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26,547,000</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95 (19, 19,
<break/>19, 19, 19)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (5, 5, 5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (1, 1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEARO
<break/>without India</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72,631,000</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">255 (51, 51,
<break/>51, 51, 51)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (15, 15, 15)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (4, 4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">308</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">India (72%
<break/>rural)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38,109,000</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135 (27, 27,
<break/>27, 27, 27)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (8, 8, 8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">159</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (2, 2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">163</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WPRO
<break/>without
<break/>China</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38,847,000</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135 (27, 27,
<break/>27, 27, 27)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (8, 8, 8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">159</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (2, 2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">163</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China (55%
<break/>rural)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71,785,000</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250 (50, 50,
<break/>50, 50, 50)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (14, 14, 14)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">292</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (4, 4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Totals for
<break/>EMRO,
<break/>EURO,
<break/>SEARO, and
<break/>WPRO</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">333,531,000</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,170
<break/>(234 million
<break/>doses a
<break/>year)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,371</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,405</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,405</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2030</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFRO total</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77,417,000</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Program
<break/>phase</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Attack phase
<break/>(5 years)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Consolidation
<break/>phase (3 years)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (phases 1
<break/>and 2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maintenance
<break/>phase</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2020&#x02013;2024</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2025&#x02013;2027</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2020&#x02013;2027</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2028&#x02013;2029</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">270 (54, 54, 54, 54, 54)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (15, 15, 15)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">315</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (4, 4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.9</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">328</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grand
<break/>total WHO
<break/>Regions</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">411,000,000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,728</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>According to a 10-year national dog immunization program (assuming an attack phase of 5 years achieving a 70% coverage annually, consolidation phase of 3 years with 20% annual coverage and maintenance phase of 2 years with 5% annual coverage). AFRO, African Regional Office; EMRO, East Mediterranean Regional Office; EURO, European Regional Office; SEARO, South East Asia Regional Office; WHO, World Health Organization; WPRO, West Pacific Regional Office.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Based on these estimates, almost 1.3 billion doses (more than 260 million doses annually including a 10% wastage rate) are needed from 2015 to 2019 for the attack phase in Asia and the Middle East. This is a conservative figure, as human populations of urban centers of China and India, which have almost a billion people and associated large dog populations, were excluded from this computation. In India, a special rabies control program targets major cities
<sup><xref rid="ref-88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref></sup>. In large Chinese cities, dog rabies prevalence is lower, but dog ownership laws (though somewhat relaxed recently and often difficult to enforce) may remain quite strict
<sup><xref rid="ref-89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref></sup>. In addition, 560 million doses are required from 2020 to 2024 (about 110 million doses annually) for the consolidation phase in these areas to initiate and conduct programs in Africa and maintain freedom in previously liberated areas. This means providing during the period of 2015&#x02013;2019, on an annual basis, five times more dog vaccine to rural India and China, three times more for Eurasia, and two times more than currently used for the Eastern Mediterranean Region as well as five times more to the entire of Africa during the period of 2020&#x02013;2024. Given the other existing priority market requirements, quantities needed in the short term (2015&#x02013;2019) are likely to exceed major manufacturers&#x02019; capacities of scaling-up. In addition, as almost 50% of these dog vaccine doses are needed in South, South Eastern, and Eastern Asian countries, especially in China and India, current procurement mechanisms for pure, potent, safe, and efficacious vaccines, mostly involving Northern Hemisphere manufacturers&#x02019; production units, will not be acceptable by all.</p><p>Besides mass dog vaccination, to achieve the concomitant goal of human rabies elimination by 2030, international organizations must also support RIG manufacturing (particularly in developing countries), fast-track the addition of new vaccines to the WHO list of pre-qualified rabies vaccines, and invest in production of new, safer, and more affordable biologics for passive immunization
<sup><xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
<xref rid="ref-78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>,
<xref rid="ref-90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref></sup>.</p><p>Together with national public health authorities, these organizations must strongly discourage the unnecessary administration of very large and inappropriate numbers of PEP, which contribute to creating shortages in areas where these rabies biologics are truly needed (
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T8">Table 8</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T8" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Table 8. </label><caption><title>Post-exposure prophylaxis (PEP), number and percentages of non-exposed persons receiving PEP per million.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" content-type="article-table"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geographical
<break/>cluster</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">World Health
<break/>Organization
<break/>region</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human
<break/>populations</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PEP per
<break/>million people
<break/>(Total PEP
<break/>administered
<break/>per cluster)</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exposures per
<break/>million (Total
<break/>exposures)</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number
<break/>of non-
<break/>exposed
<break/>humans
<break/>receiving
<break/>PEP per
<break/>million</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of
<break/>non-exposed
<break/>humans
<break/>receiving PEP</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Asia</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Asia 2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WP and SEA</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">239,987,963,
<break/>about 240 million</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,764 (1,143,377)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,195 (766,842)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,569</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Asia 3</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEA</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">367,288,960,
<break/>about 367 million</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">914 (335,740)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">667 (244,767)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Asia 4</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEA and WP</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185,887,076,
<break/>about 186 million</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,638 (862,641)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,413 (262,841)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,225</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subtotal</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,341,758</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1,274,540)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total other Asia</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indonesia, China,
<break/>India</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,859,385,227,
<break/>about 2.8 billion</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,183
<break/>(23,395,261)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,550
<break/>(13,008,455)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,633</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subtotal</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25,737,019</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(14,282,905)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eurasia</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EUR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">898,926,561,
<break/>about 899 million</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">748 (672,177)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">289 (259,650)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">495</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Africa</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SADC</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">292,678,308,
<break/>about 293 million</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,766 (517,409)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">925 (271,041)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">841</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North Africa</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,982,504,
<break/>about 21 million</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,917 (402,632)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">930 (195,237)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">987</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">West Africa</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">327,361,302,
<break/>about 327 million</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,071 (350,374)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">790 (258,341)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">281</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other Africa</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFR</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">438,878,367,
<break/>about 439 million</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">265 (116,433)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">273 (119,707)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-8</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subtotal</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,386,848</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">844,326</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMRO</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minus North
<break/>Africa and
<break/>Somalia</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">251,146,263,
<break/>about 251 million</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">932 (233,883)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">465 (116,785)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">467</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Adapted from
<xref rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>. AFR, African region; EMR, East Mediterranean region; EMRO, Eastern Mediterranean Regional Office; EUR, European (Asian portion) Region; SADC, Southern Africa Development Community; SEA, South East Asia; WHO, World Health Organization; WP, West Pacific.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Concerning dog rabies vaccines, their sustained availability at the ground level has repeatedly been shown to be essential to the initiation of dog rabies control activities
<sup><xref rid="ref-85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref></sup>. Essential steps to effectively increase veterinary rabies vaccine production to achieve human-dog-mediated rabies elimination by 2030 must be seriously considered by international organizations and vaccine manufacturers supporting this goal. These steps include accelerating technology transfer to Africa and Asia and redirecting some existing human rabies vaccine manufacturing capacities toward canine vaccine production, as proposed more than 30 years ago by a joint Rockefeller/WHO initiative
<sup><xref rid="ref-91" ref-type="bibr">91</xref></sup>. Similarly, GAVI support of human rabies vaccines might allow those eligible governments to use any conserved resources directed to veterinary public health, as begun regionally in the Americas in the 1980s. Comparatively modest investment in canine vaccination programs is predicted to have major cost-effective outcomes for the human rabies burden, even in some of the most severely affected areas
<sup><xref rid="ref-92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>Future vision</title><p>Viral taxonomy may continue to adjust subjectively to changing times, differing philosophies, and bio-political pressure, yet regardless of the specific etiological names responsible for this disease, the moniker for rabies will remain. Theories on lyssavirus and host co-evolution will be complemented by methodological improvements and pathogen discovery. With enhanced, de-centralized laboratory-based surveillance and focused detection efforts, additional lyssavirus species and host shifts are expected. Stockpiling of vaccine and RIG, attention to existing recommendations, and careful risk assessments will increase the use of pre-exposure vaccination, maximize appropriate use of biologics in those truly exposed, and reduce PEP failures. Eventual application of the growing knowledge base on rabies pathogenetic mechanisms, pronounced intensive clinical skills in managing encephalitis, and the abilities to intervene with combinations of biologics and anti-viral drugs will gradually result in additional rabies survivors in human and veterinary medicine without losing the critical focus upon disease prevention. Ideally, under a progressive global business plan (with the minimum application of estimated biologics to the populations at risk, new champions, and dedicated sponsorships without vaccination fatigue), human rabies mediated by dogs should be eliminated in Latin America over the next 5 years, in Asia within a decade, and in Africa by 2030. Although eradication is not the aim, given a diversity of wildlife reservoirs and a lack of strategies to break the chain of perpetuation among the Chiroptera, the time is long overdue to accomplish such other ambitious goals against an ancient and insidious but neglected killer.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors thank their many colleagues in academia, government, industry, and non-governmental organizations for research collaborations to date. 
</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="ref-1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Firth</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Widen</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Evolution of genome size and complexity in the
<italic>rhabdoviridae</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS Pathog.</italic></source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e1004664</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1004664</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4334499</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 25679389?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25679389</pub-id></mixed-citation><note><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://f1000.com/prime/725354552">F1000 Recommendation</ext-link>
</p></note></ref><ref id="ref-2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Afonso</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Amarasinghe</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e1;nyai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Taxonomy of the order
<italic>Mononegavirales</italic>: update 2016.</article-title>
<source><italic>Arch Virol.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>161</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>2351</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00705-016-2880-1</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4947412</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 27216929?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27216929</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Regenmortel</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Calisher</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>A proposal to change existing virus species names to non-Latinized binomials.</article-title>
<source><italic>Arch Virol.</italic></source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>155</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1909</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00705-010-0831-9</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20953644?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20953644</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Regenmortel</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ackermann</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Calisher</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Virus species polemics: 14 senior virologists oppose a proposed change to the ICTV definition of virus species.</article-title>
<source><italic>Arch Virol.</italic></source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>158</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1115</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00705-012-1583-5</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23269443?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23269443</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ar&#x000e9;chiga Ceballos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>V&#x000e1;zquez Mor&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Berciano</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Novel lyssavirus in bat, Spain.</article-title>
<source><italic>Emerg Infect Dis.</italic></source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>793</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid1905.121071</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3647500</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 23648051?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23648051</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gunawardena</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Marston</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Lyssavirus in Indian Flying Foxes, Sri Lanka.</article-title>
<source><italic>Emerg Infect Dis.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>88</issue>):<fpage>1456</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid2208.151986</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4982157</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 27434858?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27434858</pub-id></mixed-citation><note><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://f1000.com/prime/727277684">F1000 Recommendation</ext-link>
</p></note></ref><ref id="ref-7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Badrane</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahloul</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Evidence of two
<italic>Lyssavirus</italic> phylogroups with distinct pathogenicity and immunogenicity.</article-title>
<source><italic>J Virol.</italic></source>
<year>2001</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>3268</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.75.7.3268-3276.2001</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">114120</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 11238853?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11238853</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Banyard</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Marston</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Antigenic and genetic characterization of a divergent African virus, Ikoma lyssavirus.</article-title>
<source><italic>J Gen Virol.</italic></source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>95</volume>(<issue>Pt 5</issue>):<fpage>1025</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/vir.0.061952-0</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3983756</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 24496827?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24496827</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dietzgen</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Calisher</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurath</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Family Rhabdoviridae</article-title>. In: King AMQ, Adams MJ, Carstens EB, Lefkowitz EL, editors.
<italic>Virus Taxonomy: 9th report of the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses</italic> Oxford, UK: Elsevier;<year>2011</year>;<fpage>686</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>714</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-384684-6.00057-4</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>World Health Organization</collab>:
<article-title>Expert consultation on rabies. Second report</article-title>. WHO Technical Report Series; no. 982. Geneva, Switzerland: World Health Organization;<year>2013</year>;<fpage>7</fpage>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/10665/85346/1/9789240690943_eng.pdf">Reference Source</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kgaladi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Coertse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Diversity and epidemiology of Mokola virus.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS Negl Trop Dis.</italic></source>
<year>2013 </year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e2511</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0002511</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3812115</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 24205423?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24205423</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Badrane</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tordo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Host switching in
<italic>Lyssavirus</italic> history from the Chiroptera to the Carnivora orders.</article-title>
<source><italic>J Virol.</italic></source>
<year>2001</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>8096</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>104</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.75.17.8096-8104.2001</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">115054</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 11483755?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11483755</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourhy</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>The evolutionary history and dynamics of bat rabies virus.</article-title>
<source><italic>Infect Genet Evol.</italic></source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>464</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meegid.2006.02.007</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16621724?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16621724</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woelk</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Reduced positive selection in vector-borne RNA viruses.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mol Biol Evol.</italic></source>
<year>2002</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2333</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.molbev.a004059</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 12446826?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12446826</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuzmina</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuzmin</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellison</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>A reassessment of the evolutionary timescale of bat rabies viruses based upon glycoprotein gene sequences.</article-title>
<source><italic>Virus Genes.</italic></source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>305</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11262-013-0952-9</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23839669?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23839669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Streicker</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Altizer</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Velasco-Villa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Variable evolutionary routes to host establishment across repeated rabies virus host shifts among bats.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.</italic></source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>109</volume>(<issue>48</issue>):<fpage>19715</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1203456109</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23150575?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23150575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Markotter</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Randles</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rupprecht</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Lagos bat virus, South Africa.</article-title>
<source><italic>Emerg Infect Dis.</italic></source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>504</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3291461</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 16704795?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16704795</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuzmin</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name><name><surname>Niezgoda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Franka</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Lagos bat virus in Kenya.</article-title>
<source><italic>J Clin Microbiol.</italic></source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1451</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.00016-08</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2292963</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 18305130?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18305130</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Streicker</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Turmelle</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Vonhof</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Host phylogeny constrains cross-species emergence and establishment of rabies virus in bats.</article-title>
<source><italic>Science.</italic></source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>329</volume>(<issue>5992</issue>):<fpage>676</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1188836</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20689015?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20689015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuzmin</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Orciari</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Molecular inferences suggest multiple host shifts of rabies viruses from bats to mesocarnivores in Arizona during 2001&#x02013;2009.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS Pathog.</italic></source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e1002786</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002786</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22737076?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22737076</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Orciari</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rupprecht</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Evolutionary timescale of rabies virus adaptation to North American bats inferred from the substitution rate of the nucleoprotein gene.</article-title>
<source><italic>J Gen Virol.</italic></source>
<year>2005</year>;<volume>86</volume>(<issue>Pt 5</issue>):<fpage>1467</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/vir.0.80710-0</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15831959?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15831959</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nadin-Davis</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mousse</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Spatial and temporal dynamics of rabies virus variants in big brown bat populations across Canada: footprints of an emerging zoonosis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mol Ecol.</italic></source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2120</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2010.04630.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20406385?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20406385</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wertheim</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Kosakovsky Pond</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Purifying selection can obscure the ancient age of viral lineages.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mol Biol Evol.</italic></source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>3355</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msr170</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3247791</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 21705379?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21705379</pub-id></mixed-citation><note><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://f1000.com/prime/12604956">F1000 Recommendation</ext-link>
</p></note></ref><ref id="ref-24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wertheim</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Peiris</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>A case for the ancient origin of coronaviruses.</article-title>
<source><italic>J Virol.</italic></source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>87</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>7039</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>45</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.03273-12</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3676139</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 23596293?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23596293</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duch&#x000ea;ne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Duch&#x000ea;ne</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>The Performance of the Date-Randomization Test in Phylogenetic Analyses of Time-Structured Virus Data.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mol Biol Evol.</italic></source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1895</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>906</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msv056</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25771196?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25771196</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanfear</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bromham</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Time-dependent rates of molecular evolution.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mol Ecol.</italic></source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>3087</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>101</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2011.05178.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21740474?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21740474</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Complexities of Estimating Evolutionary Rates in Viruses.</article-title>
<source><italic>J Virol.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>90</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>2155</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.02570-15</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4734009</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 26822594?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26822594</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rupprecht</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Turmelle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuzmin</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>A perspective on lyssavirus emergence and perpetuation.</article-title>
<source><italic>Curr Opin Virol.</italic></source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>662</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.coviro.2011.10.014</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22440925?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22440925</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nadin-Davis</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Real</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Molecular phylogenetics of the lyssaviruses--insights from a coalescent approach.</article-title>
<source><italic>Adv Virus Res.</italic></source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>203</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-387040-7.00011-1</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21601049?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21601049</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuzmin</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name><name><surname>Tordo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Genus Lyssavirus</article-title>. In: Dietzgen RD, Kuzmin IV, editors.
<italic>Rhabdoviruses: Molecular taxonomy, evolution, genomics, ecology, host&#x02013;vector interactions, cytopathology and control</italic> London, UK: Caister Academic Press;<year>2012</year>;<fpage>37</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://books.google.co.in/books?id=2qjuL6MgBp4C&#x00026;lpg=PA1&#x00026;ots=dSKFGqz73y&#x00026;dq=Rhabdoviruses%3A%20Molecular%20taxonomy%2C%20evolution%2C%20genomics%2C%20ecology%2C%20host%E2%80%93vector%20interactions%2C%20cytopathology%20and%20control&#x00026;pg=PA37#v=onepage&#x00026;q&#x00026;f=false">Reference Source</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eick</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthee</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>A nuclear DNA phylogenetic perspective on the evolution of echolocation and historical biogeography of extant bats (chiroptera).</article-title>
<source><italic>Mol Biol Evol.</italic></source>
<year>2005</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1869</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>86</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msi180</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15930153?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15930153</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simmons</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name><name><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Habersetzer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Primitive Early Eocene bat from Wyoming and the evolution of flight and echolocation.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nature.</italic></source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>451</volume>(<issue>7180</issue>):<fpage>818</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature06549</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18270539?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18270539</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arnason</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Adegoke</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gullberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Mitogenomic relationships of placental mammals and molecular estimates of their divergences.</article-title>
<source><italic>Gene.</italic></source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>421</volume>(<issue>1&#x02013;2</issue>):<fpage>37</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gene.2008.05.024</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18590805?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18590805</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raup</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sepkoski</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Mass extinctions in the marine fossil record.</article-title>
<source><italic>Science.</italic></source>
<year>1982</year>;<volume>215</volume>(<issue>4539</issue>):<fpage>1501</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.215.4539.1501</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17788674?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17788674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aiewsakun</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Katzourakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Endogenous viruses: Connecting recent and ancient viral evolution.</article-title>
<source><italic>Virology.</italic></source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>479&#x02013;480</volume>:<fpage>26</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virol.2015.02.011</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25771486?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25771486</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaves</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Achkar</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva Ade</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Monoclonal antibodies for characterization of rabies virus isolated from non-hematophagous bats in Brazil.</article-title>
<source><italic>J Infect Dev Ctries.</italic></source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1238</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>49</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3855/jidc.6959</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26623633?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26623633</pub-id></mixed-citation><note><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://f1000.com/prime/727277685">F1000 Recommendation</ext-link>
</p></note></ref><ref id="ref-37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>OIE</collab>:
<article-title>Manual of Diagnostic Tests and Vaccines for Terrestrial Animals 2016, chapter 2.1.17 rabies</article-title>. (accessed 10/26/2016).
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.oie.int/fileadmin/Home/eng/Health_standards/tahm/2.01.17_RABIES.pdf">Reference Source</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mallewa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vallely</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Faragher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Viral CNS infections in children from a malaria-endemic area of Malawi: a prospective cohort study.</article-title>
<source><italic>Lancet Glob Health.</italic></source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e153</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2214-109X(13)70060-3</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3986031</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 24748325?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24748325</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dato</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Campagnolo</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>A Systematic Review of Human Bat Rabies Virus Variant Cases: Evaluating Unprotected Physical Contact with Claws and Teeth in Support of Accurate Risk Assessments.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS One.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>e0159443</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0159443</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4961291</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 27459720?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27459720</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>McGuone</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jindal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Phylogenetic and epidemiologic evidence of multiyear incubation in human rabies.</article-title>
<source><italic>Ann Neurol.</italic></source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>155</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ana.24016</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4118733</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 24038455?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24038455</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savadogo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Boushab</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>[Rabies in children: an often unknown risk among populations at risk].</article-title>
<source><italic>Med Sante Trop.</italic></source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>222</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1684/mst.2015.0449</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26039715?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26039715</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Probable Rabies Virus Transmission through Organ Transplantation, China, 2015.</article-title>
<source><italic>Emerg Infect Dis.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1348</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid2208.151993</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4982156</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 27331337?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27331337</pub-id></mixed-citation><note><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://f1000.com/prime/726591108">F1000 Recommendation</ext-link>
</p></note></ref><ref id="ref-43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>FY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Government Response to the Discovery of a Rabies Virus Reservoir Species on a Previously Designated Rabies-Free Island, Taiwan, 1999&#x02013;2014.</article-title>
<source><italic>Zoonoses Public Health.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>63</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>396</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>402</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/zph.12240</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26542085?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26542085</pub-id></mixed-citation><note><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://f1000.com/prime/727277686">F1000 Recommendation</ext-link>
</p></note></ref><ref id="ref-44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruszynski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Rabies in a Dog Imported from Egypt with a Falsified Rabies Vaccination Certificate--Virginia, 2015.</article-title>
<source><italic>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep.</italic></source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>49</issue>):<fpage>1359</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>62</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm6449a2</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26678293?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26678293</pub-id></mixed-citation><note><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://f1000.com/prime/726023239">F1000 Recommendation</ext-link>
</p></note></ref><ref id="ref-45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rupprecht</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagarajan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ertl</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Current Status and Development of Vaccines and Other Biologics for Human Rabies Prevention.</article-title>
<source><italic>Expert Rev Vaccines.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>731</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>49</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1586/14760584.2016.1140040</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26796599?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26796599</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giesen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gniel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Malerczyk</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>30 Years of rabies vaccination with Rabipur: a summary of clinical data and global experience.</article-title>
<source><italic>Expert Rev Vaccines.</italic></source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>351</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1586/14760584.2015.1011134</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25683583?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25683583</pub-id></mixed-citation><note><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://f1000.com/prime/727277691">F1000 Recommendation</ext-link>
</p></note></ref><ref id="ref-47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pichon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Guinet-Morlot</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Minutello</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>A serum-free, purified vero cell rabies vaccine is safe and as immunogenic as the reference vaccine Verorab for pre-exposure use in healthy adults: results from a randomized controlled phase-II trial.</article-title>
<source><italic>Vaccine.</italic></source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>18</issue>):<fpage>2295</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>301</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2013.02.058</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23510665?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23510665</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rupprecht</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Use of a reduced (4-dose) vaccine schedule for postexposure prophylaxis to prevent human rabies: recommendations of the advisory committee on immunization practices.</article-title>
<source><italic>MMWR Recomm Rep.</italic></source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>RR-2</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 20300058?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20300058</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bharti</surname><given-names>OK</given-names></name><name><surname>Madhusudana</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaunta</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Local infiltration of rabies immunoglobulins without systemic intramuscular administration: An alternative cost effective approach for passive immunization against rabies.</article-title>
<source><italic>Hum Vaccin Immunother.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>837</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/21645515.2015.1085142</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4964710</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 26317441?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26317441</pub-id></mixed-citation><note><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://f1000.com/prime/725763090">F1000 Recommendation</ext-link>
</p></note></ref><ref id="ref-50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bose</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Munshi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tripathy</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>A randomized non-inferiority clinical study to assess post-exposure prophylaxis by a new purified vero cell rabies vaccine (Rabivax-S) administered by intramuscular and intradermal routes.</article-title>
<source><italic>Vaccine.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>40</issue>):<fpage>4820</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2016.08.005</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27554534?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27554534</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Benedictis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Minola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rota Nodari</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Development of broad-spectrum human monoclonal antibodies for rabies post-exposure prophylaxis.</article-title>
<source><italic>EMBO Mol Med.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>407</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/emmm.201505986</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4818751</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 26992832?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26992832</pub-id></mixed-citation><note><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://f1000.com/prime/726227015">F1000 Recommendation</ext-link>
</p></note></ref><ref id="ref-52"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madhusudana</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashwin</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name><name><surname>Sudarshan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Feasibility of reducing rabies immunoglobulin dosage for passive immunization against rabies: results of
<italic>In vitro</italic> and
<italic>In vivo</italic> studies.</article-title>
<source><italic>Hum Vaccin Immunother.</italic></source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1914</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/hv.25431</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3906356</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 23792347?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23792347</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-53"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morimoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Khawplod</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Rabies vaccination at a virus-inoculated site as an alternative option to rabies immunoglobulin.</article-title>
<source><italic>Arch Virol.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>161</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2537</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00705-016-2916-6</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27270361?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27270361</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-54"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Zagreb regimen, an abbreviated intramuscular schedule for rabies vaccination.</article-title>
<source><italic>Clin Vaccine Immunol.</italic></source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CVI.00531-14</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4278924</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 25392012?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25392012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-55"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reveneau</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cottin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasuli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Two decades of pharmacovigilance and clinical experience with highly purified rabies immunoglobulin F(ab')
<sub>2</sub> fragments.</article-title>
<source><italic>Expert Rev Vaccines.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14760584.2017.1244009</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27809689?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27809689</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-56"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilde</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lumlertdacha</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Meslin</surname><given-names>FX</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Worldwide rabies deaths prevention--A focus on the current inadequacies in postexposure prophylaxis of animal bite victims.</article-title>
<source><italic>Vaccine.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>187</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2015.11.036</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26626211?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26626211</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-57"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wongsaroj</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Udomchaisakul</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tepsumethanon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Rabies neutralizing antibody after 2 intradermal doses on days 0 and 21 for pre-exposure prophylaxis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Vaccine.</italic></source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>1748</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2013.01.035</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23370149?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23370149</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-58"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Ineffectiveness of rabies vaccination alone for post-exposure protection against rabies infection in animal models.</article-title>
<source><italic>Antiviral Res.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>135</volume>:<fpage>56</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.antiviral.2016.10.002</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27737787?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27737787</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-59"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warrell</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>The dilemma of managing human rabies encephalitis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Trop Med Int Health.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>456</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tmi.12668</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26799263?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26799263</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-60"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Appolinario</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Antiviral therapy for human rabies.</article-title>
<source><italic>Antivir Ther.</italic></source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3851/IMP2851</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25156675?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25156675</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-61"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Willoughby</surname><given-names>RE</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Tieves</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Survival after treatment of rabies with induction of coma.</article-title>
<source><italic>N Engl J Med.</italic></source>
<year>2005</year>;<volume>352</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>2508</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa050382</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15958806?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15958806</pub-id></mixed-citation><note><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://f1000.com/prime/8176">F1000 Recommendation</ext-link>
</p></note></ref><ref id="ref-62"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeiler</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Critical Appraisal of the Milwaukee Protocol for Rabies: This Failed Approach Should Be Abandoned.</article-title>
<source><italic>Can J Neurol Sci.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>44</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/cjn.2015.331</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26639059?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26639059</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-63"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manoj</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Johri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Recovery from rabies, a universally fatal disease.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mil Med Res.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40779-016-0089-y</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4947331</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 27429788?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27429788</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-64"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahadevan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Suja</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mani</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Perspectives in Diagnosis and Treatment of Rabies Viral Encephalitis: Insights from Pathogenesis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Neurotherapeutics.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>477</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13311-016-0452-4</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4965414</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 27324391?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27324391</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-65"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>Pan American Health Organization</collab>:
<article-title>Elimination of dog-transmitted human rabies is by 2015 within reach</article-title>. PAHO,<year>2013</year>; (accessed 09/27/2016).
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.paho.org/hq/index.php?option=com_content&#x00026;view=article&#x00026;id=9047%3A2013-elimination-dog-transmitted-human-rabies-americas-2015-within-reach-experts-say&#x00026;catid=740%3Apress-releases&#x00026;Itemid=1926&#x00026;lang=en">Reference Source</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-66"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>World Health Organization</collab>:
<article-title>Sustaining the drive to overcome the global impact of neglected tropical diseases, second report on neglected tropical diseases</article-title>. World Health Organization, Geneva,<year>2012</year>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/10665/80245/1/WHO_HTM_NTD_2013.2_eng.pdf">Reference Source</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-67"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>World Health Organization</collab>:
<article-title>Accelerating work to overcome the global impact of neglected tropical diseases: a roadmap for implementation. Executive summary</article-title>. World Health Organization. Geneva,<year>2012</year>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/10665/70809/1/WHO_HTM_NTD_2012.1_eng.pdf">Reference Source</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-68"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>World Health Organization</collab>:
<article-title>Global elimination of dog-mediated human rabies</article-title>.
<italic>Report of the Global Conference, 10&#x02013;11 December 2015</italic> World Health Organization and World Animal Health Organization,<year>2016</year> WHO_HTM_NTD_NZD_ 2016.02.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/10665/204621/1/WHO_HTM_NTD_NZD_2016.02_eng.pdf">Reference Source</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-69"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>World Health Organization</collab>:
<article-title>Resolution WHA66.12 on NTD adopted by the World Health Assembly on 27 May 2013</article-title>. (accessed 10/12/2016).
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/neglected_diseases/WHA_66_seventh_day_resolution_adopted/en/">Reference Source</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-70"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hampson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Coudeville</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lembo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Estimating the global burden of endemic canine rabies.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS Negl Trop Dis.</italic></source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e0003709</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0003709</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4400070</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 25881058?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25881058</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-71"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dehove</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>OIE regional vaccine banks</article-title>.
<italic>Presentation made to the Middle East &#x00026; Eastern Europe Rabies Expert Bureau Meeting (MEEREB)</italic>7&#x02013;9 April 2015, Lyon, France; (accessed 09/27/2016).
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.fondation-merieux.org/documents/en/conference-resources/2015/3rd-meereb-meeting/current-oie-recommendations-for-rabies-control-in-alain-dehove.pdf">Reference Source</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-72"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>OIE</collab>:
<article-title>Regional Vaccine Bank for Asia provides 50,000 rabies vaccine doses to Lao PDR. </article-title>OIE Press releases, 28 September 2012; (accessed 09/27/2016).
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.oie.int/for-the-media/press-releases/detail/article/oie-regional-vaccine-bank-for-asia-provides-50000-rabies-vaccines-to-lao-pdr/">Reference Source</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-73"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abela-Ridder</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gongal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Rabies vaccine stockpile: fixing the supply chain.</article-title>
<source><italic>Bull World Health Organ.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>94</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>635</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>635A</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2471/BLT.16.183012</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5034646</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 27708465?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27708465</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-74"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>World Health Organization</collab>:
<article-title>Human and dog rabies vaccines and immunoglobulins report of a WHO/OIE meeting</article-title>. Geneva 12&#x02013;13 October 2015. WHO/HTM/NTD/NZD/2015.11.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/10665/199176/1/WHO_HTM_NTD_NZD_2015.11_eng.pdf">Reference Source</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-75"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>CDC</collab>:
<article-title>Compendium of animal rabies prevention and control</article-title>. NASPHV Recommendations and Report, MMWR.<year>2011</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/pdf/rr/rr6006.pdf">Reference Source</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-76"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Belotto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ad&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Current status of human rabies transmitted by dogs in Latin America.</article-title>
<source><italic>Cad Saude Publica.</italic></source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2049</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0102-311X2007000900013</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17700940?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17700940</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-77"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vigilato</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Clavijo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Knobl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Progress towards eliminating canine rabies: policies and perspectives from Latin America and the Caribbean.</article-title>
<source><italic>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci.</italic></source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>368</volume>(<issue>1623</issue>):<fpage>20120143</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2012.0143</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3720041</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 23798691?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23798691</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-78"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>World Health Organization</collab>:
<article-title>Vaccine standards</article-title>.<year>2016</year>; (accessed 10/26/2016).
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/immunization_standards/vaccine_quality/PQ_vaccine_list_en/en/">Reference Source</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-79"><label>79</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>Partners For Rabies Prevention</collab>:
<article-title>Human:dog ratios obtained from detailed studies in a range of rural and urban settings</article-title>. In
<italic>Canines rabies blueprint</italic> (accessed 10/06/2016).
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://caninerabiesblueprint.org/IMG/pdf/Link46_HumanDogRatios.pdf">Reference Source</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-80"><label>80</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knobel</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cleaveland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Re-evaluating the burden of rabies in Africa and Asia.</article-title>
<source><italic>Bull World Health Organ.</italic></source>
<year>2005</year>;<volume>83</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>360</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2626230</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 15976877?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15976877</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-81"><label>81</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sudarshan</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Madhusudana</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahendra</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Assessing the burden of human rabies in India: results of a national multi-center epidemiological survey.</article-title>
<source><italic>Int J Infect Dis.</italic></source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>29</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>35</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2005.10.007</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16678463?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16678463</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-82"><label>82</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000f6;gel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Meslin</surname><given-names>FX</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Economics of human and canine rabies elimination: guidelines for programme orientation.</article-title>
<source><italic>Bull World Health Organ.</italic></source>
<year>1990</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>281</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>.
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2393068</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 2118428?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2118428</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-83"><label>83</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>FAO</collab>:
<article-title>Developing a stepwise approach for rabies prevention and control</article-title>.
<italic>FAO/GARC workshop</italic> FAO Animal Production and Health Proceedings, No 18, Rome, Italy.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/3/a-i3467e.pdf">Reference Source</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-84"><label>84</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>Partners For Rabies Prevention</collab>:
<article-title>Blueprint for dog rabies control</article-title>. (accessed 10/06/2016).
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rabiesblueprint.org/">Reference Source</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-85"><label>85</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>World Health Organization</collab>:
<article-title>Report of the 4th meeting of the international coordination group of the Gates Foundation/WHO project for human and dog rabies elimination in low-income countries</article-title>. 19&#x02013;21 October 2011, PieterMartizburg, KwaZuluNatal, South Africa. Geneva, World Health Organization,<year>2011</year>; (accessed 10/06/2016).
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/rabies/bmgf_who-project/en">Reference Source</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-86"><label>86</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zinsstag</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000fc;rr</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Penny</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Transmission dynamics and economics of rabies control in dogs and humans in an African city.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.</italic></source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>106</volume>(<issue>35</issue>):<fpage>14996</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5001</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0904740106</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2728111</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 19706492?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19706492</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-87"><label>87</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>World Health Organization</collab>:
<article-title>Educate, vaccinate, eliminate: Achieving zero human deaths from dog- transmitted rabies by 2030</article-title>. Joint Statement World Health Organization (WHO), World Organisation for Animal Health (OIE), Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO), 28 September 2016 | Geneva; (accessed 10/26/2016).
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/rabies/WRD_2016_WHO_FAO_OIE_Joint_statement/en/">Reference Source</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-88"><label>88</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>NCDC</collab>:
<article-title>National Rabies Prevention &#x00026; Control Pilot Projects in Ahmedabad, Bangalore, Pune, Madurai and Delhi under the 11th five year plan [2007 &#x02013; 2012] and National Rabies Control Programme under the 12th five year plan (2012&#x02013;17)</article-title>. Zoonoses Section, National Centre for Disease Control (NCDC), Delhi, India.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-89"><label>89</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Molloy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>China to crackdown on pet dogs</article-title>. (accessed 10/13/2016).
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/asia/chinas-crackdown-on-pet-dogs-9238594.html">Reference Source</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-90"><label>90</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dietzschold</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ertl</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Development of a mouse monoclonal antibody cocktail for post-exposure rabies prophylaxis in humans.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS Negl Trop Dis.</italic></source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e542</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000542</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2765635</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 19888334?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19888334</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-91"><label>91</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halstead</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Vaccines are forever. A short history of the Rockefeller Foundation/WHO Rabies Vaccine Production Technology Transfer Project</article-title>.
<italic>Presented at the occasion of the inauguration of VECOL rabies vaccine production unit, Bogota, Columbia</italic> 1/25/<year>2002</year>; (accessed 1/23/2017).
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bariconsultants.com/attachments/Vaccines%20r%20Forever.pdf">Reference Source</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-92"><label>92</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>One Health approach to cost-effective rabies control in India.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>113</volume>(<issue>51</issue>):<fpage>14574</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1604975113</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5187709</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 27994161?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27994161</pub-id></mixed-citation><note><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://f1000.com/prime/727127628">F1000 Recommendation</ext-link>
</p></note></ref><ref id="ref-93"><label>93</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>The evolution of
<italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic>: the 'bat seeding' hypothesis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Trends Parasitol.</italic></source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>136</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pt.2012.01.006</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22365905?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22365905</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-94"><label>94</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mani</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Anand</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Madhusudana</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Human rabies in India: an audit from a rabies diagnostic laboratory.</article-title>
<source><italic>Trop Med Int Health.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>556</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tmi.12669</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26799375?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26799375</pub-id></mixed-citation><note><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://f1000.com/prime/726264633">F1000 Recommendation</ext-link>
</p></note></ref><ref id="ref-95"><label>95</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madhusudana</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Subha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Thankappan</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Evaluation of a direct rapid immunohistochemical test (dRIT) for rapid diagnosis of rabies in animals and humans.</article-title>
<source><italic>Virol Sin.</italic></source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>299</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>302</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12250-012-3265-6</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23055005?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23055005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-96"><label>96</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carrieri</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Peixoto</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></name><name><surname>Paciencia</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Laboratory diagnosis of equine rabies and its implications for human postexposure prophylaxis.</article-title>
<source><italic>J Virol Methods.</italic></source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>138</volume>(<issue>1&#x02013;2</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jviromet.2006.07.005</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16919789?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16919789</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-97"><label>97</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000e9;chenne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Na&#x000ef;ssengar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lepelletier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Validation of a Rapid Rabies Diagnostic Tool for Field Surveillance in Developing Countries.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS Negl Trop Dis.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e0005010</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0005010</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5051951</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 27706156?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27706156</pub-id></mixed-citation><note><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://f1000.com/prime/726814193">F1000 Recommendation</ext-link>
</p></note></ref><ref id="ref-98"><label>98</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eggerbauer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>de Benedictis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Evaluation of Six Commercially Available Rapid Immunochromatographic Tests for the Diagnosis of Rabies in Brain Material.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS Negl Trop Dis.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e0004776</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004776</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4918935</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 27336943?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27336943</pub-id></mixed-citation><note><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://f1000.com/prime/726443512">F1000 Recommendation</ext-link>
</p></note></ref><ref id="ref-99"><label>99</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ngoepe</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fehlner-Gardiner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wandeler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Antigenic characterisation of lyssaviruses in South Africa.</article-title>
<source><italic>Onderstepoort J Vet Res.</italic></source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>81</volume>(<issue>1</issue>).
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4102/ojvr.v81i1.711</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25685866?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25685866</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-100"><label>100</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pratt</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Henschel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Turabelidze</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Human Rabies - Missouri, 2014.</article-title>
<source><italic>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>253</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm6510a1</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26985578?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26985578</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-101"><label>101</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dacheux</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Larrous</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavenir</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Dual Combined Real-Time Reverse Transcription Polymerase Chain Reaction Assay for the Diagnosis of Lyssavirus Infection.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS Negl Trop Dis.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>e0004812</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004812</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4933377</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 27380028?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27380028</pub-id></mixed-citation><note><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://f1000.com/prime/726485110">F1000 Recommendation</ext-link>
</p></note></ref><ref id="ref-102"><label>102</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wasniewski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Baur</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>First international collaborative study to evaluate rabies antibody detection method for use in monitoring the effectiveness of oral vaccination programmes in fox and raccoon dog in Europe.</article-title>
<source><italic>J Virol Methods.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>238</volume>:<fpage>77</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>85</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jviromet.2016.10.006</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27751949?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27751949</pub-id></mixed-citation><note><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://f1000.com/prime/727277690">F1000 Recommendation</ext-link>
</p></note></ref><ref id="ref-103"><label>103</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brunker</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Marston</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Elucidating the phylodynamics of endemic rabies virus in eastern Africa using whole-genome sequencing.</article-title>
<source><italic>Virus Evol.</italic></source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>vev011</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ve/vev011</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5014479</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 27774283?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27774283</pub-id></mixed-citation><note><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://f1000.com/prime/726959560">F1000 Recommendation</ext-link>
</p></note></ref><ref id="ref-104"><label>104</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borucki</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen-Harris</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lao</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Ultra-deep sequencing of intra-host rabies virus populations during cross-species transmission.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS Negl Trop Dis.</italic></source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e2555</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0002555</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3836733</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 24278493?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24278493</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-105"><label>105</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tarantola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Crabol</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahendra</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Caring for patients with rabies in developing countries - the neglected importance of palliative care.</article-title>
<source><italic>Trop Med Int Health.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>564</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tmi.12670</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26806229?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26806229</pub-id></mixed-citation><note><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://f1000.com/prime/726264632">F1000 Recommendation</ext-link>
</p></note></ref><ref id="ref-106"><label>106</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Willoughby</surname><given-names>RE</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group>:
<article-title>Rabies: Rare Human Infection - Common Questions.</article-title>
<source><italic>Infect Dis Clin North Am.</italic></source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>637</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.idc.2015.07.006</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26384549?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26384549</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-107"><label>107</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pathak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Diagnosis, management and post-mortem findings of a human case of rabies imported into the United Kingdom from India: a case report.</article-title>
<source><italic>Virol J.</italic></source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>63</fpage>.
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3977668</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 24708671?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24708671</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-108"><label>108</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>ZQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ertl</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Protection of non-human primates against rabies with an adenovirus recombinant vaccine.</article-title>
<source><italic>Virology.</italic></source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>450&#x02013;451</volume>:<fpage>243</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virol.2013.12.029</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4038128</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 24503087?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24503087</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-109"><label>109</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Enhancement of blood-brain barrier permeability is required for intravenously administered virus neutralizing antibodies to clear an established rabies virus infection from the brain and prevent the development of rabies in mice.</article-title>
<source><italic>Antiviral Res.</italic></source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>110</volume>:<fpage>132</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.antiviral.2014.07.013</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4171353</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 25108172?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25108172</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-110"><label>110</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchicio</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>PyNTTTTGT and CpG immunostimulatory oligonucleotides: effect on granulocyte/monocyte colony-stimulating factor (GM-CSF) secretion by human CD56
<sup>+</sup> (NK and NKT) cells.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS One.</italic></source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e0117484</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0117484</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4338301</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 25706946?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25706946</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-111"><label>111</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Virojanapirom</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lumlertdacha</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wipattanakitchareon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>T-705 as a Potential Therapeutic Agent for Rabies.</article-title>
<source><italic>J Infect Dis.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>214</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>502</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiw174</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27190188?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27190188</pub-id></mixed-citation><note><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://f1000.com/prime/726364353">F1000 Recommendation</ext-link>
</p></note></ref><ref id="ref-112"><label>112</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lingappa</surname><given-names>UF</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Macieik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Host-rabies virus protein-protein interactions as druggable antiviral targets.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.</italic></source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>110</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>E861</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1210198110</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3593902</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 23404707?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23404707</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-113"><label>113</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gnanadurai</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>ZF</given-names></name></person-group>:
<article-title>CXCL10 and blood-brain barrier modulation in rabies virus infection.</article-title>
<source><italic>Oncotarget.</italic></source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>10694</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.7428</pub-id>
<!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4905431</pub-id>-->
<?supplied-pmid 26895109?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26895109</pub-id></mixed-citation><note><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://f1000.com/prime/726325191">F1000 Recommendation</ext-link>
</p></note></ref><ref id="ref-114"><label>114</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Willoughby</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Opladen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Tetrahydrobiopterin deficiency in human rabies.</article-title>
<source><italic>J Inherit Metab Dis.</italic></source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>65</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10545-008-0949-z</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18949578?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18949578</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-115"><label>115</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kammouni</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Saleh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>:
<article-title>Rabies virus phosphoprotein interacts with mitochondrial Complex I and induces mitochondrial dysfunction and oxidative stress.</article-title>
<source><italic>J Neurovirol.</italic></source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>370</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13365-015-0320-8</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25698500?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25698500</pub-id></mixed-citation><note><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://f1000.com/prime/727277693">F1000 Recommendation</ext-link>
</p></note></ref></ref-list></back></article>