<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0030">ACE2 is the receptor for SARS-CoV, but following the identification of several SARS-like CoVs (SL-CoVs) in horseshoe bats (genus 
 <italic>Rhinophus</italic>) the ACE2 molecule of 
 <italic>R. pearsonii</italic> proved incapable of serving a receptor for SARS-CoV [
 <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0165" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. These and other initial studies suggested that the ancestral SARS-CoV strain in bats used an alternate receptor and that the emergence of SARS-CoV was dependent upon either acquisition of an ACE2 binding region or initial utilization of an alternative human receptor [
 <xref rid="bib0165" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. However, while human ACE2 is genetically conserved, the bat ACE2 sequences are highly heterogeneous, with 78–84% amino acid identity between families [
 <xref rid="bib0170" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0175" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Despite this heterogeneity, the residues that interface with the SARS Spike–receptor binding domain (RBD) are more conserved [
 <xref rid="bib0180" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. A recent study determined that a minimum three substitutions in the ACE2 of 
 <italic>R. pearsonii</italic> (RpACE2) allowed this protein to serve as a receptor for SARS [
 <xref rid="bib0185" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Looking more broadly at the ACE2 molecules from seven bat species, the ACE2 proteins from 
 <italic>Myotis daubentoni</italic> and 
 <italic>Rhinolophus sinicus</italic> are capable of supporting Spike-mediated pseudovirus and SARS-CoV infection, though less efficiently than human ACE2 [
 <xref rid="bib0170" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Assessment of receptor usage by early phase and civet isolate Spike proteins might better inform our understanding of emergence pathways, determining if SL-CoV jumped directly from bat to human hosts or whether civet or other intermediate hosts were required as early intermediates before human adaptation.
</p>
