<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Moreover, sequencing of complete genome of 
 <italic>Homo sapiens neanderthalensis </italic>is underway [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B215">215</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B216">216</xref>] and could give interesting data concerning the origin of the null allele. Indeed, as Neanderthals are the extinct hominid species most closely related to contemporary humans, the continuation of the Neanderthal genome project provides a unique opportunity to identify genetic changes that are specific to modern humans [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B215">215</xref>]. Dating such genomic events would help to interpret these changes mechanistically. In addition to the different methods of age estimation based on allele frequencies and sequence comparison between species, conclusive data from the analysis of prehistoric remains of members of the genus 
 <italic>Homo </italic>(e.g. from humans and Neanderthals) would help to date such events by determining the presence and frequency of genomic variants. Moreover, Currat and Excoffier [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B217">217</xref>] using a method, which assumed environmental homogeneity, have simulated the range expansion of modern humans into Europe under realistic demographic scenarios to investigate potential admixture between colonizing humans and resident Neanderthals. Their simulations indicated that even with only a few admixture events, the contribution of Neanderthal genes to the current human gene pool should be large because new genes (which have a Neanderthal origin) have a high probability of persistence when entering a progressively expanding (modern human) population compared with those entering a stationary population. In a recent review, Hodgson and Disotell [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B218">218</xref>] have concluded that "it seems unlikely that Neanderthals contributed any substantial fraction of modern variation and it remains to be seen whether any adaptive alleles crossed the human-Neanderthal species boundary". Moreover, more recent major events in human evolution, such as the re-colonization of northern latitudes after the Ice Ages, could also be taken into account.
</p>
