<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>All movie frames were aligned using MotionCor2 (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>) and particles were picked automatically using Warp (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). The motion-corrected micrographs were imported in Relion 3.0 (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>) and used for contrast transfer function (CTF) parameter calculation with gctf (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). The particles were extracted using coordinates from Warp (∼780 000) and subjected to two iterative rounds of reference-free 2D classification. Selected 2D classes representing the different projection views (575 157 particles) were initially classified into six 3D classes with image alignment using an 
 <italic>ab initio</italic> volume created in cisTEM (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>) and low-pass filtered to 40 Å, as a reference. The 3D classification with regularization parameter 
 <italic>T</italic> = 4 was performed with 7.5° angular sampling for the first 25 iterations followed by 10 additional iterations using 3.7° angular sampling. One major class was identified as the most populated (223 604 particles) and better defined class, and was selected for auto-refinement and post-processing in Relion resulting in a 3D electron density map (SFTSV map A) with an estimated resolution of 3.8 Å using gold standard Fourier Shell Correlation (0.143 cut-off). The globally refined volume was then used as a template to sort particles again into 10 new 3D classes. This time a distinct class was visible containing additional volume for the C-terminal region (73 357 particles). This class submitted to auto-refine and post-processing and yielded a 3D EM map of 4.3 Å estimated resolution. The model was built 
 <italic>de novo</italic> into SFTSV map A by the Map-to-model program included in Phenix (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>) using the core domain of LACV L protein structure (PDB: 5AMQ) as a starting model. The structure was refined by iterative cycles of manual model building in Coot (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>) and computational optimization with PHENIX (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>).
</p>
