<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Emerging viral infections represent a threat to global health, and the recent outbreak of novel coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) caused by severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2, novel coronavirus, 2019-nCoV) exemplifies the risks (
 <xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>1</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>2</italic>
 </xref>). As viruses are obligate intracellular parasites, organisms have evolved innate immune mechanisms to sense and counter the viruses. Among these mechanisms, RNA and DNA editing mediated by endogenous deaminases can provide a potent defense against specific viruses. Two deaminase families are present in mammalian species: The ADARs (adenosine deaminases that act on RNA) target double-stranded RNA (dsRNA) for deamination of adenines into inosines (A-to-I) (
 <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>3</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>4</italic>
 </xref>), and the APOBECs deaminate cytosines into uracils (C-to-U) on single-stranded nucleic acids [single-stranded DNA (ssDNA) and single-stranded RNA (ssRNA)] (
 <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>5</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>6</italic>
 </xref>). During viral infections, ADARs act either directly, through hypermutation of the viral RNA, or indirectly, through editing of host transcripts that modulate the cellular response (
 <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>7</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>18</italic>
 </xref>). On the other hand, APOBECs target the viral genome, typically DNA intermediates (
 <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>19</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>26</italic>
 </xref>), either through C-to-U hypermutation or through a non-enzymatic path that interferes with reverse transcription (
 <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>27</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>28</italic>
 </xref>). Although some APOBEC3 proteins can interfere in vitro with Coronaviridae replication, it is not clear whether their enzymatic activity is involved (
 <xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>29</italic>
 </xref>). Ultimately, though, these restriction systems can also be exploited by the viruses to support their infectivity and increase their evolutionary potential (
 <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>9</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>11</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>15</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>30</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>32</italic>
 </xref>).
</p>
