<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Phylogenetic trees based on the structure of the SLAM and H proteins indicated that they co-evolved [
 <xref rid="B9-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The SLAM receptors have immunoglobulin-like variable (V) and constant-2 (C2) domains in their extracellular regions with the V domain providing an interface for the morbillivirus H glycoprotein [
 <xref rid="B49-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Substitution in the amino acid residues of this interface may lead to a loss of, a reduction in, or an increase in, viral infectivity [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The morbillivirus H glycoprotein displays a strong affinity for this domain in its respective host [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. However, a recent study showed that only one amino acid exchange in H was required for functional adaptation of CDV to the human SLAM cell receptor 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> [
 <xref rid="B50-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. The SLAM receptor has been characterized in seven species of mysticetes and in 19 species of odontocetes [
 <xref rid="B9-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Three-dimensional homology models showed that there are 32 amino acid residues on the interface of cetacean SLAM that may contribute to morbillivirus binding [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The similarity of the 32 residues was higher between the cetacean and cow SLAMs (26 amino acid residues) than between the Pacific white-sided dolphin (
 <italic>Lagenorhynchus obliquidens</italic>) and the spotted seal (
 <italic>Phoca largha</italic>) SLAM (21 amino acid residues) [
 <xref rid="B9-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], as would be expected based on the host relationships. Among the nine cetacean families examined, variations were found between six amino acid residues, with charge alterations for four of them [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Interestingly, three residue substitutions (G68, H90 and H130) that introduced charge alteration and possible change in viral affinity were observed in the SLAM of the Delphinidae, while these residues were mostly conserved in the receptor of the other cetacean families [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. As morbillivirus mass mortalities have mostly been detected in the Delphinidae, it is possible that their SLAMs have a higher affinity for CeMV resulting in increased viral infectivity and dissemination [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Among the Delphinidae, only 
 <italic>T. truncatus</italic>, 
 <italic>T. aduncus</italic> and, 
 <italic>S. coeruleoalba</italic> had variation at position 130 [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and during CeMV outbreaks mass die-offs were overwhelmingly dominated by these species [
 <xref rid="B7-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. The only other odontocete that presented this H130Q variation was 
 <italic>P. phocoena</italic>, a species that was affected by morbillivirus infection in 1988–1990 [
 <xref rid="B53-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Further studies are needed to confirm if the SLAM of dolphins, porpoises and whales is indeed the immune cell receptor for CeMV and should investigate whether alternate potential receptors, such as nectin4 and CD147, are present on the cells of these mammals.
</p>
