<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0016">A synthetic gene 
 <italic>ZIKV-80E</italic>, encoding amino acid (
 <italic>aa</italic>) residues 1-403 of the E protein of ZikaSPH2015, codon-optimised for 
 <italic>P. pastoris</italic> expression, was custom-synthesised by GenScript (New Jersey, USA). 
 <italic>P. pastoris</italic> expression host (strain KM71H) and the 
 <italic>P. pastoris</italic> integrative, expression plasmid, pPICZ-A, were from Invitrogen Life Technologies (Thermo Fisher Scientific), Carlsbad, CA, USA. 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> plasmids for expression of maltose-binding protein (MBP) fusions of ZIKV EDIII 
 <xref rid="bib0048" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref> and DENV EDIIIs 
 <xref rid="bib0049" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref> have been mentioned before. Vero cells (ATCC Cat# CCL-81; RRID: CVCL_0059), and K562 cells (ATCC Cat# CCL-243; RRID: CVCL_0004), from American Type Culture Collection (Manassas, VA, USA), were cultured in Dulbecco's Modified Eagle Medium supplemented with 10% heat-inactivated fetal bovine serum, at 37 °C in a humidified 10% CO
 <sub>2</sub> incubator. ZIKV reporter virus particles (RVPs), containing the structural proteins (prM and E) of ZikaSPH2015, but encoding 
 <italic>Renilla</italic> luciferase replicon, were procured from Integral Molecular, PA, USA. The Uganda 1947 (MR766) and Puerto Rico 2015 (PRVABC59) strains of ZIKV have been described before 
 <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>. DENV-1 (WP 74), DENV-2 (S16803), DENV-2 S221, DENV-3 (CH53489), and DENV-4 (TVP-360) have been described earlier [
 <xref rid="bib0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. mAb 24A12, specific to DENVs 1–3 EDIIIs 
 <xref rid="bib0052" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref> and ZIKV EDIII 
 <xref rid="bib0048" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>, mAb 4G2 
 <xref rid="bib0053" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>, specific to the flavivirus fusion loop epitope (FLE), the ZIKV EDIII-specific murine mAbs 
 <xref rid="bib0031" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, ZV48 (RRID: AB_2725796), ZV-2, and ZV-67 (RRID: AB_2725795) and the human mAb ZKA64 
 <xref rid="bib0032" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref> have also been described earlier. Anti-mouse immunoglobulin (Ig) G-horse radish peroxidase (HRPO) conjugate was from Calbiochem (San Diego, CA, USA) and the HRPO substrate 3, 3′, 5, 5′-Tetramethylbenzidine and acid-washed glass beads were obtained from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, USA). ViviRen Live Cell Substrate was purchased from Promega (WI, USA). Ni
 <sup>2+</sup>-NTA Super-flow resin was obtained from Qiagen (Hilden, Germany). Uranyl acetate and bicinchoninic acid protein assay reagent were from TAAB Laboratories Equipment Ltd (UK) and Thermo Scientific (Rockford, USA), respectively. Alhydrogel was purchased from Brenntag Biosector, Denmark. High binding polystyrene microtitre plates were from Corning Incorporated, NY, USA.
</p>
