<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The COVID-19 replicase gene encoded two polyproteins, pp1a and pp1ab with molecular weight 450 and 750 KD respectively, these polyproteins are required for viral replication and transcription (Wu et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Zhou et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) . In the proteolytic process, the functional polypeptides of spike, membrane, envelop, nucleoprotein, replicase and polymerase are released from polyproteins. This process was carried out by a chymotrypsin-fold proteinase namely main protease (M
 <sup>pro</sup>) (Anand et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>).The M
 <sup>pro</sup> is a vital role in polyprotein processing and virus maturation, hence, it is considered to be an attractive target for antiviral drug design as an approach toward COVID-19 treatment (Anand et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Pillaiyar et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Yang et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). The Chinese scientists have first published the genome and with overseas collaboration have obtained the crystal structure of three-dimensional novel COVID-19 main protease (M
 <sup>pro</sup>) and deposited in the protein data bank (Z. Jin et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). The crystal structure of COVID-19 M
 <sup>pro</sup> has 306 amino acids with the three regions, in the first region represented in blue contains 8-101 residues, second region in green are 102-184 residues and third region in orange are 201-303 residues. The first and third regions have an antiparallel β-sheet structure, third region has five alpha helices arranged into a cluster. The third region is connected to second region through a long loop region contains 185-200 residues. Mass spectroscopy determined the weight of COVID-19 M
 <sup>pro</sup> is 33797.0 Da. Theoretical studies confirmed the weight is 33796.8 Da (Z. Jin et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Furthermore, in the literature, several crystal structure of COVID-19 M
 <sup>pro</sup> (see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0003">Figure 3</xref>) in complex with different inhibitor are deposited in the protein data bank (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pdbj.org/featured/covid-19" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://pdbj.org/featured/covid-19</ext-link>) by using X-ray diffraction technique at resolution between 1.31 Å and 3.084 Å (COVID-19 featured content, 
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). On the other hand, the HIV-1 protease inhibitors, tipranavir, saquinavir, ritonavir, nelfinavir, lopinavir, indinavir, darunavir, atazanavir, and amprenavir are widely reported to be able to deactivate M
 <sup>pro</sup> (Yang et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>).
</p>
