<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There are four major structural proteins in SARS-CoV2 virus: E (envelope protein), M (membrane protein), N (nucleocapsid protein), and S (spike protein).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref54">54</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref55">55</xref>
 </sup> Each protein not only individually plays a role in the virus structure but also is involved in the mechanism of the replication cycle.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref56">56</xref>
 </sup> The smallest and most enigmatic major proteins of CoV viruses is the E protein. During the replication cycle, although a small portion of E protein is incorporated into the virion envelope, it is abundantly expressed inside the infected cell.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref57">57</xref>
 </sup> The primary function of the N protein is to bind to the CoV RNA genome and to form the structure of the nucleocapsid.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref55">55</xref>
 </sup> In addition, of its major role in processes of viral genome, it involves the CoV replication cycle and also the host cellular response to viral infection.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref58">58</xref>
 </sup> The shape of the viral envelop is defined by the M protein.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref59">59</xref>
 </sup> The other function of M protein is its role as the central organizer in CoV assembly through interactions with other major structural proteins.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref60">60</xref>
 </sup> Coronavirus enters into host cells by the attachment of transmembrane spike (S) glycoprotein to the host surface receptor. Also, the S protein mediates the subsequent fusion between the viral and host cell membranes to make the entry of viral cell easier into the host cell.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref57">57</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref61">61</xref>
 </sup> The S protein binds to ACE2, a transmembrane receptor which is widely expressed in the lungs, kidneys, gastrointestinal tissue, and heart.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref62">62</xref>
 </sup> The binding to the host cell receptor and fusion between viral and cellular membranes have been performed with two subunits of the S protein: S1 subunit and S2 subunit, respectively.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref63">63</xref>
 </sup> The S2 subunit contains neutralizing epitopes of the virus, including a conserved fusion peptide, a transmembrane domain, a cytoplasmic domain, and heptad repeats 1 and 2.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref64">64</xref>
 </sup> In the S1 subunit, the core receptor binding domains are highly conserved. The differences in the amino acids are the cause of the direct interaction between spike protein and host cell receptor.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref65">65</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
