<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To calculate the case fatality rate (CFR) of an infection, one must divide the mortality number (M) by all those who were infected. The total number of those infected includes those who were infected and recovered without presentation (I
 <sub>r</sub>), infected and presented to a health care facility (I
 <sub>p</sub>), and infected and died (I
 <sub>d</sub>). The CFR would be M/(I
 <sub>r</sub> + I
 <sub>p</sub> + I
 <sub>d</sub>). Clearly, one must have an accurate estimation of each of these parameters to accurately determine the CFR of COVID-19. While the (M) is generally easier to count, and a focus of media, the denominator can take much longer to calculate. During the early phases of a deadly epidemic, the number of those who were infected and recovered (I
 <sub>r</sub>) is not yet known, since only those who were infected and became seriously ill are recognized and tested. In addition, because this is a novel virus, there were no existing detection methods, so early deaths due to clinical entities such as influenza, for example, may have been mis-attributed to CoVID-19. The viral genome was published about 2 weeks after the start of the outbreak, and PCR analysis was quickly used to diagnose suspected cases [
 <xref rid="B6-pathogens-09-00231" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Public health officials can now test suspected cases, especially close contacts of known cases, and others with mild symptoms, but the testing capabilities can become saturated, potentially limiting the ability to get an accurate estimation of I
 <sub>p</sub>. For example, the initial ability of the Wuhan health authority was limited to 200 tests per day, but that number has grown to 4196 tests per day [
 <xref rid="B44-pathogens-09-00231" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. The combination of these factors leads to a gross underestimation of the denominator of the CFR calculation, and thus an exaggeration of the mortality. Until we are able to accurately represent I
 <sub>r</sub> and I
 <sub>p</sub>, it is currently impossible to precisely estimate the CFR of SARS-CoV-2. 
</p>
