<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this work we have constructed CHIKV vaccines based on viral-vector platforms, such as ChAdOx1 and MVA vectors. The immunogen was designed based on a mosaic consensus sequence from the Asian, East, Central and South African and West African regions. Although individual strains are antigenically related and CHIKV vaccines previously reported have been developed using heterologous strains [
 <xref rid="B34-viruses-11-00322" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], a mosaic-based approach ensures a high coverage aimed at raising neutralising antibodies against all variants circulating worldwide. Here, we have developed two different vaccine immunogen candidates: a vaccine encoding the full structural CHIKV polyprotein (sCHIKV) and a vaccine in which the capsid antigen was deleted (sCHIKV ∆C). One of the functions of the capsid is to auto-cleave from the E3-E2-6K-E1 polyprotein. This proteolytic process exposes a signal leader which is contained in the amino-terminal region of E3 and promotes the entry of the polyprotein into the endoplasmic reticulum [
 <xref rid="B41-viruses-11-00322" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. There are several advantages in comparing these two different antigenic cassettes. Genetic vaccines, such as DNA vaccines, RNA vaccines, and viral-vectored vaccines, are often limited by the number of nucleotides that can be inserted into the antigenic cassette. Exploring the minimum sequence length able to induce immunogenicity and efficacy (either by in vitro neutralisation or by sterile protection after a viral challenge), will inform the vaccine development of new generation of vaccine candidates against CHIKV. In addition, optimising the minimum number of genetic antigens could allow the inclusion of further antigens to create combined vaccines (either homologous or heterologous) to induce immune response against different pathogens, all in a single genetic vaccine approach. Based on this assumption, efforts are underway to create ChAdOx1 vaccines expressing shorter versions of the CHIKV polyprotein, such as E2 and E1 proteins from CHIKV and other alphaviruses. E2 protein is involved in receptor recognition, while E1 protein is involved in membrane fusion [
 <xref rid="B12-viruses-11-00322" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-11-00322" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Therefore, exploring single-protein CHIKV vaccines in ChAdOx1 or in other viral-vectored platforms seems feasible and promising, since anti-E2 and anti-E1 antibodies are high in convalescent CHIKV-immune populations [
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-11-00322" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. However, ensuring proper antigenic folding in such developments, identical or similar to those antigenic structures in virions from CHIKV is paramount. Here, we have demonstrated by transmission electron microscopy, that our adenoviral vaccine ChAdOx1 sCHIKV is capable of expressing chikungunya-VLPs, which promotes the correct conformational antigens to be presented upon vaccination, therefore mimicking a real exposure to wild-type CHIKV. It will be interesting to explore and compare the neutralisation efficacy between encoded chikungunya-VLPs, E2 or E1 proteins in viral-vectored vaccines.
</p>
