<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this work we have tested the immunogenicity of our viral-vectored vaccines by assessing the cellular and humoral responses in BALB/c mice. Our data shows that the T cell immunogenicity elicited by ChAdOx1 sCHIKV and ChAdOx1 sCHIKV ∆C is directed primarily to a peptide region located in the 6K protein, by IFN-γ production. It will be interesting to explore the development of T-cell based vaccines against CHIKV. The role of T cell immunity in alphavirus infection, especially in CHIKV is not very well understood. Importantly, antigen design and the modulation of its intracellular expression will play a major role at inducing T cell responses directed to the antigen. A clear example is the comparison between CHIKV and CHIKV ∆C ELISpots, in which T cell responses directed to capsid were detected in the CHIKV groups but it was ablated in the CHIKV ∆C groups. It will be interesting to explore the protective and immunological relevance of the T cell response directed by the capsid in pre-clinical models. Although we identified 6k as the immunodominant region in BALB/c, this observation may differ in other inbred or outbred mouse strains; or in the case that vaccines comprise only E3, E2 or E1 antigens. For example, CHIKV-specific CD8+T cells were directed mainly against E1 and E2 proteins in C57Bl6 mice [
 <xref rid="B42-viruses-11-00322" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-viruses-11-00322" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-viruses-11-00322" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. T cells induced after CHIKV infection in C57BL/6 mice were not essential to control viremia but CD4 T cells were involved in CHIKV pathology [
 <xref rid="B45-viruses-11-00322" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Furthermore, T cell adoptive transfer did not confer protection against CHIKV challenge [
 <xref rid="B46-viruses-11-00322" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Finally, T cell responses in human CHIKV infection is also poorly understood. T cell responses (CD8
 <sup>+</sup> &gt; CD4
 <sup>+</sup>) have been found in chronic and convalescent CHIKV patients [
 <xref rid="B47-viruses-11-00322" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], in which specific responses were detected for E2, capsid and ns protein 1 (nsP1). Further studies using CHIKV challenge models would be informative to further dissect the role of cellular responses in protective efficacy using ours or other vaccine platforms.
</p>
