<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Methods that attempt to combine viral genetic and geographical information will be worthwhile only if the spatial epidemiology of the pathogen population is recorded in its genome sequences. The degree to which that occurs for the pathogen in question will depend on its relative rates of spatial movement and molecular evolution. A pair of typical RNA virus genomes will diverge genetically from each other on average at a rate of 1–20 nucleotide changes per year (assuming 10
 <sup>−3</sup>–10
 <sup>−4</sup> substitutions per site per year and a genome 10 000–20 000 nucleotides long [
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]). Hence, to a very rough approximation, analyses of viral genomes are unlikely to contain a reliable record of spatial epidemiological trends that occur on time scales faster than a fortnight. It is therefore unsurprising that many studies focus on global or regional patterns, observed over a time scale of several years or decades. Transmission dynamics over short time scales can sometimes be partially resolved by augmenting viral gene sequences with epidemiological incidence data (e.g. [
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]). It is also possible for virus sequences, particularly those limited to the antigenic regions of capsid or envelope proteins, to evolve too quickly relative to the rate of geographical spread, in which case phylogeographic information is lost due to the mutational ‘saturation’ of informative sites in viral genes (e.g. [
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]). In general, the rate of pathogen molecular evolution will determine the time scale of the spatial processes that can be reliably inferred; for example, movement of influenza virus can, under the best circumstances, be pinpointed from whole-genome sequences to within a few weeks, whereas geographical trends in the diversity of much slower-evolving 
 <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic> genes reveal the global spread of the bacterium over more than 50 000 years [
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].
</p>
