<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The reason for the relatively milder clinical presentation in children is mostly unknown. As outlined in the Chinese study, several factors in relation to the exposure and host factors may account for this observation; in addition, since the children's immune system is still developing, it may react to pathogens differently than do adults.
 <xref rid="pai13262-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>11</sup>
 </xref> Angiotensin‐converting enzyme II (ACE‐2) which acts as the receptor for coronaviruses may be structurally and functionally less mature in the airways of children.
 <xref rid="pai13262-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>12</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="pai13262-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>13</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="pai13262-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref> As children attend daycare/schools, they are exposed to a variety of viruses including other types of coronaviruses, and they may be better equipped with general antiviral defense mechanisms of the immune system. Another potential hypothesis
 <xref rid="pai13262-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref> suggested that the simultaneous presence of other viruses in the respiratory tract mucosa, which is very typical for young children, may limit the growth of SARS‐CoV‐2 by direct virus‐to‐virus interactions and competition.
 <xref rid="pai13262-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>15</sup>
 </xref> Similar to the observation made in children with SARS,
 <xref rid="pai13262-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref> the children with COVID‐19 infection may not be mounting a generalized cytokine storm but rather may be responding with elevation of specific cytokines. In a recent study with clusters of adults with pneumonia cases in Wuhan, China, the cytokine profile associated with COVID‐19 disease severity was characterized by increased interleukin (IL)‐2, IL‐7, granulocyte colony‐stimulating factor, interferon‐γ–inducible protein 10, monocyte chemoattractant protein 1, macrophage inflammatory protein 1‐α, and tumor necrosis factor‐α.
 <xref rid="pai13262-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>11</sup>
 </xref> It is also possible that children have less severe disease because they have fewer chronic health conditions. It is important to note that although children have less severe COVID‐19 disease, they are still able to pass on the virus, even while asymptomatic.
 <xref rid="pai13262-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>17</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
