<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par35">Second-line steroid sparing immunomodulating agents are potentially detrimental on immunity although clear-cut distinctions exist between nonspecific immunosuppressive drugs, like cyclosporine and azathioprine, and biological agents targeting discrete molecular pathways associated with type 2 allergic inflammation. In fact, besides inducing nonspecific suppression of anti-infective immunity, nonbiological agents are strong inducers of hepatic cytochromes, thus requiring plasma level monitoring when used in combination with antimicrobial agents [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. According to a WAO paper [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], no definitive evidence is presently available to obligate clinical decision making. As anti-IgE, ant-IL5/IL5R and anti IL4/IL3R biologics are not likely to induce immunosuppression or interfere with virus clearance (actually the contrary seems to hold true, at least for omalizumab [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] and dupilumab [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], while mepolizumab treatment was not associated with worse immunological response to viruses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]), they can be safely continued. Anyway, until evidence-based data are available, some countries, like the UK, have advised home confinement for at least 12 weeks to patients with severe asthma on systemic immunosuppressants or biological therapy. Steroid-sparing effect of biologics is a potential advantage over steroid therapy since patients on chronic steroid therapy can be affected by subclinical adrenal insufficiency [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Depending on the specific monoclonal antibody, in-site administration or home-delivery and self-administration can be the preferred choice. When patients live far away from the Centre, National Networks can be activated in order to identify a local near-home Centre for in-site administration (in Italy the Severe Asthma Network in Italy (SANI) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]). In case of infection, discontinuation should be discussed on a case-by-case basis.
</p>
