<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0055">Since SARS-CoV emerged in 2002, there has been a large interest in emerging coronaviruses which was spurred again in 2012 with the emergence of MERS-CoV. There has been significant interest in understanding how these viruses cause disease, why they tend to cause the most severe disease in older people, how the virus and host response to infection collaborate to cause severe lung disease, and for the development of antivirals, antibodies and vaccines. There are no approved vaccines or therapies for any human coronavirus. This is in part due to perception that there is not a need for medical counter measures for emerging viruses which can rapidly emerge, cause devastating epidemic disease and then seemingly disappear from the human population as happened with SARS-CoV in 2003. Given that three new human CoV have emerged in the past 20 years, this may finally provide the activation energy needed to motivate the development of broad-spectrum therapeutics and vaccines. Since it is unknown what viruses will emerge in the future, broadly acting antivirals targeting conserved viral proteins, like the RNA polymerase, or targeting host proteins that many viruses require for replication, are the most effective therapeutic category for the current and future outbreaks. For instance, the broad-spectrum antiviral, remdesivir, targets the viral RNA dependent RNA polymerase and is potently antiviral against Ebola, respiratory syncytial virus, Nipah and Hendra viruses and multiple endemic and emerging CoV in cell culture models [
 <xref rid="bib0125" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0130" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0140" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29
  <sup>•</sup>
 </xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0150" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Remdesivir is currently being evaluated in randomized control trials in China (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Clinicaltrials.gov" id="intr0010" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Clinicaltrials.gov</ext-link>, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="ClinicalTrials.gov" xlink:href="NCT04257656" id="intr0015" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NCT04257656</ext-link>, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="ClinicalTrials.gov" xlink:href="NCT04252664" id="intr0020" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NCT04252664</ext-link>) and in the United States (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Clinicaltrials.gov" id="intr0025" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Clinicaltrials.gov</ext-link>, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="ClinicalTrials.gov" xlink:href="NCT04292899" id="intr0030" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NCT04292899</ext-link>, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="ClinicalTrials.gov" xlink:href="NCT04292730" id="intr0035" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NCT04292730</ext-link>, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="ClinicalTrials.gov" xlink:href="NCT04280705" id="intr0040" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NCT04280705</ext-link>). Alternatively, a pan-CoV antibody approach could be tested on all current Coronavirus strains to aid in the assurance that it will work for future outbreaks. The difficulty is in the targeting of the Spike protein which is wildly divergent across the CoV lineages (i.e. alph, beta, delta, gamma). For example, SARS-CoV-2 spike protein is 90% similar to that of SARS-CoV but these viruses are both beta CoV. When comparing CoV of unrelated lineages, SARS-CoV and alpha CoV 229E, spike proteins are approximately 50% similar. However, group specific antibodies or vaccines could be used to protect against many types of coronaviruses at once given the inherent intra-lineage spike protein conservation. Future therapeutic developments would hinge on the ability to test these therapeutics in humans in controlled trials such as human challenge models where an individual gets infected with hCoV-OC43 under observation while also being given either a vaccine or antibody that has been shown to be broadly active 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> or in mouse models, should they exist.
</p>
