<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0060">Four of the seven known human CoV are endemic in the human population (i.e. OC43, 229E, NL64, and HKU1) and continually circle the globe typically causing the common cold. For the cold causing coronaviruses (CCC), which are responsible for 10–26% of seasonal colds, we know very little about their longitudinal genetic variation, effects on the host and CoV immunity [
 <xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Thus, there are large gaps in knowledge that would be useful to have answers to in the context of understanding this current outbreak. The current outbreak of SARS-CoV-2 has the hallmarks of becoming a seasonal cold causing coronavirus. Thus, we have an unprecedented research opportunity to not only better understand SARS-CoV-2 but to also glean insights into the constellation of events that fostered the emergence, spread and eventual endemicity of the previously known CCC. From this pandemic, we will have a deep understanding of the degree of viral genetic drift and if this virus does become endemic, sequence variation from year to year can be compared to the volumes of sequence data being generated from the virus’ initial passage in the human population. In addition, epidemiological and clinical data in conjunction with animal models should help elucidate why there is increased viral pathogenesis with increasing age. Because of the widespread nature of this pandemic, there is also the potential for human genome wide association studies which could uncover both susceptibility and resistance alleles. These human genetic studies coupled with virus and host interaction studies may reveal host molecules or pathways that could be exploited for host targeted antiviral therapies. Lastly, an exhaustive survey of wild and domestic animal species should help elucidate the animal reservoir of SARS-CoV-2 which is needed to prevent future introduction of SARS-CoV-2-like viruses into the human population. This new body of knowledge in conjunction with the development of broadly active vaccines, drugs and antibodies should better position humanity to deal with inevitability of CoV emergence in the future.
</p>
