<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Comparing to data available from other European countries, the percentages obtained in the present study are similar to those found in Norway and Portugal (8.0% and 6.7%, respectively) [
 <xref rid="B19-ijerph-17-02059" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-ijerph-17-02059" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], but lower than those documented in France (22–25%) [
 <xref rid="B21-ijerph-17-02059" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], Spain (13.5–43.5%) [
 <xref rid="B22-ijerph-17-02059" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-ijerph-17-02059" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-ijerph-17-02059" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], Sweden (33.0%) [
 <xref rid="B25-ijerph-17-02059" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], Switzerland (24.1–32.3%) [
 <xref rid="B21-ijerph-17-02059" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], and UK (93.0%) [
 <xref rid="B26-ijerph-17-02059" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]; on the other hand, no positive results were detected in samples from Greece [
 <xref rid="B23-ijerph-17-02059" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-ijerph-17-02059" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. All these studies, however, are difficult to compare because they were very different in terms of the period of sampling, sample size, sample volume and processing, and molecular methods used. In our study, during the 9-year surveillance period, a shift of the method for concentration of viruses took place, moving from the “glycine-chloroform” to the “two-phase separation” method recommended by WHO for poliovirus environmental surveillance, which is considered the gold standard for the concentration of viruses from sewage. Both methods were applied with the use of a control virus, that was added to the sample before virus concentration in order to monitor the efficiency of the entire procedure and ensure the quality of the analytical results. Indeed, no statistically significant difference was detected in the observed period based on the concentration method used (5.8% of positive samples with “glycine-chloroform” and 4.6% with the “two-phase separation”; 
 <italic>p</italic> value = 0.33). 
</p>
