<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Of all the positive samples detected, 75.6% were G3 and 24.3% G1. While G3 strains were consistently detected in the 9 years of surveillance, G1 were mainly detected in 2011 (6 samples) and 2012 (7 samples, outnumbering G3), and then sporadically, in 2013–2016. In the last three years, only G3 strains were detected. Genotype 1 is the most common cause of hepatitis E in regions with a lower socioeconomic status, where it is predominantly spread via contaminated potable water. In Italy, infections with HEV G1 have been documented in immigrants from countries at risk after returning from a stay in their country of origin, as well as in Italian people traveling from highly endemic countries [
 <xref rid="B32-ijerph-17-02059" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-ijerph-17-02059" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-ijerph-17-02059" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. The environmental data provided in this study reflect those from clinical surveillance. Indeed, of the total 285 cases documented in SEIEVA in 2011–2018 (
 <uri xlink:href="https://www.epicentro.iss.it/epatite/bollettino/Bollettino-4-marzo-2019.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.epicentro.iss.it/epatite/bollettino/Bollettino-4-marzo-2019.pdf</uri>), 23.5% were imported (these are most probably caused by HEV G1), and 76.5% were autochthonous (caused by G3). The sporadic circulation of genotype 1, along with the predominance of genotype 3, is consistent with reports in the literature about other industrialized countries [
 <xref rid="B22-ijerph-17-02059" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-ijerph-17-02059" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. The predominance of G3 cases is likely to result in a higher concentration of G3 molecules in sewage samples compared to G1, leading to a predominance of G3 PCR amplification products and to the apparent absence of G1 in some years. Unfortunately, only two of the G3 positive samples could be typed by sequencing the ORF2 region. The possible explanations for the negative ORF2 detection in the vast majority of positive samples, besides the lower sensitivity of the ORF2 assay, include the possibility of RNA damage due to the long storage time before testing, despite the efforts for sample preservation. Moreover, being that the ORF2 assay is an amplification providing a longer template compared to ORF1 (&gt;450 bps vs 172 bp), amplification from environmental samples, which often contain inactivated viruses and fragmented RNA, may be more difficult to achieve. The two positive samples were both characterized as G3f, which is also the predominant type reported in the same period in the clinical cases tested by the Italian NRL for human viral hepatitis (unpublished data). A G3f sequence was also detected by NGS in 2017–2019 pooled samples.
</p>
