<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Genes including RSV 
 <italic>NP</italic>, RBSDV 
 <italic>p10</italic>, SRBSDV 
 <italic>p10</italic> and RGSV 
 <italic>NP</italic> linked with a Myc tag sequence were cloned into plasmid pFastBac (Invitrogen), while 
 <italic>LsST6</italic> was inserted into the BamHI/XbalI sites of pFastBacHTB (Invitrogen) vector containing a 6×His tag. Recombinant 
 <italic>LsST6</italic> DNA was used to cotransfect Sf9 cells with recombinant RSV 
 <italic>NP</italic>, RBSDV 
 <italic>p10</italic>, SRBSDV 
 <italic>p10</italic> or RGSV 
 <italic>NP</italic> DNA during a 72-h incubation at 27°C, then cultures were collected and lysed in the lysis buffer (20 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.6, 150 mM NaCl, 0.5% NP-40, 5 mM EDTA, and complete protease inhibitor cocktail tablets) for 1 h on ice. After the cultures were centrifuged at 10,000 × 
 <italic>g</italic> for 20 min at 4°C, 50 μl protein A/G plus agarose beads was added to the supernatant for 1 h at 4°C to decrease any nonspecific binding of proteins. Then the supernatant was incubated with 2 μl (1 μg/μl) anti-Myc antibody for 1 h, followed by incubation with protein A/G plus agarose beads at 4°C with end-over-end agitation for overnight. The protein A/G plus agarose beads were washed with washing buffer (20 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.6, 150 mM NaCl, 5 mM EDTA) 5 times, then mixed with 1× loading buffer (0.08 M Tris pH 6.8, 2.0% SDS, 10% glycerol, 0.1 M dithiothreitol, and 0.2% bromophenol blue) and finally boiled for 5 min. The cell lysates and IP cultures were separated on SDS-PAGE gels and transferred to nitrocellulose membranes. Membranes were incubated with antibody of anti-His or anti-Myc (1:3000) for 1.5 h at room temperature, then incubated with the secondary antibody-alkaline phosphatase-conjugated goat anti-mouse or rabbit IgG (1:5000) at 37°C for 1 h. Membranes were then incubated with a chemiluminescent substrate mixture and imaged using the imageQuant LAS 4000 mini biomolecular imager (GE Healthcare Life Sciences, USA).
</p>
