<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our studies demonstrating an antigen-driven IgA immune response in acute KD and the presence of KD antigen in intracytoplasmic inclusion bodies in KD bronchial epithelium lead us to put forth the following model of KD pathogenesis (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). We propose that a presently unidentified (likely “new”) RNA virus infects ciliated bronchial epithelium, causing asymptomatic infection in most individuals and KD in a small subset of genetically predisposed children. Children &lt; 6 months of age are less susceptible because of passive maternal antibody. The virus can result in sporadic cases of KD or in outbreaks. The agent can remain persistent in cytoplasmic inclusion bodies, with intermittent shedding into the respiratory tract of previously infected individuals. It can enter the bloodstream via macrophages and target particularly the coronary arteries and also other sites. Antigen-specific IgA plasma cells (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>) and CD8 T cells (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>) respond to the infection, but coronary arteries can be damaged. The provision of specific antibodies directed at the ubiquitous KD agent could explain the efficacy of intravenous gammaglobulin (IVIG) in the treatment of KD. These specific antibodies are present in IVIG because most adult donors were asymptomatically infected during young childhood, which accounts for the reduced prevalence in older children and the rarity of KD in adults. After infection, 97–99% of KD patients are immune to the agent and do not have a recurrence of KD. The agent can be spread through the population either from community contacts with asymptomatic primary infection particularly in the winter-spring, or from a close contact who had been previously infected and then intermittently sheds the agent, resulting in cases during other seasons. We believe that our model, although speculative, fits clinical and epidemiologic findings in KD much better than other currently proposed speculative models.
</p>
