<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par46">The emerging viral diseases have necessitated the research for new effective antiviral agents such as terpenes . As a result, scientists evaluated various terpenes for their properties, among which monoterpenes showed a good result. Monoterpenes are terpene classes that possess two isoprene units. They form a major constituent of essential oils in plants which indicates monoterpenes play a major role in defense for plants (Grabmann 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2005</xref>). A 2005 study evaluated the in vitro antiviral activity of several essential oils extracted from South American plants (Duschatzky et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2005</xref>). The oil extracts were tested against three major human viruses—herpes simplex virus-1 (HSV1), dengue virus type 2, and Junin virus. The oils that were proved to be virucidal were mainly composed of monoterpenes, namely, carvone, carveol limonene, alpha- and beta-pinene, caryophylene, camphor, beta-ocimene, and one sesquiterpene which is germacrene (Duschatzky et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2005</xref>). A similar study in 2008 analyzed the essential oils of seven plants from Lebanon for in vitro antiviral activity (Loizzo et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">2008</xref>). The viruses under investigation were HSV1 and severe acute respiratory syndrome corona virus (SARS CoV). The results were positive for antiviral effects, and the major constituents were alpha- and beta-pinene, beta-ocimene, and 1,8-cineole (Loizzo et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">2008</xref>). Following this, a 2009 study on also had similar results which suggested 1,8-cineole, α-pinene, caryophyllene oxide, and sabinene to be the major components of virucidal oils (Alim et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2009</xref>). Functional data from these studies reveal that a few monoterpenes are shared by various plants for antiviral properties (Alim et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2009</xref>). These shared monoterpenes could be of importance as they are present universally.
</p>
