<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our study might have some limitations. First, for the duration of the study, the number of samples of the youngest participants was slightly lower than planned. The study used serum samples of patients from routine work, from which a serum bank was made to test the immunity of the population to certain pathogens (measles, varicella, hepatitis A, hepatitis B and rubella). Due to the analyses done for all these agents, we had 26% less serum in the age group of 1 year for the purposes of our research on the immunity to rubella virus. Regarding the OR result for the 1y group, we understand that the OR number is high, but we can try to explain. The &gt;50y age group was taken as a reference value for comparisons. This age group belongs to the unvaccinated population which has witnessed high incidence rates of rubella during major epidemics. Of the 237 subjects over the age of 50, only one male subject was seronegative, and one male subject had an equivocal finding. As many as 99.2% were seropositive, so the OR for male subjects aged 1 was 250, and its confidence intervals were wide, which could potentially limit the ability for adequate interpretation of the results. Second, equivocal results were not retested in terms of a definitive laboratory classification (positive or negative). Third, standardization was not performed due to a lack of a reference (comparative) panel. For epidemiological purposes, the enzyme immunoassay (EIA) is a widely used method to detect antibodies to rubella in serum. However, variations in both sensitivity and specificity of several commercial EIAs have been reported, as well as inter-laboratory variability when the same assay is used. Therefore, the European Sero-Epidemiology Network recommends standardization of assays to ensure direct comparability of seroepidemiology results obtained during different projects. Fourth, we did not collect individual immunization coverage of participants, migrant status, education level and other personal data. Therefore, we could only guess whether specific anti-rubella IgG antibodies originated from vaccination or natural infection. However, that was not the initial idea of the study. This was the first study on the immunity of the Vojvodina population to rubella virus. Some future research could provide additional data. Fifth, it is quite possible that the population-level immunity to rubella virus may be lower than the results obtained in this study, since immunocompromised individuals were excluded. For that reason, we think that further research is needed in the future, which we are planning to do. The collected serums were from Vojvodina residents who came to our institution for laboratory testing during the study period. Subjects' participation in the study was voluntary. The study included the subjects who gave their written informed consent to participate in the study. It is possible that some refused to participate because they avoided vaccination (either for themselves or for their children), but we do not currently have information about it.</p>
