<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par36">Some literature has already highlighted potential links between COVID-19 virus and neurodegenerative conditions, including suggestions regarding PD
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">112</xref>
 </sup>. These are based on multiple observations:
 <list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par37">The ability of coronaviruses to enter the CNS through the nasal cavity with subsequent neuronal death
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>,
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>
    </sup>, as shown in animal studies.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par38">Hyposmia is well documented in COVID-19 patients without nasal obstruction and rhinorrhea
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108">108</xref>,
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">113</xref>,
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114">114</xref>
    </sup> and is also a common prodromal feature of PD
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115">115</xref>
    </sup>.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par39">Basal ganglia lesions may occur in the context of a thromboembolic encephalopathy in COVID-19
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR116">116</xref>
    </sup>.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par40">The presence of higher levels of antibodies against other coronaviruses that cause the common cold in the CSF of PD patients compared to healthy controls suggests a possible involvement of viral infection in the pathogenesis of PD
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>
    </sup>.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par41">There are reports that ACE2 may be expressed in various regions of the nervous system
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>,
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117">117</xref>
    </sup>, although as detailed above, further neuropathological investigation is required. Given the interferon activation of this protein, it will be important to examine subjects with CNS inflammation or encephalitis.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par42">The recent reports of syncope with no abnormal rhythms on cardiac device interrogation hint at a potential role for neurally-mediated syncope
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
    </sup> vs. orthostasis, suggesting the importance of these investigations for PD patients who often suffer from dysautonomia
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118">118</xref>
    </sup>.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par43">A single case report of a patient who developed myoclonus and an acute but spontaneously reversible hypokinetic rigid syndrome, with DaTscan showing reduction of dopamine transporter uptake in the putamen as well as hyposmia
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119">119</xref>
    </sup>.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par44">The angiotensin system, which is implicated in COVID-19 pathogenesis, may be important in neuroinflammatory and neurodegenerative mechanisms observed in PD
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120">120</xref>,
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121">121</xref>
    </sup>.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par45">SARS-CoV-2 proteins can interact with human proteins involved in biological mechanisms that drive dysfunction of protein homeostasis that may lead to protein misfolding and aggregation (Fig. 
    <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>)
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref>,
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref>
    </sup>.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par46">The release of cytokines may activate resident immune cells in the CNS and/or lead to their infiltration from the periphery that result in brain cell damage. Such cells may include activated T cells and microglia that may kill neurons
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122">122</xref>–
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR124">124</xref>
    </sup>, astrocytes, and vascular cell types. This may occur through the selection of cells that specifically recognize presented antigens from the infection or previous infections, or via a general activation of cytotoxic cells that recognize other antigens, including autoantigens, such as those derived from alpha-synuclein which are implicated in PD, Lewy Body dementias, multiple system atrophy, and multiple sclerosis
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125">125</xref>,
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR126">126</xref>
    </sup>. High levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines, such as TNF and IL-1beta, are associated with increased risk of PD, while use of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) and anti-TNF biologics reduce the risk
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR127">127</xref>
    </sup>. Anti-TNF biologics are currently under investigation for COVID-19.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
