<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">IAVs have eight segmented genomes of single-stranded, negative-sense RNAs, which express similar major proteins, such as polymerase basic 2 (PB2), polymerase basic 1 (PB1), polymerase acidic (PA), HA, nucleoprotein (NP), NA, matrix 1 (M1) and matrix 2 (M2), nonstructural 1 (NS1), and nonstructural 2 (NS2/NEP) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Studying the past influenza pandemics helps us to understand the mechanisms of such devastating outcomes. Theoretically,144 different IAV subtype viruses can be generated by the combinations of 16 HA and 9 NA subtypes of avian IAVs. However, only the H1N1, H2N2, and H3N2 subtypes have been identified as the causes of human influenza pandemics. Of these, the H1N1 subtype caused the 1918 and 2009 pandemics and the ‘abortive pandemic’-like swine influenza epidemic in 1976, which hundreds of soldiers at Fort Dix, New Jersey, the United States were infected with [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>] (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Although diverse IAV subtypes have been isolated from swine, H1, H2 and H3, and N1 and N2 subtypes have been mainly established [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. As mentioned above, the pdm2009 and 1976 H1N1 viruses were swine-origin and readily transmissible among humans [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Another pandemic H1N1 virus, pdm1918, however, appeared to be closely related with avian strains, which would be ultimately the ancestor of subsequent human and swine H1N1 IAVs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Since human-infecting avian IAVs were shown to be less transmissible among humans [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>], a ‘spill-over’ infection with avian IAVs was not likely to be a direct source of pdm1918 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. As the receptor specificity is considered another prerequisite for avian IAVs to infect and transmit to humans, there are some doubts about the avian-origin pdm1918 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. The H2 HA of the 1957 H2N2 pandemic and the H3 HA of the 1968 H3N2 pandemic were introduced from the avian reservoir to circulating human IAVs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>], but whether the reassortment events occurred in humans or in other hosts, such as swine, immediately before transmitting to humans remains unanswered [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. 
</p>
