<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20">SARS-CoV-2 encodes structural and non-structural proteins including papain-like protease, RNA-dependent RNA polymerase, 3-chymotrypsin-like protease, helicase, spike glycoprotein, and some other accessory proteins. Some of these enzymes are responsible for the viral life cycle and attachment to host cells for penetration. These structural components were also identified in MERS and SARS as the target for drug development [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. Initial analysis of structural protein and genetic sequences indicated that drug binding sites are conserved in SARS, SARS-CoV-2 and MERS, therefore repurposing of available inhibitory drugs for SARS and MERS could be effective against SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. AP2-associated protein kinase 1 (AAK1) is one of the regulators in endocytosis. Janus kinase inhibitor baricitinib has the affinity to inhibit AAK1, thus could prevent COVID-19 acute respiratory disease by reducing virus entry and inflammation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. Host Kinases are much important in initiating antiviral signaling cascades regulating the expression of cytokines and chemokines resulting in infection prevention. Another type of kinases involves c-Jun N-terminal kinases 1 and 2 (JNK1/JNK2) which regulates initiation of pro-inflammatory responses leading to the production of interleukin 6 (IL-6), TNF-α and interferon β (IFN-β) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. Similarly, upon viral infection early cytokines dysregulation is an outcome of high pathogenesis, p38 MAPK is crucial in hypercytokinemia so targeting p38 MAPK could be helpful in the antiviral drug development approach [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. G-protein coupled receptor kinase 2 (GRK2) is a potential pro-viral host protein for influenza A virus and is inhibited by paroxetine acting as virion un-coating can reduce viral load in respiratory tracts but is not helpful in lethal infection prevention [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. In another study treatment of mice with SphK1 or SphK2 inhibitors prolonged survival by decreasing RNA synthesis of influenza A virus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>], thus could be effective in RNA synthesis inhibition in SARS-CoV-2 as presented in a predictive unidentified agents in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. However, the safety and efficacy of these strategies mentioned above must be further investigated for clinical use.
</p>
