<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Among the significantly changed lipids, four fatty acids, namely, AA, DHA, DPA, and EPA, were upregulated in both EV-A71 and CV-A16-infected samples, indicating their potentially important roles in 
 <italic>Enterovirus</italic> A infections. In corroboration with our findings, a recent report also showed that human rhinovirus A, another important human pathogenic picornavirus, induces substantial fatty acid modifications in human bronchial epithelial cells [
 <xref rid="B24-ijms-20-05952" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. AA, DHA, DPA, and EPA are all polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFA). AA is an omega-6 PUFA, while DHA, DPA, and EPA are omega-3 PUFAs [
 <xref rid="B25-ijms-20-05952" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. It has been previously shown that PUFA play key roles in inflammatory processes [
 <xref rid="B9-ijms-20-05952" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-ijms-20-05952" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-ijms-20-05952" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. AA is a precursor to pro-inflammatory mediators such as prostaglandins (PG) and leukotrienes (LT), as well as lipoxins, which are endogenous anti-inflammatory, pro-resolving molecules reducing tissue injury and chronic inflammation [
 <xref rid="B27-ijms-20-05952" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. DHA and EPA inhibit lipopolysaccharide-induced and lipopeptide-induced cyclooxygenase-2 expression and thus the inflammatory response in epithelial and dendritic cells [
 <xref rid="B28-ijms-20-05952" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-ijms-20-05952" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Moreover, lipids derived from EPA (Resolvin E series) and DHA (Resolvin D series, maresins, and protectins) are involved in the resolution of inflammation and exhibit anti-inflammatory properties [
 <xref rid="B26-ijms-20-05952" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-ijms-20-05952" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The omega-3 and omega-6 PUFAs interact in a delicate manner to regulate the inflammatory response. For example, omega-3 PUFAs such as DHA and EPA may serve as competitive substrates for omega-6 PUFA metabolism to decrease AA-derived eicosanoids and their effects on inflammation [
 <xref rid="B31-ijms-20-05952" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. 
</p>
