<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig2">
 <label>Fig. 2</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Environmental Mechanistic Model (EMM) EBOV Simulation Schematic. Within 0.0416° (5.6 km at equator) grid cells across the globe (
   <bold>a</bold>), we used a 
   <italic>SEIFR</italic> (
   <italic>Susceptible, Exposed, Infectious, Funeral</italic> and 
   <italic>Removed</italic>) disease compartmental model (
   <bold>b</bold>), to estimate the number of people in each compartment. 
   <italic>S</italic>–
   <italic>E</italic> transmission rate was determined for each grid cell by calculating the force of zoonotic infection (between hosts and humans) 
   <italic>λ</italic>
   <sub>
    <italic>z</italic>
   </sub>, and within human populations 
   <italic>λ</italic> (see Methods). Travel of exposed or infectious individuals between grid cells occurred across existing road and flight transport networks, with transmission rate 
   <italic>ε</italic>
   <sub>
    <italic>fr</italic>
   </sub>. Mean transition rates used as the starting parameters for simulations were as follows: 
   <italic>α</italic> for 
   <italic>E</italic>–
   <italic>I</italic> was calculated as the reciprocal of incubation time in days (
   <italic>α</italic> = 1/7), 
   <italic>γ</italic>
   <sub>
    <italic>σ</italic>
   </sub> (
   <italic>I–F</italic> transition rate) was the product of the probability of the reciprocal of days infectious (
   <italic>γ</italic> = 1/9.6) and maximum poverty-weighted case fatality rate (
   <italic>σ</italic> = 0.78), 
   <italic>γ</italic>
   <sub>1-σ</sub> (
   <italic>I–R</italic> transition rate) was the product of the probability of the reciprocal of days infectious (
   <italic>γ</italic> = 1/9.6) and probability of recovering (1-σ), and 
   <italic>γ</italic>
   <sub>
    <italic>F</italic>
   </sub> (
   <italic>F–R</italic> transition rate) was the reciprocal of the burial time of 2 days. Each simulation was run 2500 times for 365 days, only including grid cells containing a human population. The total number of people in each compartment per grid cell, per day from each simulation was then used to calculate the total number of index and secondary cases and mapped spatially (
   <bold>c</bold>). Bioclimatic, land use and demographic conditions were then changed to predicted values for 2070 to estimate changes to 
   <italic>λ</italic> and 
   <italic>λ</italic>
   <sub>
    <italic>z</italic>
   </sub>, and the simulations repeated to investigate impacts of global change on disease (
   <bold>d</bold>)
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_12499_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e685" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
