<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4">This gender-determined dosage effect, however, is probably not the whole story. The TLR7 and 8 genes display copy number variation (CNV) in the population (Wang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2014</xref>). In addition, TLR genes display allelic polymorphisms (Menendez et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2019</xref>; Wang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2014</xref>) that may influence the strength of the interaction with their respective ligands or the quality of the ensuing signal that is transduced to the nucleus. There is ample proof that gender-based CNV of TLR7 has medical implications. The best-documented example is provided by systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE), a disorder in which the immune system attacks healthy tissue. This disease is far more prominent in females than in males, and the risk of developing SLE is associated with a higher copy number load of TLR7 (Deane et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2007</xref>; Wang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2014</xref>). As a result, TLR7-related CNV may act as a two-edged sword. A high copy number load of TLR7 may guarantee a better protective response to ssRNA viruses, but it may also suggest a poor prognosis for individuals who are at risk of developing SLE. One has to realize, however, that CNV of TLR genes was not selected in nature to foster autoimmune-related disease – its biological role in controlling virus irradication is likely to be more relevant. Therefore, it seems worthwhile to start documenting the types of TLR7 and 8 polymorphisms in different well-defined populations/cohorts that have been affected by COVID-19. Knowledge regarding the mechanisms of disease pathology may be applicable not only in future vaccine development (the constitution and dosage of vaccine components for males versus females) but also with respect to the route by which such a vaccine should be administered (local versus systemic).
</p>
