<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study we identified a novel phlebovirus, tentatively named the Drin virus after the eponymous river in the Kukës region of Albania. The virus was identified in a pool containing only male sand flies belonging to the 
 <italic>P. neglectus</italic> species which is the predominant species in that area. Other studies have demonstrated that phleboviruses were potentially transmitted by several distinct species of sand flies [
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-11-00469" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The second interesting finding is that the pool containing Drin virus RNA consisted exclusively of male sand flies—this has been previously reported in most of the studies on phlebovirus detection in sand flies [
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-11-00469" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-viruses-11-00469" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-viruses-11-00469" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-viruses-11-00469" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], and is related to trans-ovarial or venereal transmission [
 <xref rid="B31-viruses-11-00469" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Assuming that only one individual was infected in Pool #17, the sand fly infection rate was 0.18% during 2015 and 0.04% if both years are combined. For comparison, infection rates were 0.04% for the Dashli virus in Iran and 0.026% for the Toros virus in Turkey [
 <xref rid="B3-viruses-11-00469" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-viruses-11-00469" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. There is no data to allow us to calculate the infection rate for the CFUV virus in Greece [
 <xref rid="B1-viruses-11-00469" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Sand fly trapping sites were scattered to best cover the whole country (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00469-f001">Figure 1</xref>). As previously reported [
 <xref rid="B32-viruses-11-00469" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], NGS analysis of PCR products within the 
 <italic>COI</italic> and 
 <italic>Cytb</italic> genes of sand flies is an efficient approach for species identification within a pool of insects. Here, all sand flies included in Pool #17 were 
 <italic>P. neglectus</italic>, suggesting that this species is capable of transmitting the Drin virus between sand flies and possible vertebrate hosts. As 
 <italic>P. neglectus</italic> is widespread in the Balkan peninsula, in Eastern Europe, and in Turkey [
 <xref rid="B5-viruses-11-00469" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], and because it was involved in the transmission of the Balkan virus [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-11-00469" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and Toscana virus [
 <xref rid="B33-viruses-11-00469" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], competence studies are needed to understand better the potential of this species to transmit viruses of medical importance.
</p>
