<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The virucidal properties of AgNPs are still largely unexplored, but initial reports are encouraging. AgNPs can inhibit viruses by a number of mechanisms, including binding to and interacting with viral surface proteins,
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0185" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>185</sup>
 </xref> as well as denaturing enzymes by reacting with amino, carboxyl, imidazole, and sulfhydryl groups.
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0188" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>188</sup>
 </xref> In a study using 30–50 nm AgNPs surface‐coated with polyvinylpyrrolidone against various strains of HIV‐1, the AgNPs were found to bind onto surface glycoproteins (gp120) and chemically modifies it by denaturing its disulfide‐bonded domains.
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0189" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>189</sup>
 </xref> This prevents the virus from binding to receptor proteins on potential host cells which are necessary for viral entry and infection. Dilute AgNP solutions could elicit significant virucidal activity, as inhibition of 50 % of viral infectivity could be attained at AgNP concentrations of ≤ 0.91 mg/mL. Compared to commonly‐used biocidal silver nitrate and silver sulfadiazine, the AgNPs were found to be more effective against the HIV‐1 strains, suggesting that the release of Ag
 <sup>0</sup> atomic clusters from the AgNPs is more potent virucide than Ag
 <sup>+</sup> itself. Such destruction of viral surface glycoproteins has also been suggested to account for the virucidal effects of AgNPs against the Influenza virus.
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0190" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>190</sup>
 </xref> AgNPs have also been incorporated into polymer films comprising of poly (3‐hydroxybutyrate‐co‐3‐hydroxyvalerate), a biopolymeric material, which achieved the dual function of stabilizing the AgNPs and bringing about virucidal behavior against norovirus surrogates.
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0191" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>191</sup>
 </xref> AgNP‐containing products are appearing increasingly in the market, including clothing, wound‐dressings, ointments, and food packaging materials,
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0192" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>192</sup>
 </xref> whose biocidal activities are a result of slow sustained‐release of the silver nanomaterials. However, it should be noted that like all disinfecting agents aforementioned, the virucidal efficacies of AgNPs differ from virus to virus. Furthermore, the quantities, shapes, size, and types of silver nanomaterials released depend on their real‐world settings and applications,
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0193" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>193</sup>
 </xref> all of which affects their virucidal properties. Thus, the effectiveness of these AgNP‐containing products against viruses in real‐life settings, as well as their toxicity towards humans, need to be carefully evaluated and studied.
</p>
