<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Climate variation is also critical for vernal amplification. Warm winters and early termination of mosquito overwintering seem to lead to early season virus amplification. As described previously, with warmer temperatures, there are more vectors, biting more frequently due to shorter gonotrophic periods, potentially transmitting virus earlier in adult life, leading to rapid amplification of virus to outbreak levels earlier during the transmission season than during cooler temperatures. This results in more frequent tangential transmission of virus to humans, especially as vectors shift avian blood feeding patterns to feed more frequently on mammals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B77-viruses-05-02079">77</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B146-viruses-05-02079">146</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B150-viruses-05-02079">150</xref>]. Anthropogenic factors undoubtedly influence transmission during these outbreaks. Summer heat waves contribute to tangential transmission by altering human dress (less clothing worn when it is hot exposing more skin surface to mosquitoes) and behavior (tendency to postpone physical activities until after sunset when vectors are active). Often in summer manual labor associated with agriculture and other outdoor activities are shifted to after sunset and during the host-seeking period of the primary vector species, such as 
 <italic>Cx. tarsalis</italic> and 
 <italic>Cx. quinquefasciatus</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B96-viruses-05-02079">96</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B151-viruses-05-02079">151</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B152-viruses-05-02079">152</xref>]. In contrast, television viewing and air conditioning combine to keep people indoors behind closed windows and thereby may serve as important protective measures limiting host-vector contact and infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B153-viruses-05-02079">153</xref>]. However, in maritime or northern areas with infrequent warm spells, few homes have air conditioning and people therefore may spend more time with open windows or outdoors during hot weather, thereby increasing vector contact.
</p>
