<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">Peptide-based vaccines are designed to elicit immunity against particular pathogens by selectively stimulating antigens specific for B and T cells. Peptide vaccines have a whole lot of advantages though they suffer from certain challenges such as low immunogenicity, susceptibility to enzymatic digestion etc. (Skwarczynski and Toth 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2016</xref>). Advanced bioinformatics tools and databases help to speed up and design peptide-based vaccines for SARS-CoV-2 where peptides could be used as ligands (Abdelmageed et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2020</xref>). The viable approach in designing peptide vaccines should be to identify peptide epitopes on the immunogens and to use synthetic versions of these peptides. Since these vaccines are totally synthetic, they would not carry the risk of reversion or of complete inactivation, and in principle; epitopes could be selected to avoid components that give rise to unwanted side effects (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/biologicals/publications/trs/areas/vaccines/peptide/WHO_TRS_889_A1.pdf?ua=1" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.who.int/biologicals/publications/trs/areas/vaccines/peptide/WHO_TRS_889_A1.pdf?ua=1</ext-link>). Also, peptide-based vaccines do not need in vitro culture making them biologically safe, and their selectivity allows accurate activation of immune responses (Dudek et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2010</xref>). Studies shows that effective vaccines can be developed using T cell and B cell epitopes comprising the immunome, which constitutes the immune system (Groot et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2008</xref>; Tahir ul Qamar et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2019</xref>). Epitopes are short amino acid sequences of a protein which can induce an immune response and epitope finding is quite expensive and laborious. The use of in silico methods are an alternative and effective strategy due to the importance in biomedical applications such as vaccine design, disease diagnostics, biomarker studies etc. (Bahrami et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2019</xref>; Backert and Kohlbacher 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2015</xref>). There are many peptide vaccines in development, such as vaccine for AIDS by the virus human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) (Liu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2007</xref>), malaria (Epstein et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2007</xref>), anthrax (Oscherwitz et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2010</xref>), human papilloma virus (HPV) (Solares et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2011</xref>). Our hypothesis is based on the fact that, epitope region of the drug targets which share the sequence identity and similarity to human proteins may be involved in their binding and fusion to human cells (Hwa et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2008</xref>).
</p>
