<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p> General comments: 
 <list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
   <p>Overall, the methods and results section of the manuscript are well written and analysed. </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Although the study objective is clear, the rational for the study is more ambiguous. The main issue at hand in the context of vaccine development, is the need for an assay which can predict the efficacy of the vaccine –and ideally a functional assay or at least one that bridges with a functional assay. This would be important for bridging studies, in the absence of being able to undertake multiple large scale vaccine efficacy/effectiveness studies. Although the authors cite some studies reporting a positive association of PRNT antibody and risk/odds of disease, omitted from the background are other studies (including one from the same group)- which actually reported no association between PRNT and RSV LRTI. This calls into question the value of the current “gold standard”- i..e PRNT- on its own (over and above the issues with regard to standardisation and being labour intensive) in relation to whether or not it would be useful for establishing a correlate of protection.</p>
   <p> In the context of this study where the ELISA assays, as also noted by the authors, are not discriminatory in terms of measure of antibody to epitopes specifically targeted by most of the vaccines currently under clinical development (including the nanoparticle F-fusion vaccine), the likelihood of any predictive value of a relatively non-specific ELISA assay being of use to establish or impute a correlate of protection would be doubtful from the outset.</p>
   <p> These issue merit inclusion in the abstract, study rational and the discussion.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>The measure of RSV antibody could have multiple purposes- including characterising sero-epidemiology, measuring vaccine immunogenicity or trying to establish a correlate of protection. Depending on for what purpose the assay is being used, would influence the minimum characteristics required of the assay. In the context of this study, although the ELISA assays were only moderately predictive of the PRNT antibody measure, this does not necessarily preclude the use thereof in sero-epidemiology studies. Likewise, even if there was a strong correlation between the ELISA and PRNT assays, in the absence of an established correlate of protection using the PRNT assay- that too would not be of much value in terms of being used for studies to impute vaccine effectiveness in different settings.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list> Specific comments 
 <list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
   <p>Pg 3 end para 2- need to clarify that the standardised assays which are required need to be assays that are predictive of vaccine protection. Also, clarify that the main purpose of such assays are to undertake “bridging immunogenicity studies” to avoid multiple vaccine efficacy/effectiveness studies. Such assays will need to be tested for predicting vaccine efficacy often within a clinical trial and the assays could differ based on the construct of the vaccine (i.e differences in specific epitopes targeted).</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Pg 3 para 3- mention and reference studies that have shown no association between PRNT and LRTI.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Pg 3 para 4- clarify that the needs of an assay for sero-epi studies may well differ to those required to establish a correlate of protection.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Pg 3 para 5- what would the need for a serological assay be in a “large vaccine efficacy trial” which will provide the most definitive answer on vaccine efficacy?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Under lab methods- clarify where the lab assays were done.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Pg 8 para 3- neutralizing antibodies are also elicited by immune responses to the G and M protein. This might well explain some of the conflicting findings on the association of PRNT and risk for RSV LRTI.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Pg 8 para 4- the last sentence needs to be elaborated upon, including what the possibility for epitope specific antibody read-outs that might well differ between vaccine constructs.  </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
