<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Statistical research has shown a relation between the carrying capacity of mosquitoes and local climatic factors, such as the weekly temperature, amount of rainfall 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003388-Drake1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003388-AbdELRahim1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>, total temperature degree-days 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003388-Walsh1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, and the temperature of water. Many species of mosquitoes found in Africa have been reported to be the vectors of RVFV, such as 
 <italic>Aedes caspius</italic>, 
 <italic>Culex(Cx) pipiens</italic>, 
 <italic>Cx. antennatus</italic>, 
 <italic>Cx. perexiguus</italic> and 
 <italic>Cx. poicilipes</italic>. An abundance of mosquitoes may be found along the Nile, in its Delta and near the Suez Canal. Egypt is an arid country with a hot desert climate, where the most commonly reported mosquito species are 
 <italic>Culex</italic> species 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003388-AbdelHamid1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. Unlike the 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> in places like Kenya 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003388-Romoser1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, 
 <italic>Culex</italic> species are not known to be involved in the endemic maintenance of RVFV by vertical transmission. In this work, we focused on the pathogen transmission in Egypt, therefore, we only consider the 
 <italic>Culex</italic> species as vectors in our mathematical model for transmission of RVFV in Egypt and ignore the possibility of the laying of virus-laden eggs by the species 
 <italic>Aedes caspius</italic>. Of the reported species, seasonality was observed in all species, particularly the two most common species: 
 <italic>Cx. pipiens</italic> and 
 <italic>Cx. perexiguus</italic>. Both species are observed all year round, but have significantly higher densities during April/May to September/October, coinciding with high water levels and temperatures 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003388-Ammar1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. Therefore, it is biologically reasonable to believe the abundance of mosquitoes follows the seasonal patterns of the level of Nile, peaking in mid-September 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003388-Budge1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref> and reaching lowest level during the winter season 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003388-Drake1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. Motivated by the field curves for rainfall level in 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003388-Drake1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, we adopt a trigonometric function to model the seasonal variation of rainfall level. As a consequence, since the mosquito abundance follows the same pattern of rainfall, we posit that the carrying capacity of the vector is also a trigonometric function, where the period is the length of one solar year, 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pntd.0003388.e006.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula> days. In this paper, for the sake of simplicity, we use the function 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pntd.0003388.e007.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula> to model the seasonal variation of the mosquito carrying capacity, where 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pntd.0003388.e008.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula>, 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pntd.0003388.e009.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula> and 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pntd.0003388.e010.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula> are the baseline of carrying capacity, amplitude and phase, respectively. We start our simulations from January 1st, 1977; therefore, we have the phase chosen as 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pntd.0003388.e011.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula> so as to start with a low mosquito abundance. Due to the lack of field data specific to the situation we are modeling for mosquitoes, we could not get true values for baseline of mosquito carrying capacity 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pntd.0003388.e012.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula> and amplitude 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pntd.0003388.e013.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula>.
</p>
