<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack>
 <p>The authors would like to acknowledge the valuable contributions of the members of the Guillain-Barré syndrome -University Hospital -Mexican Institute of Social Security Working Group (GBS HU-IMSS WORKING GROUP): Alan Israel Benítez Álvarez, MD. Department of Neurology, University Hospital José Eleuterio González, Universidad Autonoma de Nuevo León, Monterrey, Nuevo León, Mexico; Alejandro Marfil-Rivera, MD. Department of Neurology, University Hospital José Eleuterio González, Universidad Autonoma de Nuevo León, Monterrey, Nuevo León, Mexico; Ana Sepúlveda-Núñez, MD. Epidemiology Division, UMAE Hospital de Especialidades No. 25, Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social, Monterrey, Nuevo León, Mexico; Atzimba Álvarez Cortés, MD. Epidemiology Division, UMAE Hospital de Especialidades No. 25, Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social, Monterrey, Nuevo León, Mexico; Beatriz Eugenia Chávez-Luevanos, MD. Department of Neurology, University Hospital José Eleuterio González, Universidad Autonoma de Nuevo León, Monterrey, Nuevo León, Mexico; Elsa Sierra-González, MD. Hospital General de Zona No. 33, Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social, Monterrey, Nuevo León, Mexico; Gabriela López-Becerril, RN. Medical Research Unit for Neurological Diseases, UMAE Hospital de Especialidades, Centro Médico Nacional Siglo XXI, Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social, Mexico City, Mexico; Gloria Nallely Velázquez-Castaño, MD. Department of Neurology, University Hospital José Eleuterio González, Universidad Autonoma de Nuevo León, Monterrey, Nuevo León, Mexico; Héctor Jorge Villarreal-Montemayor, MD. Department of Neurology, University Hospital José Eleuterio González, Universidad Autonoma de Nuevo León, Monterrey, Nuevo León, Mexico; Mallela Azuara-Castillo, MD. Hospital General de Zona No. 33, Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social, Monterrey, Nuevo León, Mexico; María Garza-Sagástegui, MD. Medical Provisions Directorate of Nuevo León State. Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social, Monterrey, Nuevo León, Mexico; Omar Israel Campos-Villarreal, MD. Department of Neurology, UMAE Hospital de Especialidades No. 25, Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social, Monterrey, Nuevo León, Mexico; Roberto Corrales-Pérez, MD. Medical Epidemiology Assistance Coordinator of Nuevo León State, Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social, Monterrey, Nuevo León, Mexico; Shaira España-Pérez, MD. Department of Neurology, University Hospital José Eleuterio González, Universidad Autonoma de Nuevo León, Monterrey, Nuevo León, Mexico; Víctor Hugo Borja-Aburto, MD, PhD. Primary Health-Care Unit. Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social, Mexico City, Mexico.</p>
</ack>
