<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Group B included the apoptosis inducers OSU-03012 and Obatoclax. OSU-03012 is described as a celecoxib derivative kinase inhibitor that does not inhibit cyclooxygenase activity, but instead downregulates the PI3K/Akt pathway that is involved in multiple cell signaling pathways [
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-12-01041" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. OSU-03012 has exhibited in vitro and/or in vivo antimicrobial activities against a wide range of pathogens (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t007" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-12-01041" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-12-01041" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. OSU-03012 has also been described to inhibit ZIKV PRVABC59 in Huh-7 cells (EC
 <sub>50</sub> of 0.82–0.88 µM), U251 cells (EC
 <sub>50</sub> of 0.84 µM) and SF268 cells (EC
 <sub>50</sub> of 1.18 µM) [
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-12-01041" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], and against ZIKV-MEX-2-81 in U2OS cells (EC
 <sub>50</sub> of 0.9 µM) [
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-12-01041" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Here, we have identified OSU-03012 as a weak post- and co- treatment inhibitor (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and 
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, respectively) and a moderate pre-treatment inhibitor based on SI-MTT (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), and a potent pre- and co-treatment inhibitor, and a weak post-treatment inhibitor based on SI-XTT. In addition, OSU-03012 was a weak inhibitor of ZIKV MR-766 based on SI-MTT and moderate inhibitor based on SI-XTT (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>), and a weak inhibitor of PRVABC59 based on SI-MTT and moderate inhibitor based on SI-XTT (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). In A549 cells, OSU-03012 was identified as a moderate inhibitor based on the SI-MTT and SI-XTT (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). Obatoclax has been described as a cell-directed anticancer compound that targets cellular myeloid leukemia cell differentiation protein (Mcl-1) and it has been shown to inhibit endocytosis and membrane fusion of various viruses (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t007" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B25-viruses-12-01041" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-viruses-12-01041" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Obatoclax has been previously described to have anti-ZIKV activity in retinal pigment epithelial (RPE) cells infected with ZIKV FB-GWUH-2016 (EC
 <sub>50</sub> 0.04 µM) [
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-12-01041" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], but it did not exhibit inhibitory activity in JEG-3 cells infected with a ZIKV cocktail of MR-766, FSS13025, and MEX-2-81 [
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-12-01041" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. We identified Obatoclax as a weak post-treatment inhibitor (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), a moderate pre-treatment inhibitor (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), and a potent co-treatment inhibitor (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>) based on SI-MTT values and as a potent post-, pre-, and co-treatment inhibitor based on SI-XTT values. Co-treatment results were consistent with the ability of Obatoclax to inhibit membrane fusion for other viruses. Obatoclax was a weak inhibitor of ZIKV MR-766 based on SI-MTT and moderate inhibitor based on SI-XTT (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). In addition, it is a weak inhibitor of PRVABC59 based on SI-MTT and a potent inhibitor based on SI-XTT (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). In A549 cells, Obatoclax was identified as a weak inhibitor based on the SI-MTT and SI-XTT (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). Although not identified as a potent inhibitor in any condition, OSU-03012 has the ability to inhibit ZIKV replication for multiple strains. Obatoclax was identified as a potent co-treatment inhibitor making it a good candidate for the treatment of ZIKV infection.
</p>
