<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Group C included Azaribine, Azauridine, and Pyrazofurin, which are known inhibitors of orotidine monophosphate decarboxylase (OMPD), a key enzyme involved in the pyrimidine biosynthesis pathway. Azaribine, the triacetate salt of Azauridine, was developed for the treatment of psoriasis and has been identified as an antiviral inhibitor of several RNA viruses (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t007" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-12-01041" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-viruses-12-01041" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-viruses-12-01041" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Our results identified Azaribine as a potent post- and co-treatment inhibitor based on SI-MTT and SI-XTT (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, respectively) and a moderate pre-treatment inhibitor based on SI-MTT and weak inhibitor based on SI-XTT (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Azaribine was a weak inhibitor of ZIKV MR-766 based on SI-MTT and SI-XTT (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>), and a moderate inhibitor of PRVABC59 based on SI-MTT and SI-XTT (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). In A549 cells, Azaribine was identified as a weak inhibitor based on the SI-MTT and SI-XTT (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). Azauridine inhibits de novo pyrimidine synthesis and DNA synthesis and is converted intracellularly into mono-, di-, and tri-phosphate derivatives that can be incorporated into RNA and inhibit protein synthesis [
 <xref rid="B30-viruses-12-01041" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Azauridine has been described as a broad-spectrum antiviral with activity against various viruses (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t007" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B16-viruses-12-01041" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-12-01041" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-viruses-12-01041" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-viruses-12-01041" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-viruses-12-01041" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-viruses-12-01041" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Azauridine has been previously described to inhibit ZIKV DAKAR B11514 (EC
 <sub>50</sub> of 1.5 µM), MR-766 (EC
 <sub>50</sub> of 0.98 µM) and PRVABC59 (EC
 <sub>50</sub> of 0.61 µM) strains in Vero cells, and against ZIKV KX197192.1 strain (EC
 <sub>50</sub> of 2.3 µM) in Huh7 cells [
 <xref rid="B32-viruses-12-01041" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-viruses-12-01041" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. We identified Azauridine as a weak in pre- and co-treatment inhibitor based on SI-MTT and SI-XTT (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and 
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, respectively) and a moderate post-treatment inhibitor based on SI-MTT and SI-XTT (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). In addition, Azauridine was found to be a moderate inhibitor of ZIKV MR-766 based on SI-MTT and SI-XTT (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>) and a moderate inhibitor of PRVABC59 based on SI-MTT and SI-XTT (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). In A549 cells, Azauridine was identified as a moderate inhibitor based on the SI-MTT and SI-XTT (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). Pyrazofurin has been shown to be a potent antiviral agent that inhibits multiplication of various viruses (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t007" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-12-01041" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-viruses-12-01041" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-viruses-12-01041" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-viruses-12-01041" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Our results identified Pyrazofurin as a weak pre- and co-treatment inhibitor based on SI-MTT and SI-XTT (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and 
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, respectively) and a moderate and weak post-treatment inhibitor based on SI-MTT and SI-XTT, respectively (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Pyrazofurin was a moderate inhibitor of ZIKV MR-766) and PRVABC59 based on SI-MTT and SI-XTT (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> and 
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>, respectively), and in A549 cells, it was identified as a moderate inhibitor based on the SI-MTT and SI-XTT (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01041-t006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). Altogether, Azaribine was identified as a potent post- and co-treatment inhibitor making it of value for treatment of ZIKV infections. Despite not being identified as potent inhibitors in any condition, Azauridine and Pyrazofurin have the ability to inhibit replication of multiple ZIKV strains.
</p>
