<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Hepatitis A virus reaches the gastrointestinal tract generally by contaminated food. There is evidence that the virus infects the crypt cells of the small intestine, before it spreads via the blood system and reaches its principal target organ, the liver, and replicates there in hepatocytes. The proteins TIM-1 and TIM-3 have been identified as cellular receptors; an alternative entry pathway seems to exist for virus particles complexed with IgA molecules. These immunocomplexed viruses can bind to IgA receptors on the surface of hepatocytes. Replication of hepatitis A virus occurs in the liver 8–10 days before the onset of symptoms. The viruses spread to the intestine through the bile duct, and are excreted in the faeces. During this phase, viruses are also present in the blood, reaching concentrations of up to 10
 <sup>5</sup> virus particles per millilitre. The peak of virus release has already passed at the onset of the disease. Liver cells are destroyed by infection-induced mechanisms, viral proteins are found in the cytoplasm and even virus particles can be detected by electron microscopy. The very massive damage of liver cells leads to the release of bilirubin and transaminases into the blood. In contrast to other picornaviruses, in hepatitis A virus, functions responsible for the virus-host shutoff effect are not or are only weakly developed. Liver cells are not primarily destroyed by the viral infection. Instead, the cellular immune response is principally responsible for this process, as cytotoxic CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells have been detected in the liver of patients with acute hepatitis A. These cells release interferon-γ and give rise to the active immigration of other immunologically active cells into the liver. Infiltrating mononuclear cells are mostly located near the liver portal regions. Besides liver cells, also macrophages of the spleen and Kupffer’s star cells (also known as stellate cells) contain viral proteins. They are derived from viruses. In a later infection stage, immigration of CD4
 <sup>+</sup> lymphocytes can be observed. In rare cases, a hepatitis A virus infection can cause a transient granulocytopenia and damage of bone marrow cells.
</p>
