<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0028">MSCs have immunomodulatory properties that make them potential therapeutic tools to repair tissue damage and dampen inflammation in immune-mediated disorders. Indeed, their action is displayed not only in all immune cells, but also in cell populations, such as epithelial cells, endothelial cells, fibroblasts, which take part in inflammatory cascades and are not targeted by other therapies. Moreover, MSCs are an attractive therapeutic option because they elicit no (or a weak) allogeneic immune responses when delivered to a non-identical, non-matched recipient and because they can easily be extracted from a variety of tissues including bone marrow, adipose and placental tissues including umbilical cord blood, and expanded in vitro as well as due to their high safety profile independent to the tissue source and clinical setting 
 <xref rid="bib0031" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. Although they show great promise in the treatment of many immune and inflammatory disorders, the large variability in manufactured cell products, donor cell quality, dosages, formulation as fresh or cryopreserved and differing administration routes have obscured their potential therapeutic benefit. To overcome these hurdles, a careful evaluation of appropriate cell sources, more scientific data and a better mechanistic understanding of immunosuppression of MSCs is needed 
 <xref rid="bib0032" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. The START clinical phase II study has the highest number of MSC-treated patients suffering from (non-COVID) acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS; n = 40), that is, it showed that a single dose of allogeneic bone marrow–derived MSCs did not cause short- or long-term hemodynamic or respiratory adverse events over a 60-day follow-up period. However, no significant improvement in the mortality rate related to ARDS was observed. This may be due to differences in the disease severity within the study populations as well as low MSC viability, ranging from only 35 to 80% 
 <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>.
</p>
