<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Medicinal plants yielding biologically active compounds have always been of great interest to scientists as they play an essential role in preventing human diseases. In the entire world, India is recognized where spices have been traditionally used as a source of medicine. Many active pharmaceutical gradients have been identified and extracted having a wide range of physiological and pharmacological properties (Sachan et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Apart from the regular uses of spices in culinary activities, they are widely used as indigenous medicines, nutraceuticals, in aromatherapy, as natural colouring agents, perfumes, cosmetics etc. In recent years there has been experimental evidence on physiological benefits that could be drawn in the context of various diseases like diabetes, cardiovascular issues and inflammatory disorders like arthritis and cancer. They have also been identified as preventive agents in certain conditions. Spices like red pepper, garlic, and fenugreek have been reported to have hypercholesterolemic activity, whereas fenugreek and garlic are also known to reduce and control blood sugar levels (Bhagya &amp; Raveendra, 
 <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). The main active ingredient of turmeric, Curcumin has been widely studied to have a broad spectrum of medicinal value ranging from anti-cancerous, anti-inflammatory and an anti-amyloidogenic activity (Bhagya &amp; Raveendra, 
 <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Several computational studies related to drug or vaccine development against SARS-CoV-2 is recently published (Aanouz et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Gupta et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Joshi et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Muralidharan et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Sarma et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>).
</p>
