<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Factor H is an abundant plasma protein, which has a regulatory function in the homeostasis of the complement system and in the protection of bystander host cells and tissues from injury via the complement activation of the alternative pathway (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). The most important point in the complement activation is the regulation of C3 convertase, which is monitored by factor H, a well-established sialic acid binder. A number of bacteria can recruit factor H via the presentation of specific binding proteins, including factor H binding proteins (fHbp) of 
 <italic>Neisseria meningitidis</italic> (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>), CspA and outer surface protein E of 
 <italic>Borrelia burgdorferi</italic> (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>), staphylococcal binder of IgG from 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>), and pneumococcal surface protein C of 
 <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). The factor H ligands, expressed by pathogens, are structurally distinct from each other, but they share the related binding site on factor H that can be localized on a common site of the CCP20 module (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). These interactions increase the binding ability of CCP 19-20 modules to C3b, resulting in a stable complex between factor H, C3b and microbial targets, with an enhanced co-factor activity. 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> express sialic acid on their surfaces, which reduces complement deposition via probable factor H recruitment. Sialic acid also recruits siglec-7/9 leading to immune escape (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). In addition, factor H binds to ApoE on High Density Lipoprotein (HDL) via CCP 5-7 modules, and is used by the bacteria to mimic the plasma HDL to increase their survival in the blood (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>).
</p>
