<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>First, discrete time survival analysis [
 <xref rid="pone.0210645.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0210645.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] was used to estimate age-specific monthly probabilities of dying in age groups 0, 1–11, 12–23, 24–35, 36–47, and 48–59 completed months using weighted logistic regression. Following previous work [
 <xref rid="pone.0210645.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], we picked one-year age groups with a separate age group for the first month, to account for the comparatively larger number of neonatal deaths. The weights account for the two-stage cluster design of the DHS surveys. The weight attached to each respondent reflects the sampling probability as well as a non-response adjustment. Consequently the variances associated with these estimates also reflect the survey design and the related uncertainty is propagated through to the estimates of the U5MR and its standard errors, which are the inputs to our smoothing model. For each survey, a separate weighted logistic regression model was estimated for each place and time period, resulting in survey-place-time-age-specific estimated monthly probabilities of dying with variance estimates that fully accounted for the specific design of the survey. Each model included child months that began in the specified time period at the specified place. Space was aggregated into Admin-1 geographical units and time into five-year periods from 1980–2014. Admin 0 and Admin 1 refer to administrative boundaries at the national level and the first sub-national level, respectively. The majority of DHS are designed so that there are sufficient samples to produce results that are representative at the Admin 1 level. Using a synthetic cohort approach and the standard life table definition of 
 <sub>5</sub>q
 <sub>0</sub>, the estimated monthly probabilities of dying were used to construct estimates for the U5MR, 
 <inline-formula id="pone.0210645.e001">
  <alternatives>
   <graphic xlink:href="pone.0210645.e001.jpg" id="pone.0210645.e001g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="M1">
    <mrow>
     <mover accent="true">
      <mrow>
       <msub>
        <mrow/>
        <mn>5</mn>
       </msub>
       <msub>
        <mtext>q</mtext>
        <mn>0</mn>
       </msub>
      </mrow>
      <mo stretchy="true">^</mo>
     </mover>
    </mrow>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
 </inline-formula>, and the variance of each 
 <inline-formula id="pone.0210645.e002">
  <alternatives>
   <graphic xlink:href="pone.0210645.e002.jpg" id="pone.0210645.e002g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="M2">
    <mrow>
     <mover accent="true">
      <mrow>
       <msub>
        <mrow/>
        <mn>5</mn>
       </msub>
       <msub>
        <mtext>q</mtext>
        <mn>0</mn>
       </msub>
      </mrow>
      <mo stretchy="true">^</mo>
     </mover>
    </mrow>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
 </inline-formula> was calculated via the delta method approach based on the estimated covariance matrices produced by the logistic regression models used to obtain the monthly probabilities of dying [
 <xref rid="pone.0210645.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Because most countries have more than one DHS survey, during a given time period many places had U5MR estimates derived from multiple surveys. These were combined into a single place-time-specific 
 <inline-formula id="pone.0210645.e003">
  <alternatives>
   <graphic xlink:href="pone.0210645.e003.jpg" id="pone.0210645.e003g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="M3">
    <mrow>
     <mover accent="true">
      <mrow>
       <msub>
        <mrow/>
        <mn>5</mn>
       </msub>
       <msub>
        <mtext>q</mtext>
        <mn>0</mn>
       </msub>
      </mrow>
      <mo stretchy="true">^</mo>
     </mover>
    </mrow>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
 </inline-formula> by constructing an inverse-variance weighted average of the survey-specific estimates—a standard meta-analysis approach (this operation is carried out on the logistic scale). Finally, to correct the bias caused by HIV, described above, we applied HIV prevalence-calibrated correction factors to the 
 <inline-formula id="pone.0210645.e004">
  <alternatives>
   <graphic xlink:href="pone.0210645.e004.jpg" id="pone.0210645.e004g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="M4">
    <mrow>
     <mover accent="true">
      <mrow>
       <msub>
        <mrow/>
        <mn>5</mn>
       </msub>
       <msub>
        <mtext>q</mtext>
        <mn>0</mn>
       </msub>
      </mrow>
      <mo stretchy="true">^</mo>
     </mover>
    </mrow>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
 </inline-formula> as described by Walker et al [
 <xref rid="pone.0210645.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].
</p>
