<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0290">The following steps were used by the authors of this paper, based upon research performed using TISM by Ref. [
 <xref rid="bib132" ref-type="bibr">[132]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib133" ref-type="bibr">[133]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib134" ref-type="bibr">[134]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib135" ref-type="bibr">[135]</xref>]:
 <list list-type="simple" id="olist0010">
  <list-item id="o0010">
   <label>1.</label>
   <p id="p0295">
    <bold>Identification of the factors:</bold> The first step was to identify the factors that cause repeated emergence of pandemics. The factors, listed in 
    <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> , were identified through literature review and from expert opinion.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0015">
   <label>2.</label>
   <p id="p0300">
    <bold>Interpretation of relationships among factors:</bold> In the TISM approach, this step answers the question, ‘how’, and is designed to help researchers to understand how Factor 1 influences Factor 2.The relative strength of relationships was represented on a scale between 0 and 4 in ascending order of strength. For this study, 25 responses were obtained from professors, scientists and researchers in life sciences in India. The respondents were selected on the basis of their backgrounds, especially in biomedical research or in teaching Eco-biology.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0020">
   <label>3.</label>
   <p id="p0305">
    <bold>Initial Reachability Matrix (IRM) was used to establish interconnectedness’s among factors</bold>: To arrive at the Initial Reachability Matrix (IRM), the contextual relationships among the factors had to be determined. The IRM represents the direct relationships among factors. For instance, it is needed to see whether a certain factor ‘A’ has an influence on the qualitative nature or the quantitative value of another factor ‘B’. If there is a strong or very strong influence, then ‘1’ is entered in the appropriate cell of the initial form of the reachability matrix. Else, ‘0’ is entered. To aggregate the responses of individual experts, mode is used as a method of compilation. 
    <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> presents the IRM that represents the direct relationships for the causative factors which were found to be influential in the disease ecology of emerging infectious diseases.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0025">
   <label>4.</label>
   <p id="p0310">Developing the Final Reachability Matrix (FRM) after checking for transitivity:</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
