<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0315">This process allows checking for transitivity that has been caused because of inference, between some of the pairs that are a part of the reachability matrix initially created. A transitivity check must be done before arriving at the FRM to find the significant relationships, among factors which were not directly represented in the IRM. The transitivity check was performed on all entries with ‘0’ in the IRM. 1∗ or 1∗∗ signifies the presence of transitivity, and the lack of it means that the original value of ‘0’ can be retained. 1∗ implies first level transitivity wherein if P = Q and Q = R then P = R. 1∗∗ implies second level transitivity wherein if P = Q, Q = R, and R = S, then P
 <div name="E00C" description="bond, double bond" class="private-char" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span id="pc-E00C" format="PBM" resolution="300" x-size="12" y-size="9" class="glyph-data"> 000000000000 000000000000 000000000000 111111111111 000000000000 111111111111 000000000000 000000000000 000000000000 </span>
 </div>S. 
 <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> presents the FRM that was determined for this paper.
 <list list-type="simple" id="olist0015">
  <list-item id="o0030">
   <label>5.</label>
   <p id="p0320">
    <bold>Partition of the factors from FRM into different levels</bold>: In this step, the FRM was partitioned into three sets. The first set, called the reachability set, was comprised of the row elements of the final reachability matrix. The second set, called the antecedent set, was comprised of the column elements of the final reachability matrix. The third set is called the intersection set, and it was comprised of common elements of the previous two sets. In Iteration-1, the intersection elements were ‘one’ and indicate reachability set. These factors were removed from the set and designated as level-1 factors. The process was repeated until the partitioned reachability matrices were obtained at various levels.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0035">
   <label>6.</label>
   <p id="p0325">
    <bold>Interaction matrix derived from direct and transitive links:</bold> From the expert opinion, the significant transitive links were drawn, which are highly influential relationship links among the transitive links of the FRM. The interaction matrix was developed by using the direct links as well as the transitive links that were significant. Interaction matrix representing the direct and significant transitive relationships of the causative factors which were found to be influential in the disease ecology of repeatedly emerging infectious diseases as depicted in 
    <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0040">
   <label>7.</label>
   <p id="p0330">
    <bold>Creating the digraph and the TISM model:</bold> At the final level, an entity known as the digraph, an acronym for directed graph, was created. The contents of the FRM as well as the level partitions were used for this purpose. After the digraph was developed, the direct and the significant transitive links were used to derive useful conclusions. The factors at the top of the model were called the first level factors. Subsequently, going down the digraph, the numeric value of each level increases in ascending order, one at a time. Then, using results from the interpretative matrix and the digraph, the TISM model was developed. The TISM model representing the direct and significant transitive relationships of the causative factors which were found to be influential in the disease ecology of emerging infectious diseases contains eight levels. The level eight is the base level, if any changes happened in the level-VIII factors (F4) may reflect in all other factors. The level-VII factors can influence all other factors except level-VIII factors. Likewise the factor’s impact is on upward direction; i.e., the factors in the bottom levels determines the performance of those factors in the top levels
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
