<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In order to demonstrate our methods with known data, we ran one thousand stochastic, event-based simulations with pre-defined epidemiological parameter values, where each simulation consisted of 15 plant/vector cohort repetitions. We calculated AAP and IAP response curves from the means of these simulations over these sets and computed values for initial slope and initial acceleration from the overall mean response curves. This resulted in gradient values that were equated to the formulae in 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007724.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> and solved for the virus parameters. The entries in 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007724.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> represent a system of four simultaneous equations in four unknowns that is straightforward to solve. We followed the specific solution order set out in SI section 5 to produce the parameter estimates in 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007724.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. The procedure that was tested using the simulated dataset was next applied to the access period data of Maruthi 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007724.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] for CBSV. Note that Maruthi 
 <italic>et al</italic>. did not use molecular diagnostics to confirm insect infection. Since the access period data of Maruthi 
 <italic>et al</italic>. are somewhat noisy (relating to the number of experimental repetitions used), we fit the general form for acquisition success (i.e., transmission success as a function of acquisition period, Eq S3.6, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1007724.s003">S3 Appendix</xref>) to the acquisition access period data, and the general form for inoculation success (i.e., transmission success as a function of inoculation period, Eq S3.5, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1007724.s003">S3 Appendix</xref>) to the inoculation access period data prior to extracting empirical values for initial slope, initial acceleration and asymptote (i.e., the empirical gradients). Using the same proceedure that we followed for the simulated dataset, these empirical gradients were then matched to the theoretical gradients in 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007724.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> to produce the parameter estimates in 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007724.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> (i.e., we solved the resulting simultaneous equations using the particular order of steps set out in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1007724.s005">S5 Appendix</xref>).
</p>
