<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18">CAP was defined using the definition set forth by the Infectious Society of America/American Thoracic Society Consensus Guidelines [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. In short, CAP was diagnosed when the patients had symptoms associated with respiratory tract infections and had new-onset lung infiltration or pleural effusion on chest X-rays or chest computed tomography scans. We defined fever as any temperature greater than or equal to 38 °C recorded by the tympanic route. The body temperatures of all patients were checked every hour at admission day. During the days after admission, the body temperature was often measured within 1 h when patients had a febrile sense or worsening signs of inflammation. We also recorded body temperature at the beginning of antipyretics administration. There is no standardized antipyretic treatment protocol for fever control. In our study, antipyretic therapy was administered upon reaching a body temperature ≥ of 38 °C. The interval of antipyretics administration was according to pharmacodynamics, although we performed additional antipyretics treatment when patients had a fever (two consecutive measurements ≥38 °C) and deterioration of clinical symptoms, including myalgia, general weakness, cough, nasal congestion, or dyspnea within 6 h after antipyretics administration. Responsiveness to antipyretic treatment was classified as follows: a complete response was recorded when a body temperature drop below 38 °C was observed after antipyretics treatment and sustained throughout; a partial response was recorded when a body temperature drop below 38 °C was observed but there was a resurge during observation or a need for additional antipyretics; and no response was recorded when a sustained body temperature above or equal to 38 °C was observed after antipyretics use. Unresponsive to initial antibiotic treatment was defined as observed deterioration as evidenced by worsening of clinical symptoms and signs and/or progression of lesions on radiological studies after 48 to 72 h of initial antibiotics treatment.
</p>
