<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In order to prevent the introduction of RVFV by camels, the EVS implement a series of measures that include vaccination of imported animals, quarantines and testing of a proportion of them. However, the vaccination strategy is unlikely be effective, as camels imported from Sudan receive a single dose and camels imported from Ethiopia receive two doses, but with only 7 days difference. The inactivated vaccines against RVFV require a booster 3–6 months after initial vaccination, followed by yearly boosters [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006143.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Besides, the efficacy of the inactivated vaccine has not been tested in camels [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006143.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], and further research on that field would be needed. While it has been argued that the long distance that the camels from Sudan need to walk to reach the Egyptian border would be enough to prevent the importation of infected animals, there are still many uncertainties in relation to RVFV infection in camels, and in any case, that measure does not comply with OIE rules for importation of live animals [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006143.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. On the other hand, means of transportation seem to be changing as at least some of the camels are currently transported on trucks rather than on foot (MALRE personal communication) and transmission (either direct or indirect) during the transport of camels cannot be ruled out. Seroconversions in Madagascar highlands evidenced the local circulation of RVFV in periods in which mosquitoes were rare or inactive, suggesting that other forms of transmission seem likely [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006143.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Even though camels are quarantined, for 3 days if coming from Sudan and 10–16 days if coming from Ethiopia, the efficiency of clinical detection of RVFV infection is limited by the fact that infections in camels are often unapparent. Besides, about 10% of the camels imported from Sudan and Ethiopia in the last 5 years were tested against RVF by RT-PCR, and were negative (MALRE personal communication). However, the sensitivity of such non-statistically based testing protocol for detecting the infection, if present, is questionable. While the measures currently implemented in camels are likely to reduce some of the risk of RVFV introduction into Egypt, their effect is likely to be limited. Similar conclusions may be drawn from the strategies implemented in cattle with the particularities that all cattle are slaughtered within the quarantine premises, where the risk of RVFV transmission by vectors was estimated to be very low. Therefore, vaccination of imported cattle is unlikely to have a significant effect on the reduction of the risk of RVFV introduction into Egypt.
</p>
