<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0030">Small-compound drugs act on proteins involved in the viral life cycle: entry into host cells, virus uncoating, replication and translation of the viral genome or suppression of the innate host immune response. The development of viral pseudotypes and virus-like particles (VLPs) has made research and drug discovery into virus entry and uncoating possible at a reduced containment level 
 <xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>. By contrast, analysis of subgenomic replicons enables uncoupling of viral replication, transcription and translation from virus assembly, host cell egress, entry and uncoating. Replicons are broadly defined as autonomously replicating DNA or RNA molecules, whereas viral subgenomic replicons are usually produced by deletion of one or more genes coding for structural proteins or insertion of or replacement by a reporter gene and/or selectable marker 
 <xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>. Replicons have been made possible by the advent of reverse genetics: a process of storage and manipulation of entire viral genomes hosted on plasmids, and the recreation of viral RNA genomes by 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> or 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> transcription of these plasmids. In cases where replicons cannot be established, plasmid-driven co-expression of replication factors necessary to drive replication of a reporter RNA create minimal replication systems termed minigenomes. These reporter RNAs usually contain the genomic 5′ and 3′ untranslated regions (UTRs) which are essential for replication, transcription and translation. Whereas most replicons can be maintained in cell lines by antibiotic selection and passed on during cell division, minigenomes based on plasmid transfection have a limited lifespan and need to be recreated before experimentation. Although not exhaustive, 
 <xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> lists established replicons and minigenome systems for many medically relevant viruses. Since their conception, replicons and minigenomes have been used in low- and high-throughput screens of compound libraries, to elucidate the biological mechanisms of drug action and to screen for drug escape-mutants arising in the replicon-harbouring cell pool owing to generally poor fidelity of viral RNA-dependent RNA polymerases (RdRp).
</p>
