<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The development of 
 <italic>PhyDyn</italic> was influenced by and builds upon previous efforts to incorporate mechanistic infectious disease models in BEAST2. The 
 <italic>bdsir</italic> BEAST2 package [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006546.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] implements a simple SIR model which is fitted using an approximation to the sampling-birth-death process. The 
 <italic>phylodynamics</italic> BEAST2 package [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006546.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] includes simple deterministic and stochastic SIR models which can be fitted using coalescent processes. More recently, the 
 <italic>EpiInf</italic> package has been developed which can fit stochastic SIR models using an exact likelihood with particle filtering [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006546.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. These epidemic modeling packages are, however, limited to unstructured populations (no spatial, risk-group, or demographic population heterogeneity). Other packages have been developed for spatially structured populations with a focus on phylogeographic inference, especially with the aim of estimating pathogen migration rates between discrete spatial locations [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006546.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The 
 <italic>MultiTypeTree</italic> BEAST2 package [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006546.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] implements the exact structured coalescent model with multiple demes and with constant effective population size in each deme and constant migration rates between demes. Two BEAST2 packages, 
 <italic>BASTA</italic> [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006546.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] and 
 <italic>MASCOT</italic> [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006546.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] have been independently developed to use fast approximate structured coalescent models. These packages mirror the functionality of 
 <italic>MultiTypeTree</italic> but include approximations to reduce computational requirements, enabling estimation of time-invariant effective population sizes and migration rates between spatial demes.
</p>
