<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>IFN-α, ribavirin, and inosine pranobex are also used for SSPE treatment, with relative long-term effectiveness [
 <xref rid="B210-viruses-11-01017" ref-type="bibr">210</xref>]. Many clinical reports show that Ribavirin can decrease measles antibody titers in cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) of SSPE patients and improve neurologic symptoms without side effects [
 <xref rid="B211-viruses-11-01017" ref-type="bibr">211</xref>,
 <xref rid="B212-viruses-11-01017" ref-type="bibr">212</xref>], especially when combined with IFN-α. In rare cases, long term IFN-α treatment stabilizes clinical symptoms of SSPE patients for years [
 <xref rid="B213-viruses-11-01017" ref-type="bibr">213</xref>]. A recent study suggests also that continuous intraventricular administration of ribavirin and interferon-α in CSF by using a subcutaneous infusion pump, combined with oral administration of inosine pranobex, could limit the progression of SSPE [
 <xref rid="B214-viruses-11-01017" ref-type="bibr">214</xref>]. Intrathecal IFN-α treatment combined with oral isoprinosine could also be effective to treat SSPE patients and is the most common treatment used nowadays [
 <xref rid="B215-viruses-11-01017" ref-type="bibr">215</xref>,
 <xref rid="B216-viruses-11-01017" ref-type="bibr">216</xref>]. Isoprinosine is a derivative of inosine and aims at blocking viral replication, probably through an immunoregulatory activity. Again, these treatments have rarely been shown to recover loss of function but they can stabilize the disease for several years [
 <xref rid="B98-viruses-11-01017" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>,
 <xref rid="B213-viruses-11-01017" ref-type="bibr">213</xref>,
 <xref rid="B217-viruses-11-01017" ref-type="bibr">217</xref>]. Despite the benefits of IFN-α treatments, its use can be associated with side effects and could lead to interferonopathies [
 <xref rid="B218-viruses-11-01017" ref-type="bibr">218</xref>]. Alternatively, there is induction of IFNα/β in vivo with MeV infection. This induction is associated at least partially to the presence of defective interfering (DI) particles which are also reducing the viral replication by occupying the proteins from the replication machinery and may thus constitute helpful complementary tool for treatments [
 <xref rid="B219-viruses-11-01017" ref-type="bibr">219</xref>,
 <xref rid="B220-viruses-11-01017" ref-type="bibr">220</xref>].
</p>
