<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0205">Out of the four antiviral drugs that may show CAD’s mode of action, two drugs have been claimed to utilize this mechanism: tilorone and arbidol (umifenovir). Even though tilorone was invented in the US as an interferon inducing broad spectrum antiviral, additional studies showed that its lysosomotropic potential is comparable to chloroquine, which likely contributes to its antiviral properties [
 <xref rid="bib0125" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Tilorone is currently registered and used only in Russia and some neighbouring countries, where it is approved for indications such as influenza, acute respiratory viral infection, viral hepatitis, viral encephalitis and myelitis. Arbidol is registered in Russia and China for the treatment of influenza [
 <xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. It is claimed to inhibit the membrane fusion of virus with the endosomal membrane, which possibly occurs 
 <italic>via</italic> increasing the endosomal pH, and thereby preventing infection of the cell. The third antiviral, nelfinavir is a protease inhibitor drug approved for treatment of HIV infection, but also reported effective against a wide variety of viruses: Herpes simplex, SARS-CoV, hepatitis C, dengue and Chikungunya [
 <xref rid="bib0115" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] (DrugVirus database). It is likely that its lysosomotropic properties may be responsible for this broad-spectrum activity. The last identified antiviral drug is vicriviroc, which was developed as nanomolar CCR5 antagonist for HIV infections and came to phase III clinical trials where it did not meet primary efficacy endpoints. When analysing the potential of repurposing such highly specific and potent antiviral drugs for fighting a different virus, it should be kept in mind that they would likely need a much higher concentration since their original target that they are specifically acting upon is not present in other viruses. Impact of strong lysosomotropic compounds on membranes and membrane trafficking often needs low micromolar concentrations [
 <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. It remains to be seen whether efficacious levels of any of CADs can be achieved in COVID-19 patients without trespassing into toxicity levels. In the case of CAD’s antiviral activity, it is worth investigating whether stereoselectivity could help to further separate activity and toxicity dose ranges. It has been shown previously that enantiomers (mirror image compounds) have different affinities for a range protein targets, including hERG [
 <xref rid="bib0185" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. If the antiviral effect of CADs is linked only to their physico-chemical properties, which are the same for both enantiomers, they would have the same activity, but may differ in the affinity for hERG. This would result in one enantiomer having a better safety profile than the other, with unchanged antiviral activity. 20/26 compounds from 
 <xref rid="tbl0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> possess at least one chiral centre, some even more than 10, meaning that there are many potential enantiomer pairs that could be examined from the perspective of obtaining increased safety margins.
</p>
