<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The long-term goal of SARS-CoV-2 research is developing an effective vaccine to yield neutralizing antibodies. The National Institutes of Health in the US, and Baylor University in Waco, Texas, are working on a vaccine based on what they know about the coronavirus in general, using information from the SARS outbreak. In addition, the recent mapping of the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein may pave the way for more rapid development of a specific vaccine [
 <xref rid="B76-pathogens-09-00231" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. Of interest is the use of a relatively new vaccine technology, RNA vaccines that have the ability to elicit potent immune responses against infectious diseases and certain cancers [
 <xref rid="B77-pathogens-09-00231" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>,
 <xref rid="B78-pathogens-09-00231" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. Traditional vaccines stimulate the production of antibodies via challenges with purified proteins from the pathogens, or by using whole cells (live, attenuated vaccines). While very effective, the creation of new vaccines can take years. Alternatively, RNA-based vaccines use mRNA that upon entering cells, are translated to antigenic molecules that in turn, stimulate the immune system. This process has been used effectively against some cancers [
 <xref rid="B79-pathogens-09-00231" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>,
 <xref rid="B80-pathogens-09-00231" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>], and clinical trials are underway for several other cancers [
 <xref rid="B81-pathogens-09-00231" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. In addition, the production of RNA-based vaccines is more rapid and less expensive than traditional vaccines, which can be a major advantage in pandemic situations. Clinical trials for an mRNA-based SARS-CoV-2 vaccine are currently underway [
 <xref rid="B82-pathogens-09-00231" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. Study subjects will receive the mRNA vaccine in two doses, 28 days apart and the safety and immunogenicity will be assessed.
</p>
