<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<notes id="n1">
 <title>Notes</title>
 <p>
  <bold>
   <italic>Author contributions.</italic>
  </bold> L. S. V., R. D. K., O. K., and A. R. designed the study. L. S. V. and R. D. K. formulated the analyses. L. S. V. performed the analyses. K. M., K. C. C., C. S., and J. B. performed HCV sequencing. J. F., D. B., E. B., M. H., N. L., M. C., M. R., H. G., and O. K. contributed cohort data and/or contributed to the analyses. L. S. V., R. D. K., and A. R. drafted the first version of the manuscript, which was then revised by all the other authors. All authors contributed to the interpretation of the results.
 </p>
 <p>
  <bold>
   <italic>Acknowledgments.</italic>
  </bold> We thank the participating patients, physicians, and study nurses for outstanding patient care, and the Data Center and the Coordination Center for continuous support. The members of the Swiss HIV Cohort Study (SHCS) are: Aubert V., Battegay M., Bernasconi E., Böni J., Braun D. L., Bucher H. C., Calmy A., Cavassini M., Ciuffi A., Dollenmaier G., Egger M., Elzi L., Fehr J., Fellay J., Furrer H. (Chairman of the Clinical and Laboratory Committee), Fux C. A., Günthard H. F. (President of the SHCS), Haerry D. (Deputy of Positive Council), Hasse B., Hirsch H. H., Hoffmann M., Hösli I., Kahlert C., Kaiser L., Keiser O., Klimkait T., Kouyos R. D, Kovari H., Ledergerber B., Martinetti G., Martinez de Tejada B., Marzolini C., Metzner K. J., Müller N., Nicca D., Pantaleo G., Paioni P., Rauch A. (Chairman of the Scientific Board), Rudin C. (Chairman of the Mother and Child Substudy), Scherrer A. U. (Head of Data Centre), Schmid P., Speck R., Stöckle M., Tarr P., Trkola A., Vernazza P., Wandeler G., Weber R., and Yerly S.
 </p>
 <p>
  <bold>
   <italic>Disclaimer</italic>.
  </bold> The funders had no role in the study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.
 </p>
 <p>
  <bold>
   <italic>Financial support.</italic>
  </bold> This work was supported by the Swiss National Science Foundation (grant numbers 33CSC0-108787 and 324730_179567 to the Swiss HIV Cohort Study, BSSGI0_155851 to R. D. K., and 163878 professorship grant to O. K.); and University of Zurich Clinical Research Priority Program Viral Infectious Diseases grant to D. L. B. 
 </p>
 <p>
  <bold>
   <italic>Potential conflicts of interest.</italic>
  </bold> L. S. V. received a travel grant from Gilead. H. F. G. has received unrestricted research grants from Gilead Sciences and Roche; fees for data and safety monitoring board membership from Merck; consulting/advisory board membership fees from Gilead Sciences, Sandoz, and Mepha. A. R. reports support for advisory boards and/or travel grants from Janssen-Cilag, MSD, Gilead Sciences, Abbvie, and Bristol-Myers Squibb, and an unrestricted research grant from Gilead Sciences, all paid to his institution. K. J. M. has received travel grants and honoraria from Gilead Sciences, Roche Diagnostics, GlaxoSmithKline, Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme, Bristol-Myers Squibb, ViiV, and Abbott; and the University of Zurich received research grants from Gilead Science, Roche, and Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme for studies that K. J. M. serves as principal investigator, and advisory board honoraria from Gilead Sciences. D. L. B. reports support for advisory boards and/or travel grants from MSD, ViiV, and Gilead Sciences. N. D. L. reports support for a plenary presentation from Gilead Sciences paid to his home institution. R. D. K. reports personal fees from Gilead Sciences outside the submitted work. E. B. reports support for advisory boards from MSD, Gilead Sciences, ViiV Healthcare, Pfizer, Sandoz, and Abbott. O. K. reports grants from Gilead. M. C. reports grants from ViiV and Gilead Sciences and fees for expert opinion from Viiv, MSD, and Gilead, all paid to his institution. J. F. reports grants from Merck and ViiV Healthcare. M. R. reports travel grants from BMS and Gilead. All other authors report no potential conflicts. All authors have submitted the ICMJE Form for Disclosure of Potential Conflicts of Interest. Conflicts that the editors consider relevant to the content of the manuscript have been disclosed.
 </p>
 <p>Presented in part: Conference on Retroviruses and Opportunistic Infections, 4–7 March 2018, Boston, MA (abstract number 130).</p>
</notes>
