<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0170">In a more recent study, other stilbene disulfonic acids resulted to inhibit IN by a novel mechanism [
 <xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>] (
 <xref rid="fig13" ref-type="fig">Fig. 13</xref> ). IN is an essential enzyme for HIV-1 replication, catalysing the insertion of the newly synthesized viral DNA into the host chromosome by two steps: 3′ processing (3′P), that is the IN-catalysed cleavage of the terminal dinucleotide at the 3′-end of the viral DNA mimic, and strand transfer (ST), that is integration of the 3′P product in the host DNA. Clinical integrase ST inhibitors, like raltegravir (RAL), bind the IN active site [
 <xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. However, IN tends to mutate giving rise to drug resistance. Therefore, Aknin et al. used a high-throughput screening approach to find ST inhibitors targeting IN outside of its catalytic site. In a preliminary screening they identified NSC34931 (stilbenavir, 
 <xref rid="fig13" ref-type="fig">Fig. 13</xref>), a compound already known for its cytopathic effects on HIV-1 [
 <xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>], as the most active among the molecules that showed an inhibitory activity on ST step. Notably, NCS34931 consisted of a chemical scaffold different from that of the known ST inhibitors. SAR studies were performed on the selected compounds and the naphthalene moiety resulted to be fundamental for the activity. Indeed, NSC163 and NSC163175 (
 <xref rid="fig13" ref-type="fig">Fig. 13</xref>), lacking aromatic rings, were completely inactive at the highest concentrations tested, and replacing the naphthalene ring with an ethoxybenzene caused a 10-fold decrease of potency in NSC47745 (
 <xref rid="fig13" ref-type="fig">Fig. 13</xref>). NSC34933, with just some rearrangements in the naphthalene substitution pattern with respect to NSC34931, appeared to maintain the sub-micromolar activity of the parent compound and to be even less cytotoxic (
 <xref rid="fig13" ref-type="fig">Fig. 13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> ). The two compounds were tested against clinically relevant mutants resistant to conventional IN inhibitors and the stilbene derivatives maintain their activity at sub-micromolar concentration, representing a potential therapeutic alternative. Indeed, they were found to compete with DNA in binding IN, especially involving the 
 <italic>C</italic>-terminal domain (CTD), at concentrations 10 times lower than that necessary to inhibit 3′P and ST [
 <xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>].
</p>
