<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0095">Clinical considerations for PPE selection while of great importance, probably require less change from our established practice than might be first thought. One of the consequences of HIV/AIDS epidemic of the 1980's and 1990s was an understanding of “Universal Precautions”, the presumption that all patients were an infection risk, and acting accordingly. The primary modification in the current environment is the more thorough use of PPE, including a well fitting respirator. The most common types of respirators in healthcare are N95 filtering face piece respirators (FFRs), surgical N95 FFRs, and PAPRs (available at: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/using-ppe.html" id="intref0045" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/using-ppe.html</ext-link>). Of these 3 options, PAPRs have a higher assigned protection factor than that of the reusable elastomeric nonpowered air-purifying half face piece (half mask) or disposable N95 FFRs (
 <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> ; additional information available at: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://multimedia.3m.com/mws/media/1794572O/surgical-n95-vs-standard-n95-which-to-consider.pdf" id="intref0050" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://multimedia.3m.com/mws/media/1794572O/surgical-n95-vs-standard-n95-which-to-consider.pdf</ext-link>). PAPRs reduce the aerosol concentration inhaled by the wearer to at least 1/25th of that in the air compared with the 1/10th reduction for FFRs and elastomeric half face piece air-purifying respirators. PAPRS can be used during procedures in which HCP are exposed to a greater risk of aerosolized pathogens
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> [available at: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/ppe-strategy/burn-calculator.html" id="intref0055" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/ppe-strategy/burn-calculator.html</ext-link>; personal protective equipment (PPE) burn rate calculator Excel icon (3 sheets)].
</p>
