<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Two cases can be distinguished with regard to pathogen adaptation to new host species: in the first, the pathogen completes its cycle and survives normally in a given species which acts as reservoir host, but occasionally infects other(s), causing disease in these “incidental hosts.” This occurs in a number of zoonoses. A good example is given by highly pathogenic avian influenza virus subtype H5N1 of Asian origin (H5N1 HPAIV), now present on three continents. Different wild birds act as reservoir hosts for this virus, which affects severely different species of domestic poultry, causing enormous losses to the poultry industry (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Alexander, 2000</xref>). However, besides birds, it occasionally affects some species of mammals, including humans (causing a zoonosis), cats, and mustelids like ferrets and martens, in which it is extremely pathogenic. Nevertheless, transmission of H5N1 HPAIV between individuals in mammal species is not effective at all (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">Imai and Kawaoka, 2012</xref>), a fact that luckily prevents by now a possible pandemic of disastrous consequences for humankind. In the second case, the adaptation to new species is more “genuine” in the sense that the pathogen has indeed crossed the “species barrier,” that is, has established a complete cycle of transmission in a new species. It can be assumed that all viruses currently known went through a process like this in their past evolution to adapt to the species which are their current natural hosts. Influenza viruses themselves were adapted to their avian hosts in remote times. Some of them gave rise, through analogous adaptation processes, to the current swine, equine, and human influenza viruses, which are able to complete an infectious cycle in these species, independently of birds (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B128">Suarez, 2000</xref>). Among the viruses that have undergone a process of adaptation to a new species, it is worth reminding the case of swine vesicular disease virus, which causes an economically important disease in pigs (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Escribano-Romero et al., 2000</xref>). This virus is closely related genetically to Coxsackie virus B5, a human enterovirus, and current evidence suggests that it arose as a result of a relatively recent adaptation from human to swine (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">Jimenez-Clavero et al., 2005a</xref>), providing a good example that adaptations and crossing the species barrier can go either to or from humans, and that the human being is just one more species in this regard. Other viruses that have recently emerged to affect new species are several variants of the genus Henipavirus, infecting bats in Southeast Asia (Nipah virus) and Oceania (Hendra virus; 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Eaton et al., 2006</xref>). In recent years an increase in fatal cases by these viruses in humans and livestock (pigs and horses) has been observed, but an inefficient transmission between individuals of these species has prevented further spread in the human and/or livestock populations. However, in a recent outbreak of Nipah virus occurring in Bangladesh it appeared that an efficient transmission occurred between humans (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">Gurley et al., 2007</xref>). Finally, it is important to note that there is probably a species barrier crossing after every first diagnosis of a viral emerging disease, even though the natural reservoir might remain unknown. In 2003, the first cases of what appeared to be a new disease entity with fatal consequences for affected humans, were diagnosed in Hong Kong. It received the name of severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) and caused a great social concern worldwide, particularly when clusters of cases were detected in up to a dozen countries in three continents around the world, although a rapid response prevented further spread. The causative agent of this disease, named SARS virus, was identified during earlier investigations (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Drosten et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">Kuiken et al., 2003</xref>), but its natural host remained unknown until 
 <italic>Rhinolophidae</italic> (horseshoe bats) species were identified as reservoir hosts (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">Li et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Cui et al., 2007</xref>).
</p>
