<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For orthobunyaviruses, the S segment-encoded protein NSs is a major determinant of pathogenicity, acting as an antagonist of the antiviral type I interferon (IFN) response (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). IFNs are cytokines that become produced upon virus detection by host cells and stimulate the expression of genes (ISGs) for proteins with antiviral activity (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). In the case of LACV, infection is detected by the IFN system via the RIG-I/MAVS virus sensor axis (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). RIG-I, a cytoplasmic RNA helicase (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>), is capable of recognizing the panhandle RNA of bunyaviruses, even if packaged by nucleocapsids (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). RIG-I-mediated panhandle detection activates the transcription factor IRF-3, leading to the production of IFN-β mRNA (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). It is known that orthobunyavirus multiplication is affected by IFN (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>), and several ISGs were shown to be involved in this antiviral activity (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). To counteract the IFN/ISG induction, the orthobunyavirus NSs, however, massively and rapidly inhibits cellular mRNA transcription, leaving the host unable to appropriately respond to the infection (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). We have previously shown that the NSs of the orthobunyaviruses BUNV and LACV directly interfere with mRNA synthesis by the cellular RNA polymerase II (RNAP II) (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). While BUNV NSs is reducing the mRNA elongation-relevant phosphorylation of the C-terminal serine 2 residue (part of the 52 times repeated heptapeptide motif in the C-terminal domain [CTD]) (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>), LACV NSs additionally degrades the large subunit (RPB1) of RNAP II (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). An RPB1-degradative activity was also described for the NSs of SBV (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). Interestingly, the effect of LACV NSs on RPB1 has strong similarities with parts of the DNA damage response (DDR), not only in terms of RPB1 degradation but also by activation of other DDR markers (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>).
</p>
