<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Some functional anthocyanins such 3-
 <italic>O</italic>-rutinosides and 3-
 <italic>O</italic>-glucosides of malvidin, pelargonidin, peonidin, petunidin, delphinidin, cyanidin, and cyanidin 3-
 <italic>O</italic>-arabinoside have been isolated from the extract of blackcurrant berries (
 <italic>Ribes nigrum</italic> L.) (
 <xref rid="B212" ref-type="bibr">Slimestad and Solheim, 2002</xref>). Knox et al. studied the effect of 
 <italic>R. nigrum</italic> extract against the InfV A and B and showed four anthocyanins-containing fractions with potent antiviral activity. According to the results, one of the fractions contained 3-
 <italic>O</italic>-α-L-rhamnopyranosyl-β-D-glucopyranosyl-cyanidin and 3-
 <italic>O</italic>-β-D-glucopyranosyl-cyanidin anthocyanins, and the second contained 3-
 <italic>O</italic>-α-L-rhamnopyranosyl-β-D-glucopyranosyl-delphinidin and 3-
 <italic>O</italic>-β-D-glucopyranosyl-delphinidin. Both fractions displayed strong antiviral activity against the InfV A and B. The second fraction anthocyanins prevented viral attachment and entry to cells, as well as their release from the infected cells (
 <xref rid="B111" ref-type="bibr">Knox et al., 2001</xref>). 
 <italic>R. nigrum</italic> extracts also inhibited InfV adsorption on the cell surface (
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">Ikuta et al., 2013</xref>), interference with virus internalization (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Ehrhardt et al., 2013</xref>) and completely suppressed the growth of InfV A 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> (
 <xref rid="B112" ref-type="bibr">Knox et al., 2003</xref>). As Ikuta et al. reported, a low concentration of blackcurrant inhibited the replication while a high one inhibited adsorption of InfV A and B onto the cell surface (
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">Ikuta et al., 2012</xref>). Altogether, the blackcurrant extracts displayed auspicious anti-InfV effects through different mechanisms. This extract might be a hopeful source for the drug discovery and development of new antiviral agents to struggle against InfV infections.
</p>
