<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The evolutionary history of an organism is a powerful resource for understanding its current evolutionary trajectory. The analytical framework developed can be applied to understanding the potential evolutionary pathway of many pathogens and other species that are characterized by periods of isolation. These events are common features of pathogens (
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Karlsson 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2014
 </xref>), but also occur in numerous other species, including humans and domesticated plants and animals (
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Ellstrand 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 1999
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Lecis 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2006
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Caicedo 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2007
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Green 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2010
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">Patterson 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2012
 </xref>). Reconnection following a period of isolation is increasingly recognized as an effective mechanism to trigger fast and complex adaptation (
 <xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">Seehausen 2002</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Aguilée 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2013
 </xref>). Following reconnection, accumulated diversity (from previously isolated populations) is shared, and the resulting high level of genetic diversity may increase the potential for adaptation (
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Alcala and Vuilleumier 2014</xref>). Admixture among divergent populations may also promote complex adaptation by bringing together new functions acquired in different environments that have evolved independently but are compatible with the genome. Such processes have been observed in influenza and in HIV, for example. Indeed, recombination between strains previously isolated in their nonhuman hosts preceded the HIV epidemic in humans (
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Bailes 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2003
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr">Sharp and Hahn 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr">Vuilleumier and Bonhoeffer 2015</xref>). Such events are expected to be more frequent in the future due to the increase in human mobility (
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Karlsson 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2014
 </xref>). Finally, our analytical framework could also be applied to evolutionary trajectories of other zoonotic viruses, such as Ebola virus, coronaviruses, hantaviruses, or henipaviruses.
</p>
