<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0025">Sex differences in inflammation have been well documented and attributed to various factors. Although most of the immune regulatory genes are encoded by X chromosomes, resulting in women’s generally stronger immune response, this sex difference in inflammatory response is postulated to be largely driven by sex hormones.
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref> Although estrogen has a complex role in modulating the immune system, generally in a dose-dependent manner, it is reported to have an anti-inflammatory effect at normal physiological levels in premenopausal women.
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>15</sup>
 </xref> Most cytokines, namely, IL-6, IL-8, and tumor necrosis factor α (TNF-α), are inhibited by periovulatory dosages of estrogen, while low levels of estradiol can augment inflammatory mediators, which could explain the proinflammatory states that most postmenopausal women suffer from (eg, atherosclerosis).
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref> Postmenopausal women are reported to have higher levels of proinflammatory cytokines, such as IL-1, IL-6, and TNF-α; however, these levels are reduced with the use of hormone replacement therapy, especially estrogen-containing types, to premenopausal levels.
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref> Moreover, estrogen-containing contraceptive methods have been found to enhance cellular immunity in HIV-infected patients.
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref> Female mice receiving high levels of estrogen are reported to have increased survival and lower cytokine production in the lung after influenza infection.
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref> Likewise, the activated estrogen receptor, specifically estrogen receptor-alpha, has been found to inhibit NF-κB–mediated inflammation response and cytokine production via immune cells, lymphocytes, macrophages, and neutrophils.
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>17</sup>
 </xref> The finding that Ang II activates the NF-κB pathway to increase cytokine synthesis after SARS infection while estrogen can shut down the NF-κB pathway holds possible relevance for COVID-19 treatment strategies in female patients.
</p>
