<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Hepatitis E virus belongs to the 
 <italic>Hepeviridae</italic> family. It is a spherical, non-enveloped virus with an icosahedral symmetry [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R147">147</xref>]. Viral particles are approximately 32 to 34 nm in diameter and composed of a capsid protein (ORF2) assembled into a highly structured multimer (60 copies). The buyoant density of native virion particles, isolated from infected patient stools, is between 1.39 and 1.40 g/cm
 <sup>3</sup> in CsCl and its sedimentation coefficient is 183S [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75">75</xref>]. The HEV capsid packages a single positive-stranded RNA genome, which encodes 3 open reading frames (ORF). The RNA genome of HEV is capped at the 5′ end, and polyadelylated at the 3′ end [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R116">116</xref>] with approximately 7.2 kb in length. The 5′ and 3′ extremities of the viral genome are non-coding regions probably involved in the regulation of viral translation and replication [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R135">135</xref>]. The ORF1, encompassing approximately two thirds of the viral genome, encodes non-structural proteins. Computer-based sequence analyses and predication, based upon the known motif of other positive-strand RNA viral proteins, have revealed several conserved putative functional domains in ORF1, including methyltrasferase, papain-like cystein protease, helicase, and RNA dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">68</xref>]. Due to the lack of efficient in vitro cell cultures for HEV replication, little is known regarding the translation and processing of the ORF1 polyprotein. It has been shown that when ORF1 is expressed in a baculovirus expression system, synthesis of several small proteins that correlate with the predictive motifs was observed [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R124">124</xref>]. However, when the ORF1 was expressed in bacteria or mammalian cells, no processing was observed [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R117">117</xref>]. Expression of RdRp fused to an enhanced green fluorescent protein (EGFP) in hepatoma cell line HepG2 has shown an endoplasmic reticulum (ER) localization suggesting that the HEV replication complex may be associated with the ER [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R110">110</xref>]. An ER transmembrane domain was identified in the RdRp region, and shown to interact with the 3′ end of HEV RNA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R110">110</xref>]. The second ORF, ORF2, is located at the 3′ end of the genome and encodes the capsid protein. ORF2 contains an ER signal peptide and 3 putative N-glycosylation sites [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref>]. When over-expressed in the human hepatoma cell line Huh7, the ORF2 protein is found to be glycosylated (88 kDa) in the cytoplasm, after a retrotranslocation from the ER [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R132">132</xref>] and on the cell surface [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R150">150</xref>]. The ORF2 capsid protein interacts with the 5′ end of the viral RNA which probably plays a role in the viral RNA encapsidation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R131">131</xref>]. ORF2 is putatively translated from a subgenomic RNA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R108">108</xref>]. The reported numbers and sizes of HEV subgenomic RNA differed in infected livers and cell culture [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R103">103</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R108">108</xref>]. Recently, a bicistronic subgenomic RNA, encoding both ORF2 and ORF3, was identified using an in vitro HEV replicon system [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>]. The in vitro results were further verified with an in vivo swine model demonstrating that the third in-frame start codon (AUG) of HEV is the authentic initiation site for ORF3, and that ORF3 overlaps ORF2 but neither ORF2 nor ORF3 overlaps ORF1 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">52</xref>]. The ORF3 encodes for a small phosphoprotein of 123 amino-acids associated with cytoskeleton, and may play a role in virus replication and virion morphogenesis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R148">148</xref>]. ORF3 is necessary for viral infection in rhesus macaques in vivo but not in vitro [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref>]. In vitro, ORF2 and ORF3 proteins interact with each other, suggesting that ORF3 may play a role in viral assembly of de novo particles [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R142">142</xref>].
</p>
