<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the case of the shrews from the village of Güterglück it is possible that the shrews trapped over the years reflect different family clans of which the two shrews of 2006 and the shrews of 2007–2009 were from BDV-infected ones. The accumulation of infected reservoir animals in human settlements can contribute to disease hot spot formations. Some epidemiological hot spots of BD have been known in the past. Such an epidemiological hot spot had been the Zoological Garden Erfurt where in the 1970s and 1980s several herbivore zoo animal species succumbed to BD 
 <xref rid="pone.0093659-Schppel1" ref-type="bibr">[67]</xref>. Investigations by Netzer in one district of Bavaria in the early 1950s revealed that there were different hot spots of BD in horses not only within the district but also within the villages themselves; he found that BD in horses was more common in distinct parts of the villages and within these some neighboring farms were more often affected over the years than others 
 <xref rid="pone.0093659-Netzer1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. The property in Güterglück, where BDV-positive bicolored white-toothed shrews were collected, represents a location where hot spot formation was not obvious by disease in spill-over hosts because there were no horses and sheep on-site. In the immediate neighborhood of this property chickens, ducks and pigs were kept in a small barn under poor hygienic conditions which may have attracted shrews. Investigations of epidemiological factors of BD revealed that BD more often occured in traditional farms where several different animal species were kept together and hygiene was poor 
 <xref rid="pone.0093659-Drrwald2" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0093659-Drrwald4" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. Güterglück is located in a lowland area between Magdeburg and Dessau in Saxony-Anhalt not far from the river Elbe. Although BD cases have been reported from this region in the past, BD has never been known in the village itself and the neighboring villages. The last BD cases in horses within this region were observed in the village of Nutha, 3 km from Güterglück, in 1958, and in the village of Leitzkau, 9 km away, in the early 1950s. According to local veterinarians, BD has not been observed in horses or sheep within that small area for at least 50 years.
</p>
