<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0025">Coumarin is a therapeutic agent, found as a naturally occurring secondary metabolite in plants, bacteria, fungi, essential oils and can also be chemically synthesized [
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Coumarins have been isolated from different families of plant kingdom like 
 <italic>Clusiaceae, Umbelliferae</italic> and 
 <italic>Rutaceae</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. It was isolated from Tonka beans in 1820 independently by A. Vogel of Munich, Germany and by Nicholas Guibourt of France [
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. William Henry Perkin, an English chemist first synthesized coumarin in 1868 [
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Coumarin is basically made up of a benzene moiety fused with an alpha-pyrene ring named as benzopyrene [
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Coumarin derivatives are synthesized using various synthetic pathways such as Perkin condensation, Knoevenagel condensation, Pechmann reaction and metal-catalyzed Cyclization [
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. They are stable, soluble, low molecular weight compounds without any adverse side effects and toxicity. These and several other properties of coumarins make them a potential drug candidate against many viral and bacterial diseases. Many of natural, synthetic, conjugated, hybrid potential candidate lead compounds possessing coumarin scaffold have been studied and are in different stages of drug development [
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Their biological activity can be changed depending upon the combination of various substituents and conjugates. On top of this, Coumarin motifs can be foresighted as a privileged scaffold and model framework for the design and synthesis of several pharmacological compounds having significant binding affinity with the different biological targets. They can be easily modified to satisfy “the rule of 5 “of Lipinski to make them a drug-like molecule by applying a privileged structure approach of drug discovery using combinatorial chemistry [
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Coumarin as an antiviral agent, widely studied in anti-HIV therapy [
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], attracts attention from scientists to study its significance in the prevention of other viral diseases.
</p>
