<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mice were bred in specific-pathogen-free facilities at the University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus. All mouse studies were performed in an animal biosafety level 2 or 3 laboratory. WT and 
 <italic>Rag1</italic>
 <sup>-/-</sup> C57BL/6J mice were obtained from the Jackson Laboratory. CCR2-DTR mice, in which one CCR2 locus was modified to encode a simian DT receptor (DTR) and enhanced cyan fluorescent protein [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006748.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>], were provided by Eric G. Pamer (Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center). 
 <italic>Mavs</italic>
 <sup>-/-</sup> C57BL/6 mice, originally generated at the University of Washington, were provided by Kenneth Tyler (University of Colorado School of Medicine). 
 <italic>Irf3</italic>
 <sup>-/-</sup>;
 <italic>Irf7</italic>
 <sup>-/-</sup> C57BL/6 mice were provided by Michael S. Diamond (Washington University). Three-to-four week-old mice were used for all studies. Mice were inoculated in the left rear footpad with 10
 <sup>3</sup> PFU of virus in diluent (PBS supplemented with 1% FBS). Mock-infected animals received diluent alone. Disease scores of RRV-infected mice were determined by assessing grip strength, hind limb weakness, and altered gait, as previously described [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006748.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Briefly, grip strength and hind limb weakness were assessed by testing the ability of each mouse to grip a rounded surface. Mice were scored as follows: 0, no disease signs; 1, extremely mild defect in injected hind paw gripping ability; 2, very mild defect in bilateral hind paw gripping ability; 3, bilateral loss of gripping ability and mild bilateral hind limb paresis; 4, bilateral loss of gripping ability, moderate bilateral hind limb paresis, observable altered gait, and difficulty or failure to right self; 5, bilateral loss of gripping ability, severe bilateral hind limb paresis, altered gait with hind paw dragging, and failure to right self; 6, bilateral loss of gripping ability, very severe hind limb paresis with dragging of limbs, and failure to right self. On the day of experiment termination, mice were sedated with isoflurane and euthanized by thoracotomy, blood was collected, and mice were perfused by intracardiac injection of 1x PBS. PBS-perfused tissues were removed by dissection and homogenized in TRIzol Reagent (Life Technologies) for RNA isolation using a MagNA Lyser (Roche). For cell depletion experiments in CCR2-DTR mice, mice were injected i.p. with 10 ng/g body weight diphtheria toxin (DT) per injection. For antibody depletion experiments, mice were injected with 300 μg/mouse of either anti-NK1.1 (clone PK136, BioXcell), anti-Gr1 (clone RB6-8C5, BioXcell), anti-Ly6G (clone 1A8, BioXcell), or similar amounts of appropriate control antibody per injection.
</p>
