<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0030">Coronaviruses (CoVs) are members of the family 
 <italic>Coronaviridae</italic> in the order 
 <italic>Nidovirales</italic> and the genus 
 <italic>Coronavirus</italic> (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Adams et al., 2016</xref>). CoVs are enveloped, single-stranded, positive-sense RNA viruses that have the largest genome among RNA viruses (~32 kb) (
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Perlman and Netland, 2009</xref>) and are widespread and naturally infect a variety of species. Currently, six CoVs have been identified that predominantly cause respiratory and central nervous system (CNS) pathologies in humans. HCoV-OC43 and HCoV-229E usually cause common colds during the winter and early spring (
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Larson et al., 1980</xref>), whereas HCoV-NL63 is responsible for causing croup in children and results in more severe clinical features than those of HCoV-OC43 or HCoV-229E (
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Arden et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Fouchier et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">van der Hoek et al., 2004</xref>). HCoV-HKU1 is associated with bronchiolitis and pneumonia (
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Woo et al., 2005a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">2005b</xref>). In 2003, an outbreak of severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS), a lethal zoonotic CoV infection, was reported in China and associated with SARS-CoV (
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Ksiazek et al., 2003</xref>). In 2012, a SARS-like disease emerged that resulted in a mortality rate of 30%, the causative agent of which was identified as Middle East respiratory syndrome CoV (MERS-CoV) (
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Gralinski and Baric, 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Milne-Price et al., 2014</xref>). Despite their status as infectious respiratory pathogens, CoVs can also damage the CNS and cause neurological diseases (
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Arabi et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Arbour et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Burks et al., 1980</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Hung et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Morfopoulou et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Netland et al., 2008</xref>), with HCoV-OC43, HCoV-229E, and SARS-CoV detected in the cerebrospinal fluid of patients with multiple sclerosis (
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Arbour et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Burks et al., 1980</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Hung et al., 2003</xref>). Recently, severe neurological syndromes were identified as associated with MERS-CoV (
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Arabi et al., 2015</xref>), SASR-CoV reportedly exhibits neuroinvasive properties in the CNS of mice (
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Netland et al., 2008</xref>), and HCoV-OC43 is associated with fatal encephalitis (
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Morfopoulou et al., 2016</xref>). Therefore, CoVs are thought to be responsible for CNS pathologies in a way similar to other known neuroinvasive viruses, such as measles virus, human immunodeficiency virus, and herpes virus (
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Koyuncu et al., 2013</xref>). Until recently, little was known about the process and dynamics of HCoV infection in the CNS, and no effective drugs are currently available for treating patients with these infections; therefore, easily observable animal models are required to understand viral replication and investigate potential therapeutic strategies.
</p>
