<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>SARS-CoV-2 structure</italic> - Electron microscopy imaging of SARS-CoV-2 virions indicates that they have a spherical or pleomorphic shape, with diameters ranging from 60 to 140 nm, showing prominent spikes of 9-12 nm in their surfaces that resemble a solar corona, hence the name “coronavirus”.
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>45</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>46</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>47</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>48</sup>
 </xref> SARS-CoV-2 is an enveloped virus with a single-stranded positive sense (5’-3’) RNA (+ssRNA) (~ 30 kb) containing a 5’-cap structure and a 3’-poly-A tail.
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>49</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>50</sup>
 </xref> Its genomic RNA (gRNA) has a variable number of open reading frames (ORFs) that are predicted to encode 16 non-structural (Nsp), 4 structural and several accessory proteins (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1</xref>).
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>26</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>51</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>52</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>53</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>54</sup>
 </xref> ORF1a and ORF1b represent more than 2/3 of the whole length of gRNA, and encode two polyproteins: pp1a (440-500 kDa) and pp1ab (740-810 kDa).
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>53</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>55</sup>
 </xref> The polyprotein pp1a is translated from ORF1a while pp1ab from ORF1a/ORF1b using a -1 ribosomal frameshift mechanism that occurs near the 3’ end of ORF1a which allows continued translation of ORF1b.
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>53</sup>
 </xref> Together, pp1a and pp1ab originate all Nsps (1-16), such as M
 <sup>pro</sup> (Nsp5) protease and RdRp (Nsp12) RNA polymerase, which form viral replicase/transcriptase complexes (RTCs), and are encapsulated in double-layered vesicles originated from the endoplasmic reticulum (ER).
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>56</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>57</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>58</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
