<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Remdesivir (8) a good example of maximising the term of patent is the drug remdesivir (8), which was developed by the American pharmaceutical company Gilead Sciences, Inc. in 2011. Nowadays, (8) has shown promising results as a suitable repurposed drug in the treatment of the COVID-19 disease. Indeed, there are many ongoing clinical trials with this drug in COVID-19 patients.
 <xref rid="B239" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>239</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B240" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>240</sup>
 </xref> Due to the good results concerning remdesivir (8), in January 2020, the Wuhan Institute of Virology applied for a patent on Gilead’s remdesivir (8) for the treatment of coronavirus, in an attempt to protect China’s economic and medical interests. However, remdesivir (8) has already 133 patents related to the coronavirus filed by Gilead Science in 43 countries around the globe since 2011. In fact, the company has a robust patent portfolio that includes structures of remdesivir-related compounds (Family 1), the manufacturing method of the drug (Family 2), the use of remdesivir (8) in treating Coronaviridae infection (Family 3), among other patents that claims the use of (8) for the treatment of a series of viral infections (Families 3 and 4) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f13">Fig. 13</xref>).
 <xref rid="B241" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>241</sup>
 </xref> Practically, this means that if the (8) is proved to be efficient for the treatment of COVID-19, Gilead Science is the only pharmaceutical company owing the market exclusivity of the drug, at least until 2031. In fact, the company has already started to produce larger amounts of the drug and they already made improvements to optimise the drug manufacturing timeline. Now, the company can produce the drug in 6 months, half the time that they used to need to get the final product. In addition, the company has been donating remdesivir (8) to ongoing clinical trials, a gesture that will not only help the trial patients, but Gilead itself.
 <xref rid="B242" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>242</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
