<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par39">The vector control carried out at the beginning of the twentieth century during the Rio de Janeiro epidemic was organized nationwide in 1928–29. It was reinforced by YF immunization in 1937 and DDT sprayings initiated 10 years later, which significantly reduced the burden of YF, that was considered as having been eliminated from Brazil in the 60s [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR126">126</xref>]. However, the epidemics of dengue in 1963–64 then in 1968–69 marked the beginning of the re-infestation of the continent by 
 <italic>A. aegypti</italic>, confirmed between 1971 and 1999 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR127">127</xref>], which resulted in the return of YF and, more recently, the installation of other arboviruses (chikungunya and Zika, in particular) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Several factors can explain this phenomenon. The most important is, almost certainly the reinvasion of 
 <italic>A. aegypti</italic> from isolated and poorly controlled Amazonian and Southern Brazilian forest localities, as a result of a relaxation of vector control and vaccination campaigns, as well as the deterioration of health systems in some remote areas [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128">128</xref>]. Another reason could be the insufficiency of vaccination coverage, which should have favored the extension of the disease beyond its natural limits, particularly in the regions of Brazil where vaccination was not recommended, e.g., in northeast and southern Brazil [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129">129</xref>]. Nevertheless, YF now seems well established in the form of a deeply rooted jungle cycle, as shown by the numerous epizootics reported in recent years (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Finally, the sudden population growth and unplanned urbanization that results in substandard housing, and inadequate water supply and waste management systems, at least partially explain the failure of preventive measures and the delay in the management of cases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128">128</xref>]. The vectorial competence of 
 <italic>A. aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>A. albopictus</italic> reinforce the risk of YF extension in cities, especially in the overcrowded suburbs of major Brazilian cities [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>].
</p>
