<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our regression analyses had several limitations. First, because of missing FluNet data and to minimize selection bias, we were unable to estimate deaths associated with individual influenza A subtypes or influenza B lineages. Second, few ILI cases in the FluNet database had laboratory confirmation of influenza virus, likely because virologic testing is expensive and of limited clinical value. This may have introduced some selection bias that we could not adjust for, and suggests that the influenza positivity rate data is not representative. Nonetheless, in our sensitivity analyses, the EMRs were largely unaffected by imputed influenza positivity rates for weeks with ≤1 or ≤10 specimens tested, implying that our results are robust despite the limited influenza activity data. Third, FluNet data may not be nationally-representative. Sentinel surveillance sites were only present in 13 out of 17 regions in the country [
 <xref rid="pone.0234715.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] and there is no indication that sites were distributed evenly across the country. Despite its limitations, FluNet data is the only source of influenza activity data of its scope in the country to date. Fourth, because of missingness of the data, we had to drop 15 out of 52 weather stations for the meteorological variables. We believe that this is not an issue since the meteorological variables were merely controls, not the independent variable of interest. Finally, unlike other studies [
 <xref rid="pone.0234715.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0234715.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], our analyses did not control for infections caused by respiratory syncytial virus because this data was not obtainable for the Philippines. Since respiratory syncytial viruses co-circulate with influenza viruses [
 <xref rid="pone.0234715.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], our results might have overestimated influenza mortality, particularly in the younger age groups [
 <xref rid="pone.0234715.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].
</p>
