<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Lee et al. used the term “in situ evolution” to characterize DENV in Singapore through phylogenetic analysis. Results of the analysis explained the correlation between its genetic and evolutionary aspects, suggesting that DENV had lurked locally and reappeared after some time.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>
 </sup> Rajarethinam et al.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>
 </sup> described that the dengue in Singapore from 2004 to 2016 demonstrated cyclic epidemic patterns dominated by serotypes 1 and 2. However, this in situ evolution, demonstrated by the step-ladder pattern of branching within each clade over time, has not been observed in Guangdong since 2005. Another possible transmission and evolution pattern of DENV broke out in parts (switch of the lineage), followed by silence (change of the lineage), and was then prevalent on a large scale (continuation of the lineage), achieving continuous evolution of a new lineage and the silent circulation of old lineages. In 2006, when DENV1 first became the leading serotype, it was due to a “switch” from the lineages in genotype I, which branched into Lineages I–III at the beginning.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
  <xref rid="b49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>
 </sup> From 2007 to 2012, it was observed that the prevalence of DENV was low and it frequently interchanged between the three lineages, leading to the occurrence of epidemics caused by DENV1 belonging to each lineage.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
  <xref rid="b51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>
 </sup> However, since 2012, the severity of dengue is increasing because of a continued epidemic caused by Lineage III.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>
 </sup> In 2007, a switch in Lineage IV, which was similar to the evolutionary process of Lineage III, was observed. The lineage of genotype IV was first formed in 2007, which reappeared in 2010, and was never detected in recent years.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
  <xref rid="b54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>
 </sup> It is reported that genotype V had circulated continuously from 2009 to 2011, followed by an intermittent silence and further reappearance in 2014. This type of molecular evolution was similar to the silent circulation prevalent in Indonesia, Brazil, etc.,
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
  <xref rid="b55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
  <xref rid="b56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>
 </sup> indicating that the same might happen in Guangdong. Castonguay-Vanier et al.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>
 </sup> also described the active circulation of DENV in Laos and the concurrent multiple introductions of new strains from neighboring countries, whereas Moore et al.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>
 </sup> claimed that the co-circulation of DENV1–4 in PNG provides molecular evidence of its endemic transmission. Meanwhile, compared with DENV2, DENV3, and DENV4, DENV1, which is the leading serotype in Guangdong, rarely caused severe DF.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>–
  <xref rid="b61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>
 </sup> In addition, because Guangdong is the most densely populated province in southern China, which is surrounded by a large number of dengue-endemic countries and has a subtropical climate providing optimal environmental, social, and biological conditions for mosquito breeding and reproduction, a detailed evaluation of the current dengue epidemic is significant. Nevertheless, there is still a lack of evidence on the local mosquito vector regarding its harboring of DENV during epidemic and nonepidemic periods which can support the evidences of its molecular evolution revealed by the phylogenetic analysis.
</p>
