<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Most epidemiologic studies of MPV in children show that the virus is the second leading cause of lower respiratory infection after RSV. The prevalence of MPV in studies of children with LRI is 5–25 %. A 25-year prospective study of otherwise healthy children &lt;5 years old detected MPV in 12 % of children with LRI; several children experienced recurrent infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR182">182</xref>]. A 2-years multicenter study of inpatient and outpatient Japanese children with ARI identified MPV in 57/637 (8.9 %) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR239">239</xref>]. A 5-years observational study of otherwise healthy Korean children &lt;5 years old found MPV in 24/515 (4.7 %), similar to the rates for influenza and parainfluenza virus type 3 (PIV-3) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR240">240</xref>]. A very large observational study in Queensland, Australia, tested specimens obtained from patients of all ages with LRI from 2001 to 2004; MPV was detected in 707/10,025 (7.1 %). Ninety-two percent of patients with MPV were &lt;5 years old, and MPV was the second most common virus after RSV in these children [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR241">241</xref>]. A South African group tested specimens from children hospitalized with ARI who were subjects in a prospective pneumococcal vaccine trial; MPV was present in 126/1,409 (8.9 %) and was the most common virus after RSV. The estimated incidence of MPV-associated hospitalization in HIV-negative children was 29/1,000; a number of children had repeat infections [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR242">242</xref>]. A prospective study of hospitalized children in Hong Kong over a 13-month period found MPV in 32/587 (5.5 %); the estimated incidence of MPV-associated hospitalization was 4.4 per 1,000 children &lt;6 years old [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR243">243</xref>]. A Chinese group conducted a prospective 2-years study of children hospitalized with ARI and identified MPV in 227/878 (25.9 %), with most &lt;6 years old [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR244">244</xref>]. A large, population-based, prospective surveillance study conducted in three US cities over 6 years found that the incidence of hospitalization for MPV in children &lt;5 years old was 1 per 1,000, lower than the rate of RSV-associated hospitalization in the same cohort (3/1,000) but similar to the rates for influenza (0.9/1,000) and PIV-3 (0.5/1,000) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR245">245</xref>].
</p>
