<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para50">Niehus and colleagues remind us to reflect on causes of the high early case-fatality rate in Wuhan, which has important implication for countries struggling with COVID-19 now.
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> One explanation is the strong virulence of the virus, which is presumed to have crossed the species barrier from animal to human.
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref> However, several studies on the evolution of SARS-CoV-2 imply that origin of the virus is still unknown. The virus identified in Wuhan might not be the first generation.
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> The high case-fatality rate in Wuhan is probably because the detection ability of viral nucleic acid was insufficient in the early stages of the outbreak. Most patients with mild disease had no access to a medical diagnosis and were excluded from calculation of the case-fatality rate, which was primarily contributed to by patients with severe disease.
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref> Makeshift hospitals began to be built on Feb 4, 2020, in Wuhan, for medical care of patients with mild disease, and subsequent detection and treatment of mild cases decreased the number of deaths (numerator) while increasing the total number of cases (denominator).
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref> Outside Hubei province, a lower case-fatality rate of 0·9% (121 of 13 500) has been attributed to perfect detection.
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>10</sup>
 </xref> People in China (outside Hubei province) who visited any place outside of their regular residential area received a test, whereas people with no symptoms would be home quarantined for 14 days, particularly those who had recently visited Hubei province, who would be strictly followed up through home visits and by telephone by community management staff.
</p>
