<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The highest prevalence and intensities of human schistosomiasis occur in school-aged children, adolescents, and young adults who also suffer from the highest morbidity and mortality. There are two major forms of schistosomiasis found in SSA. Approximately two-thirds of the schistosomiasis cases are due to infection caused by 
 <italic>Schistosoma haematobium</italic>, which represents an important cause of severe urinary tract disease 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-vanderWerf1" ref-type="bibr">[73]</xref>. In 2000, van der Werf et al. estimated that 70 million and 32 million individuals out of 682 million people in SSA had experienced hematuria and dysuria, respectively, within the last two weeks 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-vanderWerf1" ref-type="bibr">[73]</xref>. 
 <italic>S. haematobium</italic> produces bladder wall pathology in approximately 18 million people in SSA, and 10 million people suffer from hydronephrosis 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-vanderWerf1" ref-type="bibr">[73]</xref>. Renal failure accounts for a large percentage of the estimated 150,000 deaths from urinary tract schistosomiasis in SSA, and there is also a significant association between major bladder wall pathology and squamous cell carcinoma 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-MaxwellParkin1" ref-type="bibr">[74]</xref>. A significant percentage of women and men with urinary schistosomiasis acquire genital ulcers and other lesions 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-King1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. In the former, urogenital schistosomiasis is a significant cause of poor reproductive health, including sexual dysfunction and infertility 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Swai1" ref-type="bibr">[75]</xref>. Genital schistosomiasis also promotes the horizontal transmission of HIV/AIDS in SSA 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Kjetland1" ref-type="bibr">[76]</xref>. Intestinal schistosomiasis from 
 <italic>S. mansoni</italic> causes most of the remaining cases in SSA. An estimated 4.4 million people with 
 <italic>S. mansoni</italic> have bloody diarrhea and bowel ulceration, and 8.5 million develop hepatomegaly and/or associated periportal liver fibrosis, portal hypertension, and hematemesis from 
 <italic>S. mansoni</italic> infection, with approximately 130,000 deaths 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-King1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-vanderWerf1" ref-type="bibr">[73]</xref>. 
 <italic>S. intercalatum</italic> causes a second form of intestinal schistosomiasis, but with a restricted distribution in West and Central Africa 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-TchuemTchuente1" ref-type="bibr">[77]</xref>.
</p>
