<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition, a reorganization of the buprenorphine prescribing system is needed. In order to increase the number of providers who prescribe MOUD and improve patient access, we recommend eliminating the buprenorphine waiver requirement, removing the patient caps, and dedicating grant funding for case management and other support services to clinics that prescribe MOUDs. Increased funding and reimbursement are also needed for low-barrier care delivery models such as telehealth. These innovative programs, which have already begun to be tested in infectious diseases/OUD comanagement [
 <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>], have the potential to increase medication uptake and improve outcomes by increasing access to treatment where people reside. In addition, multidisciplinary team meetings, including surgeons, SUD specialists, inpatient internal medicine clinicians, nurses, social work, and case management, are being piloted in several hospitals across the country in order to make informed and collaborative decisions on complex patients, such as those with recurrent endocarditis following valve repair. Evaluation of the impact of these types of collaborative efforts, both on patient outcomes and workplace satisfaction, can help inform best practice for all hospitals.We also need to address the requirements of particularly high-risk patients, including pregnant women and infants born to mothers with OUD, and persons experiencing homelessness who may be unable to access traditional care. OUD among pregnant women has increased significantly and there is an urgent need to build capacity to manage OUD among pregnant women [
 <xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Infants born to mothers with OUD during pregnancy are at increased risk for HIV, HBV, and HCV. Screening for HIV, HBV, and HCV is recommended for all pregnant women [
 <xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] and has been successfully integrated into most prenatal screening paradigms, allowing for perinatal management that decreases the risk of infant infection. In September 2006, the CDC recommended screening all sexually active persons 13–65 years old for HIV at least once, but this has not occurred and needs emphasis in order to end the epidemic. In August 2019, the US Preventive Services Task Force issued a draft recommendation for universal HCV screening [
 <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Given that overall incidence of HCV is increasing alongside the opioid epidemic [
 <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>], strategies including provider education and increased resources are needed to ensure universal HCV testing is performed, particularly among women of child-bearing age and in prenatal care to prevent infant infection [
 <xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">55–57</xref>].
</p>
