<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0250">The dependence of the calculated rate of evolution during the epidemic spread of the virus on the time interval between virus isolations for sequence determination is expected for viruses that need not be transmitted by direct contact between an infected and a susceptible host. Some viruses remain infectious in the environment for prolonged time periods, until they reach a susceptible host in which to initiate replication rounds. This is the case of viruses transmitted by the fecal-oral route, such as enteroviruses. FMDV can adhere and remain infectious on many objects (fomites), including dust particles, food products with neutral pH, or insects that can transport the virus mechanically. Infectious FMDV can traverse long distances (many kilometers) on dust particles, people, trains, and the like. Even if some infectivity is lost, a few infectious particles are sufficient to infect an animal (
 <xref rid="bib125" ref-type="bibr">Sellers, 1971</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib126" ref-type="bibr">Sellers, 1981</xref>). There are some classic examples of long-distance transport of FMDV, a virus subjected to close scrutiny due to its economic impact. One is the spread of SAT1 and A22 FMDV during the 1960s in Turkey along the railway line from the cattle-raising region of Lake Van to slaughterhouses in Istanbul [this and other examples are described in (
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Brooksby, 1981</xref>)]. Computer models have been developed to explain and predict possible airborne FMDV transmission in different geographical areas, the origin of epidemics, and the effectiveness of contingency plans (
 <xref rid="bib139" ref-type="bibr">Sorensen et al., 2000</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib144" ref-type="bibr">Tidesley et al., 2017</xref>). [As an anecdote, in my experience as a member of the Research Group of the Standing Technical Committee for the Control of FMD of Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO) in the 1980s, FMD outbreaks in any country always came from somewhere else]. A time-dependent bias in evolutionary rates for viruses has been amply documented (
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Duchene et al., 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Aiewsakun and Katzourakis, 2016</xref>), including when rates are compared between present-day isolates and those that circulated thousands of years ago (
 <xref rid="bib98" ref-type="bibr">Muhlemann et al., 2018</xref>).
</p>
