<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To identify Yunnan-specific RABV circulation, nucleotide sequences of the N and G genes of all available RABV sequences sampled from non-flying mammals in Asia were downloaded from NCBI GenBank and aligned [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007392.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] together with our newly generated sequences. The resulting data sets included 543 N sequences (the entire N gene coding sequence, 1350 nt long) and 491 G sequences (the entire G gene coding sequence, 1575 nt long). RABV clades specific to Yunnan were identified using the discrete trait analysis model implemented in BEAST 1.8 [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007392.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1007392.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. For the molecular clock phylogeographic analyses, we specified a general time-reversible GTR+I nucleotide substitution model [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007392.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1007392.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], a skygrid coalescent model [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007392.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] and a relaxed uncorrelated lognormal (UCLN) molecular clock model across branches [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007392.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. The data sets lack a clear temporal signal [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007392.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1007392.s002">S1 Fig</xref>). Therefore, we specified informative prior distributions on the gene-specific mean clock rate parameter. These prior distributions were based on previously published estimated substitution rates [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007392.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]: 1.88×10
 <sup>−4</sup> substitutions/site/year (95% highest posterior density, HPD: [1.37×10
 <sup>−4</sup>, 2.41×10
 <sup>−4</sup>]) for the N gene and 2.13×10
 <sup>−4</sup> substitutions/site/year (95% HPD: [1.56×10
 <sup>−4</sup>, 2.73×10
 <sup>−4</sup>]) for the G gene. The MCMC chain was run for 250 million states and mixing and convergence were inspected using Tracer [
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/tracer/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/tracer/</ext-link>]. TreeAnnotator 1.8 [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007392.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] was used to infer maximum clade credibility (MCC) summary trees.
</p>
