<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Genetic diversity underlies individual differences in human disease pathogenesis and severity. Not surprisingly, the outcomes of arboviral infection are associated with many genetic mutations and single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs), the majority of which are related to immune pathways (
 <xref rid="viruses-11-00150-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The type I interferon (IFN) response is induced rapidly following a viral infection and is an essential early antiviral mechanism. SNPs in the genes of the type I IFN pathway influence the severity of arboviral infection in humans. SNPs in an interferon stimulated gene (ISG) for 2′-5′-oligoadenylate synthetase (OAS), an enzyme involved in the innate immune response to viral infection by destroying viral RNA, are likely associated with severe infections. In mice, a nonsense mutation, C820T, in the exon 4 of the 
 <italic>Oas1b</italic> gene produced a truncated protein that inhibits the enzymatic activity of Oas1b. This allowed for greater replication of WNV in neurons with the mutated enzyme and enhanced viral infection [
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-11-00150" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-11-00150" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. A synonymous SNP in human 
 <italic>OASL</italic> exon 2 (rs3213545) that leads to a similar dominant negative OASL isozyme was more frequent in hospitalized WNV patients than control subjects [
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-11-00150" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. A splicing variant (rs10774671) and an intron variant (rs34137742) of 
 <italic>OAS1</italic> were associated with severe WNV infection [
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-11-00150" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-11-00150" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-11-00150" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Additionally, a variant of OAS3, OAS_R381, was less effective in activating the RNase used to decimate viral RNA. This produced decreased antiviral activity toward DENV-2 and manifested as a more severe dengue infection [
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-11-00150" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. SNPs in interferon regulatory transcription factor (IRF3), an important transcription factor for type I IFNs, and myxoirus resistance 1 (MX1), an interferon-induced dynamin-like guanosine triphosphate (GTP)ase, were correlated with symptomatic WNV infection; however, the mechanism is not well understood [
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-11-00150" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].
</p>
