<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0020">However, currently, there are only limited data available linking underlying liver diseases with the course of SARS-CoV-2 infection and there are many open questions (
 <xref rid="tbox1" ref-type="boxed-text">Box 1</xref>). Chronic hepatitis B virus infection for example, which is more prevalent in China than Europe, does not appear to affect the outcome of COVID-19.
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref> In addition, although there is no proof for this assumption, immunosuppression may even provide some protection from immunopathology, which appears to contribute to lung damage in cases with more severe manifestations of the disease.
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref> These may be associated with a macrophage activation syndrome in the context of a hyperinflammatory syndrome characterised by a cytokine storm with multi-organ failure.
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>7</sup>
 </xref> On the other hand, systemic viral infections are often associated with transient elevations of transaminases which may reflect general immune activation or inflammation caused by circulating cytokines without compromising liver function, a phenomenon called “bystander hepatitis”. This may also be the case in patients with COVID-19 where liver failure has not been specifically reported, even in the most severe and fatal courses of disease.
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>2</sup>
 </xref> However, signs of liver dysfunction may occur in critically ill patients with COVID-19,
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref> as reviewed in.
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>10</sup>
 </xref> Whether patients with cirrhosis and COVID-19 are at increased risk of decompensation or development of acute-on-chronic liver failure (ACLF), as has been shown for influenza infection,
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>11</sup>
 </xref> remains to be determined. SARS-CoV-2 may also directly infect liver cells as the receptor of the virus, angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2),
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>12</sup>
 </xref> has been shown to be expressed on cholangiocytes,
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>13</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref> which may explain cases of viral shedding into the faeces.
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>15</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref> How far observations from Asian cohorts can be transferred to European populations remains to be determined, but it appears unlikely that SARS-CoV-2 infection causes liver damage to an amount that substantially contributes to the overall disease burden.
 <boxed-text id="tbox1">
  <label>Box 1</label>
  <caption>
   <title>Open questions for liver-related basic/translational research regarding COVID-19.</title>
  </caption>
  <p id="p0695"> ACLF, acute-on-chronic liver failure; COVID-19, coronavirus disease 2019; SARS-CoV-2, severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2.</p>
 </boxed-text>
</p>
