<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While these 
 <italic>ex vivo</italic> data suggested that African ZIKV lineage strains are more virulent, it was important to confirm the difference in (neuro)virulence of these 2 lineages 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>. Interferon-α/β receptor (
 <italic>Ifnar</italic>)
 <sup>-/-</sup> mice injected subcutaneously with African ZIKV strains (MR766 and 3 strains from Senegal) or with the Asian-lineage H/PF/2013 strain all presented with weight loss and succumbed to the infection after 6 (for Senegal strains) to 10 (H/PF/2013) days. Interestingly, infection with the African-lineage strain MR766 resulted in 20% survival at 2 weeks [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005821.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Another study compared the symptoms induced by African (Uganda and Senegal) and Asian (Cambodia, Malaysia, and Puerto Rico) ZIKV strains in signal transducer and activator of transcription (
 <italic>Stat2</italic>)
 <sup>-/-</sup> and 
 <italic>Ifnar</italic>
 <sup>-/-</sup> mice infected subcutaneously [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005821.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Importantly, infections with African strains resulted in more weight loss, mortality, and severe prolonged neurological symptoms compared to Asian strains. Moreover, induction of type 1 and 2 interferon (IFN) were higher following infection with African strains associated with enhanced levels of inflammatory cytokines such as interleukin 6 (IL6) or tumor necrosis factor (TNF). These observations were confirmed in another study showing that an African strain (MP1751) is pathogenic in A129 mice, contrary to an Asian strain (PRVABC59) that did not cause signs of illness [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005821.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. These studies confirm the 
 <italic>ex vivo</italic> results in neural and nonneural cells regarding the higher virulence of African strains and could suggest that different ZIKV strains may also display phenotypic differences in human subjects (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0005821.g001">Fig 1</xref>) (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005821.t002">Table 2</xref>). Many of the findings from immunocompromised mice have been recapitulated in nonhuman primates, such as rhesus and cynomolgus macaques. The development of these different animal models led to new knowledge concerning the pathogenesis of ZIKV. However, these systems have limitations, in particular, studying viral pathogenesis using animals lacking a key component of antiviral immunity, which makes it still difficult to derive definitive conclusions regarding ZIKV virulence in humans. Therefore, many unanswered questions remain, in particular, regarding the mechanisms of host restriction, immune evasion, and inflammatory response as well as the long-term neurodevelopmental implications of congenital infection in humans.
</p>
