<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0080">Despite the wide number of investigations assessing the different factors influencing susceptibility to viral infections, the mechanisms by which inhaled oxidants can modify viral pathogenesis are very complex, and at the time of that pandemic were not well established. It has been shown that oxidative stress increases severity of viral infections. Ozone, an elemental form of oxygen, is one of the most abundant air pollutants in urban areas. It is a potent inducer of oxidative stress that may cause airway inflammation and increased respiratory morbidities. 
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Kesic et al. (2012a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">2012b</xref>) demonstrated that secreted proteases from primary human respiratory nasal epithelium proteolytically, activated influenza virions, while exposure to an air oxidant pollutant such as ozone increased these effects. On the other hand, associations between PM pollution exposure and adverse health outcomes are well documented. They include respiratory diseases such as COPD and asthma. In turn, associations between PM exposure and increased susceptibility to infectious respiratory diseases have been also reported. Environmentally persistent free radicals (EPFRs) were detected in PM samples collected from various cities in the USA (
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Dellinger et al., 2001</xref>). In relation to this, 
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al. (2014)</xref> demonstrated that EPFRs associated with combustion derived PM were important in enhancing severity and mortality following respiratory tract viral infections. Moreover, 
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Hirota et al. (2015)</xref> showed that urban PM increased human airway epithelial cell IL-1β secretion, following scratch wounding and H1N1 influenza A exposure 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>. A number of investigations have been aimed at capturing the global mortality impact of influenza A (H1N1)pdm09 and identifying factors to explain mortality variations seen across populations. Some studies have focused on risk factors such as pollution exposure. For example, 
 <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al. (2013)</xref> found a significant interaction effect between PM
 <sub>10</sub> and mean temperature on pediatric influenza in Brisbane (Australia). Searching for possible explanations for why some countries were harder hit by the pandemic H1N1 virus in 2009, 
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Morales et al. (2017)</xref> highlighted the need to look at environmental exposure such as air pollution, which is a burden on the respiratory system immune-compromising chronic infections.
</p>
