<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We propose a model, whereby AI NS1 replaces PTPL1 as the interacting partner of RIL, preventing Src inactivation. RIL binds to the SH2 and kinase domain of Src, allowing NS1 interaction with the SH3 domain. Binding of a protein substrate displaces RIL from the Src-NS1-RIL complex, whereby NS1 increases the catalytic efficiency of Src. Loss of the PL domain prevents NS1 interaction with RIL. Interestingly, the F6
 <sub>Δ221–230</sub> mutant lacking all PL domains, was found to be sequestered into the insoluble fraction, upon lysis of infected cells, while the full length F3 NS1 protein was also retained in the soluble part, along with RIL and Src. The soluble fraction of active Src was indeed specifically enriched in infected cells expressing full length NS1, but not the F6
 <sub>Δ221–230</sub> mutant. Src subcellular localization is subjected to complex regulation and Src has been found associated not only to the cytoplasmic side of the plasma membrane, but also to the endoplasmatic reticulum, Golgi apparatus and cytoskeletal components 
 <xref rid="pone.0027789-Sandilands1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. Thus, it is possible that NS1 requires interaction with RIL to be relocalized at specific cellular compartments together with Src. Src transduces signals to many cellular pathways, affecting cell proliferation, cell motility, apoptosis, immune signalling 
 <xref rid="pone.0027789-Palacios1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0027789-Ingley1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. The exact role of Src activation in the AI virus replication cycle is still unknown, however, a recent report showed that IL-1 dependent inflammatory response due to influenza A viral infection, was dependent on Src activation and was completely abrogated by PP2 treatment 
 <xref rid="pone.0027789-Lietzen1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. Thus, it is tempting to speculate that viruses bearing NS1 proteins able to upregulate Src activity through the RIL axis, might be expected to induce a stronger inflammatory response than viruses with NS1 proteins lacking RIL- or Src-binding capabilities. We have shown that NS1 interaction with Src required the SHB domain 2. Interestingly, human circulating H1N1 and H3N2 strains as well as the 2009 pandemic H1N1v, all have mutations in the SHB domain 2, which prevent interaction with Src, suggesting again a possible host-specific adaptation mechanism.
</p>
