<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0095">Whether a specific CoV-induced neuroinfection will evolve to resolution, progression, or chronicization, depends on a fine balance between factors that promote or restrain inflammatory responses (
 <xref rid="bb0660" ref-type="bibr">Savarin and Bergmann, 2018</xref>). While the activation of both innate and adaptive immune responses is crucial for CoVs clearance and infection healing, the release of inflammatory mediators may seriously damage the CNS. Studies on JHMV-induced neuroinfection in mice unveiled a specific temporal sequence of the immune response: once inside the CNS, the virus triggers innate immunity with significant polymorphonucleate, macrophage and NK cell infiltration. The release of cytokines and chemokines causes tissue damage, and eventually long lasting adaptive immunity is established, thus eradicating the infection or initiating CNS autoimmune aggression (
 <xref rid="bb0085" ref-type="bibr">Bergmann et al., 2006</xref>). Early activation of innate immunity is associated with the release of INFα/β by microglial cells. A strong INF response predicts the resolution of the infection, whereas a weak response is associated to a higher risk of virus persistence and chronic CNS infection (
 <xref rid="bb0085" ref-type="bibr">Bergmann et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0660" ref-type="bibr">Savarin and Bergmann, 2018</xref>). Wheeler et al. (
 <xref rid="bb0835" ref-type="bibr">Wheeler et al., 2018</xref>) recently reported that microglial activation is essential for the survival of mice with a severe JHMV variant-induced encephalitis. Proinflammatory cytokines and chemokines, including IL-1α, IL-1β, IL-6, IFN-γ, TNF-α, and CXCL10 are released by CNS resident cells (macrophages, glial and endothelial) as well as by infiltrating cells as part of the innate immunity response, and play a crucial role both in damaging the nervous tissue and in the subsequent activation of the adaptive immunity (
 <xref rid="bb0355" ref-type="bibr">Joseph et al., 1993</xref>). As a matter of fact, it has been demonstrated that there is a correlation between the levels of the mRNAs for some of the aforementioned mediators of the innate immune response (such as TNF-α, IL-12 p40, IL-6, IL-15, and IL-1) and the neurovirulence of different MHV strains, further strengthening the role of these cytokines as master regulators of CoV neurovirulence (
 <xref rid="bb0430" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2004</xref>). In fact, IL-1 and IL-6 mRNA transcription is robustly activated in mice brains following infection with the neurovirulent JHMV, but not with the more attenuated MHV-A59 strain (
 <xref rid="bb0635" ref-type="bibr">Rempel et al., 2004</xref>). Moreover, high levels of IL-1β were found in brain-derived CD11
 <sup>+</sup> cells, microglia, and macrophages from MHV intracranially-infected mice. Survival of these mice was increased by treatment with the IL-1 receptor antagonist (IL-Ra) anakinra (
 <xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">Allan et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0790" ref-type="bibr">Vijay et al., 2017</xref>).
</p>
