<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0100">The pathophysiological relevance of some of these mechanisms also receives support from studies in humans. The levels of proinflammatory cytokines such as IL-1β, IL-6, IL-8 and TNFα and their ratio with antinflammatory cytokines such as IL-Ra and IL-10 correlate with damage progression in many CNS inflammatory diseases, including neuromyelitis optica, transverse myelitis, acute disseminated encephalomyelitis (ADEM), amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, herpes simplex encephalitis, Parkinson's disease, traumatic brain injury, epilepsy, and stroke (
 <xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">Beridze et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0185" ref-type="bibr">de Vries et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0645" ref-type="bibr">Rodney et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0775" ref-type="bibr">Vezzani et al., 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0805" ref-type="bibr">Waje-Andreassen et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0825" ref-type="bibr">Welsh et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0885" ref-type="bibr">Zaremba and Losy, 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0785" ref-type="bibr">Vezzani et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0830" ref-type="bibr">West et al., 2019</xref>). As a matter of fact, high levels of IL-6, IL-8, MCP-1, and GM-CSF were found in both serum and cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) samples from hospitalized children with acute encephalitis-like syndrome and serological evidence of recent CoV-induced respiratory tract infections (
 <xref rid="bb0435" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2016</xref>). Among the chemokines released in the early stages of CoV neuroinfection, CXCL9 and CXCL10, both induced by IFN-γ, are among the earliest inflammatory markers in the peripheral blood of patients affected with SARS (
 <xref rid="bb0345" ref-type="bibr">Jiang et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0855" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2005</xref>). The levels of both CXCL9 and CXCL10 were abnormally elevated in brain samples from a SARS-affected patient (
 <xref rid="bb0855" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2005</xref>). A potential link between direct cytotoxic and indirect immune-mediated neurovirulence mechanisms triggered by HCoV-OC43 in mice has been hypothesized upon demonstration that IL-6 promotes glutamate-dependent exocitoxicity (
 <xref rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr">Brison et al., 2014</xref>), and that the NMDA glutamate receptor antagonist memantine produces significant neuroprotection in HCoV-OC43-infected mice (
 <xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">Brison et al., 2011</xref>). Finally, a hyperactive immune response leading to the massive release of cytokines in the general circulation (
 <italic>cytokine storm)</italic> and to intravascular disseminated coagulation and multiorgan failure, is a major mechanism of death in COVID-19 patients. This further highlights the crucial role of the immune system in the progression of CoV-induced diseases (
 <xref rid="bb0350" ref-type="bibr">Jose and Manuel, 2020</xref>).
</p>
