<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Surface water is easily contaminated by stable fecal-shed viruses such as HEV and acts as a public health hazard [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B110-ijerph-10-04507">110</xref>]. The quality of surface water directly affects populations utilizing the source since drinking water, and intensive farming practices lead to higher detection rates of viruses within these sources [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B110-ijerph-10-04507">110</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B111-ijerph-10-04507">111</xref>]. In Canada, HEV Genotype 3 detected from field-grown strawberries shared 99% nucleotide sequence identity with local swine HEV strains [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B112-ijerph-10-04507">112</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B113-ijerph-10-04507">113</xref>]. In Slovenia, Genotype 3 HEV was recovered from surface waters as well as from 20% of fecal samples in local pig farms [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B114-ijerph-10-04507">114</xref>]. Typical irrigation practices allow HEV and other enteric and hepatic viruses to impact surface water quality and elevate the potential for human exposure to pathogens [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B115-ijerph-10-04507">115</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B116-ijerph-10-04507">116</xref>]. Contaminated produce may serve as a source for autochthonous HEV cases in non-endemic regions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B112-ijerph-10-04507">112</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B117-ijerph-10-04507">117</xref>]. In all cases of HEV detection in water or produce, the contamination levels were not assessed for further infectivity of humans or animals. The ability to recover infectious virus both from the local pig farms, the surface waters, and from produce receiving contaminated water would indicate that the virus is stable enough to be transmitted in these sources. Therefore, further infectivity studies should be done to assess the ability to transmit and cause infection especially in cases where the virus contamination levels are low.
</p>
