<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since the individual decision-making process is affected by the risk perception, during evolution we have developed fast decision shortcuts, called heuristics, in order to increase our survival. Heuristics are efficient cognitive processes that ignore information and enable fast decisions. Because of their cognitive limitations, humans are often unable to perform rational calculations and instead rely on error-prone heuristics; moreover, even when people could optimise, that is, to compute the best decision, they often rely on heuristics to save efforts at the price of sacrificing some accuracy. These concepts are based on the principle of an accuracy-effort trade-off: the less information, computation or time one uses, the less accurate one’s judgments will be. This trade-off is believed to be one of the few general laws of the mind. It is important to evaluate the heuristics in terms of its ecological rationality environment. How do people make decisions when optimisation is out of reach? Examples of the embedded heuristics toolbox we use at individual or social levels are the recognition heuristic, which states that if one of the two alternatives is recognised, one will infer that it has the higher value on the criterion (less-is-more effect is often detected); the 1 ∕ 
 <italic>N</italic> equality heuristic, which allocates resources equally to each of N alternatives; and 
 <italic>titfortat</italic>, in which one cooperates first and then imitates her/his partner’s last behaviour; other widely used heuristics are the imitation of the behaviour of majority and the imitation of the successful person. The last two heuristics are recognised as a driving force in bonding and group identification and therefore play an important role in our choices [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. In 1950 Herbert Simon [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] first proposed that the people satisfice rather than maximise. Maximisation means optimisation, the process of finding the best solution for a problem, whereas satisficing (satisfying and sacrificing at the same time) means finding a good enough solution. This corresponds to a well-known heuristics: in order to select a good alternative (e.g. a house or a spouse) from a series of options encountered sequentially, a person sets an aspiration level, chooses the first one that meets the aspiration and then terminates the search. The aspiration level can be fixed or adjusted following experience. For Simon, humans rely on heuristics not simply because of their cognitive limitation but also because of the task environment. We often trust a person we know well as non-infected while we may judge as potentially infected a person we do not know; sometimes these decision-making processes take less than one minute. Gigerenzer has shown that simple rules, that is, decision-making tree based on fast and frugal heuristics, behave nearly the same as more complex diagnostic procedures [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. The self-diagnosis, which may correlate with the time you decide a medical visit is opportune, the choice of a doctor or of a therapy could be biased by the underlying presence of the recognition heuristics. There is a growing activity of mathematical modelling of the impact of heuristics in the theory of mind and in the ICT. Recent approaches are based on so-called ACTR (adaptive control of thought-rational) and establish analogies with an ecological model for strategy selection. In Parma during 1980s and 1990s Rizzolatti and colleagues demonstrated the existence of a mirror-matching system in the human brain [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. It is nowadays accepted that the mirror neurons system mediates the automatic imitation and empathy; in some sense they provide basis for connecting individuals’ emotions. The neurophysiology of mirror neurons could possibly suggest the origin of heuristics in the imitation and processing capabilities of mirror neurons and in the spread of risk perception levels by imitation. The ancient structure of the mirror neurons could provide some explanation for some ancestral fears and overestimated risk perception such as that for snakes. It is noteworthy that the link between heuristics and neurophysiology and the link between epidemics spreading and heuristics generate a connection between epidemics and the functioning of brain regions affected by fear and conscience. This connection is also affected by reading newspapers, twitter and blogs, watching television and Youtube.
</p>
