<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The OAS reported for human influenza viruses was mostly between chronologically distant strains 
 <xref rid="pone.0041332-Kim1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0041332-Davenport2" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0041332-FazekasdeSt2" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0041332-Jensen2" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0041332-Webster2" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>. In these cases, the antigenic differences between these viruses are likely resulted from gradual antigenic drift over the years. Thus the OAS phenomenon may not exert a significant impact in the past for seasonal human influenza virus infection as the vaccines are regularly updated 
 <xref rid="pone.0041332-Wrammert1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. However, the 2009 H1N1 influenza pandemic introduced a new virus strain that is related to and yet antigenically different from the 2008–2009 seasonal H1N1 influenza virus. Interestingly, comparing to patterns of seasonal influenza virus infection in the past, the pandemic H1N1 influenza virus caused relatively fewer influenza-like illness in persons aged 65 or older 
 <xref rid="pone.0041332-CDC1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>. It has been suggested that OAS may have contributed to the protection of the aged population against the new H1N1 influenza virus infection 
 <xref rid="pone.0041332-Adalja1" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>. On the other hand, several reports indicated that immunization with 2008–2009 influenza vaccines may associate with a higher risk of influenza like illness caused by the new H1N1 influenza virus infection 
 <xref rid="pone.0041332-Skowronski1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0041332-CrumCianflone1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>. These observations raise the possibility that OAS induced by previous seasonal influenza vaccine may have enhanced infection by the new H1N1 influenza virus 
 <xref rid="pone.0041332-Skowronski1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>. While these studies are not corroborated by others 
 <xref rid="pone.0041332-GarciaGarcia1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0041332-Lessler1" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>, they underscore the importance to investigate the impact of OAS on influenza vaccine efficacy and virus infection for preparation against future pandemics. Although the OAS between QH and SX viruses observed in this study did not affect antibody induction to the second strain, it remains to be determined whether a different outcome will be found between H5N1 HPAIV from other clades. Further, while the HA of QH and SX viruses antigenically distinctive, both CD8 and CD4 T cell responses induced by these two HA DNA vaccines are cross reactive and T cell responses were effectively augmented by heterologous boosting similar as homologous boosting. Evidence suggests that cross-reactive T cell responses may also contribute to protection against influenza virus infection 
 <xref rid="pone.0041332-Valkenburg1" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>. However, while it is expected that priming with the SX HA DNA followed by boosting with the QH HA DNA will elicit higher levels of CD8 and CD4 T cell responses than a single immunization with the QH HA DNA vaccine, such enhanced T cell response apparently did not result in improved protection against subsequent challenge by the QH H5N1 virus. Thus, such cross reactive CD4 and CD8 T cell responses may not be very effective for protection against infection and pathogenesis by H5N1 HPAIV. Moreover, the impact of OAS to protection against subsequent heterologous H5N1 HPAIV infection in humans and other animals may also exhibit individual differences. As reported in our recent studies, evolution of H5N1 HPAIV has resulted in continuing antigenic drift of these viruses 
 <xref rid="pone.0041332-Li1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. The genetic and biological complexity of the H5N1 HPAIV detected in recent years in China alone indicates that reassortant viruses are constantly generated during natural infection of avian species, which may enable these lethal viruses to gain transmissibility in humans. In particular, the OAS observed in this study between two antigenically distinctive HA antigens did not significantly affect the induction of antibody responses against the second virus strain. However, evolution of H5N1 HPAIV may lead to emerge of viruses with antigenic-drifted HAs that share non-neutralizing epitopes, which could potentially exert a more deleterious effect on induction of protective immune responses against other strains. Therefore, the existence of OAS between different clades of H5N1 HPAIV is also of significant concern for H5N1 influenza vaccine development. In a recent study, Want et al. showed that immunization with polyvalent DNA vaccines successfully induced cross-protective immune responses against several H5N1 HPAIVs from different clades 
 <xref rid="pone.0041332-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>. Further, Giles et al. reported the design of a computationally-optimized HA that could confer cross-protection against infection by different strains of HPAIV 
 <xref rid="pone.0041332-Giles1" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>. These studies offer promising strategies to overcome the potential impact of OAS between different HPAIVs. The rapid evolution of antigenically diverse H5N1 HPAIV in domestic poultry and wild birds underscores the importance of surveillance studies to determine cross-reactivity between different virus strains and the need to develop an effective polyvalent or universal vaccine strategy against a potential H5N1 influenza pandemic.
</p>
