<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>PHASTER[
 <xref rid="pgen.1008850.ref114" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>] curated prophage sequences were classified into species and genus-level groupings based on the current criteria used by the Bacterial and Archaeal Viruses Subcommittee of the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses (ICTV)[
 <xref rid="pgen.1008850.ref120" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>]. At the species level, genomes were clustered at 95% nucleotide identity over the whole genome length, meaning that two genomes belong to two different species if they differ in more than 5% of their genome. Clustering was performed with CD-HIT-EST at 95% nucleotide identity over 95% of the alignment length (99% of alignment length of shorter sequence)[
 <xref rid="pgen.1008850.ref121" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>] and with Gegenees, a pairwise nucleotide comparison tool, using the accurate settings of 200 bp fragment size and 100 bp step size[
 <xref rid="pgen.1008850.ref122" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>]. The Gegenees output was used in combination with vConTACT2[
 <xref rid="pgen.1008850.ref123" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>] to classify the prophage sequences into new or existing genera. Briefly, coding sequences were predicted with PROKKA[
 <xref rid="pgen.1008850.ref098" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>] and transformed into a table linking genomes and their encoding proteins. This table was used as input into vConTACT along with the Viral RefSeq database v85[
 <xref rid="pgen.1008850.ref124" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>]. vConTACT then used Diamond[
 <xref rid="pgen.1008850.ref125" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>], Markov clustering MCL[
 <xref rid="pgen.1008850.ref126" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>] and ClusterONE[
 <xref rid="pgen.1008850.ref127" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>] to predict viral clusters based on shared protein content. The output was visualised using Cytoscape[
 <xref rid="pgen.1008850.ref128" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. Genera were defined as vConTACT viral clusters which shared a significant (&gt;50%) nucleotide identity. The clusters were then compared to the current and pending ICTV taxonomic classification (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ictvonline.org" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">ictvonline.org</ext-link>) using blast and vConTACT viral cluster output containing reference genomes and all prophage sequences were assigned to new or existing taxa.
</p>
