<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The initial clinical sign of the COVID‐19 that allowed its case detection was pneumonia. While some reports suggest gastrointestinal symptoms associated with this disease, others describe asymptomatic infections, particularly among young children.
 <xref rid="rmv2113-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref> SARS‐CoV‐2019 may cause lower respiratory symptoms, upper respiratory symptoms, constitutional symptoms, and, less commonly, gastrointestinal symptoms. Most patients show lower respiratory symptoms and constitutional symptoms (eg, cough and fever).
 <list list-type="bullet" id="rmv2113-list-0004">
  <list-item id="rmv2113-li-0027">
   <p>The incidence of fever is variable among studies (ranging from 43% to 98%). This may relate to different strains of virus or different levels of disease severity between several cohorts. Regardless of the frequency, absence of fever in a patient does not exclude COVID‐19.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="rmv2113-li-0028">
   <p>About 80% of patients may have lymphopenia.
    <xref rid="rmv2113-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">22</xref>, 
    <xref rid="rmv2113-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">23</xref>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="rmv2113-li-0029">
   <p>Mild thrombocytopenia is very common (but only rarely do platelet counts decline below 100).</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="rmv2113-li-0030">
   <p>Lower platelet count is a marker of poor prognosis.
    <xref rid="rmv2113-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">
     <sup>19</sup>
    </xref>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="rmv2113-li-0031">
   <p>Also, up to 10% of patients can initially show gastrointestinal symptoms (eg, nausea and diarrhea), followed by dyspnea.
    <xref rid="rmv2113-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">
     <sup>24</sup>
    </xref>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="rmv2113-li-0032">
   <p>Some patients, especially the elderly, may have “silent hypoxemia” and respiratory failure without dyspnea.
    <xref rid="rmv2113-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">
     <sup>25</sup>
    </xref>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="rmv2113-li-0033">
   <p>Approximately, 2% of patients may develop pharyngitis or tonsil enlargement.
    <xref rid="rmv2113-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">
     <sup>22</sup>
    </xref>
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
