<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> are considered the main urban vectors of dengue, Zika, and chikungunya, while 
 <italic>Culex</italic> spp. mosquitoes transmit West Nile and Japanese encephalitis viruses [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002213.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–
 <xref rid="pmed.1002213.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The presence of urban mosquito vectors also increases the emergence or re-emergence potential of other viruses including yellow fever and Mayaro [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002213.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="pmed.1002213.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Effective vaccines exist for yellow fever and Japanese encephalitis, and recent advances in dengue [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002213.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] and Zika [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002213.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] vaccine development are relatively encouraging. However, major challenges remain (e.g., [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002213.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="pmed.1002213.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]), and for most mosquito-borne viral infections vector control is still the cornerstone of disease prevention [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002213.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="pmed.1002213.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="pmed.1002213.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. In theory, effective control of disease spread requires lowering the ratio of competent vectors to susceptible human hosts below a critical threshold value, which, in turn, brings an infection’s basic reproductive number, 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub>, below unity [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002213.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>–
 <xref rid="pmed.1002213.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> is a fundamental quantity in infectious disease epidemiology [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002213.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. It measures the number of new (secondary) cases that arise from a primary (index) case entering a susceptible host population; with 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> &lt; 1.0, each case produces, on average, less than one new infection, and the disease fades out from the host population. 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub>, then, provides also a measure of the control effort needed to effectively stop transmission [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002213.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>–
 <xref rid="pmed.1002213.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].
</p>
