<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20">Without disturbance or perturbation, the URT microbiome was stable in both uninfected humans and ferrets. IAV does not directly infect any microbiome constituents, yet infection disturbs the healthy-state microbiome in both hosts in a statistically robust manner. The microbiomes of infected (unhealthy) individuals or animals were quite different from each other (Figs. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). However, in both hosts, unhealthy microbiomes were divergent from the healthy microbiomes, and numerous community assemblies were possible in the unhealthy state. This is a clear demonstration of the Anna Karenina principle
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>, restated as “all healthy microbiomes are the same, while unhealthy microbiomes are unique.” This high diversity of unhealthy microbiomes during early stages of acute infection is consistent with earlier studies
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup>, but here we demonstrate specifically that it can occur as a consequence of an indirect disturbance such as IAV infection. In agreement, in recent studies changes in the microbiome structure were also reported in a household contact setting in secondary cases of IAV infection
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup>, and in a cohort of infected individuals with either H3N2 Influenza Infection or individuals infected with Influenza B
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup>. We propose that the disturbance of the healthy URT microbiome creates transient ecological niches for opportunistic bacterial pathogens. How viral infection induces a disturbance in the microbiome requires further assessment. Nevertheless, the host antiviral responses such as the induction of interferon during IAV infection could contribute to the perturbation of the microbiome in a dynamic manner, though this requires host and microbiome metatranscriptomics or metaproteomics measurements in controlled experiments focused at the onset of infection. Nevertheless, maximum disturbance correlated with maximum viral loads and weight loss in the ferret model, which suggests a close relationship between active infection, disease, and disturbance of the microbiome, with kinetics that are similar to the antiviral response induced during IAV infection
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>
 </sup>. This is in contrast to a recent study of previously healthy individuals experimentally infected with a H3N2 influenza strain from 2005, where no oropharyngeal microbiome changes were reported
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup>. This discrepancy might be due to the fundamentally different nature of the oro- and nasopharyngeal microbiomes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>, to potential differences induced by natural versus experimental infection in humans, or due to intrinsic differences induced by different IAV subtypes. No significant influence of the host type (age and sex) or behavior (antibiotic usage) was observed on the temporal nature of the microbiome elasticity. However, more statistical power would be needed to draw any further robust associations from the data. This is particularly the case for our cases under 5 years of age and greater than 65 years of age, for which we lacked healthy age-matched controls. Hence, additional human cohort studies to underpin the factors modulating microbiome dynamics during IAV infection are warranted.
</p>
