<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par34">RSV-FA2-specific, IFNγ-secreting T cells were enumerated in freshly isolated PBMCs using ELISPOT kit (Monkey IFNγ ELISpot
 <sup>PRO</sup>, MabTech, Cincinnati, OH) specific for monkey IFNγ. Plates pre-coated with an NHP IFNγ-specific capture antibody (clones GZ-4 or MT126L) were washed four times with sterile 
 <sc>d</sc>-PBS (180 µl/well) and blocked with RPMI-10 (200 µl/well) for 30 min at 37 °C and 5% CO
 <sub>2</sub>. After removal of the blocking buffer, PBMCs in RPMI-10 were seeded at 2 × 10
 <sup>5</sup> cells/well and stimulated with an RSV-FA2 peptide pool, reconstituted in dimethylsufoxide (DMSO), consisting of 15-mers overlapping by 11 amino acids at a final concentration of 2 µg/ml for 18–20 h at 37 °C and 5% CO
 <sub>2</sub>, in a final volume of 200 µl. RPMI-10 supplemented with 0.005% DMSO served as a medium control and a 1/1000 dilution of α-CD3 antibody in RPMI-10 as a positive control. After removal of the cell suspension, wells were washed five times with PBS + 0.05% Tween20 (KD Medical, Columbia, MD) and twice with D-PBS (200 µl/well) at RT and subsequently incubated with 100 µl/well INFγ detector antibody conjugated to alkaline phosphatase (clone 7-B6-1-ALP, 1:200 in PBS + 0.5% FBS) for 2 h at RT. Plates were washed as described before and spots developed for 15 min in the dark at RT, using 100 µl of a 5-bromo-4-chloro-3'-indolyphosphate p-toluidine/nitro-blue tetrazolium chloride solution filtered through a 0.45 µm filter. The development was stopped by washing extensively with tap water. Plates were air dried for at least 72 h before spots were counted on an ImmunoSpot S5 ELISPOT plate reader (C.T.L. Europe GmBH, Bonn, Germany). All samples were analyzed in either duplicates or triplicates. Mean spot-forming units (SFU) per 10
 <sup>6</sup> cells were calculated from the replicate measurements, followed by individual background subtraction of the mean medium control values from the mean peptide-stimulated values. The lower limit of quantification was set at 50 SFU/10
 <sup>6</sup> cells, which corresponds to a coefficient of variation of 30%.
</p>
