<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par29">This integrated analysis of the SARS-CoV-2 transcriptome and proteome revealed significant findings, in particular, the identification of an eight aa deletion in the SARS-CoV-2 S glycoprotein that potentially effects protein cleavage, cell tropism and infectivity. The coronavirus S glycoprotein is made as a larger precursor that must be primed by cleavage using host cell proteases to enable subsequent viral entry [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. For different coronaviruses, cleavage can occur at one or more sites (termed the S1/S2 and S2′ sites) depending on the host cell and the amino acid consensus sequences present at each site, with major repercussions on host cell tropism and pathogenesis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. The SARS-CoV S glycoprotein has a single arginine residue at the S1/S2 site (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b) that facilitates cleavage by a number of proteases including trypsin, cathepsin L and TMPRSS11D [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] and a consensus sequence for trypsin and/or elastin cleavage at the S2′ site [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. By comparison, SARS-CoV-2 has a four amino acid insertion (
 <sub>680</sub>SPRR
 <sub>683</sub>) in the S glycoprotein that results in the generation of a furin-like cleavage site (
 <sub>682</sub>RRAR
 <sub>685</sub>) at the S1/S2 boundary that is not present in other lineage B betacoronaviruses, including SARS-CoV and the highly related bat coronavirus RaTG13 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Moreover, analysis of a cryo-EM structure of the S glycoprotein showed that the SPRR insertion creates a disordered solvent exposed loop [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] that protrudes from the trimer surface (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a). It has been proposed that this region is more available to host cell proteases for processing [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The presence of a furin-like cleavage site at the S1/S2 boundary results in cleavage of the SARS-CoV-2 S glycoprotein before viral exit from the cell, whereas the S glycoprotein of coronaviruses such as SARS-CoV, lacking a S1/S2 furin cleavage site, exit the cells with the S glycoprotein largely uncleaved, necessitating cleavage prior to or during cell entry [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>].
</p>
