<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par9">As in other environments, bacteriophages dominate over other viruses in the gut ecosystem. Transmission electron microscopy has shown that the human gut virome consists mostly of DNA bacteriophages from the order 
 <italic>Caudovirales</italic> along with members of 
 <italic>Myoviridae</italic>, 
 <italic>Podoviridae</italic>, and 
 <italic>Siphoviridae</italic> families (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Recently, the order 
 <italic>Caudovirales</italic> was expanded to include 
 <italic>Ackermannviridae</italic> and 
 <italic>Herelleviridae</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. In addition, CrAssphage has been found to be a prevalent constituent of the human gut microbiome, possibly representing a new viral family (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. This phage was recently found to be present in thousands of human-feces-associated environments around the world, confirming it as a strong marker for fecal contamination [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Highly divergent but fully colinear genome sequences from a few crAss-like candidate genera have been identified in all major groups of primates, suggesting that crAssphage has had a stable genome structure for millions of years [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. This in turn suggests that the genome structure of some phages can be remarkably conserved in the stable environment provided by the human gut [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. The abundance of eukaryotic viruses in the human gut is low, however, some studies report that small amounts are present in every faecal sample [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. These amounts increase dramatically during viral gastrointestinal infections [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. 
</p>
