<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We obtained circumcision information on ethnic groups from the Revised Ethnographic Atlas (Gray (1999) 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Gray2" ref-type="bibr">[93]</xref>, which is based on Murdock (1967) 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Murdock1" ref-type="bibr">[92]</xref>). We considered all relevant ethnic groups in the Ethnologue database 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Gordon1" ref-type="bibr">[94]</xref>. We collected primary ethnographic articles and books to complement the circumcision information provided by the Atlas, thus covering all important ethnic groups, and almost all groups with more than 20,000 people, of the areas at or near chimpanzee and sooty mangabey ranges. Most observations were from the period 1880–1940 (both those on which the Atlas is based, and those of our ethnographic collection). For each ethnic group, we gathered information on male circumcision practice, including generality, approximate time of adoption (if adopted recently), associated initiations and rituals if any, and age of circumcision. We collected demographic surveys specifying ethnic group composition of Central and West African cities, at several points in time. We generated lower and upper estimates of circumcision frequency in urban male adults of each ethnic group, based on the method explained in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s008">Text S2</xref> and implemented in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s010">Dataset S1</xref>. We then computed the distribution of adults in cities by circumcision classes displayed in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g003">Figure 3</xref>, and the estimates of circumcision frequencies displayed in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g004">Figure 4</xref>. The full tables of ethnic composition, and the supporting references of this study are in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s008">Text S2</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s010">Dataset S1</xref>.
</p>
