<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Consensus sequences are usually generated by aligning and comparing multiple sequences and selecting the most common residue at each position (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="vaccines-07-00045-f002">Figure 2</xref>A). These sequences are expected to effectively capture a profile of conserved genetic and epitope information which can induce cross-reactive cellular immune responses [
 <xref rid="B99-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>]. The outcome of this approach is a sequence alignment with conserved antigens that can be expressed on virus-like particle (VLP), which are similar to intact virions but not pathogenic [
 <xref rid="B41-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B100-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>]. Influenza VLP vaccines have advantages that a live virus is not used at any step during vaccine production [
 <xref rid="B101-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>] and they can maintain conformational epitopes by presenting surface antigens in their original structures. Consensus-based studies [
 <xref rid="B29-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B99-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>,
 <xref rid="B101-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>] have generated consensus sequences for NA protein of H1N1 and several influenza proteins of H5N1, including HA, NA and matrix protein M1, which have elicited broadly-reactive immune response. However, the nature of consensus-based antigen design determines that it is highly influenced by the input sequences and thus subject to sampling bias [
 <xref rid="B102-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. For example, H5N1 isolates were sampled in different geographical locations and from different hosts, including human and avian. If samples from one location or one host are overrepresented in the sequences used to generate consensus, then it can bias the output consensus sequence, which may not accurately represent the full conserved genetic profile of the whole H5N1 population. To overcome issues from sampling bias, an iterative optimization strategy has been implemented in an approach known as computationally optimized broadly reactive antigens (COBRA) [
 <xref rid="B41-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. 
</p>
