<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The COBRAs generated by multiple rounds of consensus generation are representative of the diversity in the viral population and are able to induce neutralizing antibodies or other immune boosting response to protect against past, current and ideally, future circulating strains of this specific HA subtype [
 <xref rid="B27-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. COBRAs-based designed HA protein of H1, H3 and H5 have been tested with 
 <italic>in-vitro</italic> assays and animal models. This preclinical evidence has showed broad HA inhibition antibody titers that were cross-reactive with different strains within the same subtype [
 <xref rid="B28-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. This approach has advantages over other universal vaccine candidates, because COBRA HA-elicited antibodies are able to neutralize the receptor binding site and the design has a clear path towards clinical proof of correlate for protective efficacy in humans [
 <xref rid="B28-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. However, there are some concerns associated with this approach. To be universally cross-reactive, the ideal CORBA HA protein should contain all the conserved information present in multiple subtypes. The conserved immunogenic profile of consensus sequences from COBRA approach is dependent upon the sharing of epidemiological and genetic data collected during public health investigations and surveillance of outbreaks. With biased viral samples, the consensus sequence generated may not represent the full profile of conserved immunogenicity along viral evolving history. Even with increased global efforts to collect data and characterize epidemics it is unlikely that sufficient data could be collected to overcome this challenge. Alternative approaches, such as phylogenetic modeling of viral proteins along a characterized evolutionary trajectory that account for impacts of sample biases and missing data could greatly improve design of COBRA candidates.
</p>
