<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par48">HEV infection is associated with high incidence and mortality (principally due to fulminant hepatitis) in pregnant women according to the majority of clinical studies and case reports from developing countries [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. A prospective field study carried out by Khuroo et al. showed that hepatitis E developed in 36 (17.3%) of 208 pregnant women, as compared to 71 (2.1%) of 3350 nonpregnant women and 107 (2.8%) of 3822 men. FHF developed in 8 (22.2%) of the 36 pregnant women with hepatitis E. In contrast, none of the nonpregnant women showed the occurrence of fulminant hepatic failure [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. For the first time, this study revealed that the incidence of hepatitis E and fulminant rates were higher in pregnant women than nonpregnant women and men. In another study, HEV infection was observed in 57.5 and 46% of pregnant and nonpregnant women, respectively. Moreover, 58% of the HEV-infected pregnant women developed FHF. The mortality rate was highest (56%) among HEV-infected FHF cases during the third trimester of pregnancy [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. This study indicated that pregnant women, especially those in the second and third trimesters, are more commonly affected during epidemics than the general population [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Various studies from different regions of the Indian subcontinent reported that the prevalence rate of HEV in acute viral hepatitis during pregnancy ranged from 58 to 86% [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. HEV infection can result in up to 30% mortality among pregnant women in their third trimester [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. HEV-1 and HEV-2 are likely responsible for most of the HEV outbreaks because they are the most prevalent genotypes in developing countries [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Additionally, HEV infection in pregnancy is also associated with high rates of preterm labor and vertical transmission [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. The frequent occurrence of other complications, such as disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC), is also associated with HEV infection in pregnant women [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. For industrialized countries, there are few reported cases in pregnant women [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]; HEV-3 and HEV-4 are associated with these cases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. Unlike HEV-1 and HEV-2, HEV-3 and HEV-4 do not appear to cause fatal infections with fulminant hepatitis in pregnant women [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. However, considering that the limitation of these studies was the small number of cases, other studies are needed to clarify this result.
</p>
