<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="jia225246-sup-0001">
 <caption>
  <p>
   <bold>Figure S1:</bold> Age groups, race groups, movement and mixing in the model.
  </p>
  <p>
   <bold>Figure S2:</bold> HIV disease progression, by HIV states and set‐point viral load, for those not on antiretroviral therapy (ART), and for those on ART but not adherent.
  </p>
  <p>
   <bold>Figure S3:</bold> Different stages of HIV care and transitions between them.
  </p>
  <p>
   <bold>Figure S4:</bold> Illustration of calculations of targets and outcomes.
  </p>
  <p>
   <bold>Figure S5:</bold> Outcomes for model fits.
  </p>
  <p>
   <bold>Figure S6:</bold> Required increase in viral suppression in 2020 above initial 2015 level needed to meet a 50% incidence reduction compared with the base‐case scenario in 2020, for all runs across all fits, against initial level of viral suppression in 2015.
  </p>
  <p>
   <bold>Figure S7:</bold> Correlations between the increase in care continuum parameters above 2015 levels (
   <italic>y</italic>‐axis) and the relative reduction in HIV incidence after five years, for all runs.
  </p>
  <p>
   <bold>Figure S8:</bold> New HIV diagnoses over time under the base‐case scenario and when different US targets are met in 2020.
  </p>
  <p>
   <bold>Figure S9:</bold> HIV incidence (new cases per 100 uninfected men who have sex with men per year) over time under the base‐case scenario and when different targets are met.
  </p>
  <p>
   <bold>Table S1:</bold> Parameters used in the HIV transmission model, with source and justification.
  </p>
  <p>
   <bold>Table S2:</bold> Data fitted to, with fitting bounds, source and justification.
  </p>
  <p>
   <bold>Table S3:</bold> Probability of reaching HIV elimination within 20 years when meeting different (a) trial incidence reduction targets after different time periods; (b) US continuum targets in 2020; (c) UNAIDS targets in 2020.
  </p>
  <p>
   <bold>Appendix S1:</bold> Methods.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <media xlink:href="JIA2-22-e25246-s001.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <caption>
   <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
  </caption>
 </media>
</supplementary-material>
