<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>WNV is one of the most widely distributed emerging mosquito-borne flaviviruses. In a natural cycle, the virus is maintained in a bird-mosquito-bird cycle. Transmission to humans occurs through the bite of 
 <italic>Culex</italic> mosquitoes[
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. Approximately 80% of immunocompetent individuals infected with WNV remain asymptomatic while 20% develop mild febrile disease (WNV fever). Less than 1% of infected individuals, mainly immunocompromised and elderly develop neuroinvasive disease (meningitis, encephalitis, myelitis)[
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]. Diagnosis is confirmed by the detection of WNV IgM and IgG antibodies in serum/CSF with confirmation by virus neutralization test in samples with cross-reactive antibodies[
 <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. Since WNV IgM antibodies may persist up to 500 d in some patients, IgG avidity differentiates current/recent WNV infection from persistent IgM seropositivity from the previous WNV transmission season[
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. WNV RNA can be detected in blood, CSF and urine samples using RT-PCR, but molecular methods are less sensitive than serology[
 <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. WNV has been identified as a cause of both donor-derived and post-transplant infection[
 <xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>]. WNV transmission by organ transplantation was first reported in 2002[
 <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>]. Thereafter, there are many reports on donor-derived or naturally acquired WNV infection in the adult transplant population[
 <xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>-
 <xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. Although WNV infection is associated with higher mortality in the transplant patients[
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>,
 <xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>,
 <xref rid="B109" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>] there are some reports on WNV in SOT recipients with a complete recovery as well as asymptomatic infections[
 <xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>,
 <xref rid="B110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>]. Few reports describing post-transplant WNV neuroinvasive disease in pediatric patients showed a complete recovery in all patients[
 <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>,
 <xref rid="B111" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>,
 <xref rid="B112" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>]. In the light of the WNV (re-) emergence, clinicians should be aware that SOT recipients could be exposed to WNV 
 <italic>via</italic> multiple sources. Therefore, WNV should be included in the differential diagnosis in all patients presenting with fever and neurological symptoms after transplantation during the arbovirus transmission season.
</p>
