<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mosquito-borne flaviviruses (MBFs) are geographically widespread viral infections and a significant cause of morbidity and mortality worldwide (Huang et al., 
 <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Neurovirulent MBFs that have recently emerged in the Western world, such as Dengue virus (DENV), Zika virus (ZIKV), and West Nile virus (WNV), deserve attention due to the unexpected high burden of associated neurological disease observed in affected regions (Sips et al., 
 <xref rid="B191" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Muñoz et al., 
 <xref rid="B145" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). WNV was endemic in some regions in Europe, Asia and Africa where it caused sporadic outbreaks (Sambri et al., 
 <xref rid="B182" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). It emerged for the first time in America in 1999 and since has become the most widespread flavivirus that causes neurological disease globally (Chancey et al., 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). One in 150 individuals infected by WNV experience a neurological disease characterized by encephalitis, meningoencephalitis, meningitis, and flaccid paralysis (Tsai et al., 
 <xref rid="B210" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>; Chowers et al., 
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Mostashari et al., 
 <xref rid="B143" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). Mortality due to WNV encephalitis ranges between 10 and 17% and increases with age and immunosuppression state (Petersen et al., 
 <xref rid="B162" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). DENV is the second most common mosquito-borne infection and is found in tropical and subtropical regions (Caraballo and King, 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Neurological symptoms are typically observed in 4–9% of infected subjects (Solomon et al., 
 <xref rid="B195" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>; Pancharoen and Thisyakorn, 
 <xref rid="B158" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Sahu et al., 
 <xref rid="B180" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), though it has been documented as high as 21% of cases in some reports (Domingues et al., 
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). ZIKV is the most recent emerging MBF in the Americas. After its arrival in 2015, an increased incidence of microcephaly in newborns and Guillain-Barré syndrome (GBS) in adults infected with ZIKV was reported (do Rosário et al., 
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Today, it is known that ZIKV causes fetal brain malformations and triggers GBS (Beckham et al., 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>).
</p>
