<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The evolution of global vs local spread is also addressed in some studies in ecology and epidemiology [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005952.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005952.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. In the cited studies, spatial structure is either not considered at all or limited only to some patchy distribution. Self-organized spatial structures are not definitely controlled or parameterized during simulation. Thus, our model defines spatial structure at first, and examines the dependences of evolutionary outcomes on spatial parameters. The other difference is the effect of "self-shading". If infected individuals are clustered, the number of susceptible individuals available for local infection decreases. Kamo and Boots [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005952.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] assumed that infected individuals will die and vacant sites will be covered only by host local reproduction, which has a strong effect against local infection. In contrast, our model assumes SIS model in which an infected cell changes its state to susceptible and the spatial structure is mainly caused by definition. Therefore, self-shading effect is weaker than the previous studies and our analytical results show the suitable parameter region where the completely local strain can be an ESS. In terms of dynamics on artificially organized spatial structure, Hiebeler [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005952.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005952.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] modeled the competition between species using different proportion of global and local reproduction. In such models, the pairwise invasibility between resident and invader (or mutant) was checked, but the evolution of the trait after invasion was not considered. Here we used similar model for the within-host viral evolution and applied adaptive dynamics framework. It suggests that invasion has the possibility of replacement by mutants and this replacement drives the evolution of traits in a population. Applying adaptive dynamics is justified by the assumption that we focus on viruses that cause persistent infection. Such persistent viruses may have sufficient time for the within-host evolution and the adaptive dynamics can be applied. There should be conflicts between the aims for the short-term increase within a host and that for the long-term spreads between hosts. However, the combined effects of these conflicting selection processes is beyond the scope of the present paper.
</p>
