<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In our main analysis, we have chosen to model commuting with a gravity law. The gravity law is a popular choice for modelling influenza/infectious disease spread [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], and has been found to capture well spatio-temporal influenza [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] and measles [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>] dynamics. An alternative to the gravity law is the radiation law [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], which is parameter free, and therefore claimed to be more universal. Some analytical inconsistencies of the gravity law are also pointed out in [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. The radiation law does not directly depend on distance, but rather on the population density between locations. The fact that the radiation law is parameter free is attractive in this setting, since we are modelling commuting in a fictional country and thus obviously do not have commuting data available for that country. However, the gravity law has been shown to have a better fit [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>], especially for finer scales, which is the case in our setting. For further information on the gravity law, the radiation law, extensions of these and other mobility models, we refer to the thorough review in [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. We have chosen to use the gravity law in our main analysis since it had a better fit to our commuting data (
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sup>2</sup> = 0.82 versus 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sup>2</sup> = 0.67 for the radiation law), and because it is commonly used in spatial models of infectious disease transmission. Regarding the shape of the gravity law, we have chosen to use a power function of distance, as in for instance [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>], [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>], [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>], [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] and [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Some commuting features that are not well captured by the gravity model are pointed out in [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], and they suggest some extensions to the gravity law for solving these issues. However, for reasons of simplicity, we have chosen to work with the more standard model. In 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1006879.s001">S1 Text</xref>, we perform sensitivity analysis on the parameters of the gravity law, the shape of the distance function, and we redo the analysis using a radiation law. The qualitative patterns are robust to the choice of commuting model. However, the different effect sizes varied with the shape of the commuting law. Comments on discrepancies in the effect sizes under the different scenarios are provided below.
</p>
