<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para290">It is important to consider the limitations of this approach. The geographic scope of currently measured factors and the need for their completeness necessitates the use of proxy covariate factors rather than specific drivers. Assuming that spillover potential scales with population, rather than explicit assessment of human-animal interactions, was necessary since systematically collected data on these interactions and their relative frequencies were not available. Data gaps in emerging infectious disease epidemiology and transmission still remain, particularly regarding reservoirs. This flexible framework could, however, add new information such as quantitative measures of risk factors,
 <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref> or include alternative modelling approaches
 <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>65</sup>
 </xref> where appropriate, when such assessments become more geographically comprehensive. Importantly, uncertainty at all stages can be propagated and included in estimates. To maximise generalisability, we were unable to include some pathogen-specific countermeasures. For instance, the high rankings of districts in Uganda and the Democratic Republic of the Congo do not account for historical viral haemorrhagic fever outbreaks in these locations
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>23</sup>
 </xref> and the sophisticated response systems now present, which will help offset some of the outbreak potential identified by this framework. Such response blueprints or experiences, however, can be referenced and replicated by other at-risk countries, including pre-emptive surveys of bat populations in Ghana,
 <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>66</sup>
 </xref> strategies to overcome logistical surveillance challenges used in Uganda,
 <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>60</sup>
 </xref> or recognition of where existing infrastructure could be co-opted, such as polio teams in Nigeria.
 <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>67</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
