<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Numerous strategies exist for modeling epidemic spread. Inspired by previous work on the foot-and mouth-disease epidemic in the UK [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005382.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], we employed semi-parametric transmission models to quantify the risk of infection as a function of demographic factors and different distance metrics across several seasons. Previous studies have used fully parametric models and have focused on a single epidemic with the goal of capturing the entire epidemic process [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005382.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005382.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005382.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. We found that fully parametric models often require time-varying baseline hazards to capture the temporal dynamics of influenza epidemics (supporting 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005382.s001">S1 Text</xref>, Table A5, Figures A8 and A9). Accordingly, a constant baseline hazard was unable to fully capture the temporal dynamics of the 1918 epidemic, with model-predicted onsets times occurring earlier on average than observations [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005382.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. For the 2009 pandemic, information on school openings was necessary to allow the baseline hazard for transmission to change over time (and space) [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005382.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. In this context, the partial likelihood method [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005382.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] provides clear advantages in obtaining robust estimates for key spatial covariates while obviating the need to specify the form of the time-varying baseline hazard. In sensitivity analyses, we found that parameter estimates for the spatial component of the model were robust to the choice of baseline hazard in fully-parametric model formulations (supporting 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005382.s001">S1 Text</xref>, Table A4). One disadvantage of the semi-parametric method, however, is that it does not allow simulations of epidemic trajectories over time and cannot be applied for real-time predictions, as the baseline hazard is not fully specified.
</p>
