<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our study is subject to several limitations. First, and most importantly, our study was limited to eight seasons, making our conclusions difficult to generalize broadly given year-to-year variability in circulating influenza strains. Second, although ~80% of the US population was eventually captured in this dataset, this percentage was lower in earlier years of data collection, and the Midwestern US was geographically under-sampled. Third, our analysis relies critically on the accurate estimation of epidemic onsets in each location, which is particularly challenging during mild epidemics because the influenza signal is weaker. To address this issue, we (1) analyzed data only from locations with sufficiently robust influenza signals, (2) quantified the uncertainty in epidemic onset estimates, and (3) computed onset times using more “traditional” methods (sinusoidal regression models), which showed excellent agreement with our estimates (supporting 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005382.s001">S1 Text</xref>, Figure A12). Further, we have shown that the main results of our study are robust to moderate uncertainties in the epidemic onset times (supporting 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005382.s001">S1 Text</xref>, Figure A13). Fourth, our dataset is based on ILI records rather than laboratory-confirmed influenza cases. Though outpatient ILI captures the aggregate effects of a number of respiratory pathogens, previous work has shown strong agreement with laboratory-based indicators of influenza virus activity at the regional and city level [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005382.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Furthermore, our analysis is focused on influenza epidemic onset times, which are identified using a linear-spline method separating background ILI rates from rapid case growth due to influenza activity. This approach controls for the effect of other respiratory pathogens in the peri-epidemic period.
</p>
