<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In general, the skin aging process is caused by both intrinsic (chronological aging) and extrinsic factors. It is a rather complex process that is associated with the gradual loss of skin integrity as well as stability, and the decline of its physiological function [
 <xref rid="B200-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">200</xref>,
 <xref rid="B201-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">201</xref>,
 <xref rid="B202-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">202</xref>,
 <xref rid="B203-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">203</xref>]. Its clinical manifestations include alterations of pigmentation/elasticity and the appearance of wrinkles and dryness, among others [
 <xref rid="B204-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">204</xref>,
 <xref rid="B205-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">205</xref>,
 <xref rid="B206-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">206</xref>]. Specifically, among various environmental (extrinsic) causing factors, exposure to UV radiation is considered as the most prominent one. In addition, extrinsic skin aging is also referred as to photo-aging which further depends on the frequency, duration and intensity of exposure to sunlight [
 <xref rid="B207-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">207</xref>]. UV-induced photo-aging is mainly mediated by the up-regulation of several matrix metalloproteinases [MMPs; responsible for the degradation of the extracellular matrix (ECM) components] such as collagen, fibronectin and elastin, that in turn, support the skin architecture at a structural and functional level [
 <xref rid="B208-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">208</xref>,
 <xref rid="B209-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">209</xref>]. In addition, the reduced expression levels of the tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinases (TIMPs) as well as the altered activity of UV-induced ROS, MAPKs and transcription factors [e.g., nuclear factor κB (NF-κΒ) and activator protein 1 (AP-1)] appear as major mediators of the photoaging process [
 <xref rid="B210-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">210</xref>,
 <xref rid="B211-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">211</xref>,
 <xref rid="B212-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">212</xref>]. In this context, anti-aging and anti-photoaging skin products dominate the cosmetic and/or cosmeceutical industry, reflecting the high demand for developing new and more effective products with such functionality [
 <xref rid="B213-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">213</xref>,
 <xref rid="B214-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">214</xref>]. Interestingly, a variety of scientific reports indicate the ability of SAAs as potential molecules capable of preventing and/or ameliorating the symptoms of aging and/or photoaging processes, in different experimental models.
</p>
