<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14">Severe cases of COVID-19 are typically marked by acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), with respiratory failure requiring oxygen support and mechanical ventilation. The infection is primarily characterized by diffuse alveolar damage without a consistent pattern of cell infiltration
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105">105</xref>
 </sup>. The pathogenesis of ARDS involves the disruption of normal barrier function, inflammation and subsequent tissue repair. Whether there are sex-specific risks for ARDS and death from other causes, such as trauma, remains unknown
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">106</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref>
 </sup>, although there is a suggestion of a higher risk of lower respiratory tract infections among males
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108">108</xref>
 </sup> and that steroid hormones modulate the immune response to respiratory viral pathogens
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">109</xref>
 </sup>. In one cohort of patients with COVID-19, severe respiratory failure was associated with a pattern of inflammation, macrophage activation and depletion of lymphocytes that was distinct from bacterial infection
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">110</xref>
 </sup>. There was a sex bias for severe COVID-19 not observed in the comparator group with bacterial infections
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">110</xref>
 </sup>. Sex-differential production of IL-6 (ref.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111">111</xref>
 </sup>), monocyte transcriptional patterns and inflammatory set point
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup> could contribute to an enhanced risk of death in males and highlight the importance of sex-stratified analyses to guide deployment of safe and effective immunomodulatory therapeutics for males and females
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">112</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
