<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>HEV has emerged as the most common etiological agent of adult acute viral hepatitis in Central and Southeast Asia and is implicated as the next biggest cause, after HBV, in the Middle East and North Africa [
 <xref rid="B18-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Genotypes of mammalian HEV (
 <italic>HEV1–4</italic>) display not only modes of transmission and clinical characteristics but also have geographical niches. Hepatitis E is typically reported to show one of the two marked epidemiological patterns; it either causes large outbreaks or sporadic cases [
 <xref rid="B7-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Yearly sporadic cases and occasional outbreaks involving numerous cases may occur intermittently in developing countries [
 <xref rid="B7-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. In outbreaks, the clinical attack rate of about 1 in 2 is seen and some studies report males to be twice as likely to be affected [
 <xref rid="B20-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. 
 <italic>HEV1</italic> is primarily reported in Asia and Africa, whereas 
 <italic>HEV2</italic> is found in Mexico and Africa. 
 <italic>HEV3</italic> is predominantly reported in Europe, USA and other industrialized western countries while 
 <italic>HEV4</italic> is found in South East Asia, mainly in Japan, China, and Taiwan [
 <xref rid="B22-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. 
 <italic>HEV1</italic> and 
 <italic>HEV2</italic> cause self-limiting hepatitis in young adults, though there is an increased fatality in pregnant females and immunocompromised patients. 
 <italic>HEV3</italic> and 
 <italic>HEV4</italic> can cause symptomatic hepatitis in middle-aged and older individuals [
 <xref rid="B23-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. The first identified epidemic of hepatitis E was reported in Delhi, India, in 1955–1956 [
 <xref rid="B24-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Since then, a number of sporadic, as well as large, outbreaks are reported each year [
 <xref rid="B25-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].
</p>
