<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this work we considered several models, before concluding that BME is the best one for the Heilongjiang study. For example, due to the presence of disease data with a considerable number of 0 values, the zero-inflated model with spatial random effect was considered, because it has been designed to handle over-dispersed data [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007091.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. We first noticed that after applying this model, the distribution of the original data will change and the data values will be also modified as a result. Second, this model usually either requires certain impact factors (e.g., environmental or gender population features) for regression purposes or the neighbor disease data should be assumed to be the independent variable (regressor). The former possibility is not applicable in the present study because of the lack of such data. As regards the latter possibility, taking the neighbor data as input could account to a limited extent for purely spatial dependency. Yet, these 
 <italic>ad hoc</italic> approximations are not necessary here, since the BME method not only can handle data with any kind of distribution but it also rigorously accounts for the spatial, temporal and composite space-time dependency of the data. Other drawbacks of the zero-inflated model with spatial random effect is that it is a “naïve” interpolator (i.e., it does not account for the varying distances between data locations, and it is impossible to obtain informative space-time maps with finer resolution compared to the original dataset), and it cannot incorporate the disease spread indicators based on probability logic. BME has none of the above drawbacks (it is an adequate interpolator, i.e. it generates accurate estimates at unsampled locations that account for the varying distances between data locations and between the data and the interpolated locations, it generates informative space-time maps with fine resolution, and it incorporates the probabilistic disease indicators).
</p>
