<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>All analyses were performed using Prism v7.0 software (GraphPad). Mann-Whitney 
 <italic>U</italic> tests were used when Zika mean titers and infection cell frequencies were compared between cohorts. The Wilcoxon matched-pair signed-rank test was used for cell subset comparisons between time points within the same cohort (i.e., 1B, 
 <italic>P</italic> = 0.0156; memory CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cell count preinfection to postinfection). AUC analysis for phenotypic proliferation analysis was carried out from day 2 to day 21 post-ZIKV infection for each animal, and then group cohort comparisons were made using the Mann-Whitney 
 <italic>U</italic> test (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>). AUC analysis for Zika mean titers was carried out similarly, except that it was limited to the curve defined by day 2 to day 7 of ZIKV infection (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1C</xref>). Comparisons of ZIKV 50% effective concentrations (EC
 <sub>50</sub>s) were analyzed via 2-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) of log-transformed data (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2E</xref>). Responses to SIV and ZIKV were determined by repeated-measures one-way ANOVA analysis (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref> to D and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">4B</xref>). Pie charts and polyfunctional capability comparisons were assessed using SPICE v5.3 (National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases), with the permutations set at 10,000 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>). The 
 <italic>P</italic> values included within the SPICE analysis reflect the differences between T cell polyfunctionality based on the expression of different combinations of cytokines and not differences in the total number of functions (e.g., 1+ function, 2+ functions). Spearman’s rank-transformed correlation analysis was utilized to evaluate any associations between immune parameters (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4A</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">C</xref>, and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">D</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5D</xref> to 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">I</xref>).
</p>
