<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A set of sera was selected (n = 242) from the 5,600 of the NRC Arbovirus serum bank, as well as a set from the ZIFAG cohort, and divided into four groups based on their genome detection, reaction against inactivated arboviruses, and epidemiological data (
 <xref rid="pntd.0007747.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0007747.s001">SD1 Fig</xref>). The “ZIKV-RT-PCR-positive” group, from the ZIFAG one-year clinical follow-up cohort, is composed of 43 sera collected in French Guyana during the 2016 ZIKV outbreak [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007747.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007747.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The ZIKV genome was detected by RT-PCR during the acute phase and tested sera were obtained during convalescence: 6 to 195 days post symptoms onset (DPSO). Eighty-four percent of this group (n = 36) was sampled during the first month post symptoms onset: two sera were obtained less than 10 days DPSO and 34 between 13 and 25 DPSO. The other sera (n = 7) were obtained between 35 and 195 DPSO [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007747.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The “ZIKV-IgM-positive” group was composed of 50 randomly selected sera, collected mainly from the Caribbean Islands or another DENV-endemic area during the 2015–2016 ZIKV epidemic (total n = 241), based on the following criteria: ZIKV-IgM-positive, DENV-IgM negative, and ZIKV-IgG positive, all tested sera neutralizing ZIKV in PRNT assays. “
 <italic>Flavivirus”</italic> sera (n = 99) group was selected to be 
 <italic>flavivirus-</italic>positive but not ZIKV-positive (total n = 797). All were 
 <italic>flavivirus-</italic>IgG positive and sampled between 2013 and 2014 in Guadeloupe, Martinique, or Saint Martin, DENV-endemic areas, where and when ZIKV was not circulating, assuming that these patients were not ZIKV infected. The “Negative” sera group was composed of 50 negative sera that were both IgM- and IgG-negative for DENV, WNV, Chikungunya virus, Encephalitis St Louis virus, ZIKV, Toscana virus, and Rift Valley fever virus. The ZIKV-IgM-positive, 
 <italic>flavivirus</italic> and negative groups were representative of the entire parent groups in terms of their mean age and immune responses. We determined the sensitivity of the ZEDIII-based ELISA with the ZIKV-RT-PCR-positive group and compared it to that of the ZIKV-IgM-positive group, and the specificity to that of the 
 <italic>flavivirus</italic>-positive group. The serology of the samples was tested upon their arrival to the arbovirus NRC and then stored at -20°C. The antibodies were stable over time and no difference in response was observed several months or years after freezing.
</p>
