<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The etiology of a novel type of coronavirus was identified on January 7, 2020, in Wuhan City in the Hubei Province of China.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>
 </sup> This novel coronavirus (CoV) was later named as severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), and the disease it causes was called coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>
 </sup> Originally, the COVID-19 epidemic was concentrated in China, but it rapidly spread around the world with approximately 15,547,081 known cases and 633,142 deaths as of July 23, 2020.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>
 </sup> COVID-19 is now one of the most devastating pandemics that has affected public health on all six populated continents. There are four known genera of CoV, alpha, beta, gamma, and delta that cause a multitude of symptoms including severe respiratory issues, nervous system alterations, immune dysfunction, as well as kidney, cardiovascular, lung, and gastrointestinal malfunction.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>
 </sup> According to recent studies, SARS-CoV-2 binds to the angiotensin converting enzyme II (ACE2) receptors of the cell of nasal epithelia, lungs, or other organs and triggers an immune response which is believed to ultimately lead to symptoms.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>
 </sup> However, in many cases, individuals have no symptoms that lead to COVID-19 but can still carry and transmit the virus for up to 14 days leading to profound exposure concerns.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>
 </sup> Several research studies have suggested that COVID-19 is a silent spreader and can be divided into asymptomatic where people carry the active virus but never develop any symptoms, presymptomatic, where people have been infected and are incubating the virus but do not show symptoms, and mildly symptomatic where people feel slightly unwell from a COVID-19 infection but continue to come in close contact with others.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>
 </sup> According to a recent global health report, 1 in 5 people worldwide have an underlying health condition that could increase their risk of severe COVID-19.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>
 </sup> Several risk factors have been identified as associated with COVID-19 and its disease severity, including older age, asthma, underlying respiratory disorder,, hypertension, cardiac disease, renal disease, diabetes, obesity, cancer, and smoking.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
