<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The capture ELISA and the lateral flow assay for DENV NS1 are easy to use, highly specific, and inexpensive, and they possess the ability to detect dengue virus NS1 proteins during the early stages of infection. The NS1 ELISA and NS1 lateral flow assay have gradually become the standard for routine clinical assessments, despite their inability to differentiate a primary from secondary dengue virus infection. At present, no existing dengue virus NS1 test kit is able to differentiate among the various dengue virus serotypes. Numerous researchers have tried addressing this issue by developing antigen detection tests for dengue virus infections, generating methods for the creation of anti-DENV NS1 monoclonal antibodies (MAb), and devising tests for dengue virus serotyping. In 2011, Ding et al. (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>) used a prokaryotic expression system to express recombinant NS1 proteins to immunize mice; however, the expressed NS1 was not in its native form and lacked protein glycosylation. In addition, their serotyping ELISAs were developed by pairing four serotype-specific capture MAbs with four other serotype-specific detection MAbs. In the same year, Puttikhunt et al. (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>) used dengue virus-infected PS clone D cells or immunoaffinity-purified NS1 to immunize mice and subsequently developed an NS1 serotyping ELISA that employed a single flavivirus-cross-reactive IgM anti-NS1 MAb to capture NS1 antigens of all four serotypes, which were then detected using four anti-NS1 MAbs. The antigen-antibody complexes were subsequently detected using goat anti-mouse IgG conjugated with HRP. In 2017, Lebani et al. (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>) isolated dengue virus serotype-specific anti-NS1 monoclonal antibodies using phage display biopanning. This involved selecting four serotype-specific MAbs for conjugation with different fluorescent microspheres, which were then paired with a DENV-cross-reactive MAb to enable the detection of DENV NS1. The use of multiplexed fluorescent microsphere beads, however, requires expensive machinery for detection. The following year, Röltgen et al. (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>) used HEK cell surface-expressed NS1 to immunize mice for the generation of anti-DENV NS1 MAbs. They achieved serotyping by pairing four anti-NS1 MAbs as capture antibodies with four biotinylated anti-NS1 MAbs to measure complexes with HRP-labeled streptavidin.
</p>
