<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0050">It seems that most early cases had a history of contact with the original market for seafood, but the disease has now advanced to be transmitted through human to human contact [
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Thus, this disease can be considered as Communicable-both contagious and infectious diseases. In Ayurveda, epidemics are discussed under the term of 
 <italic>Janapadodhwamsa</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, C.S.Vi. 3/5-6] by Charaka and 
 <italic>Maraka</italic> by Sushruta [
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, S.S.Soo. 6/17]. The symptoms like fever, cough, breathing difficulty, headache, and vomiting resemble with clinical features of SARS [
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, S.S.Soo. 6/19]. Dalhana in his commentary has mentioned that symptoms like anosmia, cough, catarrh will occur after the entry of contaminated air through the nasal opening which is similar to typical clinical features of COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, S.S.Soo. 6/19]. Furthermore, this disease can be classified as 
 <italic>Adidaivika Bala Pravritta Vyadhi</italic> (ABPV), 
 <italic>Sansargaja</italic>, 
 <italic>Upsargaja</italic>, and 
 <italic>Aupasargic Roga</italic>. ABPV are those diseases arising due to causes that cannot be controlled by human intelligence. 
 <italic>Upasargaja Vyadhi</italic> are those fever-like diseases that manifest due to close contact with diseased persons [
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, S.S.Soo. 24/7] whereas 
 <italic>Sansargaja Vyadhi</italic> resides with people who are cursed by almighty god i.e. due to influence of invisible forces/forces behind human control [
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, S.S.Soo. 24/7]. 
 <italic>Aupasargic Vyadhi</italic> is defined in two different ways by Sushruta; one as a disease which spreads from one person to another person [
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, S.S.Ni. 5/33-34] and another as ‘…
 <italic>Upadravasangyah</italic>’ i.e. complications or associated diseases that manifest after primary disease [
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, S.S.Soo. 35/18]. Susruta mentions the diseases like 
 <italic>Jwara, Kustha</italic> (skin diseases), 
 <italic>Shosha</italic> (tuberculosis), 
 <italic>Netrabhisyandi</italic> (conjunctivitis), and other 
 <italic>Aupasargika roga</italic> (alike communicable diseases) can be spread through 
 <italic>Prasanga</italic> (intimate relationship), 
 <italic>Gatra Sansparsha</italic> (direct contact), 
 <italic>Nishwasa</italic> (breathing or airborne), 
 <italic>Sahabhojana</italic> (eating together), 
 <italic>Sahashayana</italic> (sleeping together), sharing and using of others’ clothes, ornaments, ointments, etc. [
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, S.S.Ni. 5/33-34].
</p>
