<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par24">Coronaviruses are single and positive stranded RNA viruses belonging to the genus 
 <italic>Coronavirus</italic> of the family Coronaviridae that can cause acute and chronic respiratory and central nervous system illnesses in animals, including in humans [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The infection can also cause mild episodes of follicular conjunctivitis in certain patients. In animal models, the infection has been shown to induce anterior uveitis, retinitis, and optic neuritis like symptoms [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Recent study has shown formation of hyper-reflective lesions in the ganglion cell and inner plexiform layers of the retina particularly around the papillomacular bundles [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. The disease has also been shown to affect sense of smell and taste bud sensitivity in patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. All coronaviruses have a minimum of 3 basic viral proteins (i) an envelope protein (E), which is a highly hydrophobic protein involved in several aspects of the virus life cycle such as assembly and envelope formation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] (ii) a spike protein (S), a glycoprotein involved in receptor recognition and membrane fusion [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] and (iii) a membrane protein (M), which plays a key role in virion assembly [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The viral genome also encodes two open reading frames (ORF), ORFa and ORFb that activate intracellular pathways and triggers the host innate immune response [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. The polyprotein encoded by the virus are initially processed by two main viral proteases, which include a papain-like cysteine protease (PL
 <sup>pro</sup>) and chymotrypsin-like cysteine protease, known as 3C-like protease (3CL
 <sup>pro</sup>), into intermediate and mature non-structural proteins [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>].
</p>
