<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0085">The CARE Act continues to be critically important in supporting services for the uninsured and underinsured, especially in non-Medicaid expansion states.
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>37</sup>
 </xref> Importantly, the CARE Act also demanded that acceptance of funding by state programs required that they in turn had to report success metrics to and abide by the provision of ART and the wraparound services. This funding mechanism was instrumental in increasing the workforce because funded programs had to train and hire health care providers to treat PWH. The federal government also funded the AIDS Training and Education Centers (AETCs) beginning in 1987 with the mission of providing health care providers with education on HIV and comorbidities. The AETCs in 1997 became part of the CARE Act. As a result of addressing HIV from diagnosis to viral suppression, the HIV care continuum has been defined with specific outcomes including diagnosis of HIV; linkage to care; ART prescription; ART retention; and, most importantly and the goal of ART treatment, HIV viral suppression.
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>39</sup>
 </xref> In particular, it is well known that HIV viral suppression not only reduces morbidity and mortality related to HIV-related and non–HIV-related diseases but also reduces HIV transmission to the uninfected.
 <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>40</sup>
 </xref> Thus, overall, this evaluation process of the metrics used in the continuum of care provided usable data that supported PWH and improved individual and public health, and essentially upended the increasing HIV epidemic in this country. Programs that received Ryan White funding improved viral suppression rates among PWH from 69.5% to 85.9% from 2010 to 2017 and predominantly among racial/ethnic minorities,
 <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>41</sup>
 </xref> and there was a reduction in new HIV infections of 8% from 2010 to 2018, from 41,000 to 37,832.
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>42</sup>
 </xref> This reduction was caused not only by widespread HIV care through CARE Act–funded programs but also through advances in science, including preexposure prophylaxis to persons at risk for acquiring HIV,
 <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>43</sup>
 </xref> the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (ACA), the AIDS Drug Assistance Program, and significant research funded by the National Institutes of Health (NIH) and CDC. The requirements of providing services to treat HIV and providing funding for medications to treat HIV with wraparound services such as mental health treatment and SUD treatment have thus led to a reduction in morbidity and mortality from HIV as well as a reduction in new HIV infections in the United States.
</p>
