<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="emmm201910938-fig-0006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 6</label>
 <caption>
  <title>
   <styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">AAV</styled-content>‐
   <styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">HA</styled-content> and 
   <styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">AAV</styled-content>‐
   <styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">cHA</styled-content> have a protective effect in ferrets
  </title>
  <p>
   <list list-type="simple" id="emmm201910938-list-0007">
    <list-item>
     <label>A</label>
     <p>Ferrets (
      <italic>n</italic> = 4 per group) were immunized with AAV vectors or quadrivalent inactivated vaccine (QIV). Serum was obtained at indicated time points (red drops). After challenge with a Cal/7/9‐like (H1N1)pdm strain clinical signs, temperature and weight loss were monitored. At 3 dpi, animals were sacrificed and necropsied.
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <label>B</label>
     <p>Cal/7/9‐specific serum antibody titers in individual sera at indicated time points. Black lines: individual animals, red lines: mean titer. Statistical significance between pre‐immune and immune sera was determined using Friedman test with Dunn's multiple comparison testing (*
      <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **
      <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01). The lower table indicates Cal/7/9‐specific MN
      <sub>50</sub> and HAI mean titers. Assays were performed in technical duplicates.
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <label>C–E</label>
     <p>Clinical score (C), body temperature (D), and relative weight (E) during challenge period. Statistical significance between pre‐immune and immune sera was determined using Friedman test with Dunn's multiple comparison testing (AAV‐HA 
      <sup>##</sup>
      <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01; AAV‐cHA 
      <sup>§§</sup>
      <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01; AAV‐GFP 
      <sup>$</sup>
      <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; 
      <sup>$$</sup>
      <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01; QIV *
      <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Mean ± SD.
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <label>F</label>
     <p>Virus titers in nasal turbinates (NT), trachea, or lung homogenates. Statistical significance between AAV‐GFP and vaccine groups was determined using Kruskal–Wallis test with Dunn's multiple comparison testing (*
      <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Lines indicate the GMT. Assays were performed in technical duplicates.
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <label>G, H</label>
     <p>IHC staining of submucosal glands (SMG) (G) or bronchi (H) with an anti‐H1N1 polyclonal antibody (bar: 100 μm; red: influenza antigen (Neufuchsin); blue: nuclei (hematoxylin)).</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <label>I, J</label>
     <p>H&amp;E‐stained histological sections of bronchi (I) and lung parenchyma with alveolar epithelial cells (AEC, J). Arrowheads: areas of suppurative bronchitis/bronchiolitis; arrows: interstitial pneumonia, necrosis of AEC (bar: (I) 100 μm; (J) 50 μm).</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic id="nlm-graphic-23" xlink:href="EMMM-12-e10938-g012" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
