<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0085">T helper cells (CD4) are responsible for cellular immunity and for helping B cells to produce neutralizing antibodies. Importantly, all B and T cells have immunological memory after a first contact with a pathogen. Memory CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells mediate protective immunity against respiratory coronaviruses as well as neutralizing antibodies that bind the receptor binding domain in the spike of SARS-CoV were reported [
 <xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>], suggesting that a similar immune response could be observed in individuals with COVID-19. The SARS-CoV-2 Spike glycoprotein is closely related to that of SARS-CoV S and some antibodies identified in SARS-CoV-infected patients could also neutralize SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="bib92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. But although cross-reactivity in antibodies binding to the Spike protein is relatively common, cross-neutralization responses between SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 remain rare [
 <xref rid="bib93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. Convalescent sera from SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 patients showed only limited cross-neutralization [
 <xref rid="bib94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]. Pre-existing immunity could explain the relatively low confirmed cases in Africa. Pre-existing SARS-CoV-2-cross-reactive CD4
 <sup>+</sup> and CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells responses were observed in healthy people [
 <xref rid="bib96" ref-type="bibr">[96]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib97" ref-type="bibr">[97]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib98" ref-type="bibr">[98]</xref>]. SARS-CoV-2 Spike glycoprotein-reactive CD4
 <sup>+</sup> cells were found in 20%–60% of healthy individuals [
 <xref rid="bib96" ref-type="bibr">[96]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib97" ref-type="bibr">[97]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib98" ref-type="bibr">[98]</xref>]. Very recently, the analysis of immune responses to SARS-CoV-2 from patients who recovered from COVID-19 identified targets of T-cell responses to SARS-CoV-2 and revealed cross-reaction with circulating ‘common cold’ betacoronaviruses due to past infections [
 <xref rid="bib97" ref-type="bibr">[97]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib98" ref-type="bibr">[98]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr">[99]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr">[100]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib101" ref-type="bibr">[101]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib102" ref-type="bibr">[102]</xref>]. Children appear to be protected and develop mild COVID-19 or no disease [
 <xref rid="bib103" ref-type="bibr">[103]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib104" ref-type="bibr">[104]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib105" ref-type="bibr">[105]</xref>]. Common human coronaviruses (HCoV-229E, HCoV-NL63, HCoV-OC43, HCoV-HKU1) were isolated from 7% to 11% in children hospitalized for acute respiratory tract infections [
 <xref rid="bib106" ref-type="bibr">[106]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib107" ref-type="bibr">[107]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib108" ref-type="bibr">[108]</xref>]. Cross-reactivity between SARS-CoV-2 and human coronavirus is a plausible explanation for why children appear to be protected.
</p>
