<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par27">
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par28">The third epidemic of the twenty-first century:
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par4000">SARS-CoV was reported as the first epidemic of the twenty-first century in 2003 following by MERS-CoV in 2012.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par5000">COVID-19 caused by SARS-CoV-2 is the third epidemic which is declared pandemic by the WHO.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par29">Severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) and coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) portray a number of similarities:
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par7000">Virus homology: As per sequence alignment data, the spike glycoprotein sequence of COVID-19 and SARS-CoV shows 87.2% resemblance; sequences of minimal receptor-binding domain (RBD) show 83.9% similarity.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par8000">Presence of similar glycosylation sites and similar epitopes.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par9000">Routes of transmission of both the viruses (i.e., contact, droplets, and fomite).</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par30">Along with the similarities, severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) and coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) depict a number of dissimilarities also:
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par1100">Such as 12.5% of difference in S glycoprotein sequence and difference in minimal RBD with 23.6%.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par1200">Other behavioral differences, such as rate of transmission and severity of COVID-19 is much higher than SARS-CoV.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par31">The emergence of novel coronavirus 2019 (COVID-19) might be due to RNA recombination as the positive-sense RNA viruses are well reported for their ability of RNA recombination which make them potent to cross the species barrier.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par32">The structural similarity of COVID-19 with SARS-CoV could be encashed in terms of:
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par1500">Use of available treatment for the inhibition of attachment with the host cell. This could be an effective way to control the spread of disease.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par1600">Can use some drug/compound to block the entry into host cell by binding to the receptor.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
