<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Formation of supercolonies and the reduction of intercolonial aggression were commonly found in introduced populations of several invasive ant species including 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>gracilipes</italic> [
 <xref rid="B2-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], suggesting that such alterations in social structure may be associated with invasiveness of these ant species. However, the vulnerable supercolony hypothesis predicts that recurring intercolonial contact readily offers more opportunities for pathogen transmission than species with colonies displaying a territorial boundary. Our study adds to evidence supporting the hypothesis, as we found a strong link between weak social boundaries (simple colony composition) and epidemics of the TR44839 virus among the colonies in Okinawa and Taiwan. Additional support for pathogen transmission dynamics at population level can be obtained from red imported fire ant. Polygynous fire ant colonies harbor a significantly higher diversity of parasites and pathogens when compared to their monogyne conspecifics, and such differences are attributed to the presence of intensive intercolonial interactions among polygyne colonies, such as resource and worker exchanges between colonies [
 <xref rid="B5-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Intensive intercolonial interaction as a result of social structure alteration following invasion may also help explain the finding of viruses (if present) generally persisting in a higher prevalence in introduced areas than those in the native ranges [
 <xref rid="B28-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].
</p>
