<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0040">Here, we report a more comprehensive site-specific analysis of N-linked glycans from contemporary IAVs comprising six evolutionarily distinct hemagglutinin subtypes: H1, H3, H5, H6, H7, and H10 from human and avian influenza viruses. We find that HA stem-domain glycosites conserved across all subtypes exhibit extensive processing of glycans from a high-mannose to complex-type, while glycosites within the head domain of human HAs, including those added incrementally over time, exhibit significant oligomannose-type glycans with minimal processing. Consistent with the presence of conserved oligomannose glycans on influenza HAs, we show that, even when present at low frequencies, a high-mannose-specific lectin from 
 <italic>Galanthus nivalis</italic> (GNL; snowdrop lectin) (
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Kaku and Goldstein, 1989</xref>) can be used for universal labeling and detection of whole IAVs and recombinant HAs on sialoside microarrays, without the requirement for specific antiviral reagents, such as monoclonal antibodies or antisera. Moreover, GNL was also able to inhibit receptor binding and broadly neutralize recent human H3N2 viruses with either comparable or superior potency to a panel of antiviral antibodies. Energy-minimized modeling of glycosylated crystal structures for all six representative HAs reveals conservation of both the positions and types of glycans at individual glycosylation sites, particularly within the group 1 and 2 HA phylogenetic classes (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Air, 1981</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Nobusawa et al., 1991</xref>). Comparison of the glycosylated HAs suggests overall location on HA, together with local structural features surrounding the glycosites to be the major determinants of oligomannose glycoforms, rather than dense packing of multiple sites, as observed in other viruses, such as the human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) (
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Cao et al., 2017</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Cao et al., 2018</xref>). Structural mapping of high-mannose glycosites in the HA of human H3N2 viruses reveals the presence of a small high-mannose patch, in close proximity to the RBS at the top of H3, accounting for the effectiveness of GNL neutralization. Insights into immune recognition of glycosylated HAs, vaccine production and development, and universal virus detection via surface glycans are discussed in light of these findings.
</p>
