<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The most significant and successful commercial development of an irradiated vaccine was that for use against 
 <italic>Dictyocaulus viviparus</italic>, the cause of “husk” in cattle (Jarrett et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">1960</xref>). This parasite is a nematode that inhabits the bronchi and tracheae of cattle, causing a severe and sometimes fatal disease. The parasites were attenuated by irradiation at doses of 200 to 600 Gy to third-stage larvae. The lowest dose was insufficient to alter the infectivity of the larvae, and doses of 600 Gy damaged the larvae so that they did not induce protective immunity; the larvae are completely inactivated and fail to migrate to a location where they can initiate an effective immune response. An intermediate dose of 400 Gy attenuated infectivity sufficiently so that the larvae were unable to develop into adult worms but could still induce protective immune responses in cattle under both experimental and natural conditions (Jarrett et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">1960</xref>). Although X-rays were used in the initial studies, γ-irradiation was employed subsequently. Two oral doses of 1,000 irradiated larvae are effective in reducing worm burdens by up to 95%, protecting against clinical disease and providing protection for up to 12 months. The immunity is not a sterile one, but in areas where the disease is endemic, natural infections provide a boost that can result in a life-long immunity. Animals vaccinated with the radiation-attenuated larvae elicit a strong antibody response against immunodominant N-glycan moieties (Fujiwara et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2006</xref>). Being able to keep vaccines in conditions where long-term storage and distribution are easily achieved is a critical factor in the use of vaccination for animal disease control; unfortunately, cryopreservation of the irradiated 
 <italic>Dictyocaulus</italic> reduces viability by 70% (James and Peacock 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">1986</xref>) and consequently there is no long-term storage option for the vaccine and it has to be stored at &lt;8°C, under which conditions it has a shelf-life of approximately 3 months. Nevertheless, in spite of these apparent drawbacks, the vaccine became a mainstay of control of husk for over 50 years.
</p>
