<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our results demonstrate that an apparently small difference in pairwise genetic distances—for instance, between 0.5 per cent and 1.5 per cent—can make the difference between accurate forecasting of new cases among clusters and becoming misled by stochastic noise. Specifically, both cut-offs cited above are routinely used as customary settings in pairwise genetic distance clustering studies of the same HIV-1 subtype in the same country (
 <xref rid="veaa011-B26" ref-type="bibr">Oster 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2015
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="veaa011-B45" ref-type="bibr">Wolf 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2017
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="veaa011-B23" ref-type="bibr">National Center for HIV/AIDS, Viral Hepatitis, STD, and TB Prevention, 2018</xref>). To investigate the sensitivity of clustering thresholds, we have examined three data sets of anonymized HIV-1 subtype B 
 <italic>pol</italic> sequences that were collected in different regions of North America within similar time frames. All GAIC-optimized cut-offs are located in the left tails of the respective empirical distributions of pairwise distances, with no clear demarcation that might motivate the selection 
 <italic>a priori</italic> of one cut-off over another (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="veaa011-F1">Fig. 1</xref>). However, our information-based criterion reveals a stark difference between these cut-offs when we evaluate the ability of genetic clusters to ‘forecast’ the occurrence of new cases (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="veaa011-F4">Fig. 4</xref>). This discordance is a result of a trade-off between the coverage and predictive value of spatial information that is encapsulated by the MAUP (
 <xref rid="veaa011-B22" ref-type="bibr">Nakaya 2000</xref>). As we relax the clustering threshold, instances of cluster growth become more frequent such that aggregate effects (viz. case recency and mean degree) can be distinguished against the background of stochastic effects. However, the variation in growth rates among clusters eventually becomes homogenized as they are collapsed into a single giant cluster at increasingly high thresholds. These two driving forces can be differentiated in their approach to an optimum, with poor case coverage from strict thresholds resulting in erratic changes in forecasting information, and higher case coverage with relaxed thresholds resulting in a smoother gain of information. If the database is small relative to the population or the number of new cases per year is low, the global minimum in the GAIC profile may become obscured by sampling variation (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S4</xref>), especially when the true optimal threshold is low. Resampling experiments (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Supplementary Figs S4–S6</ext-link>) can help ameliorate the effects of sampling variation and identify situations where sample size may be a concern.
</p>
