<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We selected a relatively simple clustering method in widespread use (pairwise TN93 distance clustering by components; 
 <xref rid="veaa011-B2" ref-type="bibr">Aldous 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2012
 </xref>) to demonstrate our new framework for evaluating clusters, which is based on the GAIC proposed by 
 <xref rid="veaa011-B22" ref-type="bibr">Nakaya (2000)</xref>. Pairwise clustering has been widely adopted in health jurisdictions around the world, including the US-CDC (
 <xref rid="veaa011-B27" ref-type="bibr">Oster 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2018
 </xref>), in part due to the growing popularity of the HIV-TRACE software package that employs TN93 (
 <xref rid="veaa011-B29" ref-type="bibr">Pond 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2018
 </xref>). However, we hypothesize that it should be feasible to use this framework to evaluate potentially any clustering method that defines a partition on the database of known cases. For example, if we require some minimum bootstrap support value to define clusters as subtrees extracted from the total phylogenetic tree (
 <xref rid="veaa011-B33" ref-type="bibr">Ragonnet-Cronin 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2013
 </xref>), then this bootstrap support threshold can represent a second dimension (in addition to a branch length threshold) to locate the minimal GAIC in combination with a distance threshold. We have also demonstrated that the GAIC can be repurposed for model selection where different linear combinations of predictor variables, such as the mean degree size in a given year of diagnosis (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="veaa011-F4">Fig. 4</xref>), are evaluated within the Poisson regression model. 
 <xref rid="veaa011-B3" ref-type="bibr">Billock 
  <italic>et al.</italic> (2019)
 </xref> recently employed a similar model selection approach for pairwise TN93 clusters, although their analysis pre-specified a fixed clustering threshold of 1.5 per cent. Thus, if sufficient metadata are available then one can use the GAIC to select more accurate predictive models of cluster growth while adjusting the clustering criteria, so the models can be evaluated at their best performance.
</p>
