<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Genetic clustering is used increasingly for near real-time monitoring of clinical populations for the purpose of guiding public health activities (
 <xref rid="veaa011-B32" ref-type="bibr">Poon 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2016
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="veaa011-B37" ref-type="bibr">Rose 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2017
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="veaa011-B27" ref-type="bibr">Oster 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2018
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="veaa011-B3" ref-type="bibr">Billock 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2019
 </xref>). Our method is not specific to HIV-1, although the proliferation of clustering methods in HIV molecular epidemiology—driven by the abundance of genetic sequence data and the relatively rapid rate of evolution and low transmission rate of the virus—does make this approach particularly applicable to this virus. Similar pairwise distance clustering methods, for instance, have been used for 
 <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> (
 <xref rid="veaa011-B43" ref-type="bibr">Walker 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2013
 </xref>) and hepatitis C virus (
 <xref rid="veaa011-B16" ref-type="bibr">Jacka 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2014
 </xref>) to infer epidemiological characteristics from molecular sequence variation. In these cases, it may be necessary to rescale the step size/range of clustering thresholds to the expected distribution of genetic distances in order to locate the minimum GAIC. Furthermore, variation in population density and overall case prevalence among regions, as well as the proportion of diagnosed cases, will influence the GAIC. For instance, the visible difference in minimum GAIC we observed between data sets from Northern Alberta and the two locations in the USA was likely driven by differences in population density and sampling fraction. Applications of clustering for HIV-1 prevention have tended to be developed in the context of low-level epidemics, e.g. North America and western Europe, making it challenging to translate these methods to generalized epidemics in other countries without a robust statistical framework for calibrating methods. No matter what pathogen or location is the focus of investigation, it is imperative that we become more critical of clustering methods (
 <xref rid="veaa011-B40" ref-type="bibr">Volz 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2012
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="veaa011-B30" ref-type="bibr">Poon 2016</xref>). Improperly calibrated clustering methods may otherwise prioritize false positives, diverting limited public health resources away from subpopulations where the immediate need for prevention and treatment services was greatest.
</p>
