<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Data analysis is an essential component of using a DNA microarray platform for pathogen detection. Several groups have developed analysis algorithms targeting their own platforms that in some cases can be adapted to other platforms [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005017.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005017.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005017.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005017.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005017.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. The results obtained with each analysis algorithm depend on the strategy used for probe selection. Most of the platforms described in the literature have used probes selected from highly conserved regions of viruses within a specific genus or family to detect both known and new viruses; therefore, probes often cross-hybridize to multiple related genome sequences, making it difficult to correctly identify single viruses or mixtures of viruses present in clinical samples because the output of the algorithms is usually a single list of taxa ranked by some score or by 
 <italic>P</italic>-values. We aimed to design the SMAvirusChip platform to enable the surveillance of known viruses, which is why we selected highly specific probes (&gt;95% identity) for each virus species. Although some individual probes showed cross-hybridization with non-target viruses, the group of probes specific to the individual viruses or mixtures of viruses that were present in the samples were the only ones showing a mean signal intensity ≥1, which was significantly higher than the mean signal intensity of the negative control probes. This allowed clear identification of the virus/viruses present in the samples. In addition, we developed the SMAvirusChip Analysis Form (RAF) to facilitate data processing and analysis in a user-friendly environment. The RAF uses Microsoft Excel software, which is widely used in informatics. The manual entering of data on the RAF does not require additional devices or software besides a regular personal computer with Microsoft Office and a RAF template in Excel format. The user needs only to copy and paste the raw signal intensities of probes, sorted alphabetically, into the RAF to visualize all the results in several spreadsheets included in the form. The analysis algorithm used in the RAF is similar to that used in DetectiV software [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005017.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], which was written in R, a statistical programming language [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005017.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. However, the R package requires users to have some experience in coding in R because it lacks a graphical interface; therefore, DetectiV software is difficult for non-experienced users.
</p>
