<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This study reports the detection of four DENV serotypes amongst field collected 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> mosquitoes in Selangor and Kuala Lumpur in Peninsular Malaysia. In total, 31 samples were positive including dual infections in 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> larvae. Co-infections of 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> larvae with multiple serotypes of DENV have previously been reported in Brazil [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007889.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] and may have occurred as a result of transovarial transmission from the adult mosquito. Dual infections in adult 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> mosquitoes have also been found in Thailand [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007889.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The hyperendemicity of dengue in Malaysia presents an opportunity for co-infections, especially when taking into account the multiple feeding behaviour of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic>. However, as the DENV co-infections were detected in larvae it is unclear if both serotypes would remain in the vector for transmission in adulthood. The single sample positive for DENV-2 that was detected in this study was part of a co-infection with sylvatic DENV-4. Due to the short length of the detected DENV-2 sequence, we are unable to ascertain the genotype of this sequence. The DENV-1 strain detected in this study belonged to genotype I which is related to strains circulating in neighbouring Singapore and Thailand. This particular strain was also the most prevalent serotype detected between 2005 and 2010 in Malaysia. More recently, genotype I was found to be the predominant strain among dengue patients in Selangor and Kuala Lumpur during the 2014–2016 epidemic period [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007889.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Non-severe dengue infections were more commonly observed in patients infected with this strain, unlike those infected with the Cosmopolitan genotype of DENV-2 that were more prone to severe clinical manifestations.
</p>
