<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">Several clinical trials were conducted to treat DENV and reduce the impact and symptoms, but until now no any licensed medicine could deal with DF. However, supportive care with a sedative, the replacement of fluids and bed rest can be useful in some cases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] recommended that a dosage of Acetaminophen 1 g every 8 h for 3 days dealing with DENV might be useful, while Loratadine (LRD) tablets is an orally effective medicine (ethyl4-(8-chloro-5,6-dihydro-11H-benzo, cyclohepta [1,2-b] pyridin-11-ylidene)-1-iperidinecarboxylate) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], that could be used to treat antihistamine and relieve other allergy symptoms [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Additionnaly, ReDuNing (RDN) medicine a patented traditional antipyretic-detoxicate Chinese injection medicine, has been widely used as an anti-inflammatory and anti-infectious drug in Chinese clinics [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Dealing with the severity of dengue demands taking caution toward bodily fluids exchanges, while using proactive therapy for bleeding [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. RDN medicine is composed of three herbs, 
 <italic>Artemisiae annuae</italic> L. (genus Artemisia, Asteraceae), 
 <italic>Gardenia jasminoides</italic> J.Ellis (genus Gardenia, Rubiaceae) and 
 <italic>Lonicera japonica</italic> Thunb. (genus Lonicera, Caprifoliaceae) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. RDN injection medicine exhibits promising effects against enterovirus 71 in Vero monkey cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. From our previous study, some methods were experimentally established to combat inflammation and provide a systems-based strategy to find the therapeutic mechanism of traditional Chinese medicine RDN dealing with the disease [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].
</p>
