<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our analysis of the probable geographic origins of the currently circulating DENV-2 strains showed South Asia as the epicenter of C-I outbreaks, with evidence of seeding to other countries in East Asia, South East Asia, and much more recently in Africa (Kenya, Seychelles, and Reunion). The introduction of this strain into Kenya was estimated to have occurred from this particular region, and most probably from India where most of the closely related strains came from. This may be due to the interconnection between Mombasa and various countries in South Asia, particularly India (
 <xref rid="veaa026-B7" ref-type="bibr">Bita 2015</xref>). The coastal city of Mombasa is East Africa’s main shipping port and an international tourist destination; thus, it may serve as the entry point of DENVs and mosquito vectors through tourism and intercontinental trade. Indeed, a previous study on Chikungunya has supported this hypothesis whereby a strain of Chikungunya that caused an outbreak in northeastern Kenya in 2016 was found to have been introduced into Kenya from India (
 <xref rid="veaa026-B27" ref-type="bibr">Maljkovic Berry et al. 2019</xref>). At the same time, seeding of Chikungunya to the Indian Ocean Islands and the Indian mainland was shown to have happened from this location (
 <xref rid="veaa026-B50" ref-type="bibr">Volk et al. 2010</xref>), where it triggered one of the worst CHIKV epidemics between 2004 and 2007 (
 <xref rid="veaa026-B8" ref-type="bibr">Borgherini et al. 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="veaa026-B9" ref-type="bibr">Chretien et al. 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="veaa026-B22" ref-type="bibr">Kariuki Njenga et al. 2008</xref>). Our results, therefore, support this previous finding and can be explained by the fact that dengue and Chikungunya are transmitted by the same mosquito vector species. This intercontinental network between the Coastal city of Mombasa and countries in South Asia, therefore, provides a nexus for transmission of dengue between Mombasa and South Asia and may have been the channel through which C-I lineage was introduced into Kenya. The C-II lineage strain appears to have been introduced into Kenya possibly from Burkina Faso. However, the long branch as well as the estimated time of introduction between September 1979 and March 2013 points to missing data. Likewise, this lack of genomic data makes it impossible to estimate with certainty the geographical distribution of this strain over time. It is noteworthy to point out that the Wajir/Mombasa strain diverged from Burkina Faso strains in September 1979 (95% HPD: 1978.22, 1981.39). Considering the first documented DENV-2 outbreak at the Kenyan coast was in 1982 (
 <xref rid="veaa026-B19" ref-type="bibr">Johnson et al. 1982a,b</xref>), it is plausible that the ancestral strains of the Wajir/Mombasa strain were responsible for DENV-2 outbreak during that period (
 <xref rid="veaa026-B19" ref-type="bibr">Johnson et al. 1982a</xref>). However, more sequence data from previous Kenyan dengue outbreaks, would confirm whether this strain was responsible for the outbreak experienced in 1982 and later periods. The phylogenetic analysis showed the C-II lineage to have little representation with regard to the number of available sequences. Unlike the C-I lineage which has been implicated in numerous outbreaks across Asia and Africa, the only recent documented epidemic driven by C-II lineage is the Burkina Faso outbreak of 2016 (
 <xref rid="veaa026-B60" ref-type="bibr">WHO 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="veaa026-B3" ref-type="bibr">Baronti et al. 2017</xref>). Prior to this outbreak, C-II had only been isolated in Indonesia in 1975–6 and in Burkina Faso in 1983. The lack of data for this particular lineage could be due to lack of surveillance in areas where it is most common, possibly in Africa and/or Asia. Alternatively, this could also be explained by the intrinsic factors that are particular to C-II lineage of DENV-2. Nevertheless, we cannot explain with certainty the reasons why this lineage is rarely isolated compared with the other Cosmopolitan genotype lineages. It is, however, worth noting that the recent outbreaks reported in Burkina Faso in 2016 were driven by this lineage (C-II) where it was associated with at least 1,061 cases with fifteen fatalities (
 <xref rid="veaa026-B60" ref-type="bibr">WHO 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="veaa026-B3" ref-type="bibr">Baronti et al. 2017</xref>). This epidemic continued into 2017, where DENV-1, 2, and 3 were identified during this outbreak period (
 <xref rid="veaa026-B41" ref-type="bibr">ReliefWeb 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="veaa026-B61" ref-type="bibr">WHO 2017</xref>). Considering DENV-2 was among the serotypes identified, it is possible that the C-II lineage was also responsible for the DENV-2 cases during this Burkina Faso 2017 outbreak.
</p>
