<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Based on published data, SARS-CoV-2 infection seems to affect children less frequently and less severely than adults. According to the data published from different regions, the proportion of children among COVID-19 patients was quite low (2.1 – 2.4% in China, 1.3% in Italy, 2.8% in Australia, and 7.0% in Korea) [
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. In the largest pediatric study to date that analyzed 2,143 children infected with SARS-CoV-2, 5.8% children showed severe and critical illness [
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Contrary to the pediatric study, 18.5% patients were severe and critical among all age groups in an analysis of 44,672 Chinese cases with COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Among children, Dong 
 <italic>et al</italic>. found that infants were relatively more vulnerable to SARS-CoV-2 infection, and the proportion of severe and critical cases was 10.7% [
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. However, because the study also included suspected cases (not laboratory confirmed cases, 65.9% of study population), the possibility of pathogens other than SARS-CoV-2 responsible for such clinical observations remains controversial. In other studies, even though very small number of cases was reported, a severe outcome in infants was not observed [
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Although these findings were not similar to the generally accepted fact that children aged &lt;5 years were more vulnerable to respiratory viral infections, there was a common aspect with the previous finding observed in SARS-CoV and Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV) epidemics, which also had a children-sparing pattern [
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Stockman 
 <italic>et al</italic>. reported that the clinical outcome of SARS was more favorable in children aged &lt;12 years of age than in other age groups [
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. No deaths were reported in children with SARS-CoV infection [
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. In the MERS-CoV epidemic, only two pediatric deaths were reported, both of which had serious comorbidities: infantile nephrotic syndrome and cystic fibrosis [
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>].
</p>
