<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0025">Pharmacists need to be engaged in the coordinated efforts during pandemics, and be readily adaptive to changes required in pharmacy practice. As FIP advocated, “
 <italic>community pharmacies in outbreak-affected and unaffected countries are often the first point of contact with the health system for those with health-related concerns or simply in need of information and reliable advice</italic>”.
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>11</sup>
 </xref> Hence, it is important to explore how pharmacists around the world are managing their customary and newly emerging roles during the COVID-19 outbreak. From Macau, China, home of the outbreak, it was documented, from the perspective of the authors, that pharmacists had roles in ensuring the stable supply of key medicines, providing information about the coronavirus infection, performing early detection of cases and appropriate referral, and implementing government arrangement such as the 
 <italic>Guaranteed Mask Supply Scheme</italic>.
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>10</sup>
 </xref> Another study from China acknowledged that community pharmacy management teams shall support different services by providing adequate supply of COVID-19 related medications and preventative products, in addition to providing sufficient staff trainings.
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>12</sup>
 </xref> From Colombia, community pharmacists were proposed to contribute to the early detection and appropriate referral of possible cases of the virus, then to be reported through designated telephone lines in addition to providing patient education.
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>13</sup>
 </xref> From the United Arab Emirates (UAE), it was stated that pharmacists can also play a role in promoting an empathy culture to help in preventing the stigmatization of infected individuals based on ethnicity, population or nationality, and by broadcasting facts in their communities via various media.
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref> It is expected that pharmacists around the world are finding their ways to contribute to the collaborative forces in combating the spread of the virus. But for pharmacists to assume a role in humanitarian and health emergency settings, the application of real-world data,
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>10</sup>
 </xref> in addition to the provision of tailored training programs, taking into consideration all aspects, including the psychological impact of such roles, are vital.
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>15</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref> Published research so far provide reference for pharmacists on providing patient care services to improve patient's outcomes and make a contribution to the control of the pandemic. No previous study has looked into pharmacists' own perspective of their role in the management of the coronavirus pandemic, their awareness of important facts needed to be able to deliver their roles successfully, and the source of such facts.
</p>
