<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The Synthesis Project database was built through systematic reviews for HCV measures across MENA.
 <xref rid="hep41491-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="hep41491-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="hep41491-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="hep41491-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="hep41491-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="hep41491-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="hep41491-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="hep41491-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="hep41491-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">21</xref> These studies followed a standardized methodology, which can be found in each of these systematic reviews in more detail.
 <xref rid="hep41491-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="hep41491-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="hep41491-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="hep41491-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="hep41491-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="hep41491-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="hep41491-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="hep41491-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="hep41491-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">21</xref> Briefly, the methodology was developed as informed by the Cochrane Collaboration Handbook,
 <xref rid="hep41491-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">22</xref> and the findings were reported per the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta‐Analyses (PRISMA) guidelines.
 <xref rid="hep41491-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">23</xref> Literature searches were performed in international databases (PubMed and Embase), national/regional databases (WHO Index Medicus for the Eastern Mediterranean Region database, Iraqi Academic Scientific Journals database, Iran’s Scientific Information database, among others), MENA HIV/AIDS Epidemiology Synthesis Project database,
 <xref rid="hep41491-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="hep41491-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">25</xref> abstract archives of international conferences, and gray literature comprised of public health reports and routine data reporting. The literature searches used broad search criteria with no language restrictions in order to include all publications reporting HCV measures since 1989, the year in which the virus was discovered.
 <xref rid="hep41491-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">26</xref>
</p>
