<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This study involving a large sample of community-recruited HIV negative and HIV positive MSM in NYC found an overall HCV seroprevalence of 2.8%. The community-recruited sample had a low prevalence of individuals who reported injecting drugs ever in the past of 5.2%, although they did report sexual risk behaviors that would place them at risk for sexual transmission of HCV, with 14.2% of the MSM reporting any condomless insertive anal sex and 16.8% reporting any condomless receptive anal sex with a male partner in the last 3 months. We found a higher HCV prevalence among HIV-positive MSM compared to HIV-negative MSM (8.1% vs. 1.5%, respectively, p = &lt;0.001), consistent with previously published data showing higher rates of HCV infection among HIV-infected compared to uninfected MSM[
 <xref rid="pone.0200269.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0200269.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0200269.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Of the 29 men who were HCV antibody-positive in our study, only 12 or 41% were HCV RNA-positive, indicating chronic hepatitis C infection. Our HCV seroprevalence of 8.1% (17/209) among HIV-infected MSM is lower than what has been reported in the literature for NYC. In one study, the proportion of HCV infections among HIV-infected individuals in NYC who are MSM dramatically increased from 7% in 2000 to 24% in 2010[
 <xref rid="pone.0200269.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. In another NYC study from 1999–2007, 10.5% of HCV and HIV co-infected individuals were found to be non-IDU MSM; this study had an older sample of individuals with mean age of 50.4 years[
 <xref rid="pone.0200269.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. These rates are markedly higher than those reported in other U.S. cities, including San Francisco where HCV prevalence among non-IDU HIV-positive MSM decreased from 9% in 2004 to 2% in 2011[
 <xref rid="pone.0200269.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0200269.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>].
</p>
