<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0060">Furin belonging to the family of proprotein convertases, an enzyme that is responsible for activating precursor proteins like hormones, growth factors, cell surface receptors 
 <xref rid="b0240" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>. Furin selectively cleaves the proteins at multi-basic motifs of the sequence R-X-K/R-R↓ 
 <xref rid="b0245" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. Furin is also known to activate fusion proteins of viruses like Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), Ebola, highly pathogenic avian influenza A virus (HPAIV) as well as human coronaviruses like MERS and HCoV-OC43 
 <xref rid="b0245" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0250" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0255" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0260" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>. However, no such activation is reported for SARS-CoV. Recently, the genetic sequence analysis of SARS-CoV-2 S protein identified a polybasic cleavage site that may be accessible for proteases like furin, making it distinct from SARS-CoV 
 <xref rid="b0265" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0270" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0275" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>. Four amino acid sequence (RRAR) was found to be present in the S1/S2 site of SARS-CoV-2 S protein, thus corresponding to a canonical furin cleavage site. Hence, furin can also prime SARS-CoV-2 S proteins and aid in the entry of the virus. Bestle et al. and others demonstrated that furin activates SARS-CoV-2 S protein 
 <xref rid="b0280" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>. Furin was shown to cleave the S1/S2 site in the S protein of SARS-CoV-2 in HEK293 cells, which was decreased in the presence of furin inhibitor MI-1851 (
 <xref rid="f0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> ). They also demonstrated that TMPRSS2 cleaves the S2′ site of SARS-CoV-2 S protein. Inhibition of either of these enzymes was shown to inhibit the replication of the virus in Calu-3 cells while inhibition of cathepsin L did not have any effect on the replication indicating that furin and TMPRRS2 are required for S protein activation while cathepsin L may or may not have a role in the activation of S protein in Calu-3 cells 
 <xref rid="b0280" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>. Thus, furin is essential for the multiplication of SARS-CoV-2 in airway epithelial cells and hence provides a favorable target of further exploration.
</p>
