<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par77">Tachyplesin is a 17 amino acid cationic β-sheet peptide that was originally identified in the hemocytes of 
 <italic>Tachypleustridentatus</italic> (Horseshoe crab) and was demonstrated to have broad spectrum antimicrobial activity (Nakamura et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">1988</xref>). Polyphemusin I is a 18 amino acid peptide identified in the hemocytes of the American horseshoe crab, 
 <italic>Limulus polyphemus</italic>. Both peptides are thought to play a key role in the innate immune system of the crab, and have been shown to have potent LPS binding and neutralization activity (Nakamura et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">1988</xref>; Powers et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">2006</xref>). The antiviral activity of Tachyplesin against HIV was investigated by Morimoto et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">1991</xref>) who showed that the peptide could reduce virus-mediated cytopathic effects by more than 70 % in in vitro models (Morimoto et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">1991</xref>). The peptide also reduced the infectivity of the virus, an effect that was shown to be independent on the reverse transcriptase activity of HIV. Interestingly, subsequent studies by Nakashima et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">1992</xref>), Murakami et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">1997</xref>) and Xu et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR149">1999</xref>) characterized the activities of the isopeptideT22 (Tyr
 <sup>5,12</sup>, Lys
 <sup>7</sup>-polyphemusin II), and synthetic analogues against HIV, and determined that the antiviral activity was due to ability of the peptide to bind to CXCR4 (Xu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR149">1999</xref>; Murakami et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">1997</xref>; Nakashima et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">1992</xref>). CXCR4 is a chemokine receptor used by T-cell tropic strains of HIV to infect host cells. Thus, the host cell mediated mechanism of action of these peptides against HIV contrasts to the direct antiviral activity exhibited by other CHDP.
</p>
