<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In general, protein and peptide drugs are safer for humans than small-molecule chemical drugs because these big molecules do not enter the host cells, thus having no adverse effect on the functions of intracellular proteins. However, the effect of long-term use of PPVIs, especially those mimicking human proteins, such as the CD4 receptor, on the normal function of human body are still unknown, since many of these drug candidates have not been tested in clinics. To solve this problem, maybe we can design binding analogs of human proteins, like CD4M9 (
 <xref rid="B147" ref-type="bibr">Vita et al., 1999</xref>), or only select the core domain of natural structures, like mD1.22 mentioned above (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2014</xref>). Another potential problem is the immunogenicity of the protein- and peptide-based inactivators. After long-term use in humans, these exogenous proteins and peptides may induce specific antibodies against them, which may attenuate their inactivation activities. Therefore, immunogenicity of these drug candidates to humans should be assessed and reduced before further development. In recent years, strategies to remove the immunogenicity of the protein-based drug candidates are increasingly diverse and mature. In fact, they mainly focus on the T-cell epitope of the candidate, since T cell plays a key role in activating B cells to transform into antibody-producing plasma cells (
 <xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr">Moise et al., 2016</xref>) and the linear T-cell epitope is more prone to predict than the steric B-cell epitope. One method adopted widely is to calculate the T-cell epitope with a forecasting software, such as Epimatrix developed by EpiVax Inc. (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">De Groot et al., 2008</xref>), validate the T-cell epitope with experiments (such as T-cell proliferation assay) and mutate its amino-acid sequence to remove the immunogenicity (
 <xref rid="B150" ref-type="bibr">Weber et al., 2009</xref>).
</p>
