<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par54">Despites the challenges cause by microbial biofilms formation and antibiotic resistance generation, Gram-negative bacteria possess outer membranes as a highly impermeable barrier as well as additional defense mechanisms no detect in Gram-positive bacteria (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR153">153</xref>). Considering these drawbacks, González 
 <italic>et al</italic> . (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119">119</xref>) developed nanoantibiotics based on levofloxacin (LEVO)-loaded MSNs covalently modified with third-generation poly(propyleneimine) dendrimer (G3), which has high affinity to negatively charged bacteria cell walls. Beyond that, LEVO-loaded [3-(2-aminoethylamino) propyl]trimethoxysilane (labeled DAMO)-modified MSNs (noted LEVO@MSNs-DAMO) were also fabricated to evaluate antimicrobial action against Gram-negative bacteria. Spherical-shaped MSNs with 2D hexagonal mesoporous arrangement were prepared, showing average diameter and pores size of 150 and 2.4 nm, respectively. In addition, negatively charged bare MSNs (-36.4 mV) after modification become positively charged achieving zeta potential around +31.8-37.4 mV, which make them enable to interact with negatively charged bacteria walls. LEVO loading amount up to 7.8% were detected for the nanovehicles. LEVO release performance (PBS pH 7.4) were evaluated exhibiting a first-order kinetics for all nanosystems (LEVO@MSNs, LEVO@MSNs-DAMO and LEVO@MSNs-G3), with 100% of LEVO release over 72 h for LEVO@MSNs-G3. LEVO@MSNs showed lower release values indicating strong interaction via hydrogen bonding between LEVO zwitterionic form (at pH 7.4) and Si-OH groups from MSNs. 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> internalization assays confirmed good MSNs-DAMO and MSNs-G3 internalization due to their positive charge density making electrostatic interactions with 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> cells walls possible. Additionally, MSNs-G3 displayed higher internalization than MSNs-DAMO, ascribed to the MSNs-G3 high surface flexibility and high interaction points with negatively charged 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> phospholipid membranes regarding MSNs-DAMO. These results corroborated antimicrobial assays against 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> biofilms showing the MSNs-G3 with higher and remarkable antimicrobial efficacy relating to the other nanosystems. These findings demonstrated that the synergistic combination of bacterial internalization and antimicrobial agents into MSNs-based nanovehicles lead to interesting and efficient antibiotics for infections treatment.
</p>
