<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par57">Zink group (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118">118</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125">125</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132">132</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR135">135</xref>) have designed stimuli-responsive controlled drug delivery MSNs-based nanoplatforms to treat infectious diseases such as caused by 
 <italic>Francisella tularensis</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125">125</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR130">130</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR134">134</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR135">135</xref>) and 
 <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118">118</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132">132</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR133">133</xref>). From one of these works (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR135">135</xref>), authors developed a pathogen-specific detection and drug delivery nanoplatform based on MSNs modified with silane groups attached with lipopolisaccharide chain of 
 <italic>F. tularensis</italic> live vaccine strain (Ft-LVS-LPS) as stalks (modified antigen) that interact with FB11 anti-O-antigen antibody (FB11) nanovalve as a capping agent to block the mesopores avoiding drug diffusion without specific stimulus. By manipulation of the non-covalently interaction MSNs modified antigen (Ft-LVS-LPS)-antibody (FB11), the antigen produced by the target bacteria can compete effectively for binding to the gatekeeper antibody, reducing stalk-nanovalve interaction, leading to displacement of the antibody, pore uncapping and finally cargo release. Model drugs such as fluorescein or Hoechst 33342 were used to evaluate the nanoplatform specificity and action. Spherical MSNs with high surface area (840 m
 <sup>2</sup> g
 <sup>-1</sup>), surface charge of +36 mV and average diameter and pores size of 117 and 3.8 nm, respectively, were prepared as nanoplatform. The specific antigen-antibody modification was successfully confirmed by immunostaining assay showing no nonspecific binding of the FB11 antibody to the unfunctionalized MSN surface and also no nonspecific binding of the fluorescent secondary goat-antimouse (GAM) immunostaining antibody to the unfunctionalized MSN surface or the Ft-LVS-LPS. Authors also evaluated whether a competitive FB11 antibodies displacement could be achieved in the presence of Ft-LVS-LPS. From immunostaining assays, by using both types of silane groups (APTES and ICPTES) as stalks to interact with the modified antigen, successful displacement of FB11 antibodies from the MSN surface in the presence of Ft-LVS bacteria can be confirmed 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> indicating that the operation of the nanovalve is feasible at high bacterial concentration. In addition, the reduction of the FB11 antibody affinity to the LPS-modified MSNs surface was achieved by acetylation of LPS-modified MSNs reducing the OH groups available for hydrogen-bonding with FB11, requiring lower Ft bacterial concentrations to displace FB11 antibody from the nanoplatform. From cargo release studies, authors reported that the use of LPS from a Ft 
 <italic>wzy</italic> deletion mutant can promote better mesopores capping avoiding any cargo leakage before reach the target site. Beyond that, from this highly specific nature of the antibody-antigen interaction, a significant cargo release was detected only in Ft-LVS-LPS presence. These results suggested that the pathogen-sensitive controlled cargo release nanoplatforms can be also applied to other gram-negative bacteria as novel theranostic smart MSNs-based nanosystem for infectious diseases treatment.
</p>
