<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par46">Regarding bacterial biofilms infections and resistance, Vallet-Regí group (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111">111</xref>) developed a smart nanocarrier based on antibiotic levofloxacin (LEVO)-loaded MSNs decorated with the lectin concanavalin A (ConA), as displayed in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>. ConA was used to aggregate specificity to the nanosystem promoting better internalization into biofilm and then antimicrobial activity. MCM-41-like MSNs with spherical shape of 150 nm in size and hexagonal pores channels structure were fabricated. 
 <italic>In vitro</italic> release tests displayed that bare MSNs retained drug release achieving up to 30% after 48 h. This can be attributed to the hydrogen bonding interaction between MSNs Si-OH groups and LEVO zwitterionic form. On the other hand, MSN
 <sub>ConA</sub> promoted total LEVO release up to 5 days, assigned to the interaction of ConA protein on MSNs surface with LEVO that leads to its fast release from the mesopores. The nanoantibiotic (labeled MSN
 <sub>ConA</sub>@LEVO) targeting effect was successfully evaluated in 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> biofim exhibiting a dose dependent internalization, that means the greater is the MSN
 <sub>ConA</sub>@LEVO concentration, the higher is the nanosystem penetration. The nanoplatform with negatively charged surface (potential zeta of -25 mV) promoted high electrostatic affinity toward the biofilm polysaccharide. Antimicrobial 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> assays were performed in three distinct MSN
 <sub>ConA</sub>@LEVO concentrations (5, 10 and 20 μg mL
 <sup>-1</sup>). Results confirm high internalization process displaying high antimicrobial efficacy values from 97 to 100%. Beyond that, cytotoxicity assays showed MSN
 <sub>ConA</sub>@LEVO were nontoxic up to 50 μg mL
 <sup>-1</sup> enabling these smart nanocarriers for further clinical translations.
</p>
