<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par49">Infected bone defects often cause limited blood circulation in the infected sites resulting in poor ability to self-heal for restoring the structure and function of bone tissue. Take this into account, the development of bone implants based on specific and antibiotic controlled delivery systems is essential for an effective bone infection treatment. Zhou 
 <italic>et al</italic> . (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114">114</xref>) designed scaffolds based on MSNs containing vancomycin (VAN) into mesopores channels dispersed in gelatinous matrix. In addition to control drug release, MSNs incorporated into polymer scaffolds can increase their mechanical properties, enhancing cell adhesion, proliferation and osteogenic osteoblasts differentiation. In this context, spherical MSNs were successfully prepared with average size and pores diameter of 210 and 2.4 nm, respectively. 
 <italic>In vitro</italic> VAN release was investigated for VAN@gelatin and VAN@MSNs/gelatin. While VAN@gelatin displayed an initial burst release (up to 45% in the first day), VAN@MSNs/gelatin presented an initial release of 19% (first day) and about 78% over 28 days, suggesting a sustained VAN release. From 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> antibacterial (
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>) assays, both composite systems showed antibacterial activity dose-dependent with 95% of growth inhibition at 60 μg mL
 <sup>-1</sup>. Additionally, cytocompatibility tests were carried out presenting good spreadability and proliferation of bone mesenchymal stem cells (BMSCs) in the evaluated scaffolds. Osteogenic differentiation tests suggested that the incorporation of MSNs facilitated the osteogenic differentiation of BMSCs and VAN-loaded into mesopores had no negative effects on its bioactivity. 
 <italic>In vivo</italic> tests were established by bone infection induced in rabbits and the implantation of gelatin and MSNs/gelation were evaluated. High leukocytes levels were detected after 8 weeks of treatment for both samples. On the other hand, the implantation of VAN@MSNs/gelatin depicted the leukocyte concentration decreased significantly and reached a normal level after 4 weeks of treatment. The excellent result indicates that MSNs promoted a controlled VAN release at the specific site. Authors concluded that the composite scaffolds based on MSNs as nanocarriers leaded to slow and prolonged VAN release inhibiting local infection 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> and, consequently, bone regeneration, constituting a promising tool for infected bone defects therapy.
</p>
