<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="ijerph-11-03894-t002" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="pii">ijerph-11-03894-t002_Table 2</object-id>
 <label>Table 2</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Surveillance systems, tracking tools, communication systems, information exchange and outputs within Europe.</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="rows" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surveillance Organisation /System/Tool</th>
    <th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type</th>
    <th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Purpose</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ECDC Epidemic Intelligence Information System (EPIS)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Event based threat tracking</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EPIS is a secure communication platform tool, provided and coordinated by ECDC, that allows risk assessment bodies in the different European Members states (EUMS) to exchange non-structured and semi-structured information on current or emerging EU public health threats. It coordinates and shares surveillance and control work among national public health institutes to facilitate outbreak discovery. In public health crises, it allows epidemiological discussion among health institutes of the various Member States as well as political coordination based upon scientific conclusions). There are currently five different modules based on: Antibiotic Resistance and Hospital Acquired Infection (EPIS AMR-HAI), Sexually Transmitted Infections (EPIS STI), Food and Waterborne Diseases (EPIS FWD), 
     <italic>Legionella</italic> Infections (EPIS ELDSNet) and Vaccine Preventable Diseases (EPIS VPD) [
     <xref rid="B28-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. 
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ECDC Threat Tracking Tool (TTT)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Event based threat tracking</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Event-based surveillance information is collected through epidemic intelligence activities on a daily basis, including a 24/7 duty system. Data are collected in an unstructured way and are studied, verified and primarily aimed at the detection of emerging threats. The data is collected in The Threat Tracking Tool (TTT) data base that allows ECDC to keep track of verified events with a known or possible impact on public health. ECDC uses the media, the web (ProMed, GPHIN, MediSys, 
     <italic>etc.</italic>), specific websites (WHO, OIE, FAO, Governments, CDC, PH Institutes, 
     <italic>etc.</italic>) and bulletins (Eurosurveillance, EpiNorth, MMWR 
     <italic>etc.</italic>) for event-based surveillance [
     <xref rid="B28-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European Surveillance System (see associated surveillance reports) (TESSy)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Routine EU surveillance</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TESSy is the European database for collection, management and analysis of data on communicable diseases provided by the ECDC national contact points for surveillance. The system covers all statutory communicable diseases with the appropriate level of details, and follows EU-wide reporting standards, common principles of collaboration and agreements on data exchange, access and publication. Accurate and detailed systems are used to analyse surveillance data, provide trend analysis methods and models to identify subtle trends and low-level clusters or potential outbreaks [
     <xref rid="B29-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. 
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Early Warning and Response System (EWRS)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Event based threat tracking</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EWRS is a restricted network where Member States can alert other countries about serious outbreaks and severe diseases that could have an implication on other EUMS, and co-ordinate their responses. The ECDC Threat Tracking Tool is used to perform joint risk assessments where more than one Member State is affected [
     <xref rid="B30-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ECDC Communicable Disease Threats Report (CDTR)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Event based threat tracking</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The CDTR reports on communicable disease threats of concern to the European Union collated through epidemic intelligence activities are published weekly on the ECDC website [
     <xref rid="B31-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Global Early Warning System (GLEWS)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Event based threat tracking</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GLEWS combines and coordinates the alert and response mechanisms of OIE, FAO and WHO. The aim is to assist in the prediction, prevention and control of animal disease threats, including zoonoses, through information sharing, epidemiological analysis and joint field missions to assess and control the outbreak [
     <xref rid="B32-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ProMED-mail (the Program for Monitoring Emerging Diseases) (ProMed)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Event based threat tracking</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ProMed-mail publishes and transmits information on world-wide outbreaks of infectious diseases and acute exposures to toxins that affect human health, including those in animals and in plants grown for food or animal feed [
     <xref rid="B33-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The Global Public Health Intelligence Network (GPHIN)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Event based threat tracking</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GPHIN is a secure internet-based multilingual early-warning WHO-linked tool that continuously searches global media sources to identify informal information about disease outbreaks and other events of potential international public health concern [
     <xref rid="B34-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medical Information System (MediSys)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Event based threat tracking</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MediSys is a tool initiated by the European Commissions (EC) Directorate General Health and Consumer Affairs (DG SANCO) for the purpose of supporting national and international surveillance networks in their monitoring of health-related issues of public concern, such as outbreaks of communicable diseases, bioterrorism, large-scale chemical incidents, 
     <italic>etc.</italic> [
     <xref rid="B35-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Emergency Prevention System for Transboundary Animal and Plant Pests and Diseases (EMPRES)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Event based threat tracking</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EMPRES is a world-wide FAO programme. The strategy of EMPRES is to prevent and control diseases at source, across the food chain, including the occurrence of new emerging diseases [
     <xref rid="B36-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">International Food Safety Authorities Network (INFOSAN)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Event based threat tracking</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A joint global network initiated by WHO and FAO that aims at rapid exchange of food safety issues, shared information, and provision of help to countries in need. INFOSAN collaborates with several of the other surveillance and response networks and systems [
     <xref rid="B37-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The Global Foodborne Infections Network (GFN)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Event based threat tracking</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GFN is a collaborative project of the WHO and a network of institutions and individuals world-wide with the purpose to detect, control and prevent food-borne and other enteric infections “from farm to fork”, with focus on inter-sectorial collaboration among human health, veterinary and food-related disciplines, and antimicrobial resistance in food-borne pathogens [
     <xref rid="B38-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. 
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The Rapid Alert System for Food and Feed (RASFF)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Event based threat tracking</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RASFF involves EUMS, the EU Commission and EFSA, and provides threat information about food and animal feed that could be a serious risk to human health (both microbiological and chemical threats) [
     <xref rid="B39-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eurosurveillance</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Electronic Journal</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reports weekly on current health threats across Europe [
     <xref rid="B40-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Communicable Disease Control in Northern Europe (EpiNorth)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multi country Surveillance systems</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EpiNorth project provides communicable disease surveillance, control and communication in the Nordic, Baltic countries and NW Russia. This includes case and outbreak surveillance (EpiWatch), news and events (EpiNews), an online journal (EpiNorth Journal), disease notification data (EpiNorthData), vaccination programmes (EpiVax), educational and training (EpiTrain) and links within networks (EpiLinks) [
     <xref rid="B41-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Communicable Disease Control in The Mediterranean and the Balkans (EpiSouthNetwork)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multi country Surveillance systems</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EpiSouth Network aims at creating a framework of collaboration on epidemiological issues in order to improve communicable diseases surveillance and for enhancing communicable diseases surveillance and control of public health risks in South-East Europe, North Africa and the Middle-East [
     <xref rid="B42-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Morbidity &amp; Mortality Weekly Report (MMWR)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Electronic Journal</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reports weekly on current health threats in the US and other parts of the World [
     <xref rid="B43-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO Centralized Information System for Infectious Diseases (CISID)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">International surveillance</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CISID is WHO/Europe’s main surveillance platform with information on communicable diseases, immunization coverage, and on recent outbreaks in Europe. It allows detailed reviews and assessments of infectious diseases in the WHO European Region and includes some subnational level data [
     <xref rid="B44-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The European Health for All Database (WHO-HFA-DB)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">International surveillance</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO/Europe’s prime data source for international comparisons [
     <xref rid="B45-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. 
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The Mortality database (WHO-MDB)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">International surveillance</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO data allows age- and sex-specific analysis of mortality trends by broad disease-groups, as well as disaggregated to specific causes of death dated back to 1980 [
     <xref rid="B46-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The European Detailed Mortality Database (WHO-DMDB)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">International surveillance</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Provides mortality data by three-digit codes of the International Classification of Diseases, disaggregated by five-year age groups, back to 1990 [
     <xref rid="B47-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European Hospital Morbidity Database (WHO-HMDB)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">International surveillance</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO data provides tools for the analysis and international comparison of morbidity and hospital activity patterns, based on hospital-discharge data by diagnosis, age and sex, back to 1999 [
     <xref rid="B48-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFSA-EU-wide baseline surveys</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Food survey</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The European Commission has organised baseline surveys on the occurrence of zoonotic agents in food and in various animal populations in the EU. EFSA is responsible for analysing and publishing the results of these surveys that will provide a knowledgebase for example for further considerations on specific control measures [
     <xref rid="B49-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EUMS disease surveillance systems</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National surveillance systems</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Individual enhanced surveillance systems are organized for a number of key pathogens. For example a system of sentinel Dengue surveillance has been implemented in the Mediterranean region to monitor the emergence of autochthonous transmission.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Animal Disease Notification System (ADNS)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Animal surveillance</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Animal diseases that EUMS are obliged to report are established through several pieces of legislation and are the responsibility of OIE (World organisation for animal health) and EU. Outbreak reports are sent by EUMS to the European Commission via the Animal Disease Notification System (ADNS) [
     <xref rid="B50-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">World Animal Health Information System (WAHIS)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Animal based threat tracking</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WAHIS processes data on animal diseases in real-time and then informs the international community. WAHIS consists of an early-warning system and a monitoring system that monitors OIE listed animal diseases [
     <xref rid="B23-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">World Animal Health Information Database (WAHID interface)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Animal infectious disease surveillance</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WAHID provides access to all data held within OIE’s World Animal Health Information System (WAHIS) [
     <xref rid="B51-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Global Information and Early Warning System on food and agriculture (GIEWS)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Food based event threat tracking</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GIEWS exchanges and analyses information about food production and security with other organizations, such as UN, governments, regional organizations, NGOs 
     <italic>etc.</italic> and gets regular information from other early warning systems [
     <xref rid="B52-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">World Health Organization surveillance (WHO)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Worldwide disease surveillance</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A portal to health statistics and detailed monitoring and assessment tools for key areas of health policy [
     <xref rid="B53-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triple S Project (SSS)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syndromic surveillance</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Started in Sep 2010 and co-financed by the European Commission SSS provides scientific and technical guidance for developing and implementing both human and animal syndromic surveillance systems, and produces an inventory of existing and proposed syndromic surveillance systems in Europe [
     <xref rid="B54-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Global Alert and Response (WHO-GAR)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outbreak alert and response</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAR is a global alert and response system for epidemics and other public health threats managed by WHO that helps EUMS to enhance epidemic preparedness, early warning alert and response [
     <xref rid="B55-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Global Outbreak Alert and Response Network (GOARN)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outbreak alert and response</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO coordinates international outbreak technical response responses using resources from the Global Outbreak Alert and Response Network (GOARN) which was established in 2000 with the objectives of combating the international spread of outbreaks, ensuring that appropriate technical assistance reaches affected states rapidly and contributing to long-term epidemic preparedness and capacity building [
     <xref rid="B56-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European Surveillance of Antimicrobial Consumption Network (ECDC ESAC-Net)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug consumption database</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pharmacies keep records of drugs sold both with and without prescription. ESAC-Net was established to provide representative national antimicrobial consumption data since 1997, which is useful for monitoring antimicrobial resistance across EUMS [
     <xref rid="B57-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Network of medical entomologists and public health experts (Vbornet)</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vector borne disease surveillance</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Produces distribution maps of the major arthropod disease vectors and related surveillance activities and defines priority strategic topics concerning the public health perspective of vector-borne diseases and vector surveillance [
     <xref rid="B58-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European Union Summary Report on Trends and Sources of Zoonoses, Zoonotic Agents and Food-borne outbreaks in the European Union.</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Report</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mandatory annual reporting currently involves eight zoonoses (brucellosis, campylobacteriosis, echinococcosis, listeriosis, salmonellosis, trichinellosis, tuberculosis (Mycobacterium bovis), Verotoxigenic Escherichia coli). Additional zoonoses and zoonotic agents may also be reported. Reports of suspected international outbreaks are collected, and analysed by EFSA and ECDC and presented annually in the EFSA Journal [
     <xref rid="B59-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National telephone Help lines</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syndromic surveillance</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Several countries use telephone help lines as an indirect indicator tool to detect outbreaks. This allows some large outbreaks of respiratory and enteric infections to be detected before sentinel and laboratory surveillance pick up the signal.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HealthMap</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Event based threat tracking</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Utilizes online informal sources for global disease outbreak monitoring and real-time surveillance of emerging public health threats. Media reports are incorporated and HealthMap is one of the main information sources for Epidemic Intelligence [
     <xref rid="B60-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Global Atlas of Diseases</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interactive disease mapping</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO’s Communicable Disease Global Atlas uses standardized WHO data and statistics for infectious diseases at country, regional, and global levels [
     <xref rid="B61-ijerph-11-03894" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug sales</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surrogate surveillance</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drugs sold at pharmacies have been examined as sentinels for several food- and water-borne diseases which can give mild gastro-intestinal symptoms but may cause large undetected outbreaks, even if a large proportion of the population is affected.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physician visits</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syndromic surveillance</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monitoring emergency department visits and patient visits to general practitioners are often used to detect outbreaks or increased risk of disease. Such information is available several days before results of microbiological sampling from patients. Monitoring increases in the occurrence of specific syndromes like gastrointestinal or lower respiratory symptoms are also possible.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sickness records</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syndromic surveillance</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monitoring increased absence from work, schools and day care centres can be a tool for early detection of food- and water-borne outbreaks, influenza and lower respiratory infections.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ambulance records</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syndromic surveillance</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EUMS using rapid computerized reporting systems that monitor ambulance records can provide early information of increases in the occurrence of diseases/symptoms such as respiratory, gastrointestinal and influenza outbreaks.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Telephone surveys</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syndromic surveillance</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">In some EUMS Health Authorities contact people to elicit specific symptoms in order to detect the initiation of seasonal influenza increases.</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
