<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The induction of P-gp in peripheral organs and brain microvessel endothelial cells appears to be mediated through the activation of the nuclear pregnane X (PXR) and constitutive androstane (CAR) receptors [
 <xref rid="B55-pharmaceutics-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-pharmaceutics-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-pharmaceutics-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="B58-pharmaceutics-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="B59-pharmaceutics-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-pharmaceutics-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. In particular, the human receptors hPXR and hCAR appear actively involved in the regulation of P-gp expression in the human brain microvessel endothelial cell culture system [
 <xref rid="B61-pharmaceutics-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. A few PIs, such as ritonavir, amprenavir, and lopinavir, are known to be hPXR ligands or activators [
 <xref rid="B62-pharmaceutics-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-pharmaceutics-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Recently, in vitro studies performed on human brain microvessels endothelial cells hCMEC/D3 demonstrated that amprenavir, atazanavir, efavirenz, ritonavir, and lopinavir activate hPXR, whereas abacavir, efavirenz, and nepvirapine activate hCAR. Moreover, these drugs appear to be able to increase P-gp expression in hCMEC/D3 cells [
 <xref rid="B64-pharmaceutics-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. In other words, a great number of PIs are hPXR ligands: abacavir and nevirapine are hCAR ligands, and efavirenz is a ligand of both PXR and hCAR. These data suggest that the nuclear receptor activity of these ligands can further restrict their ability to enter the brain, being able to increase P-gp expression at the BBB level. Taking these aspects into account, it has been suggested that the targeted suppression of P-gp expression in the HIV-1-infected reservoirs of the body may constitute a new strategy able to inhibit antiretroviral drug efflux from the brain [
 <xref rid="B51-pharmaceutics-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>].
</p>
