<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11">The magnitude, sudden onset and severe clinical manifestations of ZIKV epidemics highlight the need for safe and effective vaccines for key patient populations including pregnant women. While effective live attenuated vaccines have been developed for several flaviviruses, they are contraindicated in pregnant women. Live vaccines typically are ineffective during the first year of life because maternal antibodies interfere with vaccine replication. It has been difficult to formulate tetravalent live attenuated DENV vaccines that stimulate balanced and effective responses to each serotype because of differential replication of vaccine virus components. Subunit vaccines may address some of these challenges, but progress has been slow and subunit vaccines have not performed well in non-human primate models
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup>. Our studies offer a potential explanation for the poor performance of subunit vaccines and a strategy for developing more effective flavivirus vaccines. Our results demonstrate that a critical aspect of rE antigen design is to develop E proteins that display complex quaternary epitopes that recapitulate antigen presentation on the surface of infectious virus particles. Here we demonstrate that ZIKV rE
 <sup>M</sup> and rE
 <sup>D</sup> subunit antigens induce antibody responses that differ in functionality and domain focus. ZIKV rE monomers stimulated an EDIII biased, poorly neutralizing IgG response. In contrast, ZIKV rE dimers induced strongly neutralizing and protective antibodies that also blocked the binding of strongly neutralizing human mAbs to quaternary epitopes on ZIKV. While finer mapping studies are required to comprehensively map the specificity of rE
 <sup>D</sup> stimulated antibodies, our studies suggest that by designing the E protein to be a stable homodimer, it is possible to induce strongly neutralizing and protective antibodies that mimic properties of protective antibodies induced by natural infection. It is possible that inactivated whole virus or virus-like particle (VLP) vaccines will also stimulate antibodies to quaternary structure epitopes. An advantage to using rE
 <sup>D</sup>-protein subunits over inactivated virion or VLP vaccines is the absence or prM protein in subunit vaccine but not virus or VLP vaccines. PrM antibodies are non-neutralizing and some studies suggest that enhance the replication of flaviviruses
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup>. Additional studies are needed to compare the immunogenicity, efficacy and safety of ZIKV rE-dimer, inactivated virus and VLP vaccines. The strategy we describe here for ZIKV E protein may also be applicable for developing subunit vaccines against other medically significant flaviviruses.
</p>
