<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0135">Among the acute neurological complications of SARS-CoV-2 worth mentioning is stroke, whose prevalence is highly increased in COVID-19 just as it was in SARS (
 <xref rid="bb0760" ref-type="bibr">Umapathi et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0755" ref-type="bibr">Tsai et al., 2005</xref>). In a retrospective series (
 <xref rid="bb0485" ref-type="bibr">Mao et al., 2020</xref>), stroke occurred in about 5.7% of severely-affected COVID-19 patients, whereas its prevalence was 2.5% among 388 consecutive COVID-19 patients admitted to a University hospital in Milan (
 <xref rid="bb0475" ref-type="bibr">Lodigiani et al., 2020</xref>). Remarkably, stroke in COVID-19 patients may occur at a much younger age than in the general population, often in the absence of classical risk factors (
 <xref rid="bb0585" ref-type="bibr">Oxley et al., 2020</xref>). Many of these COVID-19-related strokes are subcortical or distal cortical, but large vessel occlusions are also observed (
 <xref rid="bb0485" ref-type="bibr">Mao et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0305" ref-type="bibr">Helms et al., 2020a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0310" ref-type="bibr">Helms et al., 2020b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0315" ref-type="bibr">Helms et al., 2020c</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0320" ref-type="bibr">Helms et al., 2020d</xref>). Stroke in COVID-19 patients, which may have a subacute course and a subtle clinical presentation preceded by encephalopathy (
 <xref rid="bb0305" ref-type="bibr">Helms et al., 2020a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0190" ref-type="bibr">Deliwala et al., 2020</xref>) or present as an acute cerebrovascular accident (
 <xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">Avula et al., 2020</xref>), is likely just one of the clinical consequences of the increased thrombotic risk observed in this disease. This trombophilic status depends on multiple factors including immobilization, hypoxia, diffuse endothelial damage and severe coagulopathy, and may either occur in the form of the so called COVID-19-associated coagulopathy (CAC) with increased levels of dimer, fibrin, fibrinogen, or fibrinogen degradation product, or as a classical disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC), with decreased levels of these proteins (
 <xref rid="bb0370" ref-type="bibr">Klok et al., 2020a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0375" ref-type="bibr">Klok et al., 2020b</xref>). In addition, it has also been hypothesized that direct viral infection of brain endothelial cells, where the SARS-CoV-2 receptor ACE2 is expressed, may participate in the neurovascular damage of these patients (
 <xref rid="bb0555" ref-type="bibr">Nath, 2020</xref>). Importantly, in COVID-19 patients, stroke occurs despite pharmacological thromboprophylaxis recommended by the American Society of Hematology (
 <xref rid="bb0385" ref-type="bibr">Kollias et al., 2020</xref>), suggesting that anticoagulation strategies specifically tailored for COVID-19 should be developed.
</p>
