<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This is a fast moving scenario and several Phase 1 clinical trials of COVID vaccines have been published, either with or without peer reviews. Two recombinant adenovirus vaccines expressing the S spike protein of SARS-CoV-2, the Chadox1 and the Cansino vaccines (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>), and two other vaccines composed of mRNA codifying for the S-protein (mRNA1273, Moderna vaccine) (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>) or its RDB domain (mRNA BNT162b1 Pfizer-Biontech vaccine) (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>) have been assayed for safety and immunogenicity in Phase I-II clinical trials in humans. There were no serious adverse events related to any of the four vaccines (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>–
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Local and systemic reactions commonly including pain, feeling feverish, chills, muscle ache, headache, and malaise were recorded for all formulations (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>–
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>) and were reduced, in the case of the Chadox1 vaccine, with use of prophylactic paracetamol (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). Only the Cansino vaccine was given as a single dose (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>) while Chadox1, Moderna, and Pfizer Biontech vaccines were assayed in two-dose protocols (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>–
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Anti-S protein IgG responses rose by day 14 (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>) and peaked or increased by day 21–28, after the first (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>) or second immunization dose, respectively (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>–
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). In addition, spike-specific T-cell responses detected by an 
 <italic>ex-vivo</italic> interferon-γ enzyme-linked immunospot assay, peaked on day 14 for the Chadox1 (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>) and on day 28 for the Cansino adenovirus vaccine (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). Moreover, the Moderna mRNA-1,273 vaccine induced a Th1 response against the S-protein peptide pools (TNF-α &gt;Il-2 &gt;IFN-γ), with a minimal Th2 cytokine expression (IL-4 and IL-13) and with CD8 T-cell responses, only detected at low levels, after the second vaccination (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). In agreement, most participants vaccinated with the Pfizer-Biontech mRNA-RBD vaccine (BNT162b1) also had Th1 skewed T cell immune responses with RBD-specific CD8
 <sup>+</sup> and CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cell expansion and IFN-γ produced by a high fraction of RBD-specific CD8+ and CD4+ T cells (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Furthermore, the levels of neutralizing antibodies raised by each one of the vaccines could be considered as correlates of their potential efficacy. While the mRNA-1273 of Moderna disclosed 50% EC values ranging between 256 and 512 (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>), the maximal titer for the mRNA RBD vaccine of Pfizer-Biontech was 308 (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>) and for the Chadox1 vaccine, from 256 to 512 (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). The Cansino vaccine expresses its results as GMT (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>–
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>) impeding an accurate comparison (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). Unfortunately, the results of Phase I-II clinical trial of the whole virus inactivated vaccine of Sinovac have not yet been published in detail, therefore although the vaccine was tested in the largest number of individuals (
 <italic>n</italic> = 1,166) (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>), a fair comparison of the safety and immunogenicity results is not yet possible. Ultimately, only the results of the Phase III trials will disclose the potential impact of the vaccines on reduction of deaths, clinical cases, and virus particles or viral RNA in nasopharynx and will allow their efficacy and capability to interrupt the epidemic to be evaluated.
</p>
