<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study, we collected 419 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>pneumoniae</italic> isolates in Osaka prefecture between 2011 and 2017, established their 
 <italic>p1</italic> gene type, and identified MR-conferring mutations. Several previous studies reported that the dominant 
 <italic>p1</italic> type of 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>pneumoniae</italic> clinical isolates in Japan was type 1 since 2003 [
 <xref rid="pone.0209938.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0209938.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. This was also true in the large epidemic period in 2011 and 2012 [
 <xref rid="pone.0209938.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0209938.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Our study in Osaka was consistent with these previous reports, showing high prevalence of type 1 isolate between 2011 and 2014 (
 <xref rid="pone.0209938.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). However, after that period, type 2 lineage (type 2 and 2c) isolates increased rapidly and comprised more than half of all isolates in 2015 and 2016 (
 <xref rid="pone.0209938.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Interestingly, in contrast to type 1 isolates that are largely MRMP strains, most of type 2 lineage isolates were MSMP strains (
 <xref rid="pone.0209938.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0209938.g004">Fig 4</xref>). Therefore, the total ratio of MR strains among 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>pneumoniae</italic> isolates in Osaka decreased in 2015 and thereafter (
 <xref rid="pone.0209938.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0209938.g004">Fig 4</xref>). Low prevalence of MR in 
 <italic>p1</italic> type 2 strains has already been reported in 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>pneumoniae</italic> isolates in Yamagata prefecture of northern Japan between 2004 and 2014 [
 <xref rid="pone.0209938.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0209938.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. In addition, a recent epidemiological study of 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>pneumoniae</italic> pneumonia in Japan reported nationwide decrease of MRMP strains after 2013, although 
 <italic>p1</italic> typing was not performed [
 <xref rid="pone.0209938.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In that nationwide report, publication of treatment guidelines for 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>pneumoniae</italic> pneumonia is mentioned as one of the major factors for the decrease of MRMP strains in Japan after 2013. With these guidelines published in 2011, clinicians may have started paying more attention to the appropriate use of macrolides to prevent the spread of MRMP. This may partly explain the decrease of MRMP strains in Japan after 2013. However, as shown in our study in Osaka, we consider that the increase in MSMP strains with 
 <italic>p1</italic> gene type 2 lineages was another major factor for the decrease of MR rate in Japan.
</p>
