<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study, we have identified new type 2 variant 
 <italic>p1</italic> genes designated as type 2f and 2g (GenBank accession nos. LC311244 and LC385984). These type 2 variants partially encompassed type 1 
 <italic>p1</italic> gene sequences derived from the RepMP4 sequence outside the 
 <italic>p1</italic> operon (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0209938.s001">S1 Fig</xref>). New 
 <italic>p1</italic> variant strains may appear spontaneously at a low frequency in the population of 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>pneumoniae</italic> due to shuffling of RepMP sequences mediated by gene conversion-like DNA recombination [
 <xref rid="pone.0209938.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0209938.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0209938.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. However, the fate of new 
 <italic>p1</italic> strains, i.e., whether they become a major subtype or disappear, may depend on natural selection, survival of the fittest, or chance. It is empirically known that 
 <italic>p1</italic> types of isolates do not change easily during repeated passages in laboratory. The stability of 
 <italic>p1</italic> type may be related to the low level of DNA recombination in this bacterium [
 <xref rid="pone.0209938.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0209938.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Therefore, we believe that type 2f and 2g strains isolated in this study were the cause of pneumonia and were not created during culture isolation, although we did not confirm this by direct 
 <italic>p1</italic> typing of clinical specimens. Furthermore, another isolate, M241, displayed no cytadherence activity due to a large deletion in the 
 <italic>p1</italic> operon (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0209938.s002">S2 Fig</xref>). Cytadherence is an essential factor for 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>pneumoniae</italic> pathogenesis, therefore, there is a possibility that M241 was not involved in the disease onset and was selected or emerged during culture isolation. Strain S355 isolated in China (GenBank accession no. CP013829) also had a large deletion similar to that in M241 in the 
 <italic>p1</italic> operon probably due to DNA recombination between RepMP4 sequences, although the phenotype of that strain has not been described [
 <xref rid="pone.0209938.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Spontaneous loss of functional 
 <italic>p1</italic> operon by recombination between RepMP sequences may occur more frequently than generation of new 
 <italic>p1</italic> variants in the population of 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>pneumoniae</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0209938.s002">S2 Fig</xref>).
</p>
