<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par39">This was a cross-sectional study to estimate the prevalence of PDR in adults initiating antiretroviral therapy in China. The method of HIVDR test was used to explore the level of PDR in part of regions in China. The study design was performed according to the 2014 WHO protocol for PDR [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. China has twenty-three provinces, four municipalities, five autonomous regions, and two special administrative regions. HIV infection was originally identified among injected drug users (IDUs) in Yunnan Province, which is located in southwest China, and was subsequently disseminated into IDU populations in Guangxi Zhuang Autonomous Region and Sichuan Province [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. HIV was subsequently disseminated by sexual transmission to populations in China. According to the numbers of newly reported HIV/AIDS in the year 2016 in China [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], the high prevalence regions were recognized when the number in the region was equal to 8000 or more; the moderate prevalence regions were defined when the number ranged from 2500 to 7999; and the low prevalence region refers to where the number was below 2500. This pilot investigation was conducted in high prevalence regions (Yunnan Province which included Dehong Prefecture and Lincang City, Guangxi Zhuang Autonomous Region which included Nanning City and Liuzhou City, Sichuan Province which included Liangshan Prefecture and Neijiang City, Guangdong Province which included Shenzhen City) and moderate prevalence regions (Chongqing Municipality, Guizhou Province, Hunan Province, Beijing Municipality, Jiangsu Province, and Shandong Province). WHO recommended that the number of patients would typically fall within the range of 300–500 during 6 months in a country according to the HIV drug resistance surveillance guideline in 2015 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. According to this guideline, at least 300 patients were recruited in high prevalence regions and moderate prevalence regions.
</p>
