<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par36">A study performed by Leuschner et al. brings a direction in the use of nanotechnology to control the cytokine storm. Cytokine storm is one of the clinical complications of COVID-19. It consists of the exacerbated production of pro-inflammatory cytokines, which leads to dysfunction in multiple organs and rapid clinical deterioration [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR139">139</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR140">140</xref>]. The produced small interfering RNA (siRNA) encapsulated in lipidic nanoparticles are specific for silencing the chemokine receptor CCR2, which inflammatory monocytes depend on to find areas of inflammation. Adequate degradation of CCR2 messenger RNA in monocytes avoids its accumulation in inflammatory sites. In this way, the uncontrolled recruitment of monocytes in inflammatory processes was solved, with promising results obtained in mice [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR141">141</xref>]. It is already known that some commercially available medicines, such as tocilizumab and C
 <sub>1</sub> esterase inhibitor, have shown positive results in the control of cytokine storm; however, these are very expensive drugs, and their production is not easily scalable. In order to both reduce the treatment costs and streamline the production, Testori suggests the use of plasmids as engineered vectors to produce interleukin (IL)-10 inside cells to contain the inflammatory process [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR142">142</xref>]. Nanoparticles made of polyethylenimine (PEI) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR143">143</xref>], PLGA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR144">144</xref>] PEG-PCL [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR145">145</xref>], PLA-PEG [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR146">146</xref>] and so on have been successfully studied with regard to the systematic delivery of interleukins as immunotherapy for different types of diseases, and these findings could be helpful in the development of efficient nanoparticle therapies for cytokine storm in patients with COVID-19.
</p>
