<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par13">While Southeast Asia has been known as a ZIKV endemic region for more than 60 years, large ZIKV epidemics has only been reported recently [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Although the virus has been first isolated from mosquitoes in Malaysia in 1966, the first human cases were only reported in 1977 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. In 2016, a total of 455 cases were confirmed in Singapore [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] and, in Thailand, 386 cases were reported in 29 out of 76 provinces from 2015 to 2017 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. During this period, cases of ZIKV infection were also reported in other Southeast Asia nations including Malaysia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>] and Myanmar [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. In 2016, 3 tourists were confirmed to have ZIKV infection after visiting Vietnam [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. As of June 2019, a total of 265 cases has been reported in Vietnam, most of which occurred in Ho Chi Minh City [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Additionally, in 2016, a case of Zika-associated microcephaly was reported in the Central Highlands of Vietnam and 5 family members and 2 neighbors were confirmed positive for ZIKV infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Despite the endemicity for dengue and the high density of mosquito vectors, the numbers of cases of ZIKV infection in Vietnam remain substantially lower than the number of cases of dengue. Vietnam lies within the tropical zone where 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> mosquitoes are endemic. While neighboring areas have reported ZIKV outbreaks in recent years, there are limited data available on the extent of ZIKV infection in local populations in Vietnam. Additionally, it has been hypothesized that dengue hyperendemicity may lead to cross-reactive immunity toward ZIKV, thus limiting the size of ZIKV epidemics in Southeast Asia. However, there were limited seroprevalence data to support this hypothesis. Cross-reactivity between ZIKV and DENV antibodies has led to difficulties in the interpretation in some studies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Annually, Vietnam reports approximately 100,000 dengue cases. The incidence of dengue has remained stable over the past few decades in Vietnam [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], and dengue seroprevalence remains high, with up to 64% of the adult population being seropositive [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Recent studies have suggested that while DENV is cross-reactive with ZIKV, the level of cross-neutralization and hence disease protection is limited [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. In Vietnam, the number of ZIKV infections peaked at 219 in 2016, and has subsequently decreased, with only one reported case in 2019 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. The purpose of this study was to determine the seroprevalence of ZIKV antibodies among the population in Vietnam during and after the 2016 Zika epidemic using ZIKV and DENV neutralizing assays to elucidate the extent of the ZIKV epidemic in the local population.
</p>
