<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="pcbi.1007954.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007954.g005</object-id>
 <label>Fig 5</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Probability of Zika emergence across space and time.</title>
  <p>The top figures (A and B) show the seasonal variations in λ
   <sub>
    <italic>I</italic>
    <sup>
     <italic>V</italic>
    </sup>, 
    <italic>E</italic>
    <sup>
     <italic>H</italic>
    </sup>
   </sub>, the transmission rate from humans to the vectors because of the fluctuations the density of vectors in two habitats (this illustrates the effect of 
   <italic>space</italic> on Zika emergence): a minor variation in mean temperature, 29°C (A and C) versus 27°C (B and D), has a massive impact on transmission and, consequently, on pathogen emergence. In C and D we illustrate the effect of the 
   <italic>time</italic> of introduction 
   <italic>t</italic>
   <sub>0</sub> on Zika emergence. The dotted black line refers to the naive expectation for the probability of pathogen emergence at time 
   <italic>t</italic>
   <sub>0</sub> if all the rates were constant and frozen at their 
   <italic>t</italic>
   <sub>0</sub> values (see (
   <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1007954.e014">7</xref>)). The gray shading in B and D refers to the low transmission season where the product of the transmission rates is lower than the product of death rates (see 
   <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1007954.s001">S1 Text</xref>). The exact probability of emergence 
   <italic>p</italic>
   <sub>
    <italic>e</italic>
   </sub>(
   <italic>t</italic>
   <sub>0</sub>
   <italic>T</italic>, 
   <italic>T</italic>) is indicated as a solid black line. Higher seasonality (B and D) increases the discrepancy between the naive expectation and the exact value of the probability of pathogen emergence. This discrepancy is due to the 
   <italic>winter is coming</italic> effect (light gray shading in D). Parameter values are given in table S1 A (model I) of section 3 of 
   <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1007954.s001">S1 Text</xref>.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1007954.g005" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
