<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In some FMD endemic countries, the World Organisation for Animal Health (OIE) has recognized zones within the country (such as Botswana) that are allowed to export livestock on the international market. For these areas, it is highly desirable to understand and model the risks of FMD importation in FMD free zones. This assessment could thereby assist decision-makers during further outbreaks by implementing appropriate measures in due time. Consequently, the application of modelling including epidemic models could be warranted, even in an endemic setting. A valuable modelling study, recently carried out in an endemic country is illustrative and strongly encouraging for the application of models especially in areas where the threat of disease is persistent. Indeed, by catalytic and reverse catalytic models applied to serological data to estimate the force of infection and the rate of waning immunity and to detect periods of sustained transmission, Pomeroy 
 <italic>et al</italic>.,[
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref112" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>] were able to reconstruct the historical burden of FMDV in Cameroon and to quantify control efforts necessary to stop the transmission. Additionally, in recent years, relevant studies demonstrated the feasibility of implementing epidemiological modelling based on simulations in endemic areas in SSA [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref113" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>] as well as in countries where FMD free zones exist, such as in southern Africa [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref114" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref117" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>]. Dynamic models such as SEIR are widely used and have the advantage of simplicity, but some care is needed in their application to FMDV infection, especially in endemic settings. For instance, one of the problems is that the compartments susceptible, exposed, infectious and recovered correspond only imperfectly to the states that can be defined in the field as FMDV can be demonstrated by the detection of virus, the detection of antibodies or by the appearance of clinical signs [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref118" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref119" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]. There is, however, no simple correspondence between these assays and whether or not the host is exposed, infectious or recovered as for example animal may become infectious before the clinical signs appear [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref120" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref121" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>]. Consequently, from our point of view, the catalytic and reverse catalytic models developed by Pomeroy 
 <italic>et al</italic>., [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref112" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>] and applied in FMDV infectious in endemic situation would be interesting for future research on FMD modelling in Africa where the disease remain a serious threat for livestock development.
</p>
