<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Allstars non-targeting, Allstars cell-death and unmodified siRNA oligos targeting the NP, COPA and ATP6AP1 were purchased from Qiagen. Silencer Select siRNA oligos targeting the NXF1, NUP98, ARCN1, PGD and RPS14 genes (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0197246.t002">Table 2</xref>) were purchased from Life Technologies. For short form use in this manuscript, a combination of co-transfected siRNAs is referred to as a “combo”. All siRNA transfections were performed in 96 well plates. For A549 cells, 3000 cells per well diluted in 100μl DMEM complete medium were plated. Twenty-four hours later, 0.2μl Lipofectamine RNAiMAX plus 9.8μl OptiMEM I (Life Technologies) were added to siRNA diluted in 10μl OptiMEM and incubated for 10 minutes at room temperature; complexes were then added to cells. For cells transfected with siRNAs directed at multiple genes, the final concentration of siRNA per host target and the total volume of Lipofectamine RNAiMAX per well were the same as for single gene siRNA transfections. For NHBE cells, 10,000 cells per well diluted in 100μl BEGM were plated, followed 24 hours later by the addition of 20μl transfection complexes as described above. The final concentrations of siRNA to achieve maximal knockdown for single gene and multiple gene targeting were determined in initial optimization experiments using quantitative PCR (data not shown). The final concentration of siRNA was 20nM for unmodified siRNAs and 5nM for silencer select siRNAs with the exception of siNUP98, for which 20nM and 50nM final concentrations were required for A549 and NHBE cells, respectively, to achieve optimal knockdown levels. Cells were incubated at 37 °C and 5% CO2 for 24–48 hours prior to RNA isolation, WST-1 cell viability assays, or virus infection (see below). The siRNA targeting the A/WSN/33 (WSN) nucleoprotein siNP 
 <monospace>5′-AAGGAUCUUAUUUCUUCGGAG-3′</monospace> [
 <xref rid="pone.0197246.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], the non-targeting Allstars siRNA, and cell-death Allstars siRNA were included in all plates as positive and negative controls.
</p>
