<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Detection of viral RNA on infected mosquitoes and mice samples were performed through quantitative real-time PCR (RT-qPCR) using LightCycler® Multiplex RNA Virus Master (Roche), according to the previously published protocol 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>
 </sup>. RNA extractions were performed following manufacturer's protocols. Mosquito samples were processed through the High Pure Viral Nucleic Acid kit (Roche), mice tissue samples (liver, spleen) were extracted with Trizol (Invitrogen), whereas mice lymph node samples were isolated with the QIAamp® Viral RNA kit (Qiagen). Multiplex reactions were performed with primers and probes described in 
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Reactions were performed on a Lightcycler96 real-time PCR machine (Roche) with the following program: first step at 50°C for 10 min for reverse transcription, 95°C for 30 sec for inactivation and initial denaturation and 95°C for 5 sec followed by 60°C for 30 sec for 40 cycles. The reaction volume was 10 μL (5× RT-PCR Reaction Mix (Roche), 200× RT-enzyme solution (Roche), 2.5 μM each primer (IDT) and 2 μM YF (target yellow fever) probe (IDT) and 1 μM WSPTM2 (target 
 <italic>w</italic>Mel-specific) probe and 0.7 μM RPS 17S (target 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> ribosomal S17) probe. For mouse samples, only the YFV probe was used. A fraction (1/20) of the total isolated RNA was used in the reactions. Head and thorax samples from YFV-challenged mosquitoes were analyzed in duplicate through RT-qPCR and viral and 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic> quantification were performed in comparison with serial dilution of a standard curve of the respective genes cloned into the pGEMT plasmid (Promega) 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
  <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, it was possible to calculate the number of copies per tissue. As a mosquito control gene, we used the RPS 17S sequence of 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> (Moreira 2009) 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>
 </sup>. Viable viral loads were quantified by titration assay in permissive Vero cells as described in Costa 
 <italic>et al.,</italic> 2012 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
