<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">Standard assays were carried out to measure the effects of these compounds on the cytotoxicity, virus yield and infection rates of 2019-nCoVs. Firstly, the cytotoxicity of the candidate compounds in Vero E6 cells (ATCC-1586) was determined by the CCK8 assay. Then, Vero E6 cells were infected with nCoV-2019BetaCoV/Wuhan/WIV04/2019
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>
 </sup> at a multiplicity of infection (MOI) of 0.05 in the presence of varying concentrations of the test drugs. DMSO was used in the controls. Efficacies were evaluated by quantification of viral copy numbers in the cell supernatant via quantitative real-time RT-PCR (qRT-PCR) and confirmed with visualization of virus nucleoprotein (NP) expression through immunofluorescence microscopy at 48 h post infection (p.i.) (cytopathic effect was not obvious at this time point of infection). Among the seven tested drugs, high concentrations of three nucleoside analogs including ribavirin (half-maximal effective concentration (EC
 <sub>50</sub>) = 109.50 μM, half-cytotoxic concentration (CC
 <sub>50</sub>) &gt; 400 μM, selectivity index (SI) &gt; 3.65), penciclovir (EC
 <sub>50</sub> = 95.96 μM, CC
 <sub>50</sub> &gt; 400 μM, SI &gt; 4.17) and favipiravir (EC
 <sub>50</sub> = 61.88 μM, CC
 <sub>50</sub> &gt; 400 μM, SI &gt; 6.46) were required to reduce the viral infection (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref> and Supplementary information, Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). However, favipiravir has been shown to be 100% effective in protecting mice against Ebola virus challenge, although its EC
 <sub>50</sub> value in Vero E6 cells was as high as 67 μM,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup> suggesting further in vivo studies are recommended to evaluate this antiviral nucleoside. Nafamostat, a potent inhibitor of MERS-CoV, which prevents membrane fusion, was inhibitive against the 2019-nCoV infection (EC
 <sub>50</sub> = 22.50 μM, CC
 <sub>50</sub> &gt; 100 μM, SI &gt; 4.44). Nitazoxanide, a commercial antiprotozoal agent with an antiviral potential against a broad range of viruses including human and animal coronaviruses, inhibited the 2019-nCoV at a low-micromolar concentration (EC
 <sub>50</sub> = 2.12 μM; CC
 <sub>50</sub> &gt; 35.53 μM; SI &gt; 16.76). Further in vivo evaluation of this drug against 2019-nCoV infection is recommended. Notably, two compounds remdesivir (EC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.77 μM; CC
 <sub>50</sub> &gt; 100 μM; SI &gt; 129.87) and chloroquine (EC
 <sub>50</sub> = 1.13 μM; CC
 <sub>50</sub> &gt; 100 μM, SI &gt; 88.50) potently blocked virus infection at low-micromolar concentration and showed high SI (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a, b</xref>).
</p>
