<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Another HMPV protein that has been studied extensively is the second matrix (M2) protein. The HMPV M2 gene contains two overlapping open reading frames (ORF) that encodes two putative proteins: M2-1 and M2-2 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00505-f001">Figure 1</xref>). The HMPV M2-1 protein is dispensable for viral recovery in in vitro studies [
 <xref rid="B117-viruses-10-00505" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>], compared to its RSV counterpart, which is important for the transcription of the viral genome in vitro [
 <xref rid="B118-viruses-10-00505" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>]. However, the expression of M2-1 appears to be necessary for HMPV replication in vivo [
 <xref rid="B117-viruses-10-00505" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>]. The complexity of the in vivo environment might account for the discrepancy of HMPV replication in the in vitro experiments when using the M2-1 mutant virus. As for M2-2 protein, the replication of M2-2 mutant HMPV was also highly attenuated in challenged hamsters and African green monkeys, and at the same time confers high levels of immunogenicity and protective efficacy [
 <xref rid="B9-viruses-10-00505" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B117-viruses-10-00505" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>,
 <xref rid="B119-viruses-10-00505" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>], thus making it a favorable vaccine candidate that needs further testing. Other studies have shown that the M2-2 viral protein suppresses the host innate immunity. For instance, infection of human airway cells with rHMPVΔM2-2 resulted in a significant increase in IFN-β secretion, compared to infection with its wild type counterpart [
 <xref rid="B111-viruses-10-00505" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]. This outcome is suggested to be as a result of the M2-2 protein targeting the mitochondrial antiviral-signaling protein (MAVS) leading to the blockage of IFN-β transcription [
 <xref rid="B111-viruses-10-00505" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>,
 <xref rid="B112-viruses-10-00505" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>]. Additional data from the same group demonstrated that deletion of the M2-2 ORF protein leads to higher IFN-α, IFN-β, and IFN-γ secretion by human monocyte-derived dendritic cells (moDCs) [
 <xref rid="B120-viruses-10-00505" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>]. They illustrated that the M2-2 protein targets the MyD88 mediated signaling pathway. In contrast to this work, Kitagawa et al. show that the M2-2 protein does not have an inhibitory effect on MyD88-induced NF-κB activation. However, they confirmed that removal of the M2-2 protein upregulates the production of IFN-α by human plasmacytoid dendritic cells (pDCs) via TLR7/9-dependent pathway [
 <xref rid="B113-viruses-10-00505" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00505-f003">Figure 3</xref>).
</p>
