<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Findings from the SARS epidemic provide possible viral-specific mechanisms for ARDS and uncontrolled coagulation. Autopsy studies of patients who died of SARS pneumonia, identified the SARS-CoV spike (S) protein in cells expressing the receptor angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2),
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr84-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>
  <xref rid="bibr85-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr"/>
  <xref rid="bibr86-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr"/>–
  <xref rid="bibr87-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>
 </sup> the leading candidate receptor for SARS-CoV-2.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr88-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr89-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>
 </sup> Binding of the S protein to ACE2 induces expression of a nuclear factor kappa B (NFκB)-driven inflammatory module, resulting in production of proinflammatory cytokines including monocyte chemoattractant protein 1 (MCP-1), transforming growth factor-beta 1 (TGF-β1), tumor necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-α), interleukin (IL)-1β, and IL-6, which have been implicated in thrombogenesis.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr90-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>
 </sup> Although inflammatory responses are important in host-defense, hyperinflammatory responses result in tissue damage, disruption of the endothelial barrier, and uncontrolled activation of coagulation.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr54-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>
 </sup> Overall, these findings are consistent with a model in which SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 directly infect endothelial and epithelial cells, increasing levels of proinflammatory cytokines, causing immune-mediated damage to the vasculature and surrounding tissue, with exposure of tissue factor and associated thromboinflammatory changes.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr91-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>
 </sup> While these changes appear to be predominantly in the lungs, endotheliitis in COVID-19 has been observed in kidneys, liver, heart, and intestine.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr91-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
