<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Cells of the single-layer multi-row cylindrical ciliated epithelium of the respiratory tract are main targets of the influenza virus. For infection, the virus must overcome the factors of non-specific resistance of the organism such as the viscous properties of mucus, the movement of the cilia of the cylindrical epithelium, action of non-specific inhibitors of viral replication in mucus, the macrophagal barrier and IgA [
 <xref rid="B30-marinedrugs-17-00373" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. With the help of HA, the virus attaches to the receptors of target cells and penetrates them, where the replication cycle takes place [
 <xref rid="B5-marinedrugs-17-00373" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. After 4–6 h, a batch of new viruses appears in the cell and then they are pushed out through the cell membrane to the outside. After 24 h, the number of viruses whose “parent” entered the cell can reach several hundred million. The released virions infect neighboring cells and some of them enter in the blood. The subsequent death of epithelial cells is caused not only by the cytopathogenic effect of the virus but also by the inability of the cell to fully recover after the replication of the pathogen. In the early stages of infection, Toll-like receptors (TLR) are involved in the recognition of conservative molecules characteristic of pathogenic microorganisms. The influenza virus stimulates the TLR responses of innate and adaptive immunity [
 <xref rid="B31-marinedrugs-17-00373" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. On the cell membrane, TLR4 and C-type lectin receptors (MMR-mannose and MGL-galactose) interact with the glycoproteins of the viral membrane, HA, and NA [
 <xref rid="B32-marinedrugs-17-00373" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Inside cells, the endosomal receptors TLR3, TLR7, TLR10, and cytoplasmic RIG1 respond to viral RNA and RNP [
 <xref rid="B33-marinedrugs-17-00373" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-marinedrugs-17-00373" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].
</p>
