<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par38">Those with history of influenza vaccination appeared to have a higher rate of identification of influenza viruses in the NPA than those without vaccination for both AECOPD and asthma exacerbation though this did not reach statistical significance. A previous study suggested that protective serum antibody titres in COPD patients after influenza vaccination was lower than control subjects [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Overall the mortality benefit of influenza vaccine in COPD is suggested by some studies but the impact on exacerbation prevention is less clear [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Another systemic review indicated a favorable benefit-risk ratio for seasonal influenza vaccination in patients with COPD [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. For persons with asthma, a recent systematic review observed that influenza vaccination might be effective in both reducing influenza infection and asthma attacks [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. However, another Cochrane review has expressed uncertainty of the degree of protection that influenza vaccination might confer against asthma exacerbations that are related to influenza infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. During the study period from August 2016 to July 2017, influenza A(H3N2) was the main circulating strain causing the Summer and Winter epidemics in Hong Kong [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Influenza vaccine effectiveness depends on many factors including matching between vaccine strains and the circulating strains, immunocompetence, age, repeated vaccination, antigenic sites and distances in addition to egg adaptation especially for influenza A(H3N2) virus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. A previous systematic review found substantial variations in influenza vaccine effectiveness across types and subtypes of influenza with substantially lower protection against H3N2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Examination of influenza vaccine effectiveness by serology is beyond the scope of this study as it would require a large sample size. In addition, as these patients had some time delay in presenting to the hospitals, it would be difficult to determine whether this was due to current or previous infection or vaccination by measuring influenza antibody based on haemagglutinin inhibition. While identification of pathogens in the NPA was associated with a lower rate of readmissions for asthma, exacerbations of COPD and asthma might also be due to other acute and transient factors such as exposure to air pollutants [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], change in temperature, etc.
</p>
