<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Based on phylogenetic analysis, MCMV isolates identified in this study are highly similar to those from other east African countries (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pathogens-09-00004-f001">Figure 1</xref>). The observed similarity of MCMV isolates from the current study and those from the neighboring countries showsthat combined regional efforts should be applied to control MLN. Currently, initiatives have been taken by the International Maize and Wheat Improvement Center (CIMMYT) and other agricultural research institutes across east Africa to breed for MLN resistant maize varieties. Putative genes and quantitative trait loci (QTL) for MLN resistance have been identified in tropical maize germplasm and will be useful in the breeding efforts [
 <xref rid="B38-pathogens-09-00004" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-pathogens-09-00004" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-pathogens-09-00004" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Interestingly, we observed significant genetic dissimilarities between the SCMV recovered in the current study compared to those from other east African countries retrieved from the NCBI. The observed differences in SCMV could likely indicate that the virus is more sensitive to variations in climate across geographical locations, as pointed out by other authors [
 <xref rid="B7-pathogens-09-00004" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-pathogens-09-00004" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-pathogens-09-00004" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-pathogens-09-00004" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Furthermore, SCMV is an RNA virus, and its variations could be caused by inherent replication errors due to the lack of proofreading activity of RNA-dependent RNA polymerases [
 <xref rid="B41-pathogens-09-00004" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-pathogens-09-00004" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Previous reports show that quarantine measures to control the movement of MCMV in uninfected areas could be more effective than similar measures for controlling SCMV [
 <xref rid="B5-pathogens-09-00004" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. It is not known whether the observed diversity in SCMV affects MLN and whether this could complicate the management of the disease.
</p>
