<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As described above, the main cell lines that have been traditionally used for studying influenza included the MDCK cells and cancer-derived lung cell lines such as A549 and Calu-3. HEK293 and Vero have also been used quite widely. The use of defined immortal cell lines that are readily infectable and in which influenza replicates is of obvious convenience. These systems contributed indeed significantly to our current understanding of influenza (reviewed in Powell et al., 2018,2018 [
 <xref rid="B12-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B245-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">245</xref>]). Nevertheless, established cell lines possess major disadvantages. In addition to the inherent disadvantage of cells in culture that are disconnected from the organism’s systems (immune, endocrine, neuronal), established cell lines, particularly those that are oncogenically transformed, develop unique biochemical wirings and create their own repertoire of gene expression. Many cell lines are therefore significantly different from the original parental cells that were taken from the tissue and used to establish the cell line [
 <xref rid="B246-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">246</xref>]. Such cells may respond to viral infection in a different manner than cells in the intact tissue. Primary cell cultures, on the other hand, provide both the advantage of the convenience of studies in culture and the advantage of cells that have not re-wired their biochemical networks and have not yet shed their identity. An unequivocal advantage of the primary culture approach is the fact that they could be prepared from patients. These patient-derived cells may come with known patients’ characteristics such as gender, co-morbidities, or lifestyle habits like smoking, allowing a personalized investigation of the disease. Amongst all the experimental models, the primary cells are in fact the only one that could be derived from patients and could provide the closest physiology to an actual human clinical subject. 
</p>
