<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The study was designed as a cross-sectional study with prospective patient inclusion. As the proportion of pathogens can change over time, especially for epidemic-prone diseases, we included patients proportionally from November 2015 to June 2016. Only patients of at least 2 years old, presenting at the outpatient department with a history of acute fever (
 <italic>i</italic>.
 <italic>e</italic>. ≥ 2 days and ≤ 7 days) or having an axillary temperature of ≥ 37.5°C, were eligible. Patients with any history of an acute injury, trauma or poisoning, suspicion of meningitis/encephalitis, recent hospitalization or women who gave birth in the preceding two weeks, were excluded. Reported recent intake of antimicrobials was not an exclusion criterion, but was recorded accordingly. There were two categories of patients included: the ‘undifferentiated fevers’, with as case definition history of acute fever and without any clear clinical focus of infection and the ‘differentiated fevers’, with a history of fever and with acute respiratory infection (ARI), gastroenteritis (GE) or urinary tract infection (UTI) categorized on clinical grounds. Of the first group, a maximum of 6 patients per day (3 children and 3 adults), and of the second group a maximum of 2 patients per day (1 child and 1 adult) were to be included. The latter category was included given the non-specificity of the signs and symptoms of a possible arboviral infection and in order to estimate the burden of co-infection–which was also the reason not to exclude the confirmed malaria cases based on laboratory analysis. Our main interest was the distribution of viral pathogens among the undifferentiated fevers. To be able to detect the presence of a disease whose prevalence is 5% with a precision of 2.5% at a confidence level of 95%, 290 patients needed to be included. Increased with 10% for incomplete data or loss of biological samples, we came to a minimal sample size of 320.
</p>
