<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We have already discussed above the role of endosomal/lysosomal acidification and the role of their acidic pH‐dependent proteases in the virus life cycle (Yang &amp; Shen, 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0193" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). The inhibition of this pathway might be a potential therapeutic strategy. Several therapeutics such as Chloroquine (CQ), a well‐studied lysosomotropic antimalarial drug, and its derivatives hydroxychloroquine and colchicine would be an option for blocking this target. CQ effectively blocks viral progression by raising endosomal pH needed for membrane fusion between the host cell and viral candidates and releasing RNA from endosomes (Savarino, Boelaert, Cassone, Majori, &amp; Cauda, 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0143" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>). Although CQ and hydroxychloroquine were found to be effective against SARS‐CoV‐2 (Gautret et al., 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0062" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>; Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0183" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>), several recent evidence claimed some unprecedented effects. A recent study reported that hydroxychloroquine (either alone or in combination with azithromycin) showed no positive outcome in patients with COVID‐19 (Magagnoli et al., 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0117" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>), instead was linked with increased overall mortality (27.8% in hydroxychloroquine and 22.1% in hydroxychloroquine plus azithromycin versus 11.4% in the control group). A multinational, observational, real‐world study of patients with COVID‐19 also claimed that hydroxychloroquine or chloroquine showed no evidence of benefit, rather it was associated with an increase in the risk of ventricular arrhythmias and a greater hazard for in‐hospital death with COVID‐19 (Mehra, Desai, Ruschitzka, &amp; Patel, 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0124" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Moreover, a recent systematic review found no difference between the hydroxychloroquine treated group and an untreated group of COVID‐19 patients (Sarma et al., 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0141" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). WHO had recently postponed further clinical trials on hydroxychloroquine due to unexpected results in previous trials, however, this repurposed drug has been allowed for re‐evaluation. All of this evidence points to the significance of waiting for the final results of ongoing prospective, randomized, controlled studies before considering these drugs as a therapeutic option for COVID‐19.
</p>
