<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>MIA cannot be easily modelled in humans and longitudinal, prospective research on effects of infection during pregnancy on human development is scarce (
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>). Hence, translational animal models of MIA have been developed: these models have been critical in providing causality to the epidemiological data and are starting to provide clues as to the cellular and molecular mechanisms that may underlie the associations (
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>). Rodents in gestational periods are exposed either directly to a pathogen such as influenza, or more commonly to nonvirulent immune-activating agents such as the viral mimetic polyriboinosinic-polyribocytidilic acid (poly(I:C)) or the bacterial endotoxin lipopolysaccharide (LPS), the inflammatory agent turpentine, or specific proinflammatory cytokines (
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>). These animal models of MIA provide evidence for behavioral, neurochemical, neuroanatomic, and neurophysiologic disruptions in the offspring which map onto endophenotypes observed across human psychiatric disorders with a neurodevelopmental onset (
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>). Such translational research complements the insights from human epidemiology by establishing causal relationships, identifying cellular and molecular mechanisms and offering the potential to explore therapeutic interventions (
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>). Frequently, these aforementioned deficits in the MIA model demonstrate a maturational delay, such that they are not evident before young adulthood, and many studies have sought to mitigate these deficits with treatments (e.g., pharmacological, immunological, behavioral) (
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>). Another important etiological advance for such animal models is to recapitulate a “two-hit” approach, in which pathology becomes evident in MIA-exposed offspring only after a second hit, such as unpredictable psychological stress (
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>).
</p>
