<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14">The food industry is known to be very committed to food safety assurance but less concerned with the safety of food operators unless they may compromise the quality of the food product. It is common in studies on occupational risk assessment of the food industry that the perspective of zoonosis as a source of risk is not referenced in occupational health and safety plans. In the latest report from the European Food Safety Authority of 2018 zoonoses are among the most common foodborne diseases (commonly referred to as food poisoning) and can also be spread to humans either by direct contact with a sick animal or by contact with a vector (or carrier) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. However, the focus on of biological agents is essential in food processing industry namely in activities such as slaughterhouses and poultry and meat processing industries not only due to air spread or contact with organic dust. However, we must not overlook another crucial aspect which is the antimicrobial resistance that may be associated with biological agents, nowadays one of the biggest threats to global health, food security and development [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Risk assessment in professional activities, where exposure to biological agents can be frequent and intense, considers the potential levels of exposure, and the level of infectious risk of the potentially existing agents. However, current risk assessment models are inadequate to evaluate the effect of antibiotics and antibiotic resistance genes (ARGs) on resistance emergence and selection, especially in non-clinical environments [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Biological risk assessment has become even more complex because, in addition to detecting biological agents with potential for risk for workers, it is necessary to assess the antimicrobial resistance that can be seen to bring to the workplaces being an aggravated danger to public health issues. The emergence of antimicrobial-resistant bacteria in mass animal husbandry has raised further concern regarding occupational exposure and its potential public health consequences. Particular attention has been paid to methicillin-resistant 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA) and multidrug-resistant Gram-negative enteric pathogens (GNEP) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>].
</p>
