<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since the single D1 domain of CD4 is unstable and has low gp120-binding affinity, 
 <xref rid="B133" ref-type="bibr">Sharma et al. (2005)</xref> and 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al. (2011)</xref> constructed two mutants of the CD4 D1 domain, CD4D1 and CD4PEP1, using mutagenesis. They demonstrated that both CD4D1 and CD4PEP1 could interact with gp120 with KD values of 40 and 26 nM, respectively. However, their virus inhibition or inactivation activities have not been detected and reported. 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al. (2011)</xref> identified two monomeric D1 mutants with high stability, solubility and gp120-binding affinity, designated mD1.1 and mD1.2, through screening a large D1 mutant library and found that both mD1.1 and mD1.2 could effectively neutralize HIV-1 primary isolates (
 <xref rid="B133" ref-type="bibr">Sharma et al., 2005</xref>). Subsequently, they identified an mD1.2 mutant, mD1.22, which had higher thermostability, better solubility and stronger gp120-binding affinity compared to mD1.2. 
 <italic>In vitro</italic> studies showed that mD1.22 was several folds more potent than D1D2 and mD1.2 in inhibiting R5-tropic HIV-1 primary isolates, Bal and JRFL (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2014</xref>). To further improve its anti-HIV-1 activity and breadth, mD1.22 was fused with m36.4, an engineered human antibody domain targeting a CD4-induced (CD4i) epitope, which overlaps the HIV-1 coreceptor-binding site (CoRbs) on gp120 (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2008</xref>). This resulted in the generation of two bispecific multivalent fusion proteins, 2Dm2m and 4Dm2m, which could inhibit infection by all HIV-1 strains tested, including 41 HIV-1 isolates circulating predominantly in China, with an average IC50 of 1.7 and 0.2 nM, respectively (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2014</xref>). Most recently, the virus inactivation assay was utilized to compare the ability of 2Dm2m and 4Dm2m to inactivate cell-free HIV-1 IIIB virions against full-length sCD4, D1D2 (
 <xref rid="B133" ref-type="bibr">Sharma et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2011</xref>), and mD1.22 (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2014</xref>). The results implied that mD1.22, 2Dm2m, and 4Dm2m were highly effective in inactivating HIV-1 with EC50s of 3.1, 1.1, and 0.3 nM, respectively, which are much more potent than those of sCD4 (EC50: 153 nM) and D1D2 (EC50: 64.7 nM) (
 <xref rid="B123" ref-type="bibr">Qi et al., 2017</xref>). These results indicate that the single-domain protein mD1.22 and the bispecific multivalent proteins 2Dm2m and 4Dm2m are important HIV inactivators and are promising to be further developed into new anti-HIV drugs for treatment and prevention of HIV infection.
</p>
