<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We selected a total of 12 sites from three islands of varying latitudes, namely Okinawa, Japan (N = 2, JP1 &amp; 2), Taiwan (N = 7, TW1-7) and Penang, Malaysia (N = 3, MY1-3), and collected various numbers of 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>gracilipes</italic> colonies in each site (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="insects-10-00436-f001">Figure 1</xref>). The colony in the current study was defined as a physical nest unit, containing all castes/stages (queens, workers and brood, and sometimes alates), clearly delineated from another unit by at least 100 m. A total of 28, 27 and 40 colonies (all sites combined) were collected from Okinawa, Taiwan, and Penang, respectively. We screened for the presence of the TR44839 virus in each site and calculated the infection rate based on the number of infected colonies over the total number of collected colonies in a site. To understand if the TR44839 virus can be horizontally transmitted among colonies, and also if the virus actively replicates in 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>gracilipes</italic>, an artificial inoculation assay of the virus was carried out. Additionally, three colonies confirmed to be TR44839 virus-uninfected (note, these three colonies were not involved in subsequent aggression assay) were collected and fed with a fixed amount of 10% honey solution homogenized with virus-infected 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>gracilipes</italic> workers for 24 h. Given the fact that the replication of the virus in the 
 <italic>Dicistroviridae</italic> family proceeds via the synthesis of a complementary negative strand, the presence of a negative strand would serve as evidence of replication. We, therefore, attempted to detect the negative strand of the virus using strand-specific RT-PCR at Day 7 after feeding. The RNA of five workers from each colony was extracted and used as the template for cDNA synthesis, using oligo-dT primer and the strand-specific primer. The resultant cDNA was then added to the subsequent PCR reaction in which the target viral fragment was amplified using the previously reported primer set (TR44839: AGACGAACGAACAAAGGACCT / CAATTCAGTTCTGCGGGTGC) [
 <xref rid="B17-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The PCR amplification protocol included 94 °C for 3 min, then 35 cycles of 94 °C for 30 s, 60 °C for 30 s, and 72 °C for 30 s, with a final extension step of 72 °C for 5 min. Samples were confirmed TR44839-virus-positive if a 130 bp fragment was visualized on the agarose gel electrophoresis. We included a positive control (RNA extracted from individuals previously confirmed positive by both gel electrophoresis and sequencing), negative control (RNA extracted from individuals previously confirmed negative for the virus), and blank (ddH
 <sub>2</sub>O) in every batch of RT-PCR reaction.
</p>
