<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Following our hypothesis of the activation of pre-formed EGFR clusters, we aimed to test if EGFR clusters exist long enough to allow their activation. We thus went on to probe the stability of EGFR nanoclusters by conducting live-cell sptPALM experiments. We found that the lifetime of EGFR nanodomains in both, the dorsal as well as the ventral side of the cell went up to 2 to 4 minutes. This time resembles the duration IAVs where shown to stay on the plasma membrane before onset of endocytosis (2–3 min [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008656.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]). While a long cluster lifetime would allow activation of pre-existing clusters, this observation raises the question for the stabilization of EGFR clusters. Hence, we tested the stability of EGFR clusters upon treatment with classical membrane domain-destabilizing conditions such as actin depolymerization (latrunculin A) and cholesterol extraction (methyl-β-cyclodextrin). As also observed before [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008656.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008656.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], our results suggest cluster destabilization following both perturbations indicated by an increased fraction of unclustered EGFR molecules. Interestingly, we found a stronger effect after cholesterol depletion, a condition that was previously shown to attenuate IAV replication [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008656.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Very long receptor cluster lifetimes were observed previously for class I major histocompatibility complex (MHC) molecules, that form actin-stabilized domains [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008656.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008656.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. At this point, we can only speculate about the function of membrane receptor clusters [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008656.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008656.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. It can be excitatory as shown for T-cell receptor [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008656.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] and linker for activation of T-cell (Lat) [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008656.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008656.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] as well as LFA-1 [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008656.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] or CD36 [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008656.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. These nanodomains render the cell highly sensitive to small amounts of signaling molecules and due to the high local receptor concentration allow a fast signaling response [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008656.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Such a function seems likely for EGFR clusters involved in IAV cell entry observed in our study. But their function can also be inhibitory as shown for the B-cell receptor [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008656.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] or its negative co-receptor CD22 [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008656.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Receptor nanodomains could even engage in modulating the signaling output. As EGFR sits at the top of a broad array of signaling cascades, an asymmetric distribution of receptors could enable cells to rapidly respond and process different stimuli [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008656.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>].
</p>
