<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22">Groups of 5–6 animals were immunized sequentially through an 
 <italic>i.n</italic>. route with various influenza VLP formulations containing 10 μg of HA in total from different subtypes per immunization as shown in the table. Briefly, we sequentially immunized mice with different phylogenetic group 1 HA VLPs (group 1); phylogenetic group 2 HA VLPs (group 2); with a mixture of two HA VLPs from phylogenetic group 1 and group 2 (group 3); with a mixture of all of six types of both phylogenetic group 1 and group 2 HA VLPs (group 4); or with PBS as negative control (group 5) (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The HA antigens chosen from phylogenetic group 1 and group 2 were selected to maximize genetic divergence. This type of antigenic selection may increase the possibility to get more specific and effective antibody responses mainly against highly pathogenic strains such as H5N1 or H7N9. Mice were immunized at weeks 0, 3 and 6. One month after the last vaccination, animal groups were challenged intranasally with 10 × LD
 <sub>50</sub> of live mouse adapted A/California/07/2009 (Cal09, H1N1), A/Philippines/2/1982 (Phi82, H3N2), rVet (H5N1), or rSH (H7N9) viruses (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). For rVet, the HA and NA genes were derived from A/Vietnam/1203/2004 (H5N1, Vet) and the remaining backbone genes from A/Puerto Rico/8/1934 (H1N1, PR8) and for rSH, the HA and NA genes were derived from A/Shanghai/2/2013 (H7N9, SH), and the remaining backbone genes from A/Puerto Rico/8/1934 (H1N1, PR8)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>
 </sup>. Vaccination and control groups were monitored up to 14 days for body weight changes and mortality. Mice that lost more than 20% of their original body weight were terminated and recorded as dead
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>
 </sup>. For post-challenge inflammatory responses, the levels of various inflammatory cytokines were measured at day 4 post challenge using ELISA in BALF without any prior 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> stimulation.
</p>
