<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mechanistic understanding is valuable for extrapolating beyond the current spatial and temporal range of transmission (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0005568.g004">Fig 4</xref>), as compared to environmental niche models, for example [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Of the six previous mechanistic temperature-dependent models of DENV, CHIKV, or ZIKV transmission by 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> that we were able to reproduce, three had similar thermal optima [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] while the other three had dramatically higher optima (3–6°C) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] (Fig E in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0005568.s001">S1 Text</xref>). Two of the models were very similar to ours [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]; of the remaining four models, two predicted much greater suitability for transmission at low temperatures [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] and all four predicted greater suitability at high temperatures [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] (Fig E in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0005568.s001">S1 Text</xref>). Only one of these previous models was (like ours) statistically validated against independent data not used to estimate model parameters, and its predictions were very similar to those of our model [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Other mechanistic and environmental niche models could not be directly compared with ours [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], either because fully reproducible equations, parameters, and/or code were not provided or because their predicted marginal effects of temperature were not displayed. Visually, our maps are similar to maps based on a previous model of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> persistence suitability indices [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Recent environmental niche models of Zika distribution have shown similar but more constrained predicted distributions of environmental suitability, in part because these models include not just temperature suitability but also further environmental, socioeconomic, and demographic constraints [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>].
</p>
