<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We and others have previously reported the spontaneous development of ST-246 resistance, both 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Duraffour et al., 2015</xref>) and clinically in a smallpox-vaccinated PV patient receiving ST-246 as part of their treatment regimen (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Lederman et al., 2012</xref>). In healthy individuals, it is possible that the immune response might overcome such resistant viruses, if they arise. However, additional interventions may be required for at-risk groups that cannot mount a protective immune response, such as individuals with immune deficiencies. For such cases, it would be beneficial to have additional antiviral candidates that can be administered in combination with ST-246 and can suppress ST-246-resistant viruses. We tested the inhibitory potential of PA104, PA63, and PA24 against two different ST-246-resistant viruses and found that all three compounds reduced viral spread of both viruses, as determined by a reduction in viral plaque size. Interestingly, while RV2 was substantially inhibited by all three Retro-1 compounds, RV1 appeared to be less efficiently inhibited by PA24 and PA63. These differences in the levels of viral inhibition by the same compounds could potentially be caused by additional uncharacterized mutations in other genes, or strain differences between the viruses; whereas RV1 was an Acambis strain of VACV, RV2 was a Western Reserve strain. Nevertheless, PA104 treatment resulted in maximal inhibition of plaque size for wild-type as well as RV1 and RV2 ST-246-resistant viruses. We hypothesize that its superior capacity to inhibit these viruses compared to PA24 and PA63 could be due to its ability to target multiple steps of VACV infection, including viral entry and MV formation, in addition to EV formation (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3"> 3</xref>).
</p>
