<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As outlined above, RV can be teratogenic from early pregnancy onwards. Experimental proof is provided for in utero transmission of ZIKV before formation of the placenta is initiated and even before implantation of the blastocyst [
 <xref rid="B18-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Although accessibility of the blastocyst at these early time points of embryogenesis is under discussion, it was already demonstrated in 1959, by Wilson et al., that the teratogenic substance trypan blue can cross the blastocyst wall, resulting in its direct access to the embryo [
 <xref rid="B27-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. As a hypothesis, we want to point out the potential role played by maternal immune cells in the transfer of pathogens such as RV in utero as early as one week after conception (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="cells-09-00542-f001">Figure 1</xref>B). Decidual leukocytes, such as natural killer cells and macrophages, are involved through multiple functions in gestational processes such as decidualization and implantation [
 <xref rid="B3-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The trophoblast cells of the blastocyst interact with those immune cells that are infiltrating the decidua, which in turn supports implantation and formation of the placenta. As discussed before, the so far present paradigm of a maternal immune response against a so-called semi-allogenic fetus has changed to a necessary fetal-maternal interaction in support of implantation. This idea of a host-semi allograft model was suggested in 1952 by Sir Peter Medawar and, in analogy to the immune response during organ transplantation, received support through the high proportion of maternal immune cells within the decidua [
 <xref rid="B29-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Several studies on the crucial role of these immune cells during pregnancy have revised our view on blastocyst implantation and the development of maternal immune tolerance from a state of immune suppression to a rather dynamic maternal-fetal interface [
 <xref rid="B30-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. To name some of the studies, Hanna et al. demonstrated that depletion of natural killer cells within the decidua negatively affects trophoblast invasion [
 <xref rid="B31-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Furthermore, a conditional mouse model of macrophage depletion confirmed the key role of macrophages from early pregnancy onwards, as their depletion during early pregnancy resulted in failure of embryo implantation [
 <xref rid="B32-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. As a potentially infected cell population, they could enter the endometrium from circulating blood, providing viral access to the trophoblast cells. The experimental proof for this notion and the identification of ways of in utero transfer around the time point of implantation in general remains a challenge for the future.
</p>
