<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0015">
 <italic>What's known about neonatal COVID-19 infection?</italic> It is not yet established whether COVID-19 has transplacental or vertical transmission. Recently, a report from China described three infants with elevated serum levels of IgG and IgM antibodies for SARS-CoV-2 after birth.
 <xref rid="bib0205" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0210" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> The postnatal courses were benign and quantitative reverse transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) from nasopharyngeal swabs, serum, vaginal secretions, and maternal breast milk were negative. Thus, in the light of negative RT-PCR results and given that IgM false positives results are not uncommon, and that the decline of IGM levels were very unusual in comparison with other congenital infections, the possibility of maternal-infant transmission is difficult to ascertain.
 <xref rid="bib0215" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref> Fetal outcomes may depend more on the severity of the maternal infection and/or concomitant obstetric diseases, rather than on a putative transmission of the COVID-19 from the pregnant mother to the fetus.
 <xref rid="bib0220" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>15</sup>
 </xref> At this point, very few positive confirmed neonatal COVID-19 cases have been reported in scientific journals, and all of them had no symptoms or very mild to moderate symptoms, with no fatal cases reported in infants &lt;28 days.
 <xref rid="bib0150" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0225" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0230" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0235" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0240" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> Acquisition of COVID-19 has been so far attributed to horizontal transmission from an infected mother or health care provider, rather than vertical. Based on this limited evidence, no specific clinical picture for neonatal COVID-19 infection has consistently emerged. Indeed, a few positive cases of neonatal COVID-19 in Brazil have been very recently reported by the news or personal communications, and clinical presentations and neonatal courses were reassuringly similar to the reported cases. Nevertheless, as the disease continues to spread throughout the world, we must remain vigilant.
</p>
