<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Chloroquine (CQ) is a classically used antimalarial drug. Its antiviral activity against dengue virus and other flaviviruses has already been demonstrated [
 <xref rid="B128-pharmaceuticals-12-00060" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>,
 <xref rid="B129-pharmaceuticals-12-00060" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>] and several groups started to test its possible anti-ZIKV activity. Delvecchio and colleagues tested CQ against African and Brazilian strains of ZIKV in human neural progenitor cells, human brain microvascular endothelial cells and mouse neurospheres, indicating its ability to inhibit viral replication and rescue cell viability (Delvecchio 2016). CQ also reduced mortality and weight loss caused by ZIKV infection in adult AG129 mice, when administered in drinking water at the dose of 50 mg/kg for two days before infection and five days after, with a maintenance dose of 5 mg/kg until the end of the experiment [
 <xref rid="B85-pharmaceuticals-12-00060" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. In that same study, authors showed that vertical transmission was attenuated when pregnant dams received 30 mg/kg/day of CQ in their drinking water, resulting in decreased levels of viral RNA and ZIKV-positive cells in the brains of fetuses. These results were further replicated in another study, which employed a similar treatment schedule: when given to pregnant BALB/c dams (20 mg/kg/day s.c.) between embryonic days 13.5 and 18.5, CQ was able to reestablish cortical thickness, reduce caspase-3 immunolabeling and rescue the expression of several proliferation markers in ZIKV-infected embryos [
 <xref rid="B86-pharmaceuticals-12-00060" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. CQs safety profile during pregnancy is outstanding in every trimester as well as with prolonged use. Human studies performed in lactating women reported no abnormalities [
 <xref rid="B130-pharmaceuticals-12-00060" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>]. Moreover, CQ is extensively available worldwide and its low cost makes it a good candidate for both prophylaxis and treatment of ZIKV-infected men and women.
</p>
