<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <title>Abstract</title>
 <p>
  <bold>Context:</bold> Fuzheng Huayu recipe (FZHY) combined with entecavir (ETV) is used to treat the cirrhosis caused by chronic hepatitis B (CHB) infection.
 </p>
 <p>
  <bold>Objective:</bold> To investigate the effect of FZHY on ETV pharmacokinetics under different conditions.
 </p>
 <p>
  <bold>Materials and methods:</bold> A model of liver fibrosis was created by intraperitoneal injection of dimethylnitrosamine (DMN; 10 μg/kg) for 4 weeks in Wistar rats. Ultra-high-performance liquid chromatography–tandem mass spectrometry was used to determine the blood concentration of ETV. Pharmacokinetic characteristics of ETV (0.9 mg/kg) were investigated after co-administration with FZHY (0.55 g/kg) at certain time intervals in normal and model rats.
 </p>
 <p>
  <bold>Results:</bold> The analytical method for ETV was validated at 0.5–50 μg/L with a correlation coefficient = 0.9996, lower limit of quantitation of 0.5 μg/L and mean accuracy of 104.18 ± 9.46%. Compared with the ETV-N group, the pharmacokinetic parameters of the EF-2 group did not change significantly, but that of the EF-0 group decreased in 
  <italic>C</italic>
  <sub>max</sub> to 27.38 μg/L, in AUC
  <sub>0–</sub>
  <italic>
   <sub>t</sub>
  </italic> from 323.84 to 236.67 μg/h/L, and a delay in 
  <italic>T</italic>
  <sub>max</sub> from 0.75 to 6.00 h; that of the EF-0 group presented a decrease in 
  <italic>C</italic>
  <sub>max</sub> of 61.92%, delay in 
  <italic>t</italic>
  <sub>1/2</sub> of 2.45 h and delay in 
  <italic>T</italic>
  <sub>max</sub> of 2.92 h. The 
  <italic>t</italic>
  <sub>1/2e</sub> and 
  <italic>V</italic>
  <sub>d</sub>/
  <italic>F</italic> of ETV were increased significantly to 8.01 h and 24.38 L/kg in the ETV-M group.
 </p>
 <p>
  <bold>Conclusions:</bold> The effects of FZHY on ETV pharmacokinetics were diminished with an increase of interval time. The best time to administer both drugs is &gt;2 h apart.
 </p>
</abstract>
