<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite the availability of these computational methods in identifying antigenicity-associated sites and predicting antigenic variants for influenza, most of the models were built for influenza A/H3N2. There is still insufficient knowledge on the influenza H1N1 that caused numerous epidemics all over the world. Besides, high-performance model for rapid prediction of H1N1 antigenicity from sequences is needed. In this study, we built a stacking model to include all influenza periods of H1N1 based on epidemics and pandemics for the prediction of antigenic variants. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first attempt to take epidemic and pandemic events into account for inferring the antigenic relation between H1N1 virus strains. We categorized influenza strains into two types, pandemic-based and epidemic-based, denoted as “PDM” and “EPD”. The period of five pandemics in recent centuries was shown in 
 <xref rid="pone.0207777.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> and the rest of the time is regarded as an epidemic period. In this way, we not only classified the antigenic relation of two influenza strains within a certain period, but also compared antigenic relation of two strains more broadly. By analyzing sequence data and calculating the entropy of each residue position of HA1 protein for strains, we demonstrated that influenza H1N1 went through different variations across the periods. Pearson Correlation Coefficient (PCC) [
 <xref rid="pone.0207777.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] was performed to further identify the distinct mutation patterns of H1N1 strains in each period. Individual prediction models of a pair of strains across periods were constructed for the antigenic variants prediction. Finally, a stacking model was built to predict antigenic variants combining H1N1 epidemic and pandemic strains from all periods. The accuracy of the stacking model exceeded those of above-mentioned for H1N1. Three different feature generation methods applied to the construction of models proved its feasibility and reliability. We believe this model could help to analyze epidemic and pandemic strains. The highlighted mutation patterns and constructed models may also help facilitate rough determination of antigenic variants, the surveillance of influenza and as a reference to the selection of vaccine strains.
</p>
