<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Prior to phylogenetic analysis multiple sequence alignments were performed using BioEdit Sequence Alignment Editor Version 7.0.9.0 and verified by Clustal X program (version 1.8). Phylogenetic trees were constructed on A. 63 nucleotide sequences (1824 bp long comprising complete N, P, and X genes; 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093659-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>, unrooted tree, Neighbor-Joining method), B. 76 almost entire p24 (P) gene sequences where only the two last nucleotides were missing (604 bp corresponding to nt positions 1272–1875 of reference strain V, GenBank acc. No. U04608; the length is determined by the shortest sequence) with strain He/80 as outgroup (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093659-g004">Fig. 4B</xref>, Maximum Likelihood method), C. 69 almost entire p40 (N) gene sequences where only the three last nucleotides were missing (1110 bp corresponding to nt positions 54–1163 of reference strain V, GenBank acc. No. U04608; the length is determined by the shortest sequence) using strain No/98 as outgroup (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093659-g004">Fig. 4C</xref>, Maximum Likelihood method), D. 63 nucleotide sequences (1824 bp long comprising complete N, P, and X genes; 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093659.s002">Figure S2</xref>, radial tree, Neighbor-Joining method), and E. 88 nucleotide sequences of a stretch within the p40 (N) gene (399 bp corresponding to nt positions 312–710 of reference strain V, GenBank acc. No. U04608; 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0093659.s003">Figure S3</xref>, unrooted tree, Neighbor-Joining method). Phylogenetic analyses were conducted using the MEGA5 program 
 <xref rid="pone.0093659-Tamura1" ref-type="bibr">[72]</xref>. For each tree the evolutionary history was inferred using either the Neighbor-Joining or the Maximum Likelihood method. The evolutionary distances were computed using the Kimura 2-parameter model. The optimal trees with the highest percentages of replicates in the bootstrap test (1000 replicates) were chosen.
</p>
