<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20">The names of the countries and regions have almost invariably appeared in Cluster (i) across all three datasets. In certain cases, the country names that have occurred most often are those from which the outbreaks originated or those that suffered most from the impact of the outbreak. For example, “
 <italic>Saudi Arabia</italic>” appears quite distinctly on the Cluster (i) of the MERS dataset. Similarly, the presence of the names of south-east Asian countries/regions such as “China”, “Hong Kong”, “Taiwan”, “Singapore” on the Cluster (i) of the SARS map, or the term “Wuhan” on the Cluster (i) of the Covid-19 map are quite pronounced. The occurrence of the names of countries also could be a reflection of the early (case) studies that have addressed the local impacts/spread of the outbreaks within their own society. On the issue of early studies, the terms “
 <italic>letters</italic>”, “
 <italic>editorial</italic>”, and “
 <italic>review</italic>” (which have intentionally been kept on the maps) seem to also have distinctly occurred in Cluster (i) of each literature which is an indication that this cluster includes early studies that appeared at a time where the amount of data and clinical trials were insufficient for full-length articles. An inspection of the Figs. 
 <xref rid="Fig18" ref-type="fig">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="Fig20" ref-type="fig">20</xref> does, in fact, confirm this hypothesis at least in association with the SARS and MERS literature, that the Cluster (i) of keywords represent studies that on average emerged earlier during the developments of their respective literatures. Figures 
 <xref rid="Fig19" ref-type="fig">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="Fig21" ref-type="fig">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="Fig23" ref-type="fig">23</xref> that have illustrated the colour-coding of the average number of citations on the maps also show that, although Cluster (i) is associated with the early studies that generally preceded studies of the two other clusters and although it represents the largest variety of topics compared to the two other clusters, it is also associated with the studies that, on average, been the recipient of a lesser number of citations when compared to the two other clusters. This pattern appears to have commonly occurred across all three datasets.
</p>
