<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14">Astroviruses are small, nonenveloped viruses with a genome consisting of single-stranded, positive-sense RNA. The genome includes three overlapping open reading frames (ORFs) flanked by untranslated regions and a poly-A tail, with ORF1a and ORF1b encoding nonstructural proteins (either as nsp1a or nsp1ab through a ribosomal frameshift mechanism) and ORF2 encoding the capsid protein precursor [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Within the family 
 <italic>Astroviridae</italic>, members of the genus 
 <italic>Avastrovirus</italic> infect birds, whereas those of the genus 
 <italic>Mamastrovirus</italic> are found in mammals. The taxonomy of astroviruses is currently based on their host species as well as their full capsid protein precursor sequence, with amino acid distances (p-dist) greater than 0.338 defining distinct genotype species [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Innumerable strains of these viruses were described from faecal samples of various mammalian species [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Apart from humans and minks, in which they are known to cause gastroenteric disease, their association with illness in many animals yet remains unclear. In cattle and sheep, astroviruses were found in diarrheic [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] as well as healthy animals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Besides, astroviruses were reported in association with neurological disease in an increasing number of hosts in recent years: humans [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], minks [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], cattle [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], sheep [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] and pigs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Interestingly, many of these neurotropic astroviruses genetically cluster together in the so-called human-mink-ovine (HMO) clade, of which various enterotropic strains are also part [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].
</p>
