<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4">The discovery of broadly protective antibodies that bind to the conserved stalk domain of the HA and cross-react between HA subtypes sparked hopes for the development of a universal influenza virus vaccine.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup> Regular licensed influenza virus vaccines do not induce high antibody levels against the immuno-subdominant HA stalk domain but work through the induction of potent strain-specific antibodies against the immuno-dominant head domain.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup> Sequential immunizations with chimeric HAs (cHAs), which consist of HA stalk domains derived from circulating influenza viruses in combination with ‘exotic’ head domains of influenza viruses that do not circulate in humans, can selectively boost anti-stalk antibodies.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup> When the immune system is presented with a cHA, it responds mainly to the head domain but some priming effect against the stalk domain is achieved as well (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). Exposure to another cHA with the same stalk but a different head domain then boosts antibodies against the stalk domain but only induces a primary response against the novel head domain. This procedure can be repeated several times to induce high and protective titers against the conserved stalk domain. Importantly, adult humans are already primed against the stalk domain and it is expected that they mount a solid anti-stalk response after one to two vaccinations with cHAs.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup> Another promising vaccination strategy that has recently been described includes heterologous prime boost strategies. In this case, an LAIV or a DNA vaccine is used as a priming immunization followed by a booster immunization with inactivated influenza virus vaccine (IIV) or protein vaccine.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup> Here, using the ferret model, we compare a cHA-based LAIV prime—IIV boost immunization regimen with an IIV–IIV immunization regimen with and without the addition of the adjuvant AS03. 
</p>
