<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0080">Under the conditions of in vitro experiments, the degree of virus-induced cytotoxicity (that is, the severity of symptoms) is clearly proportional to the multiplicity of input (amount of virus inoculated). In other words, the greater the amount of virus (or the more frequently the virus infection takes place), the faster (and more strongly) the degree of cell damage (symptoms) appears. The more contagious and infectious the virus, the more difficult it is for the host to control its replication and spread. This explains the effect of high virus doses very well. The enhancing effect of repeated application of lower doses of virus is more complex, but there exist interesting examples in the literature. Using a challenge model by infecting mice repeatedly in short intervals with low doses of influenza A virus, Song et al. reported that compared to a single high-dose infection, mice that received repeated low-dose challenges showed earlier morbidity and mortality and more severe disease 
 <xref rid="b0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. Mice developed higher viral loads, more severe lung pathology, and greater inflammatory responses and generated only limited influenza A virus-specific B and T cell responses. Although several pathways could contribute to higher viral loads in mice that received influenza A virus repeatedly, the authors suggested the possibility that the inflammatory response elicited by the first dose of influenza A virus damaged the mucosal barrier, thus allowing the virus given as a second or third dose to penetrate more deeply into the lungs. Higher viral loads will lead to the induction of stronger cytokine storms. These data are in agreement with clinical findings in humans, where high-risk individuals were exposed to multiple small doses of HBV, as well as in the woodchuck model, in which animals were repeatedly exposed to small quantities of infectious HBV 
 <xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. In both cases, viral infection was molecularly evident and there were detectable virus-specific CD8-T cell responses but undetectable virus-specific antibody responses.
</p>
