<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6976597</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">55730</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-55730-6</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A possible role for autoimmunity through molecular mimicry in alphavirus mediated arthritis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Venigalla</surname><given-names>Siva Sai Krishna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Premakumar</surname><given-names>Sowmya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Janakiraman</surname><given-names>Vani</given-names></name><address><email>vani@iitm.ac.in</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2315 1926</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.417969.4</institution-id><institution>Department of Biotechnology, </institution><institution>Bhupat and Jyoti Mehta School of Biosciences, Indian Institute of Technology Madras, </institution></institution-wrap>Chennai, 600036 India </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>22</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>938</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>3</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>9</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Alphaviral infections are foremost in causing debilitating clinical outcomes in humans characterized by rheumatic arthritis like conditions. Though the presence of virus in joints and associated inflammation has been implicated as one of the reasons for the acute and chronic polyarthritis post alphaviral infections, the basis for rheumatic like outcomes is not clear. Through an <italic>in silico</italic> analysis, we have investigated the possibility of an autoimmune process mediated through molecular mimicry in alphaviral infection induced pathogenicity. Interestingly, sequence alignment of the structural polyproteins belonging to arthritogenic alphaviruses revealed conserved regions which share homology with human proteins implicated in rheumatoid arthritis (RA). These conserved regions were predicted to exhibit binding to HLA class II alleles, showcasing their potential to incite T cell help. Molecular docking of the viral peptide and the corresponding homologous region in the human protein onto HLA-DRB1 revealed strong similarities in their binding patterns. Linear and conformational B cell epitope prediction analyses showed that these potential mimics have high propensity to elicit an efficient B cell response. We thus propose that the origin of polyarthritis post-arthritogenic alphaviral infections may also be mediated through a hitherto unknown autoimmune response due to the presence of cross-reactive epitopes between viral and human proteins.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Computational biology and bioinformatics</kwd><kwd>Autoimmunity</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Alphaviruses belonging to the group IV togoviridae family are positive sense, single stranded RNA viruses. These enveloped viruses are classified as old world and new world. While new world viruses are encephalitogenic, members of the old world are known to induce polyarthritis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. The members of the old world viruses include Chikungunya Virus (CHIKV), Ross River Virus (RRV), Mayaro Virus (MAYV), O&#x02019;nyong nyong virus (ONV), Semiliki Forest Virus (SFV) and the Barmah Forest Virus (BFV). These mosquito transmitted viruses are globally distributed and are known to cause acute febrile illnesses, malaise, maculopapular rashes, myalgia, and severe arthralgia in humans<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. Most often the infection remains endemic, but some viral strains are also associated with large epidemics such as the Chikungunya virus (CHIKV) out-break which was spread across 40 countries with 1.4&#x02013;6.5 million reported cases globally<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Several studies also report a simultaneous increase in alpha virus associated arthritis lasting even after decrease in viral load<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">While there is a resurgence of alphavirus associated arthritis cases, the knowledge about the molecular level events during infections involved in these conditions and about the direct cause and effect of the phenomenon is very sparse. For instance, macrophages, natural killer cells, CD4+ and CD8+ T lymphocytes have been shown as the main components of the inflammatory cellular infiltrate in animal models of CHIKV and RRV infections<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Production of a broad range of pro-inflammatory cytokines (IL-6, TNF, IFN-&#x003b1;/&#x003b2;, and IFN&#x003b3;) and chemokines (MCP-1 and RANTES) post alpha viral infections has also been reported by <italic>Lidbury et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Interestingly, a comparative study between CHIKV infection induced gene expression and rheumatoid arthritis induced gene expression changes in mouse models showed similarity in induced cytokine (TNF, IL-8, IL-15, IFN-&#x003b3;, GM-CSF and lymphotoxin B) profiles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Another study by Morrison <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>, demonstrated the presence of activated complement products in the serum of RRV infected mice, drawing similarities with the pathogenesis of rheumatoid arthritis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">Resemblance between proteins of pathogens and host components has been examined as a trigger for many autoimmune diseases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. In these scenarios, initiation of autoimmune disease by an infectious pathogen is hypothesized to involve immune recognition of self-peptides by way of &#x0201c;molecular mimicry&#x0201d;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup> thereby activating autoreactive T cells and generation of autoantibodies. Previous studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> hypothesized that microbial antigens like pulD from Klebsiella sp., nuclear antigen-1 from Epstein-Barr virus and OSP-A from Borrelia sp. may have a possible association with autoimmune diseases like ankylosing spondylitis, Systemic Lupus Erythematosus (SLE) and Lyme arthritis, respectively. A significant sequence similarity between P2-C protein of Coxsackie virus and glutamate decarboxylase of humans has been proposed as a trigger for Type 1 diabetes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. The similitude in clinical manifestation of an alphaviral infection induced arthralgia and rheumatoid arthritis at both phenotypic and molecular levels suggests that alphaviral infections could be a causative link for rheumatoid arthritis.</p><p id="Par5">Overarching goal of this study is to explore the possibility of existence of peptides in alphaviruses which may set off an autoimmune response resulting in rheumatoid arthritis like symptoms in alphavirus infected patients. Structural polyproteins of the alphaviruses were scanned for the presence of conserved stretches of amino acids that might share homology with sequences in human proteins implicated in rheumatoid arthritis. These conserved regions were validated <italic>in silico</italic> both at sequence and structural level for their immunogenic potential in terms of their ability to act as T and B cell epitopes. Overall, our results posit that polyarthritis associated with alpha viral infections may also involve an autoimmune component due to cross reactivity between viral epitopes and host proteins.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p id="Par6">Arthritogenic alpha viruses such as Chikungunya virus (CHIKV), Ross river virus (RRV), Semiliki forest virus (SFV), Mayaro virus, O&#x02019;nyong-nyong virus (ONV) and Barmah forest virus (BFV) are generally associated with rheumatic diseases in humans, primarily characterized by polyarthralgia and polyarthritis. Although most patients recover within few weeks, the clinical conditions last for 6 months to more than 3 years<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. However, molecular mechanisms contributing to this pathology are not very well understood. In the present study, we show a possible role of autoimmune process mediated through molecular mimicry as a likely cause for arthritic like conditions post alphaviral infections. The overall workflow of the study is depicted in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Computational pipeline for the prediction of possible induction of rheumatoid arthritis through molecular mimicry post alphaviral infection.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_55730_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e306"/></fig></p><sec id="Sec3"><title>Multiple sequence alignment reveals conserved regions in the structural polyproteins of arthritogenic alpha viruses</title><p id="Par7">Alphaviral infections share a common feature of inducing RA like conditions, but the commonality in the alphaviruses leading to such a rheumatic outcome is not known. We hypothesized that the commonality could lie in the structural polyprotein of these viruses. Therefore, we have analyzed the structural polyproteins of six arthritogenic alpha viruses for the presence of conserved regions amongst them. As described in the methods section, amino acid sequences of the structural polyproteins of CHIKV, RRV, SFV, ONV, BFV and Mayaro virus were retrieved from UniProt database and subsequently multiple sequence alignment was performed using MUSCLE. Conserved regions identified are shown in Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>. The positions of the conserved regions have been depicted in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> using the structural polyprotein of the Chikungunya virus as a representative model.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Domain diagram of the regions conserved in the structural polyprotein of the alphaviruses. The regions have been depicted using Chikungunya virus (strain S27 African prototype) structural polyprotein as a representative model.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_55730_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e326"/></fig></p><p id="Par8">The structural polyproteins of arthritogenic alphaviruses are about 71% identical at the primary (amino acid sequence) level. A total of 41 conserved regions were identified in the structural polyproteins, with E1 glycoprotein region exhibiting highest conservancy with 18 conserved regions, followed by p62 and capsid proteins harboring 15 and 8 conserved regions respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Conserved regions across alpha viruses share homology with human proteins implicated in arthritis</title><p id="Par9">To deduce the possibility of autoimmune reactions involved in mediating post alphaviral polyarthralgia through the presence of molecular mimics, we performed a sequence similarity search between the conserved regions among arthritogenic alpha viruses and the human proteome using the standard BLASTp program. Each of the 41 conserved regions was scanned against the human proteome. Very interestingly, 24 regions showed varying degrees of homology (52.7% to 100%) with human proteins that have been implicated in arthritis like conditions in humans (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>List of human proteins sharing homology with conserved regions of structural polyproteins of alphaviruses and shown to contribute to rheumatoid arthritis-like-condition.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Viral peptide</th><th>Human peptide</th><th>Human protein</th><th>UniProt ID</th><th>% similarity</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><underline>FIPT</underline>QTFY</td><td><underline>FIPT</underline></td><td>Ryanodine receptor 1</td><td>P21817</td><td>100%</td></tr><tr><td>KGRVVAIVLGGANEG<underline>ARTALS</underline>VVTW</td><td><underline>ARTALS</underline></td><td>Interleukin-17 receptor C</td><td>Q8NAC3</td><td>100%</td></tr><tr><td>TSAPCT<underline>ITGTM</underline>GHFILARCPKG</td><td><underline>ITGTM</underline></td><td>Monocyte differentiation antigen CD14</td><td>P08571</td><td>100%</td></tr><tr><td><bold>RKGKIHIPF</bold><bold><underline>PLANVT</underline></bold><bold>CMVPKA</bold></td><td><bold><underline>PLANVT</underline></bold></td><td><bold>Alpha-1B-glycoprotein</bold><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup></td><td>P04217</td><td>100%</td></tr><tr><td><underline>PTVTYG</underline>K</td><td><underline>PTVTYG</underline></td><td>Intercellular adhesion molecule 1</td><td>P05362</td><td>100%</td></tr><tr><td><bold>P</bold><bold><underline>TVTY</underline></bold><bold>GK</bold></td><td><bold><underline>TVTY</underline></bold></td><td><bold>Low-density lipoprotein receptor-related protein 2</bold><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup></td><td>P98164</td><td>100%</td></tr><tr><td>CG<underline>TAEC</underline></td><td><underline>TAEC</underline></td><td>Interleukin-23 receptor</td><td>Q5VWK5</td><td>100%</td></tr><tr><td>PDYSCKVFTGVYPFMWGGA<underline>YCFC</underline>D</td><td><underline>YCFC</underline></td><td>Platelet glycoprotein 4</td><td>P16671</td><td>100%</td></tr><tr><td>PDY<underline>SCKVF</underline>TGVYPFMWGGAYCFCD</td><td><underline>SCKVF</underline></td><td>Glucocorticoid receptor</td><td>P04150</td><td>100%</td></tr><tr><td>PDY<underline>SCKVF</underline>TGVYPFMWGGAYCFCD</td><td><underline>SCKVF</underline></td><td>Androgen receptor</td><td>P10275</td><td>100%</td></tr><tr><td>F<underline>STALA</underline>S</td><td><underline>STALA</underline></td><td>Leukocyte cell-derived chemotaxin-2</td><td>O14960</td><td>100%</td></tr><tr><td>PPCIPCC<underline>YEKEPEE</underline>TLRMLEDNV</td><td><underline>YEKEP</underline>G<underline>EE</underline></td><td>Interleukin-1 receptor accessory protein</td><td>Q9NPH3</td><td>87.5%</td></tr><tr><td><bold>YSGGRFTIPTGA</bold><bold><underline>GKPGD</underline></bold><bold>S</bold><bold><underline>G</underline></bold><bold>RPIFDN</bold></td><td><bold><underline>GKPGD</underline></bold><bold>D</bold><bold><underline>G</underline></bold></td><td><bold>Collagen alpha-1(II) chain</bold><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup></td><td>P02458</td><td>86%</td></tr><tr><td>RKGKIHIPF<underline>PLANV</underline>T<underline>C</underline>MVPKA</td><td><underline>PLANV</underline>I<underline>C</underline></td><td>TNF receptor-associated factor 6</td><td>Q9Y4K3</td><td>85.7%</td></tr><tr><td><bold>YNMDYPPFGAGRPGQFGD</bold><bold><underline>I</underline></bold><bold>Q</bold><bold><underline>SRTPE</underline></bold></td><td><bold><underline>I</underline></bold><bold>A</bold><bold><underline>SRTPE</underline></bold></td><td><bold>Annexin A5</bold><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup></td><td>P08758</td><td>85.7%</td></tr><tr><td>DIP<underline>DAAFTR</underline>VVDAP</td><td><underline>DAAFTR</underline>I</td><td>Vitronectin</td><td>P04004</td><td>85.7%</td></tr><tr><td>P<underline>GYY</underline>Q<underline>LL</underline></td><td><underline>GYY</underline>D<underline>LL</underline></td><td>Ryanodine receptor 1</td><td>P21817</td><td>83.3%</td></tr><tr><td>D<underline>GTLKI</underline>QVSLQIG</td><td>N<underline>GTLKI</underline></td><td>T-cell surface antigen CD2</td><td>P06729</td><td>83.3%</td></tr><tr><td>T<underline>SAPCT</underline>ITGTMGHFILARCPKG</td><td><underline>SAPCT</underline>V</td><td>Integrin alpha-IIb</td><td>P08514</td><td>83.3%</td></tr><tr><td>KWQYN<underline>SPLVP</underline>R</td><td>D<underline>SPLVP</underline></td><td>Leptin receptor</td><td>P48357</td><td>83.3%</td></tr><tr><td>KWQYN<underline>SP</underline>L<underline>VPR</underline></td><td><underline>SP</underline>I<underline>VPR</underline></td><td>Peptidoglycan recognition protein 1</td><td>O75594</td><td>83.3%</td></tr><tr><td><bold>QAP</bold><bold><underline>SGF</underline></bold><bold>K</bold><bold><underline>YW</underline></bold><bold>LKE</bold></td><td><bold><underline>SGF</underline></bold><bold>I</bold><bold><underline>YW</underline></bold></td><td><bold>Low-density lipoprotein receptor-related protein 2</bold><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup></td><td>P98164</td><td>83.3%</td></tr><tr><td><underline>DGTL</underline>KI<underline>QV</underline>SLQIG</td><td><underline>DGTL</underline>F<underline>K</underline>V<underline>QV</underline></td><td>Beta-sarcoglycan</td><td>Q16585</td><td>77.8%</td></tr><tr><td>M<underline>KS</underline>D<underline>A</underline>S<underline>KFT</underline>HEKPEGYYNWHHGAVQ</td><td><underline>KS</underline>E<underline>A</underline>D<underline>KFT</underline></td><td>Immunoglobulin superfamily member 6</td><td>O95976</td><td>75%</td></tr><tr><td>YSGGRFTIPTG<underline>AG</underline>K<underline>PG</underline>D<underline>SG</underline>RPIFDN</td><td><underline>AG</underline>R<underline>PG</underline>N<underline>SG</underline></td><td>Macrophage scavenger receptor types I and II</td><td>P21757</td><td>75%</td></tr><tr><td>KFIVGPMSSAWTP<underline>FDN</underline>KI<underline>VVY</underline>KGDV</td><td><underline>FDN</underline>TT<underline>VVY</underline></td><td>Interleukin-23 receptor</td><td>Q5VWK5</td><td>75%</td></tr><tr><td>SKDVYAN<underline>T</underline>QLV<underline>LQRP</underline>AAGTVHVPYS</td><td><underline>T</underline>KLL<underline>LQRP</underline></td><td>High affinity immunoglobulin gamma Fc receptor I</td><td>P12314</td><td>75%</td></tr><tr><td>APFGCQIATNPVRAMNC<underline>A</underline>V<underline>G</underline>N<underline>MPIS</underline></td><td><underline>A</underline>L<underline>G</underline>Q<underline>MPIS</underline></td><td>Coagulation factor V</td><td>P12259</td><td>75%</td></tr><tr><td>RKGKIHIPF<underline>P</underline>LA<underline>NVTC</underline>MVPKA</td><td><underline>P</underline>MV<underline>NVTC</underline></td><td>MHC class I polypeptide-related sequence B</td><td>Q29980</td><td>71.4%</td></tr><tr><td>KFIVGPMSSA<underline>W</underline>T<underline>PF</underline>D<underline>NK</underline>IVVYKGDV</td><td><underline>W</underline>I<underline>PF</underline>Q<underline>NK</underline></td><td>Lymphocyte antigen 75</td><td>O60449</td><td>71.4%</td></tr><tr><td>KPGRRERMCMKI<underline>EN</underline>D<underline>C</underline>I<underline>FE</underline>VK</td><td><underline>EN</underline>E<underline>C</underline>F<underline>FE</underline></td><td>Protocadherin-9</td><td>Q9HC56</td><td>71%</td></tr><tr><td><bold>SKDVYANTQLVL</bold><bold><underline>Q</underline></bold><bold>R</bold><bold><underline>PAAGTV</underline></bold><bold>H</bold><bold><underline>VP</underline></bold><bold>YS</bold></td><td><bold><underline>Q</underline></bold><bold>S</bold><bold><underline>PAAGTV</underline></bold><bold>QGR</bold><bold><underline>VP</underline></bold></td><td><bold>Cartilage intermediate layer protein 1</bold><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup></td><td>O75339</td><td>69.2%</td></tr><tr><td>FI<underline>PT</underline>QT<underline>FY</underline></td><td><underline>PT</underline>EK<underline>FY</underline></td><td>Complement C3</td><td>P01024</td><td>67%</td></tr><tr><td><underline>CG</underline>T<underline>A</underline>E<underline>C</underline></td><td><underline>CG</underline>V<underline>A</underline>Q<underline>C</underline></td><td>Integrin alpha-V</td><td>P06756</td><td>66.6%</td></tr><tr><td>RKGKIH<underline>IP</underline>F<underline>PLA</underline>N<underline>VTC</underline>M<underline>V</underline>PKA</td><td><underline>IP</underline>I<underline>PLA</underline>-<underline>V</underline>IT<underline>TC</underline>I<underline>V</underline></td><td>Lymphocyte function-associated antigen 3</td><td>P19256</td><td>64. 3%</td></tr><tr><td>NADLAKLAFKRSSK<underline>YDL</underline>E<underline>CA</underline>Q<underline>IP</underline>VH</td><td><underline>YDL</underline>D<underline>C</underline>PT<underline>A</underline>P<underline>IP</underline></td><td>TNF receptor-associated factor 6</td><td>Q9Y4K3</td><td>64%</td></tr><tr><td><underline>FI</underline>P<underline>TQTF</underline>Y</td><td><underline>FI</underline>S<underline>TQ</underline>QQV<underline>TF</underline></td><td>High affinity immunoglobulin epsilon receptor subunit alpha</td><td>P12319</td><td>60%</td></tr><tr><td>P<underline>GYYQLL</underline></td><td><underline>GY</underline>RETR<underline>YQLL</underline></td><td>N-alpha-acetyltransferase 16</td><td>Q6N069</td><td>60%</td></tr><tr><td><underline>PTVTYG</underline>K</td><td><underline>PTVT</underline>TGSG<underline>YG</underline></td><td>V-set and immunoglobulin domain-containing protein 4</td><td>Q9Y279</td><td>60%</td></tr><tr><td>RKGKIH<underline>IP</underline>FP<underline>LA</underline>N<underline>VTC</underline>MV<underline>P</underline>KA</td><td><underline>IP</underline>Y-<underline>LA</underline>TD<underline>VTC</underline>VG<underline>P</underline></td><td>Toll-like receptor 7</td><td>Q9NYK1</td><td>57.1%</td></tr><tr><td><bold>E</bold><bold><underline>GL</underline></bold><bold>E</bold><bold><underline>V</underline></bold><bold>T</bold><bold><underline>W</underline></bold><bold>GNN</bold></td><td><bold>D</bold><bold><underline>GL</underline></bold><bold>D</bold><bold><underline>V</underline></bold><bold>S</bold><bold><underline>W</underline></bold></td><td><bold>Chitinase-3-like protein 2</bold><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup></td><td>Q15782</td><td>57.1%</td></tr><tr><td><bold>F</bold><bold><underline>IP</underline></bold><bold>TQT</bold><bold><underline>FY</underline></bold></td><td><bold><underline>IP</underline></bold><bold>SRS</bold><bold><underline>FY</underline></bold></td><td><bold>Cartilage intermediate layer protein 1</bold><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup></td><td>O75339</td><td>57%</td></tr><tr><td><bold>MKSD</bold><bold><underline>A</underline></bold><bold>S</bold><bold><underline>KFT</underline></bold><bold>HEK</bold><bold><underline>P</underline></bold><bold>EG</bold><bold><underline>YY</underline></bold><bold>NWHHGAVQ</bold></td><td><bold><underline>A</underline></bold><bold>N</bold><bold><underline>KFT</underline></bold><bold>ETNPQV</bold><bold><underline>YY</underline></bold></td><td><bold>Low-density lipoprotein receptor-related protein 2</bold><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup></td><td>P98164</td><td>54%</td></tr><tr><td>AYEHVTVI<underline>P</underline>N<underline>TVGVP</underline>YKTLVN<underline>R</underline>P<underline>GY</underline></td><td><underline>P</underline>A<underline>TVGV</underline>TQ<underline>PY</underline>&#x02013;LD<underline>R</underline>L<underline>GY</underline></td><td>Cartilage intermediate layer protein 2</td><td>Q8IUL8</td><td>52.6%</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Human proteins highlighted in bold are experimentally proven to have antibodies developed against them in patients diagnosed with rheumatoid arthritis.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Potential mimic regions harbor HLA binding motifs</title><p id="Par10">Human leukocyte antigen (HLA) is the most widely distributed molecule with high level of polymorphism and are the major governing factors in initiating cellular immune responses. It is thus important that immunogenic peptides bind to multiple HLA alleles to elicit a strong immune response. The 24 conserved regions of the structural polyprotein (refer Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) were analyzed for HLA class II binding ability using propred II server. The nonameric peptides generated from each conserved region were scanned against 51 HLA alleles available in the ProPred II server. The number of nonameric peptides generated from each of 24 conserved regions and the number of peptides predicted to bind to different alleles is summarized in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. Peptides generated from 19 of the conserved regions bound to at least one HLA allele, while the peptides from the remaining 5 of the conserved regions did not bind to any of the alleles.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>HLA binding profiles of potential mimics from the alpha viral structural proteins. A total of 51 HLA class II alleles were used for the study.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Peptide</th><th rowspan="2">Peptide Length (aa)</th><th colspan="3">Binding profile -HLA Class II</th></tr><tr><th>Nonamers generated</th><th>Nonamers bound</th><th>% binding</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>PPCIPCCYEKEPEETLRMLEDNV</td><td>23</td><td>15</td><td>0</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>PTVTYGK</td><td>7</td><td>5</td><td>0</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>EGLEVTWGNN</td><td>10</td><td>2</td><td>0</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>QAPSGFKYWLKE</td><td>12</td><td>4</td><td>0</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>DIPDFTRVVDAP</td><td>14</td><td>6</td><td>0</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>KPGRRERMCMKIENDCIFEVK</td><td>21</td><td>13</td><td>3</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>NADLAKLAFKRSSKYDLECAQIPVH</td><td>25</td><td>17</td><td>1</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>MKSDASKFTHEKPEGYYNWHHGAVQ</td><td>25</td><td>17</td><td>1</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>YSGGRFTIPTGAGKPGDSGRPIFDN</td><td>25</td><td>17</td><td>1</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>YNMDYPPFGAGRPGQFGDIQSRTPE</td><td>25</td><td>17</td><td>2</td><td>12</td></tr><tr><td>SKDVYANTQLVLQRPGTVHVPYS</td><td>25</td><td>17</td><td>2</td><td>12</td></tr><tr><td>APFGCQIATNPVRAMNCAVGNMPIS</td><td>25</td><td>17</td><td>2</td><td>12</td></tr><tr><td>RKGKIHIPFPLANVTCMVPKA</td><td>21</td><td>13</td><td>2</td><td>15</td></tr><tr><td>KGRVVAIVLGGANEGARTALSVVTW</td><td>25</td><td>17</td><td>3</td><td>17</td></tr><tr><td>KFIVGPMSSAWTPFDNKIVVYKGDV</td><td>25</td><td>17</td><td>3</td><td>18</td></tr><tr><td>PDYSCKVFTGVYPFMWGGAYCFCD</td><td>24</td><td>16</td><td>3</td><td>19</td></tr><tr><td>PGYYQLL</td><td>7</td><td>5</td><td>1</td><td>20</td></tr><tr><td>DGTLKIQVSLQIG</td><td>13</td><td>5</td><td>1</td><td>20</td></tr><tr><td>FSTALAS</td><td>7</td><td>5</td><td>1</td><td>20</td></tr><tr><td>TSAPCTITGTMGHFILARCPKG</td><td>22</td><td>14</td><td>3</td><td>21</td></tr><tr><td>AYEHVTVIPNTVGVPYKTLVNRPGY</td><td>25</td><td>17</td><td>4</td><td>24</td></tr><tr><td>CGTAEC</td><td>12</td><td>4</td><td>1</td><td>25</td></tr><tr><td>KWQYNSPLVPR</td><td>11</td><td>3</td><td>1</td><td>33</td></tr><tr><td>FIPTQTFY</td><td>8</td><td>5</td><td>2</td><td>40</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par11">As illustrated in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, maximum numbers of nonamers were found to be recognized by the allele HLA DRB1_0308, which bound to nine of the conserved region peptides. DRB1_0101 bound to eight and DRB1_1321 bound to seven, DRB1_0102, 0401, 0426, 1101, 1107 and 1120 bound to six conserved region peptides respectively.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Number of conserved regions from alpha virus structural proteins binding to individual class II alleles as predicted by ProPred II server. Alleles that exhibited binding to more than 3 peptides are represented out of the 51 alleles studied.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_55730_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e2050"/></fig></p><p id="Par12">Since the quality of immune response elicited by the mimic peptide in humans should be similar to the one elicited by the viral peptide for an efficient autoimmune response to occur, the structure of the HLA DRII-peptide complex was analyzed. Molecular docking analysis was performed to assess the structural similarity in the binding patterns of the viral peptide and its homologous region in the human protein. The ability of one of the potential conserved regions, FPLANVTCM (viral derived) and its corresponding homologous region KPLANVTLM (human derived) to bind to a class II HLA allele was assessed by docking the peptides in the binding groove of HLA-DRB1, an allele known to predispose individuals to rheumatoid arthritis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. The peptides were docked using GalaxyPepDock server and the docked peptides are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>. The root mean square deviation between the docked peptides shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> is 0.86&#x02009;&#x000c5;.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>A Structural representation of the peptide-MHC complex generated by docking of the peptide F<underline>PLANVT</underline>CM from the alpha virus structural polyproteins (cyan) and the peptide K<underline>PLANVT</underline>LM from the alpha 1-B glycoprotein of human (red) into the binding groove of HLA-DRB1. Both the peptides exhibit similar fit and interactions with the amino acids (yellow) in the binding pocket of HLA.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_55730_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e2077"/></fig></p><p id="Par13">The docked p-MHC complexes were analyzed for the hydrogen bonding interactions between the peptides and HLA-DRB1. The binding interactions between the viral and human peptide with HLA-DRB1 were visualized using LigPlot+. Post docking analysis of the peptides revealed significant interactions with HLA-DRB1. In viral peptide-HLA-DRB1 complex, ten hydrogen bonds within a distance of 3.5&#x02009;&#x000c5; suggested the stability of the peptide in the binding groove of the pocket. Similarly, a set of eleven hydrogen bonds were formed between human peptide and HLA-DRB1 within a distance of 3.5&#x02009;&#x000c5;. Furthermore, it can be seen in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> that the amino acids in the conserved regions of both the peptides form identical hydrogen bonds with the amino acids (Ser51, Asn260, Lys249, Trp235, Asn67, Tyr 208) present in the binding pocket of HLA-DRB1.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Analysis of molecular interactions of viral peptide docked onto HLA-DRB1 (top) and its homologous region in the human protein docked onto HLA-DRB1 (bottom).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_55730_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e2091"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Potential mimics could also act as B cell epitopes</title><p id="Par14">To further strengthen the case of alpha viral induced molecular mimicry, we have analyzed the 24 conserved regions for the presence of both linear and structural B cell epitopes which in turn is a measure of their ability to act as stimulators of B cells and generate an autoimmune reaction against its homologous region in the human protein leading to polyarthralgia. Linear B cell epitope prediction was performed using three different prediction algorithms namely Bepipred linear epitope prediction, Emini surface accessibility scale and Kolaskar and Tongaonkar antigenicity scale. Prediction results are summarized in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Analysis of conserved regions of alpha viruses sharing homology with human peptides (refer Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) for their ability to act as B cell epitopes.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Conserved region</th><th>Bepipred</th><th>ESA</th><th>KT</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>FIPTQTFY</td><td>&#x000d7;</td><td>&#x000d7;</td><td>&#x000d7;</td></tr><tr><td>KPGRRERMCMKIENDCIFEVK</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td></tr><tr><td>NADLAKLAFKRSSKYDLECAQIPVH</td><td>&#x000d7;</td><td>&#x000d7;</td><td>&#x02713;</td></tr><tr><td>MKSDASKFTHEKPEGYYNWHHGAVQ</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x000d7;</td><td>&#x02713;</td></tr><tr><td>YSGGRFTIPTGAGKPGDSGRPIFDN</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x000d7;</td><td>&#x000d7;</td></tr><tr><td>KGRVVAIVLGGANEGARTALSVVTW</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x000d7;</td><td>&#x02713;</td></tr><tr><td>PPCIPCCYEKEPEETLRMLEDNV</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td></tr><tr><td>PGYYQLL</td><td>&#x000d7;</td><td>&#x000d7;</td><td>&#x02713;</td></tr><tr><td>DGTLKIQVSLQIG</td><td>&#x000d7;</td><td>&#x000d7;</td><td>&#x02713;</td></tr><tr><td>TSAPCTITGTMGHFILARCPKG</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x000d7;</td><td>&#x02713;</td></tr><tr><td>KWQYNSPLVPR</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td></tr><tr><td>RKGKIHIPFPLANVTCMVPKA</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x000d7;</td><td>&#x02713;</td></tr><tr><td>PTVTYGK</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x000d7;</td><td>&#x000d7;</td></tr><tr><td>EGLEVTWGNN</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x000d7;</td><td>&#x000d7;</td></tr><tr><td>AYEHVTVIPNTVGVPYKTLVNRPGY</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x000d7;</td><td>&#x02713;</td></tr><tr><td>CGTAEC</td><td>&#x000d7;</td><td>&#x000d7;</td><td>&#x000d7;</td></tr><tr><td>PDYSCKVFTGVYPFMWGGAYCFCD</td><td>&#x000d7;</td><td>&#x000d7;</td><td>&#x02713;</td></tr><tr><td>KFIVGPMSSAWTPFDNKIVVYKGDV</td><td>&#x000d7;</td><td>&#x000d7;</td><td>&#x02713;</td></tr><tr><td>YNMDYPPFGAGRPGQFGDIQSRTPE</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x000d7;</td></tr><tr><td>SKDVYANTQLVLQRPAAGTVHVPYS</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td></tr><tr><td>QAPSGFKYWLKE</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x000d7;</td></tr><tr><td>APFGCQIATNPVRAMNCAVGNMPIS</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x000d7;</td><td>&#x02713;</td></tr><tr><td>DIPDAAFTRVVDAP</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td/><td>&#x02713;</td></tr><tr><td>FSTALAS</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x000d7;</td><td>&#x02713;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The algorithms used for prediction are Bepipred, Emini Surface Accessibility Area (ESA), Kolaskar and Tongaonkar (KT). Tick (&#x02713;) indicates that it is a predicted potential B cell epitope and cross (&#x000d7;) indicates that it is not a potential B cell epitope.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par15">Out of the 24 conserved regions analyzed, 5 regions were predicted to be plausible B cell epitopes by all the three algorithms. 6 regions were predicted to be plausible B cell epitopes by at least 2 of the 3 algorithms tested. 12 regions were predicted to be B cell epitopes by only one of the algorithm. Only one out of the 24 conserved regions was not predicted as B cell epitope by all the three algorithms.</p><p id="Par16">Interestingly, 9 out of the 24 conserved regions shared homology with human proteins which were experimentally proven to have antibodies developed against them in patients diagnosed with rheumatoid arthritis (highlighted in bold in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par17">To further validate if the potential mimics could act as plausible B cell epitopes also at a conformational level, CHIKV structural polyprotein was used as a model to locate conformational B cell epitopes using Ellipro server from IEDB. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>, the parts of the peptides MKSDASKFTHEKPEGYYNWHHGAVQ and YSGGRFTIPTGAGKPGDSGRPIFDN (labelled A in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>) present on the Capsid protein, the part of the peptide RKGKIHIPFPLANVTCMVPKA (labelled B), PTVTYGK (labelled C) and EGLEVTWGNN (labelled D) present on the p62 protein are exposed to the surface and predicted to be potential conformational B cell epitopes.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Epitopes predicted based on the 3D structure of the Chikungunya virus structural polyprotein (PDB ID: 3J2W) using ElliPro. The predicted peptides are shown in sphere representation and are colored yellow.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_55730_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e2468"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par18">Viral infection as one of the etiological agents for autoimmune diseases is being discussed for a long time. Several mechanisms have been proposed to explain this phenomenon including molecular mimicry, bystander activation and viral persistence<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> individually or in multiple combinations to account for the immunopathology observed at the site of infection and/or sites of autoimmune disease and normally the infections precede the occurrence of inflammation in the target organ<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Triggered immune response as result of infection is critical for viral clearance. However, in some instances, immune regulatory mechanisms may aberrate, leading to the breakdown of self-tolerance, resulting in immune-mediated attack directed against both viral and self-antigens as it happens in the case of molecular mimicry or shared homology between viral and host epitopes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par19">Human infections caused by the alphaviruses group share a common feature of the clinical picture of arthralgia and chronic arthritis that closely resembles rheumatoid arthritis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Further, more severe and delayed recovery of alpha viral disease in patients with pre-existing arthritic conditions has been reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Though the cellular components and inflammatory scenario involved in such conditions have been looked at<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>, knowledge about the actual cause of such persistent symptoms characterized by articular disease and myalgia remains sparse. Though one of the speculations regarding the basis for this rheumatic like manifestations is the possible induction of autoimmunity as a side effect of adaptive immune responses, caused by cross-reactivity between viral and host antigens<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>, there are no systematic studies towards proving this hypothesis.</p><p id="Par20">In the present work, through an <italic>in silico</italic> analysis we have identified the presence of conserved regions in the structural polyprotein of alphaviruses. A high sequence identity (71%) suggests that the origin of commonality in the clinical features may lie in the amino acid sequence of the structural polyprotein of the viruses. On comparative analysis of these regions of consensus with the human proteome, we have identified proteins that share stretches of homologous regions with the structural polyprotein. Further, very interestingly we found that presence of auto antibodies specific to some of these proteins in rheumatoid arthritis (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Serum and synovial fluid from RA patients have been shown to contain auto antibodies specific to some of the proteins that we identified in our analysis. These proteins are highlighted in table-1. The underlined region of the peptide <underline>SKDVYANTQLVLQRPAA</underline>GTVHVPYS has been experimentally tested in mice to induce polyarthralgia. The mouse injected with this peptide recapitulated the pathology seen chikungunya infection<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. These reports give further credibility to our findings and strengthen our current premise.</p><p id="Par21">Our results further show that these regions are immuno-dominant stressing their ability for induction of potential auto-immune reaction. Based on the amino acid sequence analysis, twenty-four of the conserved regions (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) bound to HLA class II alleles, suggesting the possibility of calling in for T helper cell responses. Three conserved regions were predicted to be potential B cell epitopes by all the algorithms tested. Since majority of the antigenic epitopes have been shown to have high surface accessibility, we hypothesized that identical amino acids would give rise to similar structural features too. Therefore, we validated the antigenicity of chosen conserved regions at structural level. The root mean square deviation between the peptides is 0.86&#x02009;&#x000c5; which suggests that the two peptides bind to class II MHC in a similar orientation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Docking the conserved region (FPLANVTCM) from the structural polyprotein and its homologous sequence in the human proteome revealed similar interactions with HLA-DRB1 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Plausible B cell epitope prediction analysis based on the structure of CHIKV structural polyprotein concurred with some of the conserved regions we identified. Thus, validation at both the amino acid and structural level affirmed the antigenic potential of conserved regions in the structural polyprotein. In addition, through the revelation of presence of significant conserved regions in the alphaviral proteins, we surmise that antibodies for differential diagnosis of alpha virus infections should be directed towards the non-conserved regions of the structural proteins for higher specificity. In summary (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>), our results computationally tease out a possible mechanism mediated through molecular mimicry leading to development of autoimmunity during alpha virus infections which could culminate in arthritis like conditions in infected individuals.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Highly conserved peptide sequences present in the structural polyprotein of alphaviruses are antigenic and could act as a trigger for autoimmune reactions explaining one of the possible origins for polyarthritis post-arthritogenic alphaviral infections.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_55730_Fig7_HTML" id="d29e2553"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>Viral protein sequences</title><p id="Par22">We carried out the bioinformatic analysis using protein sequences available for the clinical isolates of alphaviruses known to cause polyarthralgia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup> and used as protype strains in the literature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Structural polyproteins of the six arthritogenic alphaviruses: Chikungunya virus (strain S2-African prototype)(UniProt ID: Q8JUX5), the Ross river virus (strain NB5092) (UniProt ID: P13890), the Semliki forest virus (UniProt ID: P03315), the Mayaro virus (strain Brazil) (UniProt ID: Q8QZ72), the O&#x02019;nyong-nyong virus (strain SG650) (UniProt ID: O90369) and the Barmah forest virus (UniProt ID: P89946) were investigated for the presence of conserved regions. Amino acid sequences of these proteins were retrieved from the UniProt database<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Multiple sequence alignment</title><p id="Par23">Conserved regions within the structural polyproteins were identified by multiple sequence alignment using MUSCLE alignment algorithm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup> in MEGA 7.0<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. A stretch of amino acids was scored as conserved region if it is present in at least four out of the six alpha viruses.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Homology search</title><p id="Par24">BLASTp program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi">https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup> was employed to expound the existence of sequence homology between the conserved regions identified in the alpha viruses and the human proteome. The search set was limited to <italic>Homo sapiens</italic> (taxid: 9606) in the UniProtKB/Swiss-Prot database. Default BLASTp algorithm parameters were used and the results were limited only to the top 100 hits.</p><p id="Par25">The homologous proteins list obtained from the BLAST search was manually curated using the Open Targets Platform server<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup> to identify if a given protein has been reported to be involved in the pathogenesis of rheumatoid arthritis. The Open Targets Platform server is a repository of human proteins and their involvement in diseases at various levels. These proteins bearing the homologous sequences to conserved regions within the structural polyproteins were chosen for further investigation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Prediction of potential T cell epitopes</title><p id="Par26">The shortlisted conserved regions in the structural polyprotein were explored for their ability to act as T cell epitopes. Peptides from these regions were subjected to HLA II binding analysis using ProPred II analysis tool<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. The server uses quantitative matrices for predicting binding of nonamers to HLA class II. Quantitative matrices are chosen for predictive binding because they provide a linear model and are easy to implement. Nonameric peptides generated from the conserved regions, which were predicted as potential binders for HLA class II alleles were selected for further analysis. A frequency distribution of the ability of these peptides to bind to multiple HLA class II alleles was generated.</p><p id="Par27">Peptide-MHC docking was performed using GalaxyPepDock<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup> server to evaluate the similarity in binding patterns among a conserved region in the alphavirus structural polyprotein and its corresponding homologous region in the human protein. GalaxyPepDock works by identifying templates from experimentally resolved structure databases to predict the protein structure, followed by an energy-based optimization to provide structural flexibility. Default parameters available with the tool have been used and the back-end data containing the parameters used for docking are not available. Crystal structure of HLA-DRB1 complexed with Type II collagen peptide (PDB ID: 6BIN) was retrieved from Protein Data Bank database<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. The resident peptide in the crystal structure was stripped off using PyMol to make the binding groove of HLA-DRB1 available for docking the viral peptide and its human homologue.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Prediction of potential linear B cell epitopes</title><p id="Par28">Shortlisted conserved regions from the structural polyprotein were explored for their ability to act as B cell epitopes. Full length amino acid sequence of structural polyprotein of Chikungunya virus (strain S27-African prototype) (UniProt ID: Q8JUX5) was subjected to linear B cell epitope prediction analysis available at Immune epitope database (IEDB)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. The analysis was performed using three different prediction algorithms namely, Bipipred, Emini surface accessibility and Kolaskar and Tongaonkar with default algorithm parameters.</p><p id="Par29">Further, to validate if the conserved regions act as potential linear B cell epitopes at the structural level, we employed ElliPro server<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup> to predict the regions on the structural polyprotein of the Chikungunya virus (PDB ID: 3J2W). ElliPro accepts a PDB structure as input and uses three different algorithms based on protrusion index of the residues, protein shape approximation and neighboring residues clustering to predict linear antibody-based epitopes. Default parameters of the ElliPro program were used for prediction analysis.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec14"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2019_55730_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p>is available for this paper at 10.1038/s41598-019-55730-6.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Dr. Nagasuma Chandra, Department of Biochemistry, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore, India, for the discussions on T cell epitope predictions and comments on the work. VJ acknowledges funding from IIT Madras vide grants BIO/14-15/645/NFSG.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>V.J. contributed to the concept, design, and analysis of the study and editing of the manuscript. S.S.K.V. performed the work and contributed to analysis of the data and writing of the manuscript. S.P. contributed for part of HLA peptide binding prediction analysis.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All the viral sequences used for analysis were retrieved are from publicly available databases. Criteria used for analyzing and short listing peptide sequences have been explained clearly in materials and methods section. Most of the softwares used for HLA class II-peptide binding prediction and B cell epitope prediction are also available on the public domain and have been referenced accordingly. Protein structures used are from protein data bank and the relevant literature has been cited wherever appropriate. The other raw datasets generated during and/or analyzed during the study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request. We declare that we will be fully willing to comply with the journal policy and will be able to make any materials/data available required for the review process and thereafter.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par30">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>New world and old world alphaviruses have evolved to exploit different components of stress granules, FXR and G3BP Proteins, for assembly of viral replication complexes</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2016</year><volume>12</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>e1005810</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1005810</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27509095?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27509095</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rulli</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Melton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilmes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ewart</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahalingam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The molecular and cellular aspects of arthritis due to alphavirus infections: lesson learned from Ross River virus</article-title><source>Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences</source><year>2007</year><volume>1102</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>96</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1196/annals.1408.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17470914?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17470914</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burt</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahalingam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chikungunya virus and arthritic disease</article-title><source>The Lancet. Infectious diseases</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>789</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(14)70869-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25164188?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25164188</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Receveur</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Grandadam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pistone</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Malvy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Infection with Mayaro virus in a French traveller returning from the Amazon region, Brazil, January, 2010</article-title><source>Eurosurveillance</source><year>2010</year><volume>15</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>19563</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2807/ese.15.18.19563-en</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20460093?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20460093</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurkela</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Helve</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaheri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vapalahti</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arthritis and arthralgia three years after Sindbis virus infection: clinical follow-up of a cohort of 49 patients</article-title><source>Scandinavian journal of infectious diseases</source><year>2008</year><volume>40</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00365540701586996</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17852949?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17852949</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suhrbier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaffar-Bandjee</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasque</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arthritogenic alphaviruses&#x02014;an overview. <italic>Nature Reviews</italic></article-title><source>Rheumatology</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>420</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrrheum.2012.64</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22565316?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22565316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toivanen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alphaviruses: an emerging cause of arthritis?</article-title><source>Current opinion in rheumatology</source><year>2008</year><volume>20</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>486</fpage><lpage>490</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/BOR.0b013e328303220b</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18525365?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18525365</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chikungunya virus arthritis in adult wild-type mice</article-title><source>Journal of virology</source><year>2010</year><volume>84</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>8021</fpage><lpage>8032</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.02603-09</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20519386?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20519386</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A mouse model of chikungunya virus&#x02013;induced musculoskeletal inflammatory disease: evidence of arthritis, tenosynovitis, myositis, and persistence</article-title><source>The American journal of pathology</source><year>2011</year><volume>178</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>32</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajpath.2010.11.018</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21224040?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21224040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterization of Ross River virus tropism and virus-induced inflammation in a mouse model of viral arthritis and myositis</article-title><source>Journal of virology</source><year>2006</year><volume>80</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>737</fpage><lpage>749</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.80.2.737-749.2006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16378976?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16378976</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lidbury</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Macrophage-derived proinflammatory factors contribute to the development of arthritis and myositis after infection with an arthrogenic alphavirus</article-title><source>The Journal of infectious diseases</source><year>2008</year><volume>197</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1585</fpage><lpage>1593</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/587841</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18433328?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18433328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakaya</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene profiling of Chikungunya virus arthritis in a mouse model reveals significant overlap with rheumatoid arthritis</article-title><source>Arthritis &#x00026; Rheumatism</source><year>2012</year><volume>64</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>3553</fpage><lpage>3563</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/art.34631</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22833339</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahalingam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Heise</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complement contributes to inflammatory tissue destruction in a mouse model of Ross River virus-induced disease</article-title><source>Journal of virology</source><year>2007</year><volume>81</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>5132</fpage><lpage>5143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.02799-06</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17314163?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17314163</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benedek</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The history of bacteriologic concepts of rheumatic fever and rheumatoid arthritis</article-title><source>Seminars in arthritis and rheumatism</source><year>2006</year><volume>36</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.semarthrit.2006.05.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16884972?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16884972</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Croxford</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Calenoff</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dal Canto</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A virus-induced molecular mimicry model of multiple sclerosis</article-title><source>The Journal of clinical investigation</source><year>2001</year><volume>108</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI13032</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11457884?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11457884</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fielder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular mimicry and ankylosing spondylitis: possible role of a novel sequence in pullulanase of Klebsiella pneumoniae</article-title><source>FEBS letters</source><year>1995</year><volume>369</volume><issue>2&#x02013;3</issue><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0014-5793(95)00760-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7649265?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7649265</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McClain</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Early events in lupus humoral autoimmunity suggest initiation through molecular mimicry</article-title><source>Nature medicine</source><year>2005</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>85</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm1167</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15619631?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15619631</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cellular immunity to a determinant common to glutamate decarboxylase and coxsackie virus in insulin-dependent diabetes</article-title><source>The Journal of clinical investigation</source><year>1994</year><volume>94</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>2125</fpage><lpage>2129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI117567</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7962558?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7962558</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scally</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A molecular basis for the association of the HLA-DRB1 locus, citrullination, and rheumatoid arthritis</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Medicine</source><year>2013</year><volume>210</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2569</fpage><lpage>2582</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20131241</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24190431?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24190431</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wucherpfennig</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms for the induction of autoimmunity by infectious agents</article-title><source>The Journal of clinical investigation</source><year>2001</year><volume>108</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1097</fpage><lpage>1104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI14235</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11602615?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11602615</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujinami</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>von Herrath</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Christen</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitton</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular mimicry, bystander activation, or viral persistence: infections and autoimmune disease</article-title><source>Clinical microbiology reviews</source><year>2006</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.19.1.80-94.2006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16418524?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16418524</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Getts</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chastain</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Terry</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Virus infection, antiviral immunity, and autoimmunity</article-title><source>Immunological reviews</source><year>2013</year><volume>255</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/imr.12091</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23947356?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23947356</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Segal</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoenfeld</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vaccine-induced autoimmunity: the role of molecular mimicry and immune crossreaction</article-title><source>Cellular &#x00026; molecular immunology</source><year>2018</year><volume>15</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>586</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cmi.2017.151</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29503439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marks, M. &#x00026; Marks, J. L. Viral arthritis. <italic>Clinical Medicine</italic>. <bold>16</bold>(2), 129&#x02013;134, 10.7861%2Fclinmedicine.16-2-129 (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wesula Olivia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global emergence of alphaviruses that cause arthritis in humans</article-title><source>Infection ecology &#x00026; epidemiology</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>29853</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3402/iee.v5.29853</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26689654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Arthritogenic alphaviruses: new insights into arthritis and bone pathology</article-title><source>Trends in microbiology</source><year>2015</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tim.2014.09.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25449049?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25449049</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Assun&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o-Miranda</surname><given-names>Iranaia</given-names></name><name><surname>Cruz-Oliveira</surname><given-names>Christine</given-names></name><name><surname>Da Poian</surname><given-names>Andrea T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular Mechanisms Involved in the Pathogenesis of Alphavirus-Induced Arthritis</article-title><source>BioMed Research International</source><year>2013</year><volume>2013</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2013/973516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biology and pathogenesis of chikungunya virus</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Microbiology</source><year>2010</year><volume>8</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>491</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro2368</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20551973?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20551973</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Krishna</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasanthapuram</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular mimicry between chikungunya virus and host components: a possible mechanism for the arthritic manifestations</article-title><source>PLoS neglected tropical diseases</source><year>2017</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e0005238</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0005238</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28125580?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28125580</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Newala epidemic: III. The virus: isolation, pathogenic properties and relationship to the epidemic. <italic>Epidemiology &#x00026;</italic></article-title><source>Infection</source><year>1956</year><volume>54</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0022172400044442</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faragher</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Meek</surname><given-names>ADJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalgarno</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome sequences of a mouse-avirulent and a mouse-virulent strain of Ross River virus</article-title><source>Virology</source><year>1988</year><volume>163</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>509</fpage><lpage>526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0042-6822(88)90292-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 2833022?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2833022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mota</surname><given-names>MTO</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Complete genome sequence of Mayaro virus imported from the Amazon basin to Sao Paulo State, Brazil</article-title><source>Genome Announc.</source><year>2015</year><volume>3</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>e01341</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/genomeA.01341-15</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26607884?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26607884</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lanciotti</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Emergence of epidemic O&#x02019;nyong-nyong fever in Uganda after a 35-year absence: genetic characterization of the virus</article-title><source>Virology</source><year>1998</year><volume>252</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>258</fpage><lpage>268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/viro.1998.9437</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9875334?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9875334</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>UniProt Consortium</collab></person-group><article-title>UniProt: a hub for protein information</article-title><source>Nucleic acids research.</source><year>2014</year><volume>43.D1</volume><fpage>D204</fpage><lpage>D212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gku989</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25348405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughput</article-title><source>Nucleic acids research</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1792</fpage><lpage>1797</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkh340</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15034147?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15034147</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MEGA7: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 7.0 for bigger datasets</article-title><source>Molecular biology and evolution</source><year>2016</year><volume>33</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1870</fpage><lpage>1874</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msw054</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27004904?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27004904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gish</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Basic local alignment search tool</article-title><source>Journal of molecular biology</source><year>1990</year><volume>215</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-2836(05)80360-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 2231712?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2231712</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koscielny</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Open Targets: a platform for therapeutic target identification and validation</article-title><source>Nucleic acids research</source><year>2016</year><volume>45</volume><issue>D1</issue><fpage>D985</fpage><lpage>D994</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkw1055</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27899665?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27899665</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Raghava</surname><given-names>GPS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ProPred: prediction of HLA-DR binding sites</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2001</year><volume>17</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1236</fpage><lpage>1237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/17.12.1236</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11751237?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11751237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>London</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Raveh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fathi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Schueler-Furman</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rosetta FlexPepDock web server&#x02014;high resolution modeling of peptide&#x02013;protein interactions</article-title><source>Nucleic acids research</source><year>2011</year><volume>39</volume><issue>suppl_2</issue><fpage>W249</fpage><lpage>W253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/17.12.1236</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21622962?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21622962</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The protein data bank</article-title><source>Nucleic acids research</source><year>2000</year><volume>28</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/28.1.235</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10592235?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10592235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vita</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The immune epitope database (IEDB) 3.0</article-title><source>Nucleic acids research</source><year>2014</year><volume>43</volume><issue>D1</issue><fpage>D405</fpage><lpage>D412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gku938</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25300482?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25300482</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ponomarenko</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ElliPro: a new structure-based tool for the prediction of antibody epitopes</article-title><source>BMC bioinformatics</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>514</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-9-514</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19055730?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19055730</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of novel autoantigen in the synovial fluid of rheumatoid arthritis patients using an immunoproteomics approach</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e56246</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0056246</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23418544?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23418544</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ooka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishioka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Autoantibodies to low-density-lipoprotein-receptor-related protein 2 (LRP2) in systemic autoimmune diseases</article-title><source>Arthritis Res Ther</source><year>2003</year><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>R174</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/ar754</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12723989?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12723989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Londei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Persistence of collagen type II-specific T-cell clones in the synovial membrane of a patient with rheumatoid arthritis</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>1989</year><volume>86</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>636</fpage><lpage>640</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.86.2.636</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mullazehi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wick</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Klareskog</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>van Vollenhoven</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000f6;nnelid</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-type II collagen antibodies are associated with early radiographic destruction in rheumatoid arthritis</article-title><source>Arthritis research &#x00026; therapy</source><year>2012</year><volume>14</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>R100</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/ar3825</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22548748</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodriguez-Garcia</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Annexin V autoantibodies in rheumatoid arthritis</article-title><source>Annals of the rheumatic diseases</source><year>1996</year><volume>55</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>895</fpage><lpage>900</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/ard.55.12.895</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9014583</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proteomic surveillance of autoimmunity in osteoarthritis: identification of triosephosphate isomerase as an autoantigen in patients with osteoarthritis</article-title><source>Arthritis &#x00026; Rheumatism</source><year>2004</year><volume>50</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1511</fpage><lpage>1521</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/art.20189</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15146421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsuruha</surname><given-names>Jun-ichiro</given-names></name><name><surname>Masuko-Hongo</surname><given-names>Kayo</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>Tomohiro</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakata</surname><given-names>Masahiro</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Hiroshi</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishioka</surname><given-names>Kusuki</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Implication of cartilage intermediate layer protein in cartilage destruction in subsets of patients with osteoarthritis and rheumatoid arthritis</article-title><source>Arthritis &#x00026; Rheumatism</source><year>2001</year><volume>44</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>838</fpage><lpage>845</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1529-0131(200104)44:4&#x0003c;838::AID-ANR140&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-C</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11315923</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsuruha</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Autoimmunity against YKL-39, a human cartilage derived protein, in patients with osteoarthritis</article-title><source>The Journal of rheumatology</source><year>2002</year><volume>29</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1459</fpage><lpage>1466</lpage><?supplied-pmid 12136906?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12136906</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>