<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The potential of transmission of SARS-CoV-2 by objects or surfaces and by the faecal–oral route is a major concern in endoscopy units. On the other hand, exhaustion, burnout and inexperience in a crisis, like the one we are experiencing, increase the possibility of human errors.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr22-2050640620920157" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>
 </sup> Endoscopy should still be regarded as a risky procedure that can expose endoscopists to potential contamination. Viruses, in particular, can spread via the airborne route during endoscopy aerosolization. This is a potential risk concerning SARS- CoV-2 virus as transmission may be favoured during endoscopy. In this context, endoscopy should be performed in a negative-pressure room and the staff of the endoscopy department should follow standardized precautions. Personal protective equipment (PPE) should be used according to low or high-risk dressing.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr23-2050640620920157" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
 </sup> In addition, the American Society of Gastroenterology Endoscopy (ASGE) guidelines for infection control in endoscopy
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr23-2050640620920157" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
 </sup> and the European Society of Gastrointestinal Endoscopy (ESGE) guidelines
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr24-2050640620920157" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
 </sup> must be strictly followed. All the equipment, including endoscopes and reusable accessories, should be reprocessed with a standardized reprocessing procedure. The disinfectants, used for this purpose, must be bactericidal, mycobactericidal, fungicidal and virucidal (against enveloped and non-enveloped viruses). SARS-CoV-2 is easily inactivated by many commonly used disinfectants and no additional approach should be implemented to clean and disinfect the endoscope.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr25-2050640620920157" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>
 </sup> Regarding the endoscopy-centre environment, UV irradiation and ozone treatment are recommended for the cleaning and sterilization of air and surfaces, such as endoscopic equipment, office tables and the walls of the examination room. As surfaces might be a possible source of contamination and can lead to infection, cleaning all the surfaces in the procedure room is a key point. Endoscopy-centre furniture and floors can be heavily contaminated in the case of SARS-CoV-2 infection and should be thoroughly disinfected after each procedure. Chlorine-containing detergent is recommended for daily floor cleaning. Due to the risk of aerosolization, in the absence of negative pressure the room should be kept empty for at least 1 h, and for 30 min in the case of negative-pressure rooms, before the procedure.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr22-2050640620920157" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>
 </sup> In outbreak areas, only emergency endoscopies should be performed. These exceptions can include cases of acute gastrointestinal bleeding, presence of foreign bodies in the gastrointestinal tract and acute suppurative cholangitis. In pandemic areas the basic protection requirements of the medical staff in the endoscopy centre should reach Biosafety level 2 (the wearing of disposable gowns, N95 masks, goggles, caps and shoe covers during endoscopy) for all kinds of GI endoscopic procedures. Biosafety level 3 (PPE, respirators, plus negative-pressure rooms, due to the aerosolization risk of SARS-CoV-2 virus during endoscopy) protection is required for all endoscopic procedures in SARS-CoV-2 infected or suspected patients, and for those with very high risk of potential exposure. The criteria for the selection of the adequate biosafety protection level in an endoscopy unit are outlined in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-2050640620920157">Figure 1</xref>.
</p>
