<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0030">VLP technology can overcome numerous drawbacks associated with traditional methods of vaccine production, such as infectiousness and lengthy production time. The yield and cost of the vaccine depend on the choice of expression systems and the purification process. VLP technology is rapidly developing especially in the optimization of the expression system and VLP purity. For example, for the expression system, a study reported that when produced in 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>, the murine polyomavirus (MuPyV) capsomere platform was capable of producing 320 million vaccine doses in a few days, at a low cost. This shows its suitability as a rapid response and low-cost vaccine platform 
 <xref rid="bib0133" ref-type="bibr">[133]</xref>. The recently optimized Insect Cell-Baculovirus Expression Vector System (IC-BEVS) has a similar potential 
 <xref rid="bib0134" ref-type="bibr">[134]</xref>. IC-BEVS is used to manufacture approved VLP vaccines such as Cervarix® and Porcilis PCV®. The purification of VLPs is usually performed via polyethylene glycol precipitation, diafiltration, chromatography, density gradient ultracentrifugation, ultracentrifugation or continuous flow ultracentrifugation [
 <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0136" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>]. Although these technologies are widely used, they have the following disadvantages: the inability to remove host cell-derived contaminants, the rupture of particles that affect immunogenicity, the expensive equipment required for continuous flow ultracentrifugation, and the potentially hazardous materials generated by viral ultracentrifugation 
 <xref rid="bib0137" ref-type="bibr">[137]</xref>. Chromatography is still used in industry to purify VLP vaccines, but this method is time-consuming and costly. There is still a need to develop more efficient and cost-effective purification methods. The purification method based on sulfated cellulose membrane adsorbers is significantly better than the traditional method 
 <xref rid="bib0138" ref-type="bibr">[138]</xref>. As it is easy to popularize and simplifies the purification steps, it can be used as a general purification platform for VLP vaccines, and this technology is expected to be used to purify VLPs on a large scale.
</p>
