<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>SARS‐CoV‐2 is composed of at least 11 ORFs (Open Reading Frames) with the full length of 29 903 bp.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref> Its genome is similar to SARS‐CoV with a gene order 5'‐ORF1ab‐S‐E‐M‐N‐3'. A large gene encoding a replicase (ORF1ab) is followed by 4 major structural protein‐coding genes: S (Spike protein), E (Envelope protein), M (Membrane protein) and N (Nucleocapsid protein). There are also at least 6 accessory ORFs.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>22</sup>
 </xref> SARS‐CoV‐2 belongs to the β coronavirus and its sequence significantly differs from that of SARS‐CoV and MERS‐CoV, which have caused epidemics previously.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref> Sequence alignment displays that SARS‐CoV‐2 has 79% and 50% identity with SARS‐CoV and MERS‐CoV, respectively,
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>23</sup>
 </xref> whereas 96.3% identity with a bat's coronavirus.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref> Phylogenetic analysis suggests that the closest relatives of SARS‐CoV‐2 are several viruses originated from bats, such as Bat‐CoV RaTG3, Bat SARSr CoV‐ZC45 and Bat SARSr CoV‐ZXC21. Therefore, bats are assumed to be the original host of SARS‐CoV‐2. However, there should be an intermediate host, who transfers the novel coronavirus to human because the sequence of SARS‐CoV‐2 and bat virus Bat‐CoV RaTG3 has minor difference.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>23</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>25</sup>
 </xref> The suspicious intermediate host has been suggested to be the pangolin by Chinese scientists on the basis of genetic analyses, which has not been confirmed until now with the release of new pangolin coronavirus genome studies.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>26</sup>
 </xref> A recent study has found that the SARS‐COV‐2 was easy to infect cats and ferrets, but weakly infectious to dogs, pigs, chickens and ducks, which could be important for the traceability of the SARS‐COV‐2.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>27</sup>
 </xref> Multiple sequence analysis studies have shown that the genome sequences of SARS‐CoV‐2 exhibit more than 99% sequence identity.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>22</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>23</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>25</sup>
 </xref> As a typical RNA virus, the average substitution rate for coronavirus is 10
 <sup>−4</sup> substitutions per year per site.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>28</sup>
 </xref> The low heterogeneity among sequences suggests that all these SARS‐CoV‐2 originated from the same ancestor within a very short period.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>23</sup>
 </xref> Despite the low heterogeneity, the number of viral genome variants will consistently increase with the continuous spread of COVID‐19. So far, 4007 variants have been identified and include single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP), deletion, indel and insertion with the mutant numbers of 3951, 82, 10 and 20, respectively (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bigd.big.ac.cn/ncov" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://bigd.big.ac.cn/ncov</ext-link>). A deletion of eight amino acid has been reported in viral polyprotein 1ab (pp1ab) protein, encoded by ORF1ab gene of SARS‐CoV‐2. The pp1ab protein is composed of 16 mature non‐structural proteins (NSPs) and seldom reported to have mutations previously. This mutant was isolated from a Japanese COVID‐19 patient, who did not show critical symptoms.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>29</sup>
 </xref> Domenico group described the presence of two mutations of SARS‐CoV‐2, affecting the NSP6 (amino acid position 3691) and ORF10 adjacent regions (amino acid position 9659), respectively, and both mutations could confer lower stability of the protein structures.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>30</sup>
 </xref> Another two mutations of nt28144 in ORF8 and nt8782 in ORF1a of SARS‐CoV‐2 have been noticed to have higher mutation rate of 30.53% and 29.47%, respectively.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>31</sup>
 </xref> A study analysed 103 SARS‐CoV‐2 genomes and also found nt28144 mutant in ORF8. They classified the SARS‐CoV‐2 virus as type L (28144T) and S (28144C) based on the different amino acid of leucine and serine in nt28144. S type was indicated to be the ancestral version although the L type (mutation rate ~70%) was more prevalent than the S type (mutation rate ~30%).
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>32</sup>
 </xref> L type was speculated to be more aggressive and contagious. By analysis of 160 complete human SARS‐CoV‐2 genomes, researchers from the University of Cambridge found three central variants distinguished by amino acid alteration, named A (8782T, 28144C), B (derived from A, 8782C, 28144T) and C (derived from B, 26144T), with A being the ancestral type according to the bat out‐group coronavirus.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>33</sup>
 </xref> The A and C types were found mainly in Europeans and Americans, whereas the B type was the most common type in East Asia.
</p>
