<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0345">Favipiravir has been developed as an anti-influenza drug with efficacy against severe infections caused by a high viral load and was approved as an anti-influenza drug in Japan. Favipiravir has a similar mechanism of action to the antiherpesvirus drug acyclovir and has the property of not producing a resistant virus. Favipiravir is contraindicated in pregnant women due to its teratogenicity and embryotoxicity in animals. Subsequent stockpiling of doses for 2 million people has been performed as a countermeasure against novel influenza in Japan. Favipiravir has been used to treat lethal infections in humans because its efficacy has been confirmed in a wide range of animal models of lethal RNA infections. Severe human RNA infections are sporadic, and the number of cases is limited. In patients with these infections, favipiravir has been used for urgent and life-saving purposes because there is no standard effective treatment, rather than to show efficacy. Clinical trials have been performed to compare historical control patients and patients treated with favipiravir for Ebola virus infection (
 <xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">Bai et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0265" ref-type="bibr">Jacobs et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0540" ref-type="bibr">Sissoko et al., 2016</xref>) and SFTS (
 <xref rid="bb0645" ref-type="bibr">Yasukawa, 2016</xref>). Subsequently, favipiravir has been submitted for additional indications based on clinical trials for SFTS in Japan. The establishment of a placebo group that does not receive an effective drug in a lethal animal model is a challenging problem to confirm the efficacy of favipiravir by a randomized placebo-controlled trial. As an example of this situation, PEP of human immunodeficiency virus has been performed to protect against needle sticks or occupational exposures without placebo and has become a standard procedure in the guideline due to its prophylactic effect as a result of many years of implementation (
 <xref rid="bb0310" ref-type="bibr">Kuhar et al., 2013</xref>).
</p>
