<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par57">Writers induce m6A modification, which is mediated by methyltransferase-like 3 (METTL3), methyltransferase-like 14 (METTL14), Wilms’ tumor 1-associating protein (WTAP), methyltransferase-like 16 (METTL16), RNA binding motif protein 15 (RBM15), and KIAA1429 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Bokar et al. discovered a ~ 200 kDa methyltransferase (MT) complex in nuclear extract lysate from HeLa cell which exhibited methyltransferase activity, from which a 70 kDa protein was identified, named MT-A70 or METTL3 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Recently, 
 <italic>Liu</italic> et al. found that METTL14, an RNA writer, forms a stable heterodimer core complex with METTL3 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. This complex component facilitates m6A deposition on nuclear RNA in mammalian cells. Furthermore, the combination of METTL3 and METTL14 dramatically enhanced methyltransferase activity compared to single protein. In addition, WTAP is a regulatory subunit in the m6A methyltransferase complex. Although it lacked methylation activity, it interacted with METTL3/14 complex to influence the deposition of m6A. Moreover, Ping and colleagues showed that WTAP might play a critical role in epitranscriptomic regulation of RNA metabolism [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Besides WTAP, RBM15 and KIAA1429, which are part of the complex, affected the activity of METTL3/14 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Schwartz et al. showed that depletion of KIAA1429 decreased m6A level in vitro [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Moreover, knockdown of RBM15 caused a significant reduction of m6A deposition on mRNAs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. This means RBM15 and KIAA1429 might be involved in methylation process. A recent study [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] identified a new component of writers METTL16, which is independent from the METTL3/METTL14/WTAP complex, that caused m6A deposition on U6 snRNA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] and U6-like hairpins of MAT2A mRNA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] in a C-m6A-G context.
</p>
