<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0050">We have identified two antipyretic steps in influenza infections, as shown in 
 <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> . Influenza infection and its replication in the epithelium of the upper respiratory tract induce the production of interferon (IFN) and cytokines that induce cyclooxygenase expression and prostaglandin E
 <sub>2</sub> production and cause fever. The effects of interferon and interleukin (IL)-1α were determined by neutralizing their actions through the intravenous injection of their respective antibodies in influenza-infected mice (
 <xref rid="bb0325" ref-type="bibr">Kurokawa, Imakita, Kumeda, &amp; Shiraki, 1996</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0345" ref-type="bibr">Kurokawa, Watanabe, Shimizu, Sawamura, &amp; Shiraki, 2010</xref>). The effects of aspirin, NSAIDs, and cinnamyl compounds derived from herbal extracts on influenza-infected mice or mouse macrophage-derived P388D1 cells were determined, and 48 cinnamyl compounds showed compound-specific responses to fever and increased IL-1 levels in influenza-infected mice. Cinnamyl compounds regulate cytokine levels by modulating the amount of NF-κB (
 <xref rid="bb0350" ref-type="bibr">Kurokawa et al., 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0320" ref-type="bibr">Kurokawa, Brown, Kagawa, &amp; Shiraki, 2003</xref>). Cinnamyl compounds and clarithromycin increase the levels of IL-12 on day 2 and IFN-γ on day 3 in the bronchoalveolar fluids of mice and decrease the area of pneumonia throughout the lungs. The role of IL-12 on day 2 was confirmed through its direct nasal application, and nasal administration of IL-12 reduced the virus yield in the bronchoalveolar fluids from influenza-infected mice (
 <xref rid="bb0230" ref-type="bibr">Hama et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0340" ref-type="bibr">Kurokawa, Tsurita, Brown, Fukuda, &amp; Shiraki, 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0590" ref-type="bibr">Tsurita et al., 2001</xref>). Cinnamyl compounds that are mainly derived from medicinal herbs prevent the induction of fever in influenza-infected mice by decreasing the serum IL-1 level. In contrast, aspirin suppresses fever by inhibiting hypothalamic cyclooxygenase activity and prostaglandin E
 <sub>2</sub> production without affecting the high level of IL-1 (
 <xref rid="bb0325" ref-type="bibr">Kurokawa, Imakita, Kumeda, &amp; Shiraki, 1996</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0330" ref-type="bibr">Kurokawa, Imakita, Kumeda, Yukawa, &amp; Shiraki, 1996</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0335" ref-type="bibr">Kurokawa, Kumeda, Yamamura, Kamiyama, &amp; Shiraki, 1998</xref>). We have determined two steps of antipyretic action by cinnamyl compounds and NSAIDs in the fever cascade in influenza infection.
</p>
