<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">While ZIKV exists as three genotypes (West African, East African and Asian), they all behave as a single serotype
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>
 </sup>. Our previous studies demonstrated that PIZV is capable of eliciting antibodies that neutralize both African and Asian ZIKV isolates 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup>. Others have shown that the magnitude or duration of viremia in unvaccinated macaques challenged with ZIKV isolates from Brazil or Puerto Rico is similar
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup>, and that vaccinated macaques are protected against challenge with heterologous ZIKV strains
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup>. Protection of animal models against heterologous challenge and cross-neutralization capabilities of antisera from multiple vaccine platforms
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup> suggest that data from a single challenge strain may be sufficient to show cross protection against ZIKV strains from other lineages. Several groups have developed rhesus macaque challenge models using Zika strain PRVABC59
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup> which is a well-documented and characterized isolate from human serum and is representative of viruses that were circulating in the Americas during the 2015–2016 outbreak
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup>. We therefore selected PRVABC59 as the challenge strain for our studies.
</p>
