<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>FIG 5</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Influenza A virus polymerase activity is supported by murine Anp32B but not by Anp32A. (a) Minigenome reporter assay in dKO cells with cotransfected FLAG-tagged Anp32A from pig (SusA), mouse (MusA), duck (AnasA), or chicken (GallusA) with H3N2 Victoria RNP components, pPolI-firefly minigenome reporter, and 
   <italic>Renilla</italic> transcription control. Data show mean (SD) of firefly activity normalized to that of 
   <italic>Renilla</italic> and analyzed by one-way ANOVA from one representative repeat (
   <italic>n</italic> = 2 triplicate experiments). ns, not significant; ****, 
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001. Accompanying Western blot shows expression of vRNP component PB2 and coexpressed FLAG-tagged ANP32 constructs. (b) Minigenome assay showing activity of Vic/75 polymerase in eHPA1 dKO cells coexpressing mouse Anp32A, Anp32B, or Anp32A
   <sup>128-153</sup> Data were analyzed as described for panel a. Accompanying Western blot shows expression of vRNP component PB2 and coexpressed FLAG-tagged ANP32 constructs. (c) Immunofluorescence analysis showing nuclear expression of FLAG-tagged MusA, MusB, and MusA
   <sup>128-153</sup> detected with anti-FLAG antibody and Alexa Fluor-594 anti-rabbit conjugate and counterstained with DAPI. (d) Cartoon showing chimeric mouse ANP32 protein with 26 amino acids from mouse Anp32A LRR 5 replaced by the equivalent sequence from mouse Anp32B. (e) Alignment comparing LRR 5 amino acid sequence of mouse Anp32A to its Anp32B homologue, human ANP32A, and human ANP32B. (f) Structural model of mouse Anp32B highlighting the swapped domain in blue (LRR in dark gray, LCAR in semitransparent gray, and the domain swap in blue with amino acid 130 represented as a red stick). (g) Minigenome assay for activity of H3N2 Victoria polymerase in eHAP1 dKO cells coexpressing wild-type human or mouse ANP32A or position 130 point mutants. Data show mean (SD) of firefly activity normalized to that of 
   <italic>Renilla</italic> and analyzed by one-way ANOVA from one representative repeat (
   <italic>n</italic> = 3 triplicate experiments). **, 
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01; ****, 
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001. Accompanying Western blot shows expression of vRNP component PB2 and coexpressed FLAG-tagged ANP32 constructs.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="JVI.00217-19-f0005" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
