<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
   <p>A 3 month old, former 27 week premature infant with bronchopulmonary dysplasia presents with clinical signs of bronchiolitis. Analysis of nasopharyngeal secretions by polymerase chain reaction testing identifies respiratory syncitial virus. Which of the following therapies have been proven to be a consistent benefit for RSV bronchiolitis?
    <list list-type="simple">
     <list-item>
      <label>A.</label>
      <p>Aminophylline</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>B.</label>
      <p>Bronchodilators</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>C.</label>
      <p>Corticosteroids</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>D.</label>
      <p>Ribavirin</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>E.</label>
      <p>Supportive care</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Palivizumab is indicated for which of the following children? 
    <list list-type="simple">
     <list-item>
      <label>A.</label>
      <p>A 5 month old, former 27 week premature infant who just underwent surgical repair of a large ventricular septal defect who received palivizumab 2 weeks ago</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>B.</label>
      <p>A 9 month old, former 28 week premature infant with mild bronchopulmonary dysplasia who received palivizumab 2 weeks ago</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>C.</label>
      <p>A 1 month old, former 36 week premature infant with peripheral pulmonic stenosis who has never received palivizumab</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>D.</label>
      <p>A 2 month old full term infant with a urea cycle defect who has never received palivizumab</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>E.</label>
      <p>An 8 month old, former 25 week premature infant with bronchopulmonary dysplasia who received his fifth dose of palivizumab a month ago</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>A 5 year old, unimmunized male with moderately severe asthma requires hospital admission with a 12 h history of fever, cough and myalgias in the middle of an H1N1 influenza outbreak. The most appropriate initial management of this child includes which of the following? 
    <list list-type="simple">
     <list-item>
      <label>A.</label>
      <p>Intravenous peramivir administered after confirming the diagnosis with rapid testing</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>B.</label>
      <p>Intravenous zanamivir administered as soon as possible</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>C.</label>
      <p>Oral amantidine administered as soon as possible</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>D.</label>
      <p>Oral oseltamivir administered as soon as possible</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>E.</label>
      <p>Orally inhaled zanamivir administered after confirming the diagnosis with rapid testing</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>A 7 year old presents with a high fever, respiratory distress, and a parapneumonic effusion on chest radiograph. Which of the following findings would MOST likely suggest the need for video-assisted thorascopic surgical drainage of this effusion? 
    <list list-type="simple">
     <list-item>
      <label>A.</label>
      <p>A mediastinal shift away from the effusion</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>B.</label>
      <p>A pleural fluid pH  &gt;  7.3 and glucose &gt;200 mg/dL</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>C.</label>
      <p>Persistent drainage for more than 5 days from a percutaneously-placed thoracentesis catheter</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>D.</label>
      <p>The persistence of fever following 48 h of parenteral antibiotics</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>E.</label>
      <p>The presence of loculations on ultrasound or computer tomography images</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>A 4 year old male presents with acute hypoxemic respiratory failure (PaO
    <sub>2</sub>/FiO
    <sub>2</sub> ratio  =  150), disseminated intravascular coagulation, and renal insufficiency secondary to catecholeamine-resistant shock. Rapid antigen testing identifies the H1N1 virus. In addition to oral oseltamivir, the initial antimicrobial coverage should include which of the following? 
    <list list-type="simple">
     <list-item>
      <label>A.</label>
      <p>Cefepime</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>B.</label>
      <p>Intravenous immunoglobulin</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>C.</label>
      <p>Intravenous zanamivir</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>D.</label>
      <p>Trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>E.</label>
      <p>Vancomycin</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>A 16 year old male presents with a 3 day history of fever, chills, myalgia, headache, and gastrointestinal symptoms. On clinical exam, he is febrile, tachypneic with scattered rales, and hypotensive. There is no rash or evidence of animal bite on exam. His initial laboratory results are remarkable for thrombocytopenia, leukocytosis with an increased percentage of circulating immunoblasts, and elevated levels of lactate dehydrogenase, aspartate aminotransferase, and alanine aminotransferase. His prothrombin time is 16 s. He is admitted and his respiratory status continues to deteriorate ultimately requiring mechanical ventilation. He remains in refractory shock for several days. After an extensive diagnostic work-up, he is diagnosed with hantavirus cardiopulmonary syndrome based on the detection of hantavirus-specific immunoglobulin M. Of the following, which is most likely to be part of his medical history? 
    <list list-type="simple">
     <list-item>
      <label>A.</label>
      <p>An underlying immunodeficiency</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>B.</label>
      <p>Being a member of the high school wrestling team</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>C.</label>
      <p>Exposure to rodent excrement</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>D.</label>
      <p>Intravenous drug use</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>E.</label>
      <p>Residence in the Southeastern United States</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Corticosteroids have the MOST established benefit in which of the following clinical scenarios? 
    <list list-type="simple">
     <list-item>
      <label>A.</label>
      <p>A 7 week old infant with severe bronchiolitis secondary to respiratory syncitial virus</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>B.</label>
      <p>A 6 month old, unimmunized infant with severe hypoxia and respiratory failure secondary to pertussis</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>C.</label>
      <p>A 14 year old female with necrotizing pneumonia secondary to community acquired methicillin resistant 
       <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>
      </p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>D.</label>
      <p>A 14 month old with a history of acquired immune deficiency syndrome and currently in hypoxic respiratory failure secondary to 
       <italic>Pneumocystis jiroveci</italic> pneumonia (
       <italic>Pneumocystis carinii</italic> pneumonia)
      </p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>E.</label>
      <p>A 16 year old native American female with severe cardiopulmonary dysfunction secondary to a Hantavirus infection</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
