<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The use of DNA vaccines has been more extensively studied to prevent VEEV infection, while only a few studies exist for DNA vaccines targeting EEEV and WEEV. Although several VEEV vaccine studies are listed in 
 <xref rid="vaccines-08-00273-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, the structural genes have been derived from only two strains, viz., Trinidad donkey and TC-83. The rationale for selecting these strains is likely in part because of convenience, the body of literature on TC-83 as a live attenuated vaccine, and viral vectors delivering structural proteins from these strains. Vaccines 26S [
 <xref rid="B105-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>] and VEEV DNA [
 <xref rid="B108-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>] used sequences corresponding to structural proteins from Trinidad donkey to create vaccine plasmids delivered via gene gun. The delivery of vaccine plasmids by electroporation (EP) or gene gun elicits a strong immune response and requires less DNA, but the tradeoff is often cell death due to its inherent invasiveness [
 <xref rid="B95-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]. The 26S vaccine induced IgG antibodies and protected 100% of subcutaneous- and 80% of aerosol-challenged mice [
 <xref rid="B105-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. Furthermore, the VEEV DNA vaccine induced a humoral immune response and protected two of three macaques from serum viremia, whereas all control animals developed serum viremia in a nonlethal aerosol challenge [
 <xref rid="B108-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. Immunoinformatics was used to present tailored epitopes of VEEV antigens derived from Trinidad donkey in a multiepitope vaccine, which induced cellular and humoral immune responses but had a low level of protection against homologous challenge [
 <xref rid="B113-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>]. Directed molecular evolution was another approach used with the intent to improve the ability of the cross-protection of DNA vaccines derived from Trinidad donkey [
 <xref rid="B107-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]. These vaccines (AG2-5A7, AG2-5A10, AG4-1C7, and AG-1G2) yielded 70–100% protection against a homologous challenge, but a heterologous challenge was not tested. Trinidad donkey sequences were codon-optimized to improve the protective efficacy of a VEEV DNA vaccine. The VEEV
 <sub>COCAP</sub> and VEEV
 <sub>CO</sub> plasmids were constructed using codon-optimized sequences of Trinidad donkey structural proteins with or without the capsid, respectively [
 <xref rid="B109-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. The capsid was removed from this vaccine and others, because it can be cytotoxic and inhibit translation [
 <xref rid="B117-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>]. Mice immunized with VEEV
 <sub>CO</sub> had improved neutralization titers compared to VEEV
 <sub>COCAP</sub>, and it was subsequently used in other studies to evaluate the efficacy in combination with adjuvants [
 <xref rid="B110-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>] and in a Phase 1 clinical trial [
 <xref rid="B111-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>].
</p>
