<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Host defense barriers that prevent transmission of influenza viruses from one species of animal to another do not allow the virus to grow efficiently in other species. The receptor specificity of the hemagglutinin and internal genes of influenza viruses play roles in host range restriction (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Kuiken et al., 2006</xref>). In addition to the virus itself, host restriction proteins also play important roles in virus replication (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Brass et al., 2009</xref>). Although numerous studies have documented the roles of various influenza virus proteins in immune evasion, factors that maintain the balance between protective and pathological host responses to infection are less well understood (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Taubenberger and Morens, 2013</xref>). The application of genome-wide profiling techniques, such as microarray analysis, has resulted in the identification of novel host factors involved in H1N1 IAV infection of mice, ferrets, and macaques (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Cameron et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Boon et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Cilloniz et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Go et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Shinya et al., 2012</xref>). In addition to animal models, RNA-seq technology is also widely used to explore host cell responses to human IAV infection (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Chakrabarti et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Fabozzi et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Russell et al., 2018</xref>). In this experiment, two different H1N1 IAV strains were used to independently infect A549 and 293T cells. RNA-seq was used to identify host DEGs during infection with two different H1N1 IAV strains. Numerous genes displayed significantly altered expression levels upon infection with different virus types. To better understand the host cell response to H1N1 IAV infection at 8 h, a total of 249 common DEGs were identified in A549 cells infected with the two different strains, but only 137 common DEGs were identified in CA04- and PR8-infected 293T cells, corresponding to the lower viral titers in 293T cells. Our previous work demonstrated that DEGs in H5N1-infected 293T and A549 cells were mainly linked to cellular function and metabolic processes (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Cao et al., 2019</xref>). These differential expression patterns motivated us to investigate the complicated relationship between H1N1 IAV and host cells.
</p>
