<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Once taken into the cell, there are additional host factors that interact with the IAV components in a host-specific manner [
 <xref rid="RSTB20190017C11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20190017C37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. While several important host factors have been identified, three that are well characterized are the tripartite motif-containing protein 25 (TRIM25) and the retinoic acid-inducible gene I (RIG-I), which can bind the incoming viral ribonuleoproteins and reduce infection, and the MxA protein (in humans) which is a nuclear interferon-stimulated gene (ISG) that binds to the viral ribonuleoproteins to block infection. Viruses from birds or other hosts may be able to evade those factors through the acquisition of specific mutations in PB2 or nucleoprotein. During replication, IAVs induce additional host immune responses, in particular the interferon response, which triggers the expression of many different interferon-stimulated genes that can block many steps of the viral replication cycle. The IAV non-structural 1 protein is a multipurpose protein that can block or downregulate many of those responses, and evolution of NS1 occurs after transfer into new hosts to optimize the antagonism of the host innate immune response [
 <xref rid="RSTB20190017C11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20190017C37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20190017C38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Some of these changes are likely to be involved in fine tuning the virus:host interaction after pandemic spread has already been accomplished [
 <xref rid="RSTB20190017C39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. For example, the ability of IAV NS1 to interact with the cellular cleavage and polyadenylation-specific factor 30 and inhibit host gene expression and interfering with the Janus kinase/signal transducers and activators of transcription (JAK/STAT) pathway have been shown to be an important mechanism of IAV host adaptation [
 <xref rid="RSTB20190017C40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>].
</p>
