<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For approval of cancer therapeutics, such as regorafenib and sorafenib, more severe adverse events are tolerable than for influenza drugs considering influenza is usually not lethal. Although the therapeutic margin of regorafenib/sorafenib is indeed lower compared to standard anti-influenza drugs, such as zanamivir, it is still larger than that of ribavirin, a drug approved for treatment of several virus infections [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007601.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. The most prominent side effects of regorafenib and sorafenib are rash and hypertension. However, both UBKIs are usually administered over weeks or months during cancer therapy, whereas a few days might be sufficient in case of influenza treatment. Although short-term treatment would not necessarily prevent any occurrence of adverse events, the duration of side effects would be shortened and the impairment of patients’ quality of lives lowered compared to cancer treatment. In addition, it might be possible to apply both UBKIs locally by inhalation, in contrast to the systemic administration used for cancer therapy, which would allow lower dosing (relative to the bodyweight) and thus potentially reduce adverse events. Furthermore, especially in cases of severe influenza or acute respiratory distress syndrome, the potential side effects of regorafenib/sorafenib may be acceptable. With the standard dosing regimen (160 mg, once daily), the plasma concentration of regorafenib reaches a maximum of 3.6 μM and stays above the IC
 <sub>50</sub> for IAV replication in A549 cells (i.e. &gt; 0.89 μM) for at least 48 h [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007601.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Standard administration of sorafenib (400 mg, twice daily) achieves a plasma concentration of approximately 4 μM, which is stable for at least 24 h [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007601.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Thus, there is reason for confidence that regorafenib and sorafenib are viable treatment options.
</p>
