<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The 
 <italic>de novo</italic> development of drugs is a long and expensive process, making the repurposing of pharmaceuticals for new indications an attractive strategy. By drug database screening, we identified several approved or experimental drugs targeting strain-independent host factors. Most of these drugs were screened in A549 cells for antiviral activity and cytotoxicity rendering fourteen with a potential for therapeutic application. We focused on the FLT4 inhibitors regorafenib and sorafenib and found that in addition to VEGFR3 at least three other RTKs (FGFR1, VEGFR1, PDGFRB) targeted by these drugs are relevant to IV replication. Therefore, the antiviral activity of regorafenib and sorafenib is likely to be due to the inhibition of several target proteins in parallel, and may even include further kinases. Both drugs interfered with fusion of the viral and the endosomal membranes. Impairment of an early step in the IV life cycle, such as fusion, necessarily would affect all downstream steps. Consequently, it remains an open question if regorafenib and sorafenib affect additional (post-fusion) steps of viral replication. Interestingly, the broad-range RTK inhibitor genistein as well as a broad-range RTK inhibitor mix (containing the VEGFR/PDGFR inhibitor SU4312), have been shown to inhibit the uptake of IV virions [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007601.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], indicating that while some RTKs are required for internalization, others are required for fusion. It is possible that regorafenib and sorafenib inhibit kinases involved in endosomal maturation or block kinases that phosphorylate the V-ATPase subunits, since their phosphorylation status regulates their activity and thus endosomal acidification [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007601.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007601.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Future studies will shed more light on the mechanisms involved in the UBKI-mediated block of fusion.
</p>
