<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For the Endo H/PNGase F digestion Western blots, protein stability assays Western blots, NS1 internalization kinetic Western blots, siRNA knockdown Western blots, and ZIKV/WNV native-PAGE Western blots total cell lysates or recombinant proteins were collected in protein sample buffer (0.1 M Tris [pH 6.8], 4% SDS, 4 mM EDTA, 286 mM 2-mercaptoethanol, 3.2 M glycerol, 0.05% bromophenol blue) and then resolved by SDS-PAGE. The same protocol and buffer were used for native-PAGE but without SDS. The resolved proteins were then transferred onto nitrocellulose membranes and probed with primary antibodies diluted in TBS/0.1% Tween 20 (TBST) containing 5% skim milk, rocking overnight at 4°C. Secondary antibodies were diluted in TBST with 5% skim milk for 1-hour rocking at room temperature. After each antibody incubation, membranes were washed three times for 5 minutes each with TBST. Membranes were visualized using ECL reagents on a ChemiDoc system with Image Lab software from Bio-Rad. All antibodies were probed by the above method except rabbit anti-Caveolin1 and rabbit anti-DynaminI/II which were probed in TBST with 5% bovine serum albumin according to the manufacturer’s instructions. The following antibodies were used: mouse anti-6xHis (MA1-21315, Thermo Scientific), anti-NS1 monoclonal antibody (7E11), rabbit anti-clathrin heavy chain (ab172958, Abcam), rabbit anti-Dynamin I/II (2342S, Cell Signaling), rabbit anti-caveolin 1 (3267, Cell Signaling), mouse anti-βactin (sc-47778, Santa Cruz Biotechnology), mouse anti- αtubulin (ab4074, Abcam), goat anti-mouse HRP (405306, Biolegend), and donkey anti-rabbit HRP (406401, Biolegend). For the N-glycan digestion Western blots, 1 μg of denatured NS1s were digested with 750 units Endo H (NEB) or 500 units PNGase F (NEB) treatment at 37°C for 1 hour according to manufacturer’s protocol. For the NS1 stability assays 100 ng of protein were mixed with EGM-2 media (Lonza) and incubated in a tissue-culture incubator for the times indicated in the figures.</p>
