<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0080">Eleutheroside B1, a coumarin compound has been earlier demonstrated to inhibit expression of many chemokine genes and gene for Nucleoprotein, an influenza structural protein that is a constituent of vRNPs viral ribonucleoprotein complex important for viral replication [
 <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. RNA sequencing technology has confirmed that the eleutheroside B1 acts on chemokine signaling pathways and cytokine-cytokine receptor interactions. Recently, the mechanism of action against influenza viral infection of eleutheroside B1 has been assessed showing that the target for this compound is POLR2A gene which is responsible for the expression of viral polymerase [
 <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Thiazolyl-coumarin hybrids synthesized by Osman 
 <italic>et al.</italic>, were found to show promising antiviral against the H3N2 and H1N1 strains of influenza in MDCK cell-based assays. Molecular docking studies has shown this anti-influenza activity is probably because of inhibition of viral envelope protein neuraminidase [
 <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Similarly, derivatives of coumarin, bis(triazolothiadiazinyl coumarin) was synthesized and evaluated for their anti-influenza activity. Site of target of this synthesized coumarin was neuraminidase protein, this was observed by measuring binding affinity between the coumarin derivative and target protein of influenza virus using molecular docking [
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Another research study has shown the neuraminidase inhibitory action of coumarins isolated from methanol extracts from the roots of a plant, Glycyrrhiza uralensis. Glycyrol, a ring-closed coumarin was shown to have the strongest inhibitory activity, the presence of the five-membered furan rings was essential for the potency of polyphenols against neuraminidase [
 <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Other probable targets of a compound containing both coumarin and monoterpenoid derivative in influenza was viral hemagglutinin HA which is involved in viral entry in host cell by membrane fusion. The activities of these compounds against virus is thought to be due to presence of bulky polycyclic moiety which is responsible to block the changes in conformation of HA molecule which is essential for the entry of viruses into host cell. Thus, these derivatives inhibit the activity of the virus by blocking the early stages of viral reproduction [
 <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Due to the high mutation tendency of influenza viral proteins [
 <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>], redox-sensitive pathways which are useful for viral replication and are independent of variability of the strains, are gaining importance as the new target to inhibit viral infection. Coumarins oxidized with 2-iodobenzoic acid (IBX) with different catechol and pyrogallol derivatives have shown antiviral activity against influenza A H1N1 by modulating proteins involved in redox pathways [
 <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>].
</p>
