<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0090">One likely biological determinant of the ability of a virus to jump between species is whether or not they use a cell receptor that is highly conserved across different (mammalian) hosts. The viruses that use conserved receptors ought to be more likely to have a broad host range. A comprehensive review identified that, for 88 human virus species, only one cell receptor was identified. Although this was only 40% of the species of interest, 21 (out of 23) families were illustrated; this set constitutes a good cross section of corresponding taxonomic diversity. Of these 88 species, 22 use nonprotein receptors (e.g., heparin sulfate) and, of the remainder, 2 of the proteins were not entered in the UniProt database (making it impossible to determine whether the protein was “conserved” or not), leaving 64 species from 16 families. On the basis of a published studies of virus host ranges, these viruses have been accorded either a “narrow” host range (if the only nonhuman hosts they were known to infect were other primates) or a “broad” host range (if they were known to infect also other kinds of mammals or birds). Using the UniProt database it can be determined whether the cell receptor protein was “conserved” by quantifying the amino acid sequence homology between humans and mice. (For the subset of proteins where amino acid sequences data were also available for cows, pigs, or dogs, very similar patterns were found) The most prominent characteristic of the plot is that there are no instances of human viruses with wide host ranges that do not use highly conserved cell receptors (i.e., more than 90% amino acid sequence homology). Statistical analysis needs correction for phylogenetic correlation; viruses of the common family are both more likely to use the same cell receptor. This can be crudely (but conservatively) allowed by testing for an association between host range and receptor homology at the family; not species, level. This gives a statistically significant result (
 <italic>P</italic>=.015). Notably, the use of a conserved receptor is a necessary but not sufficient condition for a virus to have a broad host range encompassing different mammalian orders. It follows that a useful piece of knowledge about a novel mammalian virus, helping to predict whether or not it poses a risk to humans, would be to identify the cell receptor it uses. However, this may not always be practicable: at present, the cell receptor used by over half the viruses that infect humans is not known, and this fraction is considerably smaller for those that infect other mammals. The emergence of new human viruses is a long-standing and ongoing biological process. The first line of defense against emerging viruses is effective surveillance. There are three important key points in surveillance (
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Greninger et al., 2009</xref>). First, emerging viruses are everyone’s problem: the ease with which viruses can disperse, potentially worldwide within days, coupled with the very wide geographical distribution of emergence events, means that a coordinated, global surveillance network is essential if we are to ensure rapid detection of novel viruses. This immediately highlights the enormous national and regional differences in detection capacity, with the vast majority of suitable facilities located in Europe or North America. Second, reporting of unusual disease events is patchy, even once detected, reflecting both governance issues and lack of incentives. Third, we need to consider extending the surveillance effort to other mammal populations as well as humans, because these are the most likely source of new human viruses. Improving the situation will require both political will and considerable investment in infrastructure, human capacity and new tools. However, the benefits are potentially enormous (
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Gaynor et al., 2007</xref>). It is possible to forestall an emerging disease event, as experience with SARS has shown. However, our ability to achieve this is closely linked to our ability to detect such an event, and deliver effective interventions, as rapidly as possible. A better understanding of the emergence of new human viruses as a biological and ecological process will allow us to refine our currently very crude notions of the kinds of pathogens, or the kinds of circumstances, we should be most concerned about, and so direct our efforts at detection and prevention more efficiently.
</p>
