<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Influenza A virus ribonucleoprotein complexes (RNPs) are responsible for viral RNA transcription and replication and are central to the viral life cycle [
 <xref rid="pone.0185998.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The RNA comprises a linear viral genome, a single RdRp, and multiple copies of NP monomers. The RdRp is formed by the association of acidic subunit PA and two basic subunits PB1 and PB2. The N-terminal domain of PA functions as an endonuclease, while its C-terminal domain interacts with PB1 [
 <xref rid="pone.0185998.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0185998.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The PB1 subunit performs both de novo RNA-dependent RNA synthesis and mRNA-primed transcription. PB1 contains four conserved motifs that form a large catalytic domain at the center of the protein [
 <xref rid="pone.0185998.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0185998.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The N-terminal domain of PB1 interacts with PA, while its C-terminus interacts with the N-terminus of PB2 [
 <xref rid="pone.0185998.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], forming the RdRp heterotrimer complex. PB2 binds the m
 <sup>7</sup>guanosine (m
 <sup>7</sup>G) cap of host pre-mRNAs and enables downstream cleavage by the endonuclease domain of PA. Cleavage of host pre-mRNA generates a m
 <sup>7</sup>G capped10-13-mer oligonucleotide that serves as a primer for viral RNA transcription. Crystal structures have demonstrated that cap-binding domain of PB2 binds a cap analog m
 <sup>7</sup>GTP while the N-terminal domain interacts with the C-terminus of PB1 [
 <xref rid="pone.0185998.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0185998.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In addition, PB2 plays important roles in polymerase activity, host range, cold sensitivity, and pathogenesis [
 <xref rid="pone.0185998.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0185998.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Nucleotide analog inhibitors targeting the influenza RdRp complex have been an attractive strategy due to frequent occurrence of drug-resistant viruses to M2 ion channel blockers and neuraminidase inhibitors. A clear and detailed mechanism of inhibition of polymerase inhibitors is crucial for the design of effective antivirals.
</p>
