<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our studies also provide a glimpse into the mechanisms of viral clearance in central nervous system. It is noticeable that neither Bartha-gC
 <sub>
  <italic>HB</italic>
 </sub>
 <sub>1201</sub> nor Bartha-gD
 <sub>
  <italic>HB</italic>
 </sub>
 <sub>1201</sub> was able to reduce viral load in brain, although either gC or gD-substituted mutants was capable of inducing protective immunity (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8A</xref>). In contrast, simultaneous substitution of both provided much better protection. There were no obvious or significantly reduced microscopic lesions revealed by HE staining in all organs immunized with Bartha-gCD
 <sub>
  <italic>HB</italic>
 </sub>
 <sub>1201</sub> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>). Moreover, this significantly reduced the viral load in brain (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8B</xref>). Collectively, these results suggest that the clearance of PRV from brain may require immunity induced by multiple viral antigens. Previous studies have demonstrated that neutralizing antibodies play an important role in mediating clearance of several neurotropic viruses from central nervous system, such as rabies virus, sindbis virus, murine hepatitis virus, and so on (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Dietzschold et al., 1992</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Matthews et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Burdeinick-Kerr et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Hooper et al., 2009</xref>). Emerging evidence indicates that antibody blockade of neurotropic viruses requires CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cell-dependent opening of the blood–brain barrier (BBB). For example, antibody-dependent protection against HSV-2 requires IFN-γ secretion by CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells in the mouse model (
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Iijima and Iwasaki, 2016</xref>), and CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cell-dependent antibody access to the CNS is likely required for protection against Rabies virus (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Hooper et al., 1998</xref>). Since the gD genetic variability contributes secondarily to inefficient cross-neutralization but the corresponding chimeric mutant was capable of inducing protective immunity, we speculate that gD-induced cellular immunity may have a cooperative role together with the neutralizing antibodies in helping reduce the viral load in brain. Further experiments are required to test this hypothesis in the future.
</p>
