<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>CRISPR/Cas9 system is a powerful tool for targeted and precise genome editing in eukaryotic cells (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Cong et al., 2013</xref>). So far, it has been widely used in genome editing of many viruses, such as herpes simplex virus (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Roehm et al., 2016</xref>), adenovirus (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Bi et al., 2014</xref>), hepatitis B virus (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2018</xref>), African swine fever virus (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Borca et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Hubner et al., 2018</xref>), and so on. However, most of manipulations were focuses on viral non-essential genes and on insertion of a foreign gene (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Guo et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Liang et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Tang et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). There is no good approach to replace essential genes among the different PRV strains. The key dilemma is that Cas9 can cleave donor sequence, in addition to the target gene, preventing efficient rescue of the recombinant viruses. We developed a novel strategy to solve this problem (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). That is, the sgRNA-targeted donor region was mutated by synonymous mutations to avoid the cleavage by Cas9. In this sense, only recombined virus could be rescued because of essentiality of the target gene. We also found that the length of homologous arm is important for recombination. Although previous study indicated that homologous sequences (50 bp) could result in a higher recombination (
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">Zheng et al., 2014</xref>), we found that longer homologous arms of about 0.5 kb could increase the efficiency of homologous recombination, leading to higher efficiency of virus rescue. In addition, we found that donor DNA in linear form was more efficient in homologous recombination than the circular form. Together, our improvement of CRISPR/Cas9 platform provides an important means for manipulating essential viral genes in the future. This should aid rapid generation of recombinant PRV viruses for vaccine development and dissection of the function of essential genes.
</p>
