<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several studies have investigated the protein–protein interactions between ASFV and swine. Some important interactions were listed as follows: the viral DP71L protein interacts specifically with and activates protein phosphatase 1 (PP1) (
 <xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Rivera et al., 2007</xref>); the viral A224L interacts with the proteolytic fragment of caspase-3 and inhibits the activity of this protease during ASFV infection (
 <xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr">Nogal et al., 2001</xref>); the viral p54 binds to the light chain of cytoplasmic dynein (LC8) to hijack the microtubule motor complex during ASFV infection (
 <xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Alonso et al., 2001</xref>); the viral A238L binds to the catalytic subunit of calcineurin and inhibits NFAT-regulated gene transcription in vivo (
 <xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Miskin et al., 1998</xref>); the viral p30 may down-regulate the mRNA translation of host cells by interacting with hnRNP-K (
 <xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">Hernaez, Escribano &amp; Alonso, 2008</xref>); the viral Ep152R interacts with BAG6 to block the immune response during viral infection (
 <xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Borca et al., 2016</xref>); the viral A179L protein was able to interact with the main core Bcl-2 proapoptotic proteins Bax and Bak, and may play an important role during productive ASFV infection (
 <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Brun et al., 1996</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Galindo et al., 2008</xref>). This study firstly curated a set of protein–protein interactions between ASFV and swine proteins by integration of protein–protein interactions from public databases and literatures; then, the swine proteins related to ASFV infection were identified; their roles in swine protein–protein interaction network and in interacting with other viruses, and their functions were further investigated; finally, the candidate antiviral drugs targeting these swine proteins and ASFV proteins were predicted. This work could not only deepen our understanding towards the ASFV-swine interactions, but also help for the development of effective antiviral drugs against the ASFVs.
</p>
