<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par83">As it is mentioned before, up to now, there is not any special therapy to be effective for reducing COVID-19 infection. However, there are some supportive treatments, like oxygen supply in mild patients and extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for the critical cases. In SARS-infected cases to enhance the survival rate of patients in cases whose state deteriorated, the last resort in treatment was applying immunoglobulins or convalescent plasma despite therapy with pulsed methylprednisolone. Besides, many different studies indicated a shorter hospital stay and less fatality in patients cured with convalescent plasma [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>]. In 2014, WHO suggested the use of convalescent plasma acquired from Ebola virus-infected cases who had recovered as an empirical treatment through prevalence [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>]. In 2015, a protocol for the use of convalescent plasma in the remedy of Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus was appointed [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>]. In a study, Hung and colleagues indicated that in the influenza A H1N1 (H1N1pdm09) virus-infected cases in 2009, there was a great decrease in the relative risk of mortality for those cases treated with convalescent plasma [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>]. Besides, in a subgroup analysis, after convalescent plasma therapy viral load was lower on days 3, 5, and 7 after intensive care unit admission. There were not any adverse events [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>]. One of the results for indicating the efficacy of convalescent plasma treatment is that the antibodies from these kinds of plasma might repress viremia. Schoofs et al. described that 3BNC117-mediated immunotherapy, which is a wide neutralizing antibody to HIV-1, increases host humoral immunity to HIV-1 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>].. Moreover, an in vivo test indicated that the effects of this antibody were not only blocking new infection and viral clearance but also involves fast clearance of infected cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>]. In the first week of infection, Viraemia peaks occur in viral infections. By days 10–14 and through virus clearance, the patient usually arises a primary immune response [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>]. So, theoretically, it looks like that it should be more useful to administer the convalescent plasma at the primary stage of disease [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>]. However, other therapies might affect the connection between antibody level and convalescent plasma, involving antiviral drugs, intravenous immunoglobulin, and steroids [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>]. WHO recommended the main focus on infection prevention, infected detection and monitoring, and supportive treatment for COVID-19. However, there is not any special anti-SARS-CoV-2 treatment recommended due to the lack of evidence. There is a recommendation in a Comment in 
 <italic>The Lancet</italic>, which emphasizes that systematic corticosteroids should not be given typically for the remedy of COVID-19 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>]. Evidence indicates that convalescent plasma from patients who have recovered from viral infections can be applied as a therapy without the occurrence of severe harmful events. So, it might be beneficial to test the efficacy and safety of convalescent plasma transfusion in SARS-CoV-2-infected cases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>]. There are more than 30,000 recovered COVID-19 patients and they are the perfect source of convalescent plasma for health care providers. China National Biotec Group Co has claimed that 10 severely ill patients receiving this convalescent plasma treatment showed better oxygenation and less inflammation and viral load [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">102</xref>]. In one study Chenguang Shen et al., [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref>] used the plasma therapy method for patients.
</p>
