<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Given the increased incidence of IDU-associated infections and overdose deaths [
 <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], there is a need to provide ongoing support for and increased access to SSPs. The HIV outbreak in Scott County, Indiana, in addition to other emerging HBV and HCV epidemics, has highlighted the need to expand SSPs, particularly in nonurban areas [
 <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Although federal funds to support SSPs was an important step, additional federal funding and flexibility are needed to fully cover services and costs associated with these programs, including purchasing of sterile syringes and to support delivery of MOUD at SSPs [
 <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In jurisdictions where SSPs are prohibited or sparse, cities and states should be incentivized to modify their laws and to encourage uptake by local jurisdictions. In some states, there is a limit on the number or location of such programs, or SSPs may only be allowed during certain circumstances (ie, public health emergencies) [
 <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Such limitations should be eliminated given the documented need for these programs and their potential to reduce infectious diseases [
 <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Additionally, drug paraphernalia laws, which prohibit possession of syringes, pose barriers to SSP expansion and effectiveness [
 <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. State and local governments should be encouraged to employ innovative programming, including mobile delivery and contracting with community-based organizations. Additionally, states should be incentivized to eliminate 1-for-1 syringe exchange (ie, exchanging 1 used syringe for 1 sterile syringe) because they create barriers to individuals who inject drugs having an adequate supply of sterile syringes. Secondary exchange, or the distribution of sterile syringes from 1 person to a social network, is often necessary due to distance and transportation barriers.
</p>
