<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>NS1 is encoded by segment 8 of the influenza and range in size 217–237 amino acids. NS1 is comprised of two functional domains, N-terminal RNA-binding domain (RBD) and C-terminal effector domain (ED). RBD, amino acids 1–73 of NS1, forms a six-helical homodimer, and its major role is double-stranded RNA (dsRNA) binding, thereby blocking IFN induction on infection (
 <xref rid="b21-molce-42-10-721" ref-type="bibr">Pichlmair et al., 2006</xref>). ED also dimerizes and binds several cellular proteins (
 <xref rid="b1-molce-42-10-721" ref-type="bibr">Aramini et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="b13-molce-42-10-721" ref-type="bibr">Hale et al., 2008</xref>), which is responsible for sequence variations of different virus strains. In fact, NS1 has multiple functions in infected cells. Of the various functions, the major role of NS1 is the disruption of host cell innate immune system, and inhibits the induction of IFN (
 <xref rid="b12-molce-42-10-721" ref-type="bibr">Garcia-Sastre et al., 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="b17-molce-42-10-721" ref-type="bibr">Kochs et al., 2007</xref>). Thus far, there have been many attempts to elucidate the molecular mechanism by which NS1 suppresses the IFN production. One explanation of the NS1 function is sequestration of viral RNA, which leads to inhibition of main viral RNA sensor RIG-I in the host cell (
 <xref rid="b6-molce-42-10-721" ref-type="bibr">Chien et al., 2004</xref>). Strain-specific direct interaction between NS1 and RIG-I was also suggested. 
 <xref rid="b15-molce-42-10-721" ref-type="bibr">Jureka et al. (2015)</xref> demonstrated that RBD of 1918 H1N1 NS1 interacted directly with second caspase activation and recruitment domain (CARD) of RIG-I, but no interaction was observed in case of Udorn H3N2 strain. In addition to direct interaction, NS1 has been shown to inhibit tripartite motif-containing protein 25 (TRIM25)-mediated RIG-I ubiquitination, which suppresses the RIG-I signaling pathway (
 <xref rid="b9-molce-42-10-721" ref-type="bibr">Gack et al., 2009</xref>). Regarding the RIG-I ubiquitination, two kinds of mechanism were suggested. After recognition of viral RNA harboring 5′-triphosphate by RIG-I, CARD is activated by either TRIM25-mediated ubiquitination (
 <xref rid="b10-molce-42-10-721" ref-type="bibr">Gack et al., 2008</xref>) or binding of polyubiquitin chains that are previously synthesized by TRIM25 (
 <xref rid="b26-molce-42-10-721" ref-type="bibr">Zeng et al., 2010</xref>). However, it is not clear how NS1 antagonizes IFN induction exactly at present. Because of the important role of NS1 during viral infection, many attempts have been made to develop antiviral therapeutics targeting NS1. This involves antiviral compounds (
 <xref rid="b8-molce-42-10-721" ref-type="bibr">Engel, 2013</xref>), antisense oligonucleotides (
 <xref rid="b24-molce-42-10-721" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2014</xref>), nucleic acid aptamers (
 <xref rid="b23-molce-42-10-721" ref-type="bibr">Woo et al., 2013</xref>), and so on.
</p>
