<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Previous research had claimed that DENV 1 and DENV 2 are often associated with primary infections and secondary infections, respectively [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006817.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Contrary to these findings, our investigation revealed insignificant differences between dengue serotypes and infection type as in primary and secondary infection. Indeed, this could be mainly due to low number of secondary infected cases in the present study. In our study, primary dengue infections were found to be more frequent than secondary infections. This finding contradicted with reports of high seroprevalence rate of secondary infection in Malaysia [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006817.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The seroprevalence rates in Malaysia were shown to be age dependent, whereby as the age increases the seroprevalence also increases and by 70 years old almost 80% of the Malaysian population were already infected with dengue. Our findings on secondary infection rate was different from the above study based on two aspects. Firstly, the distribution of subjects by age group in our study indicate that more than half of the study subjects belonged to younger age group (≤ 20); hence, less likely to have past exposures (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0006817.s002">S1 Table</xref>). Past studies also supported this in which a shift of the dengue infection from affecting primarily children to adults more than age 20 years old, was demonstrated [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006817.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006817.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Secondly, in our study, exclusion of samples with incomplete information, unable to be serotyped or genotyped and the coverage of only two locations contributed to small sample size, thus, we are unable to provide a detailed description of the seroprevalence rate. However, our study findings on high primary infection rate could pose a serious implication if the next outbreak is predominantly caused by DENV 2. It is known that severe dengue is associated with secondary infection and infection with DENV 2 superimposed on previous DENV 1 infection carries the highest risk for development of severe dengue [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006817.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Even though the DENV 3 upsurge after the current outbreak is predicted, however as mentioned earlier, one study [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006817.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] has cautioned that this cycle was recently disrupted, raising the possibility for DENV 2 dominance. Therefore, our study findings on the high prevalence of primary infection is very crucial in the conveyance of early warning for a severe outbreak in the future.
</p>
