<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <p id="Par1">Treatments against influenza A viruses (IAV) have to be updated regularly due to antigenic drift and drug resistance. Poly (ADP-ribose) polymerases (PARPs) are considered effective therapeutic targets of acute lung inflammatory injury. This study aimed to explore the effects of PARP-1 inhibitor olaparib on IAV-induced lung injury and the underlying mechanisms. Male wild-type C57BL/6 mice were intranasally infected with IAV strain H1N1 to mimic pneumonia experimentally. Olaparib at different doses was intraperitoneally injected 2 days before and 5 consecutive days after virus stimulation. On day 6 post-infection, lung tissues as well as bronchoalveolar lavage fluid (BALF) were sampled for histological and biochemical analyses. Olaparib increased the survival rate of IAV mice dose-dependently. Olaparib remarkably reduced IAV mRNA expression, myeloperoxidase (MPO) level, and inflammatory cell infiltration in IAV lungs. Moreover, olaparib significantly reduced the level of interleukin (IL)-1β, tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-α, interferon (IFN)-γ, IL-6, and IL-4 and increased IL-10 in IAV lungs. Also, olaparib efficiently reduced IL-6, monocyte chemotactic protein (MCP)-1, granulocyte colony-stimulating factor (G-CSF), TNF-α, chemokine (C–X–C motif) ligand (CXCL)1, CXCL10, chemokine (C–C motif) ligand (CCL)3, and regulated on activation, normal T cell expressed and secreted (RANTES) release in IAV BALF. Olaparib decreased PARylated protein content and p65, IκBα phosphorylation in IAV lung tissues
  <bold>.</bold> This study successfully constructed the pneumonia murine model using IAV. Olaparib decreased IAV-induced mortality in mice, lung injury, and cytokine production possibly via modulation of PARP-1/NF-κB axis.
 </p>
 <sec>
  <title>Electronic supplementary material</title>
  <p>The online version of this article (10.1007/s10096-020-04020-5) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
