<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0045">The biological basis for developing nanovaccines is the activation of the host’s immune system against viruses through nanoagents (
 <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>c). For this purpose, the dominant antigens of viruses can be used to construct nanovaccines for pathogenic viruses. Thus, ENMs loaded with viral antigens (viral nucleic acids or inactivated proteins) can pre-stimulate the immune system to produce specific virus antibodies that promote antiviral inflammatory responses [
 <xref rid="bib0115" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. For instance, Au NPs modified with West Nile virus (WNV) envelope proteins have been demonstrated to stimulate the release of proinflammatory factors (
 <italic>i.e.</italic>, tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α), interleuin-6 (IL-6), interleuin-2 (IL-2) and granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor) to achieve antiviral immune responses [
 <xref rid="bib0125" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Similarly, the loading of viral DNA or RNA onto ENMs is another effective way of preparing nanovaccines by introducing an eukaryotic expression vector to encode the viral antigen protein into a host cell to provoke the immune system into combating viral infections [
 <xref rid="bib0130" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Moreover, ENMs can also be used as an auxiliary to overcome the obstacle of inefficient DNA vaccine intake [
 <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The coadministration of Au NPs with an anti-HCV DNA vaccine was observed to generate vibrational and dipole-like oscillations, increase the DNA vaccine uptake, and ultimately improve antibody levels and immune response to the HCV infection in immunized mice [
 <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Furthermore, nanovaccines based on genetic engineering, bioconjugation, infusion, or mineralization have been successfully applied to treat infections due to HIV-1, Ebola, and foot-and-mouth disease virus (FMDV) [
 <xref rid="bib0140" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].
</p>
