<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Microfluidic or lab-on-a-chip techniques use microsized channels to process or manipulate fluids. Microfluidics has been widely utilized in various fields, including drug screening, tissue engineering, disease diagnostics, and nucleic acid detection [
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Based on its portability and ultralow sample consumption, microfluidics shows significant promises in clinical applications [
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Regarding nucleic acid analyses, microfluidic devices aliquot diluted nucleic acid samples into hundreds to millions of discrete nanoliter chambers. The isolated chambers contain only one or zero target molecule according to a Poisson distribution. Consequently, the absolute copy number of target nucleic acid can be calculated from the number of positive and negative reactions, based on the Poisson distribution formulas [
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Both digital PCR and digital LAMP have employed microfluidics for pathogen analysis, which is suitable for COVID-19 detection. For instance, Ottesen and colleagues used digital PCR to amplify and analyze multiple genes on a microfluidic chip [
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. This chip consisted of parallel chambers and micromechanical valves. The micromechanical valves segmented chambers into independent PCR reactors after the sample flowed into chambers through connection channels. The chip was able to detect several kinds of genes with parallel sample panels. Digital PCR can also be conducted with droplets generated by the microfluidic chip. However, the detection of fluorescent signals in droplets requires special instruments, such as flow cytometers, which may limit its application in point-of-care testing. Additionally, the high temperature in PCR amplification tends to evaporate the reaction liquid (nanoliter or even femtoliter), leading to unacceptable errors. Using airtight devices or high pressure delays liquid evaporation but complicates the devices and increases testing costs.
</p>
