<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<notes notes-type="version-changes">
 <sec sec-type="version-changes">
  <label>Revised</label>
  <title>Amendments from Version 1</title>
  <p>
   <underline>Background</underline>: 
   <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
     <p>We added the text: “Although the YFV vaccine is safe and effective, it does not always reach populations at greatest risk of infection and there is an acknowledged global shortage of vaccine supply”.</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
   <underline>Introduction</underline>: 
   <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
     <p>More details on 
      <italic>Wolbachia</italic> were added.
     </p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
   <underline>Methods</underline>
   <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
     <p>Sample collection – We added Adungo 
      <italic>et al</italic>., 2016 and cited Domingo 
      <italic>et al</italic>., 2012.
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>Mosquitoes and infections – We added the number of mosquitoes analyzed per group and the text: “ 
      <italic>Wolbachia</italic> density was analyzed in the three time-points, being 40 mosquitoes at 7dpf, 39 at 14dpf and 38 mosquitoes after 21dpf.”
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>Mosquito saliva trasmission assay – The word “Individual” was added in the sentence “Individual saliva…” and the following text “Usually, with one saliva sample it is possible to inject 15 mosquitoes, but due mortality, 8 mosquitoes were analyzed from each nanoinjected saliva sample”.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>Viral detection in mosquitoes and mice – We added the following text “Head and thorax samples from YFV-challenged mosquitoes were analyzed in duplicate through RT-qPCR and viral and 
      <italic>Wolbachia</italic> quantification were performed in comparison with serial dilution of a standard curve of the respective genes cloned into the pGEMT plasmid (Promega). Therefore, it was possible to calculate the number of copies per tissue. As a mosquito control gene, we used the RPS 17S sequence of 
      <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> (Moreira, 2009).”
     </p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
   <underline>Results:</underline>
   <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
     <p>Figure 3 legend – added 
      <italic>p</italic> values.
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>Figure 4 legend was corrected.</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
   <underline>Discussion</underline>
   <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
     <p>We added extra text to include the rationale behind giving a second blood meal to infected mosquitoes.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>In the end we added text regarding possible evolution on the system, as requested by the reviewer.</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
 </sec>
</notes>
