<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>More significantly, a cross-serocomplex ADE between ZIKV and DENV has also been reproduced in mouse model. DENV and WNV immune sera were both found to enhance Zika virus infection in mice (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Bardina et al., 2017</xref>). Also, the presence of DENV-specific antibodies in ZIKV-infected pregnant mice significantly enhanced viral replication in placenta, and increased placenta damage, reduced fetal growth, and accelerated fetal resorption (
 <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">Leborgne et al., 2019</xref>). Reciprocally, maternally acquired Zika virus antibodies also enhanced dengue disease severity in mice (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Fowler et al., 2018</xref>). In non-human primate models, the results are not as clear. Two studies did not show enhanced Zika virus infection in macaques that were infected by DENV either 420 days or 2.8 years before experiments (
 <xref rid="B120" ref-type="bibr">McCracken et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B138" ref-type="bibr">Pantoja et al., 2017</xref>). However, it should be noted that the interval between primary and secondary DENV infections is critical for disease severity, and DENV ADE in human has only occurred within a relatively narrow range of pre-existing DENV antibody concentration (
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">Katzelnick et al., 2017</xref>). In dengue infected patients, this interval was usually 12 months or longer, but unknown for enhancement of Zika virus infection. Limited data from a long-term cohort study in Brazil before and after the 2015 ZIKV outbreak have found that the pre-existing DENV NS1 specific IgG3 antibody within 4–6 months of infection was positively associated with the risk of subsequent ZIKV infection, but high titer of total IgG to DENV was associated with protection against the acquisition of ZIKV infection (
 <xref rid="B154" ref-type="bibr">Rodriguez-Barraquer et al., 2019</xref>). Our previous study using sera of convalescent dengue patients also revealed that stronger cross-serocomplex ADE of ZIKV infection in PBMC appeared more often in sera obtained within 3 months of DENV infection (
 <xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2018</xref>). These results are supportive of the idea that concentrations of cross-reactive antibodies or intervals between two infections are important factors for determining cross-serocomplex enhancement between ZIKV and DENV.
</p>
