<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par37">Oseltamivir and zanamivir are the two major NAIs currently in clinical use in most countries. Both target the NA surface protein, inhibiting cleavage of viral HA from sialic acid residues expressed on the cell surface.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>
 </sup> Oseltamivir is active orally (or via a nasogastric tube) and zanamivir is normally administered via inhalation as a dry powder (or as an intravenous infusion in certain circumstances). Alternatives are available in some countries including intravenous peramivir and the long-acting inhaled NAI, laninamivir,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>
 </sup> and Baloxavir marboxil, the most recent antiviral to be approved. Baloxavir is an oral, single-dose, cap-dependent endonuclease that inhibits influenza polymerase, thus interrupting the synthesis of new virions. The addition of an antiviral that acts in a different way to NAIs is useful, but there is already evidence of decreased susceptibility to baloxavir emerging in clinical trials.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>
 </sup> Since early treatment may prevent progression to severe illness,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>
 </sup> guidelines generally recommend empirical antiviral treatment (oseltamivir or zanamivir) when influenza is suspected and while awaiting laboratory confirmation.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>
 </sup> Molecular tests for influenza viruses, typically PCR detection methods, are commonly used in hospital and tend to perform better than non-molecular rapid diagnostic tests. Point of care molecular platforms mean that diagnostics are now available for use in clinical areas, in addition to laboratory-based diagnostic testing. Regardless of the methods used, high quality sampling is required. This includes obtaining lower respiratory tract samples when there is evidence of lower respiratory tract disease, since lower respiratory tract samples may be positive when upper respiratory tract samples are negative.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
