<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>According to a study published in medRxiv, the preprint health sciences server, BCG vaccination seems to be contributing significantly in reduction of number of COVID-19 deaths, with the most substantial reduction in deaths observed in countries that had adopted a BCG vaccination policy earlier, suggesting that there might be less COVID-19 cases and mortality in those countries.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="cit0073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>
 </sup> Though it is early to declare and would need further investigations before a conclusion is reached, the statistical figures on BCG vaccination in India during the early 1950s with target coverage of 80% indicate that the country might benefit from the presence of enhanced acquired innate immunity in a large population. Nevertheless, the low- and middle-income countries have reported 0–0.78 deaths per million, while the countries that adopted a universal BCG policy later than other countries, like Iran in 1984, have exhibited a high death rate, which is contrary to the hypothesis that BCG protects the vaccinated population against COVID-19. The current population of India is 1339.2 million, and to date, India has reported 0.42 deaths per million, which is in accordance with the calculations and range provided by Miller and coworkers.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>
 </sup> Based on the current situation and data available, we can say that BCG vaccination may have an influence on the number of COVID-19 cases and deaths and might provide protection against COVID-19 but to show the actual causality between BCG vaccine and severity of COVID-19, the scientists must confirm the Bradford Hill Criteria which include specificity, reversibility, temporality, and experiment.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="cit0079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>
 </sup> There have been inconsistencies in data related to COVID-19 collected from different countries,; therefore, its important to have a proven result for the use of BCG vaccine in context of COVID-19. Toward this end, it is reported that three clinical trials, with an aim to confirm the role of BCG vaccine in protection against COVID-19, have been intiated.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
  <xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
  <xref rid="cit0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,
  <xref rid="cit0080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>
 </sup> The clinical trial planned by Max Plank Institute for Infection Biology in Berlin include the use of genetically modified version of BCG while other two trails have been planned in Australia and Netherland. However, some group also suggest that COVID-19 vaccination should include multiple-doses of BCG vaccine.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
