<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our study capitalized on using the set of RNA viruses in Alto et al., (
 <xref rid="ece36287-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>) as an empirical model to test the general scenario of populations well‐adapted versus maladapted in their current environments, and whether this differing prior history affected rate of fitness improvement under a new challenge. Environmental fluctuations (e.g., random temperatures) can either cause maladaptation or select for adaptive generalism, which may fortuitously increase ability to invade novel environments (Ketola et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36287-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>); whereas a static environment (e.g., constant 37°C) tends to select for specialists (Kassen, 
 <xref rid="ece36287-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>). Furthermore, the genetic architectures of populations evolved under these scenarios also should differ. For example, a population selected in environments A and B should have a different genetic signature than a population selected in environment A or B alone, attributable to mutations with fitness trade‐offs that are unlikely to fix in a population selected in both environments. Our data are consistent with the idea that populations selected in stochastically fluctuating (random) environments are advantaged at niche limits (Kassen, 
 <xref rid="ece36287-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>; Levins, 
 <xref rid="ece36287-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">1968</xref>). Also, altered thermal tolerance limits have been observed in 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> (“stepping stone” and “sliding niche” hypotheses, Mongold, Bennett, &amp; Lenski, 
 <xref rid="ece36287-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">1996</xref>; Mongold, Bennett, &amp; Lenski, 
 <xref rid="ece36287-bib-0046" ref-type="ref">1999</xref>) and 
 <italic>Drosophila</italic> (Huey, Partridge, &amp; Fowler, 
 <xref rid="ece36287-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">1991</xref>; Watson &amp; Hoffmann, 
 <xref rid="ece36287-bib-0058" ref-type="ref">1996</xref>) following selection in higher or fluctuating temperatures. Although the current study was not intended to test a specific circumstance in the evolution of natural virus populations, our results could help inform how virus adaptation might proceed in roughly analogous situations.
</p>
