<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec id="sec001">
  <title>Background</title>
  <p>The epidemic of hand, foot, and mouth disease (HFMD) has become a severe public health problem in the world and has also brought a high economic and health burden. Furthermore, the prevalence of HFMD varies significantly among different locations. However, there have been few investigations of the effects of socioeconomic factors and air pollution factors on the incidence of HFMD.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec002">
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>This study collected data on HFMD in Shenzhen, China, from 2012 to 2015. We selected eleven factors as potential risk factors for HFMD. A Bayesian spatiotemporal model was used to quantify the influence of the factors on HFMD and to identify the relative risks in different districts.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec003">
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>The risk factors of HFMD were the population, population density, concentration of SO
   <sub>2</sub>, and concentration of NO
   <sub>2</sub>. The relative risks (
   <italic>RRs</italic>) were 1.00473 (95% 
   <italic>CI</italic>: 1.00059–1.00761), 1.00010 (95% 
   <italic>CI</italic>: 1.00002–1.00016), 1.00215 (95% 
   <italic>CI</italic>: 1.00170–1.00232) and 1.00058 (95% 
   <italic>CI</italic>: 1.00028–1.00078), respectively. The protective factors against HFMD were the per capita GDP, the number of public kindergartens, the concentration of PM
   <sub>10</sub>, and the concentration of O
   <sub>3</sub>. The 
   <italic>RRs</italic> were 0.98840 (95% 
   <italic>CI</italic>: 0.98660–0.99026), 0.97686 (95% 
   <italic>CI</italic>: 0.96946–0.98403), 0.99108 (95% 
   <italic>CI</italic>: 0.98551–0.99840) and 0.99587 (95% 
   <italic>CI</italic>: 0.99534–0.99610), respectively. The risk of incidence in Longgang district and Pingshan district decreased, while the risk of incidence in Baoan district increased.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec004">
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p>Studies have confirmed that socioeconomic factors and air pollution factors have an impact on the incidence of HFMD in Shenzhen, China. The results will be of great practical significance to local authorities, which is conducive to accurate prevention and can be used to formulate HFMD early warning systems.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
