<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18">Interferon (IFNs) induces the expression of interferon-stimulated genes (ISGs) for defense against numerous viral infections. IFNs have been classified into three major subfamilies: type I IFNs (comprising mainly IFN-α and IFN-β), type II IFNs (IFN-γ), and the recently identified type III IFNs (IFN-λ). Type I interferons(T1-IFN)have immune defense effect on many viral infections [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>] and are a critical effector of the innate immune response following virus infection. IFN-α/β is a pluripotent inflammatory cytokine typically induced by viral infections. IFN-α is produced by leukocytes while IFN-β is a fibroblast product. IFN-α suppresses classical swine fever virus (CSFV) replication through Interferon stimulated gene 15 (ISG15) mediated Beclin-1 (BECN1) ISGylation and autophagy inhibition [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. IFN-α inhibits acute IAV replication and controls the excessive immunopathology caused by IAV. A recent study showed that IFN-α and IFN-β both have protective effects during acute chikungunya virus (CHIKV) infection, but the mechanisms are different. IFN-α inhibits CHIKV replication, whereas IFN-β prevents CHIKV pathogenesis by alleviating inflammation induced by neutrophils [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. IFN-γ, as type II interferons are released by activated T cells, natural killer cells (NK cells), and NKT cells. IFN-γ plays an important role in both innate and adaptive immunity. IFN-γ is a hallmark cytokine of type I helper T cells (Th1 cells), which have antivirus, immune regulation, and antitumor properties. Type III IFN or IFN-λ is mainly as an epithelial cytokine, which inhibits viral replication in epithelial cells and has a protective effect on mucosal sites [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. IFN-λ exhibits biological characteristics, signal transducer, and effector functions similar to T1-IFN. IFN-λ also acts directly or indirectly on NK cells to potentiate their activation and protect against viruses. Studies have shown that IFN-λ controls multiple gut viruses and is a potent innate immune regulator of intestinal viral infections, such as rotavirus, reovirus, norovirus, enterovirus, parvovirus, and coronavirus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. IFN-λ restricts Influenza A virus (IAV) replication and alleviates infection‐induced morbidity, while prevents the potential inflammatory complications associated with IFNα [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. IFN-λ also suppresses the replication of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV) in both lung and gastrointestinal tracts. IFN-λ3 has anti-HBV activities and immune-modulatory effects to restrict HBV replication. Preclinical studies show that IFN-λ effectively inhibits HCV replication and has fewer side effects than IFN-α due to its more restricted receptor distribution [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. While treating the inflammatory diseases biological agents are effective sources, but they have some limitations which includes the loss of response and cost. Also they may have large number of side effects in patients. Here an example is that many patients do not tolerate chimeric antibodies because of the hypersensitivity reactions to the agents which are non-human components. There is another issue regarding immunosuppression which results in increasing the microorganisms’ infections so in patients the latent infections may reactivate such as tuberculosis, Hepatitis B and Pnuemocystis pneumonia. As these agents should be administrated subcutaneously or intravenously so there is also an issue regarding their administration because of the reaction of the site of injection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>].
</p>
