<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0170">Three important animal pathogens have been treated with CP: avian influenza virus (AIV), Newcastle disease virus (NDV), and porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome virus (PRRSv). All three viruses pose a significant threat to global food security and economic stability. Some strains of AIV can cause up to 100% mortality in chickens (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/flu/avianflu/influenza-a-virus-subtypes.htm" id="ir0020" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.cdc.gov/flu/avianflu/influenza-a-virus-subtypes.htm</ext-link>), and some strains of NDV can cause up to 100% mortality in different avian species [
 <xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Prevention of their spread by vaccination is essential. Vaccines against both viruses would benefit from improvements that would allow them to be more cost-effective, provide higher immune protection, and decrease the risk of disease development by ensuring complete virus inactivation without affecting the antigens responsible for inducing the immune response [
 <xref rid="bb0180" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0185" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. For this purpose, CP was used as a possible inactivation step in vaccine preparation [
 <xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Complete inactivation was achieved after a 2-min treatment with a plasma jet. This was shown to be ideal for vaccine preparation because longer treatment times can alter the antigen determinants responsible for immunogenicity. Both vaccines have been used to successfully induce the production of specific antibodies, and the NDV vaccine induced even higher antibody titers than the traditionally inactivated vaccines. Additional prevention methods to stop the spread of these viruses include decontamination of surfaces and tools that are in contact with potentially infected poultry by using CP-activated solutions. It has been shown that, at specific ratios, CP-activated distilled water, 0.9% NaCl, and 0.3% H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> completely inactivated viruses, and the chicken embryos attained 100% survival [
 <xref rid="bb0190" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].
</p>
