<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="bullet">
 <list-item>
  <p>Carey, Monath and co-workers 
   <xref rid="pntd.0003398-Carey1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, 
   <xref rid="pntd.0003398-Monath1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref> provided evidence of nosocomial and extra-nosocomial chains that are examples of human-to-human transmission of LASV. Based on these early works
   <xref rid="pntd.0003398-Carey1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, 
   <xref rid="pntd.0003398-Monath1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref> and on the arguments listed in the introduction, it is reasonable to hypothesize that a proportion 
   <inline-formula>
    <inline-graphic xlink:href="pntd.0003398.e037.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </inline-formula> of hospitalized patients in KGH (
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd-0003398-g002">Fig. 2</xref>) contracted the disease from a human source (see section “Available data and evidence of human-to-human transmission”).
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>The next step was to estimate this proportion 
   <inline-formula>
    <inline-graphic xlink:href="pntd.0003398.e038.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </inline-formula> ensuring that aspects of (
   <italic>e.g.</italic> the effective reproduction number) the epidemic curve from KGH are compatible with those in the observed chains 
   <xref rid="pntd.0003398-Carey1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, 
   <xref rid="pntd.0003398-Monath1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>To this end, we employed and re-adapted the method of Wallinga and Teunis 
   <xref rid="pntd.0003398-Wallinga1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, who developed a method to calculate the effective reproduction number (which takes into account depletion of susceptibles) for an epidemic curve. If the network of transmission is known, no further information is required (see section “The effective reproduction number in the nosocomial and extra-nosocomial outbreaks”). Otherwise the distribution of the generation time, 
   <italic>i.e.</italic> the time between a primary case and a secondary case, needs to be ascertained (see section “The effective reproduction number for cases of hospitalised patients in KGH”).
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>An important feature of the approach of 
   <xref rid="pntd.0003398-Wallinga1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref> is the option to consider a fraction of cases in the curve as externally imported, 
   <italic>i.e.</italic> people being infected outside the community. In the context of hospitalized patients in KGH, the cases from animal-to-human transmission are interpreted as externally imported cases, whose proportion is 
   <inline-formula>
    <inline-graphic xlink:href="pntd.0003398.e039.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </inline-formula>. As we don't know which cases arises from zoonotic or human origin, we randomly selected a fraction 
   <inline-formula>
    <inline-graphic xlink:href="pntd.0003398.e040.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </inline-formula> of the number of hospitalized patients at the Lassa ward and considered this subset of the epidemic curve as a pure human-to-human chain of transmission. This random sampling was repeated many times to ensure the findings are based on a reliable statistics.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>We calculated i) a daily mean effective reproduction numbers, 
   <inline-formula>
    <inline-graphic xlink:href="pntd.0003398.e041.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </inline-formula> and 
   <inline-formula>
    <inline-graphic xlink:href="pntd.0003398.e042.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </inline-formula> (definition below and in the glossary in 
   <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0003398.s001">S1 Text</xref>), associated with the nosocomial and extra-nosocomial chains of pure human-to-human transmission 
   <xref rid="pntd.0003398-Carey1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, 
   <xref rid="pntd.0003398-Monath1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref> as well as the corresponding distributions of the generation times; ii) based on these distributions of the generation times we then estimated a daily mean effective reproduction numbers, 
   <inline-formula>
    <inline-graphic xlink:href="pntd.0003398.e043.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </inline-formula>, associated to each subset, consisting of a fraction 
   <inline-formula>
    <inline-graphic xlink:href="pntd.0003398.e044.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </inline-formula> of patients, of the epidemic curve from KGH; iii) finally, by imposing equality of the two reproduction numbers: either 
   <inline-formula>
    <inline-graphic xlink:href="pntd.0003398.e045.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </inline-formula> or 
   <inline-formula>
    <inline-graphic xlink:href="pntd.0003398.e046.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </inline-formula>, we estimated the proportion of cases arising from human-to-human transmission, 
   <inline-formula>
    <inline-graphic xlink:href="pntd.0003398.e047.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </inline-formula>.
  </p>
 </list-item>
</list>
