<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The cellular responses to vaccination were measure by IFN-γ ELISpot assay with peptide arrays (A/New Caledonia/20/1999 NR-2606; A/Puerto Rico/8/1934 NR-18973; A/California/07/2009 NR-19244; A/Brisbane/59/2007 NR-18970) provided by Biodefense and Emerging Infections Research Resources Repository NIAID (BEI Resources, Manassas, VA, USA). All peptide arrays span the entire HA gene and consist of 13 to 17-mers with 11 or 12 amino acid overlap. Potential immunogenic peptides were identified using a matrix of peptide pools and confirmed using individual peptides, whereas total T cell responses were performed with a pool of all peptides in the array. Polyvinylidene difluoride-backed 96-well plates (MultiScreen-IP, Millipore Sigma, Burlington, MA, USA) were coated with 50 µL of anti-mouse IFN-γ mAb AN18 (5 µg/mL; Mabtech, Stockholm, Sweden) overnight at 4 °C. Plates were washed 4× with PBS and blocked in RPMI with 5% FBS at 37 °C for one hour. Equal volumes (50 µL) of the single-cell suspension splenocytes (2 × 10
 <sup>6</sup> cells/mL) and peptide (5 ug/mL) were added to the wells before overnight incubation at 37 °C and 5% CO
 <sub>2</sub>. Plates were washed 6× with PBS and incubated with 100 µL of biotinylated anti-mouse IFN-γ R4-6A2 mAb (1:1000 dilution; Mabtech, Stockholm, Sweden) diluted in PBS with 1.0% FBS. After an hour incubation at RT, Plates were washed 6× with PBS and incubated with 100 µL of streptavidin-alkaline phosphatase conjugate (1:1000 dilution; Mabtech, Stockholm, Sweden) diluted in PBS 1.0% FBS for one hour. The plates were washed 6× with PBS before development. 100 µL of BCIP/NBT (Plus) alkaline phosphatase substrate (Thermo Fisher, Waltham, MA, USA) was added to each well and development was stopped by rinsing several times in dH
 <sub>2</sub>O. Plates were air dried prior to analysis by an automated ELISpot plate reader (AID iSpot Reader Spectrum; Autoimmun Diagnostika GmbH, Straberg, Germany). Data is shown as spot-forming cells (SFC) per 10
 <sup>6</sup> splenocytes.
</p>
