<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par60">The coexpression of ACE2 receptors and TMPRSS2 transmembrane proteases by type 2 pneumocytes explains the susceptibility of the lungs to SP-mediated SARS-Cov-2 infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Well-differentiated type 2 pneumocytes express ACE2 more abundantly than poorly differentiated cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. The targeting of these critical lung cells by SP has important functional consequences that manifest as SARS. SARS initially presents as fever, lethargy, pain, and cough, although it rapidly advances to shortness of breath and pneumonia. Macrophages of the innate immune system in the lungs likely detect SARS-Cov-A using RNA viral genome-recognizing RIG-like receptors, a specific type of toll-like receptor (TLR) present on dendritic cells and macrophages designed to complex with foreign molecules. Binding of the viral RNA to RIG-like receptors induces the recruitment of MyD88 and MAVS [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. These two proteins promote NF-kB and type 1 interferon production culminating in the release of IL-6 and TNF alpha cytokines [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. This immune cascade results in extensive tracheobronchial inflammation, diffuse alveolar damage, alveolar edema, pneumocyte desquamation, fibrin deposition, pneumocyte hyperplasia, and recruitment of alveolar macrophages 
 <bold>(</bold>Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>
 <bold>)</bold> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Furthermore, a less severe form of pneumoconiosis known as anthracosis develops due to carbon accumulation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. SP interacts with ACE2 receptors on alveolar macrophages, both types of pneumocytes in the lungs, and the bronchial and submucosal gland epithelium of the upper airways [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. After replication, SARS-Cov-2 preferentially exits cells via the apical surface, returning it to the lumen where it can continue to propagate through lung tissues [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>].
</p>
