<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">One of the most common approaches in antiviral drug discovery is rational drug design, which is based on the understanding of the structures and functions of target molecules. It comprises three steps of drug design: (1) identification of the receptor or enzyme relevant for the disease that the drug is being developed for, (2) discovery of the structure and function of the receptor or enzyme of interest and (3) use of the information from step 2 in order to design a drug molecule that would interact with the receptor or enzyme in a therapeutically beneficial way. The best known example of this approach is azidothymidine (AZT), used in the treatment of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), which acts by inhibiting HIV reverse transcription. Interestingly, it was originally developed to target reverse transcription of avian retroviruses that may cause cancer and was later successfully applied to HIV as well (Olivero 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">2018</xref>). The other widely used approach is high-throughput screening (HTS) methods, which enable validation of a number of biological modulators against a chosen set of defined targets. They yield rich data sets over a short span of time by combining expertise in liquid handling and robotic automation, multiplatform plate reading and high-content imaging. The number of thus emerged “active hits” is normally around 2% of the total number of potential biological modulators screened. Steps in HTS pipeline can be summarized as follows: (1) sample preparation, (2) sample handling and (3) readouts and data acquisition. The most common HTS methods are targeted/selected screens, diversity and high-content screens and RNAi screens (Szymański et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">2012</xref>). Targeted or selected screening is based on identification of compounds that can selectively inhibit or bind to a specific protein of interest. If the crystal structure of the protein of interest is known, it is usually done by in silico three-dimensional (3-D) modelling, while if the ligand for the protein of interest is known, software can search libraries for the other compounds with similar characteristics and binding properties. Examples of such approach include identification of compounds against HIV, filoviruses, poxviruses, arenaviruses, etc. (Marriott et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">1999</xref>). Another commonly used screening method is diversity screening, based on identification of compounds that inhibit viral replication or pathogenesis at any level. This approach involves a much broader target base, instead of focusing the screening against one specific protein of interest. It has been applied in the identification of candidate small-molecule inhibitors against dengue virus, yellow fever virus and New World arenaviruses (Valler and Green 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">2000</xref>). High-content screening (HCS) is a subclass of diversity screening method developed upon automation of cellular imaging and analysis techniques. It allows imaging multiple cells at the same time and measurement of multiple parameters, such as shape, texture, staining localization and intensity, total number of cells, size of the nucleus and percentage of virus-positive cells (Brodin and Christophe 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2011</xref>). Another type of screening for antiviral drug discovery is RNAi screens. siRNAs incorporate into the RNA-induced silencing complex and bind to the target mRNA, thereby inducing degradation of the mRNA and thus preventing its translation into a protein. shRNA, on the other hand, silences protein by forming a “short hairpin” loop through folding back upon itself. Genome-wide RNAi screens have been used to study the pathogenesis of HIV, influenza virus, West Nile virus, Ebola virus, etc. (Hirsch 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2010</xref>). In addition to the above-mentioned methods, recent advances in genomics, bioinformatics and associated technologies offer new opportunities in antiviral drug discovery. Computational methods enabled construction of databases that contain information related to biological function, chemical structure, biologic activity and many other properties of potential antiviral compounds that can all contribute to identification of new lead bioactive species (Prichard 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">2007</xref>).
</p>
