<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par37">Based on in vitro macrolide sensitivity tests, the macrolide resistance rates of MP pneumonia have recently been identified as 50–90% in Asia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]; these rates differ dramatically among nations. When we defined clinical MSMP, MLEP, and MRMP according to fever duration after the initiation of macrolides in each pneumonia episode, regardless of the results of in vitro macrolide sensitivity tests, the ratios of clinical MLEP and MRMP of total MP pneumonia showed increasing trends after adjustment for monthly time series. However, the estimated clinical MRMP/total MP pneumonia ratio during the study period in the present study (0.0–11.0%) was far lower than that based on in vitro macrolide sensitivity tests (50–90%, especially in Asia) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Therefore, the results of our present study suggest that the clinical response to macrolides in MP pneumonia in the real world might not be as weak as that has been reported, based on in vitro macrolide sensitivity tests, which could partially be due to the self-limiting features of MP infections [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Due to the high prevalence of MRMP, there are a great deal of concerns regarding second-line treatment options for MRMP, including tetracycline or fluoroquinolones [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Some previous studies have reported no significant differences with respect to clinical and radiologic findings between MRMP and MSMP pneumonia in children [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. When combined with the results of the present and previous studies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], a considerable proportion of cases of macrolide-resistant MP pneumonia might be recategorized as clinical MSMP or MLEP pneumonia. Therefore, the first-line treatment for MP pneumonia can be initially started, even in cases of MRMP pneumonia. Considering the exaggerated immune response in children with MP pneumonia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], the application of immune-modulators, such as corticosteroids or immunoglobulin, rather than antibiotics, might play more important roles in the management of MP pneumonia, even in some cases of MLEP or MRMP pneumonia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. When selecting the proper treatment strategy for MLEP and MRMP pneumonia, consideration of diverse clinical courses, including self-limiting features and combined immune responses in each case, might be more important than the results of in vitro sensitivity tests to macrolide.
</p>
