<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="simple">
 <list-item>
  <label>(1)</label>
  <p>As mAbs mediated Fc-effector activities are epitope dependent, identifying epitopes that can elicit nnAbs will serve as a good start for the rational design of universal vaccines and therapeutics. Some studies show that ADCC-Abs recognize linear epitopes [
   <xref rid="B70-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Arunkumar et al. demonstrated that antibodies recognizing conformational epitopes exhibit better protection compared to the antibodies targeting linear epitopes [
   <xref rid="B17-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Further investigation should be focused on the elucidation of which epitope type can induce a more potent ADCC response and as a result provide better protection.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <label>(2)</label>
  <p>ADCC-Abs may also exert immune pressure on the virus, resulting in escape mutants that evade antibody recognition similar to what is seen with traditional neutralizing antibodies. No influenza studies have reported ADCC-antibody escape mutants currently, but Chung et al. demonstrated the critical amino acids in the linear epitope could mutate to escape ADCC responses in HIV-1 [
   <xref rid="B139-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">139</xref>]. Lee et al. summarized two potential mechanisms employed by HIV-1 to resist ADCC responses, i. by directly reducing envelope antigen expression on the infected cell surface and ii. by restricting the exposure of epitopes on the envelope to reduce antibody binding [
   <xref rid="B56-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
   <xref rid="B140-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>,
   <xref rid="B141-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">141</xref>]. Similar or different scenarios may present in influenza, which may need further exploration in future studies.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <label>(3)</label>
  <p>It remains unclear about the viral replication step(s) in which ADCC occurs. It is indicated that ADCC activity does not intervene in viral entry and fusion and there is a high possibility that ADCC may target the virus-infected cell, which has HA, or other virus protein expressed [
   <xref rid="B142-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">142</xref>]. This should be better investigated.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <label>(4)</label>
  <p>Designing antibodies with enhanced capacity to induce ADCC activities against influenza infection should be pursued vigorously. As stated above, new approaches are being developed to augment ADCC in cancer research. These studies in cancer research may provide valuable insights into influenza research towards developing better vaccines or therapeutics to improve influenza patient outcomes. Therefore, it would be beneficial to measure the ADCC potency threshold for protective immunity. However, it is worth noting that a more potent ADCC response may not guarantee better protection. Arunkumar et at. reported that two non-neutralizing antibodies, KL-BHA-9B9 and KL-BHA-4C10, exhibited uncorrelated ADCC activity with 
   <italic>in vivo</italic> protection [
   <xref rid="B17-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. KL-BHA-9B9 had potent ADCC activity 
   <italic>in vitro</italic> but poor protection 
   <italic>in vivo</italic>, whereas KL-BHA-4C10 conferred strong protection 
   <italic>in vivo</italic> but had almost undetectable ADCC 
   <italic>in vitro</italic>. A better understanding of ADCC activation may facilitate the mechanistic elucidation of this phenomenon as well as other variabilities emerged in current assays.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <label>(5)</label>
  <p>Although diverse assays have been developed to measure ADCC activity 
   <italic>in vitro</italic>, it is still obscure to what extent these assays can correlate to the efficacy 
   <italic>in vivo</italic>. It is challenging to predict ADCC-Ab efficacy in humans. The transgenic mouse model expresses human FcγRs may better evaluate the antibody therapeutic effect in humans. However, mice are not natural hosts of influenza and influenza viruses causing human epidemics or pandemics typically replicate inefficiently in this animal model unless adapted viruses are used. Non-human primate models such as rhesus macaques or cynomolgus macaques are used in ADCC-Abs research and research findings from this model collectively indicated that ADCC-Abs are associated with reduced shedding of influenza viruses [
   <xref rid="B16-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
   <xref rid="B130-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>]. Considering the different expression patterns of FcγRs in humans and non-human primate animals, it remains uncertain whether the correlation of treatment outcome can be expected in humans. In this regard, clinical studies regarding ADCC-Abs are instrumental to examine the potential role of ADCC-Abs in combating influenza virus infection in humans [
   <xref rid="B143-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">143</xref>].
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <label>(6)</label>
  <p>It would be interesting and worthwhile to study the synergy between neutralizing antibody and non-neutralizing antibody 
   <italic>in vivo</italic> since both classes of antibodies will be elicited after viral infection. The high complexity of each type of antibodies and the lack of an ideal animal model make this investigation relatively challenging. In some cases, the Fc-effector functions induced by nnAb can increase the potency of neutralizing antibodies [
   <xref rid="B14-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. In contrast, it is also revealed that Fc-effector functions may not play any role when there is a high dose of neutralizing antibodies [
   <xref rid="B29-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. One possible explanation for this is that the function elicited by neutralizing antibodies, such as viral entry blocking or fusion disruption, is potent and sufficient for 
   <italic>in vivo</italic> protection alone.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <label>(7)</label>
  <p>The interplay among ADCC-Abs targeting HA, NA, M2e and NP needs to be investigated. It is critical to identify what antibody combination patterns can induce synergistic protection to augment vaccine efficacy. It is reported that the NA-inhibiting antibody elicited weak ADCC response alone, but it may cooperate with antibodies targeting the HA stem to enhance their potency of ADCC activity [
   <xref rid="B83-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. NA inhibitors can enhance Fc-dependent functions induced by anti-stalk antibody, suggesting a therapeutic synergy between NA inhibitors and anti-stalk antibody in humans [
   <xref rid="B144-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>]. Deng et al. demonstrated that the vaccination with double-layered nanoparticles containing HA-stalk and M2e induced potent long-lasting immunity and full protection against divergent influenza A viruses challenge in mice, indicating that the combination of antibodies targeting HA stalk domain and M2e can improve the potency and breadth of vaccine-induced protection [
   <xref rid="B145-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>]. The cocktail of therapeutic antibodies may overcome the emergence of viral escape mutants [
   <xref rid="B37-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Further studies on antibody or inhibitor interplay may guide the better design of future universal anti-influenza countermeasures with broad-spectrum protection via multiple mechanisms.
  </p>
 </list-item>
</list>
