<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To overcome the barrier to HIV entry and infection in mouse cells, Browning et al. [
 <xref rid="B30-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] generated human CD4 and CCR5 double Tg mice (hu CD4/CCR5 Tg mice). Though human CD4 and a chemokine receptor CCR5 helped HIV-1 to enter mouse cells, establishment of further 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> infection and replication in these human CD4/CCR5 Tg mice was not observed due to other cellular blocks [
 <xref rid="B31-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Tg rats with human CD4 and CCR5 also supported HIV infection; however, as in double Tg mice, spread of the virus was blocked [
 <xref rid="B32-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Transient trans complementation of human Tat interacting protein Cyclin T1 elevated HIV gene expression, suggesting novel ways of enhancing HIV infection and replication in rat models [
 <xref rid="B32-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Multiple research groups have constructed different Tg mice that express the whole or partial HIV-1 genome. They include Tg mice expressing the HIV-1 genome with modified long terminal repeats (LTR), resulting in cataracts, weeping eyes, and wasting in Tg mice [
 <xref rid="B33-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]; 3′ half of the HIV genome, causing severe nephropathy [
 <xref rid="B34-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]; and expression of HIV-1 Tat or Nef proteins, leading to epidermal hyperplasia [
 <xref rid="B35-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Hanna et al [
 <xref rid="B36-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] constructed Tg mice by expressing entire HIV coding sequences in T-cells and cells of the macrophage/dendritic cell lineage under the control of a human CD4 promoter flanked by an enhancer of mouse CD4. Tg mice expressing defective provirus with gag and pol genes deleted or expressing individual HIV-1 genes have been shown to develop various pathologies resembling those in humans [
 <xref rid="B37-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. 
 <italic>In vivo</italic>, a negative factor (Nef) was observed to promote viral replication and pathogenicity. Tg mice expressing entire coding sequences of HIV-1 (CD4/HIV
 <sup>WT</sup>) or HIV-1 Nef alone (CD4C/HIV
 <sup>Nef</sup>) under the control of a CD4 promoter in HIV-1 target cells showed human AIDS-like symptoms [
 <xref rid="B38-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Inducible HIV-1 type Nef Tg mice (
 <xref rid="viruses-11-00252-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) were generated using a tetracycline-inducible system to prevent the developmental defects due to the continuous expression of Nef in CD4C/HIV
 <sup>nef</sup> Tg mice. The Nef gene was induced in (CD4C/rtTA X TRE/HIV
 <sup>Nef</sup>) or (CD4C/rtTA2
 <sup>S</sup>-M2 X TRE/HIV
 <sup>Nef</sup>) double-Tg mice upon doxycycline (DOX) treatment, and these mice developed disease similar to that seen in constitutively Nef-expressing 
</p>
