<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The primary reason for the difference between mass action and standard incidences with disease fatalities is that with standard incidence, the number of contacts remains the same regardless of the population size or density, whereas in mass action incidence the number of contacts decreases as the population density decreases. For a few systems where data are available, either standard or mass action incidence, have provided reasonable fits to observed data in wildlife. For example, standard incidence was fit to feline leukemia virus (FeLV) data from feral cats (
 <xref rid="b69" ref-type="ref">Fromont et al. [1997]</xref>) and mass action incidence (plus transmission of the virus via the environment) was fit to avian influenza data from wild birds from the Camargue, France (
 <xref rid="b144" ref-type="ref">Roche et al. [2009]</xref>). Estimates for the transmission rate for FeLV were obtained from the “time between the first contact with a contagious individual and the onset of infection” (
 <xref rid="b69" ref-type="ref">Fromont et al. [1997]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b133" ref-type="ref">Pedersen et al. [1977]</xref>). The reciprocal of this value gives an estimate of β in the case of standard incidence ranging from 3.08 to 11.76 per year, with population densities ranging from 120 in rural settings to 1100 in urban settings (
 <xref rid="b69" ref-type="ref">Fromont et al. [1997]</xref>). The contact rates for avian influenza, reported in Roche et al. 
 <xref rid="b144" ref-type="ref">[2009]</xref>, were varied (with non transmission parameters kept fixed) to find the best fit of the model results to data. Contact rate was not calculated explicitly but the transmission rate was calculated. The value of 
 <italic>N</italic> was in the region of 10
 <sup>5</sup>, large enough to use a deterministic model, and was calculated from ornithological data. Other possible incidence rates are discussed by 
 <xref rid="b116" ref-type="ref">McCallum et al. [2001]</xref>.
</p>
