<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="pbio.1002520.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1002520.g002</object-id>
 <label>Fig 2</label>
 <caption>
  <title>ZIKV transmission and pathology model schematic.</title>
  <p>Susceptible-Infected-Recovered model of ZIKV transmission. (a) Transmission model. Births enter the population seasonally, as illustrated by 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.1002520.g001">Fig 1B</xref>. Susceptible individuals are categorized as infants and children (“susceptible children”), adult males and women past reproductive age (“other susceptible individuals”), women of childbearing age, and pregnant women. There are three infected classes. The general infected class (“other infected individuals”) includes infants, children, adult males, and non-pregnant women. The infected class relevant to congenital ZIKV tracks pregnant women, who can transmit trans-placentally to infect their fetus. The recovered class (“immune”) contains individuals who have recovered from infection and are immune from infection, but it is unknown how long immunity lasts and the nature of repeat infection, indicated by knowledge gap 3. The transmission process is unobserved because transmission events are not captured in surveillance. Interventions are indicated. (b) Surveillance model. Symptomatic ZIKV infections and past infections are observable through surveillance systems. The model assumes a subset of infected individuals will have symptoms and the infection of a fetus can result in miscarriage, congenital Zika syndrome (CZS), or other forms of disease, the risk of which remains unknown (knowledge gap 2). Immunity in the host population can be observed through serology surveys, and mosquito abundance (“susceptible vectors” and “infected vectors”) can be measured based on vector surveillance. Vector abundance is seasonal as illustrated by 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.1002520.g001">Fig 1A</xref> and this likely affects seasonal transmission, indicated by knowledge gap 1.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="pbio.1002520.g002" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
