<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Yang et al. (Z. Jin et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; F. Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Yang et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>) have designed Michael acceptor N3 inhibitors are found to have an optimal pharmaceutical activity against viral protease through mechanism-based irreversible inhibition. They also evaluated a series of wide-spectrum inhibitors targeting the M
 <sup>pro</sup> proteases of multiple coronaviruses including SARS AND MERS (Ren et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; F. Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Xue et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Yang et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>), and also exhibited an antiviral activity for infectious bronchitis virus in an animal model(Xue et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>), it fights to porcine epidemic diarrhea virus which causes high mortality in pigs as well as COVID-19 (F. Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Recently, Jin et al. (
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) have constructed a homology model for COVID-19 M
 <sup>pro</sup> and they used molecular docking to monitor whether the N3 binds with it. The docking showed that N3 binds with the COVID-19 M
 <sup>pro</sup> as shown in right side 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0004">Figure 4</xref>. Subsequently, the crystal structure of COVID-19 M
 <sup>pro</sup> in complex with N3 inhibitor have been determined at 2.3 Å resolution and deposited in the protein data bank [pdb id: 6LU7], where the N3 inhibitor binds with the residues of 164-168 in the long strand 155-168 residues, and with residues 189-191 of the loop connecting between second and third region. Further, it can form several hydrogen bonds with the main chain of the residues in the substrate-binding pocket. The contact between N3 and COVID-19 M
 <sup>pro</sup> is locked the inhibitor inside the substrate binding pocket. Several X-ray studies (COVID-19 featured content, 
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) demonstrated that small antiviral compound including lopinar (Zhao et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>) is locked in the same position of N3 in the substrate-binding pocket as shown in left side of 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0004">Figure 4</xref> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure S1</xref> and Table S1). The second region of the COVID-19 M
 <sup>pro</sup> is the favorable position for the inhibitors binding (Yang et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Zhao et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). In the literature, the number of small bioactive compounds reported has reached 135 million (Boström et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). In this regard, researchers should device strategies to identify an anti-COVID-19 M
 <sup>pro</sup> properties candidate based on structure-based virtual screening computational approach.
</p>
