<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>H5N1 influenza virus can cause severe respiratory diseases in humans and mammals. The clinical symptoms include fever, muscle aches, cough, headache, diarrhea, viral pneumonia, encephalitis, and acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS).
 <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> In the mouse model, it can cause hair thickening, bowed limbs, blindness, trembling, significant weight loss, severe pathological tissue changes, and even death.
 <xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> Previous studies have shown that virus-induced acute lung injury or ARDS is triggered by a cytokine storm and is a serious consequence of inflammation resulting from the release of pro-inflammatory cytokines and the recruitment of immune cells to the infected area.
 <xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref> Excessive inflammation can cause systemic inflammatory response syndrome, during which the body enters a state of high metabolic activity and energy usage. High levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines, including IL-6, IFN-γ, MCP-1, and TNF-α, have been detected in humans and mice infected with highly pathogenic H5N1 influenza virus.
 <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> In the present study, we investigated the antiviral effects of positively-charged ZrO
 <sub>2</sub> on IAV in a mouse model and the mechanism of action of these NPs. Several studies have shown that positive charges can facilitate retention of NPs in cells for a relatively long time, which is likely related to intracellular agglomeration. The native surface chemistries of NPs also play crucial roles in their exocytosis patterns from cells. Here, we provide the first data that positively-charged ZrO
 <sub>2</sub> NPs can downregulate the levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines and thereby alleviate the inflammatory response, making them effective anti-inflammatory agents against highly pathogenic H5N1 influenza virus.
</p>
