<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2">
 <italic>Oropouche virus</italic> (OROV) belongs to one of the largest and most diversified families of RNA virus, the 
 <italic>Orthobunyaviridae</italic>, which include several Arboviruses responsible for many important acute but self-limiting febrile illnesses in humans and also hemorrhagic fevers and encephalitis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>
 </sup>. In regard to the epidemiologic aspects, a recent review reported that over the past 60 years, more than 30 outbreaks, comprising more than half a million clinical cases, have been attributed to OROV fever including affected areas in Brazil, Peru, Panama, Trinidad and Tobago. In Brazil, the Amazon region has been stricken for the largest OROV fever epidemics and is the largest endemic area for OROV
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup>. In fact, until recently, OROV fever was the second most frequent arboviral infection in Brazil, surpassed only by dengue. Now due the recent 
 <italic>Chikungunya and Zika viruses</italic> epidemics, OROV fever is considered the 4
 <sup>th</sup> most prevalent arbovirus disease in the country. OROV is raising public agencies concern due to its prospective to spread geographically and emerge in naïve areas, which calls to its importance at an international panorama. The OROV disease starts by an infected arthropod bite, frequently by the midge 
 <italic>Culicoides paraensis</italic>, its main urban vector, allowing for viral entry and replication in the muscle cells, followed by systemic dissemination to several organs and blood that results in high viremia detected between 2–4 days of symptoms onset
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup>. Clinically, OROV fever can be characterized as acute febrile disease, with common symptoms and signs such as skin rash, headache, fever, muscle and joint pain
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>
 </sup>. The virus may cause meningitis, resulting in typical clinical manifestations of meningeal irritation; then it crosses the blood-brain barrier and infects neurons, producing encephalitis in more susceptible individuals
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>
 </sup>. Nevertheless, OROV fever is usually not diagnosed because of its mild and self-limited manifestations or eventually mistakenly diagnosed due to its similar clinical features with dengue, chikungunya, zika, other arboviral diseases and even malaria
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
