<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">Discovery of nucleoside or nucleotide analogs and host-targeting antivirals (HTAs) are two main strategies for developing BSA (Min and Subbarao, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2010</xref>; Jordheim et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2013</xref>; Jordan et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2018</xref>). With the former drug class usually causing drug resistance and toxicity, the discovery of HTAs has attracted much attention (Adalja and Inglesby, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2019</xref>). Several independent studies searching for HTAs collectively end up to compounds targeting the host’s pyrimidine synthesis pathway to inhibit virus infections, which indicates that the replication of viruses is widely dependent on the host pyrimidine synthesis (Zeng et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2005</xref>; Qing et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2010</xref>; Hoffmann et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2011</xref>; Das et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2013</xref>; Lucas-Hourani et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2013</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2017</xref>; Marschall et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2013</xref>; Raveh et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2013</xref>; Chung et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2016</xref>; Grandin et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2016</xref>; Cheung et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2017</xref>; Luthra et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2018</xref>; Chen et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2019</xref>; Kottkamp et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2019</xref>; Mei-jiao et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2019</xref>; Yang et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2019</xref>). However, most of these compounds lack verified drug targets making subsequent drug optimization and further application impossible (Zeng et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2005</xref>; Hoffmann et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2011</xref>; Lucas-Hourani et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2013</xref>; Raveh et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2013</xref>; Chung et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2016</xref>; Grandin et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2016</xref>; Lucas-Hourani et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2017</xref>; Luthra et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2018</xref>; Kottkamp et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2019</xref>). There are only a few inhibitors against pyrimidine synthesis that can be carried forward to animal studies, however, their antiviral efficacies were unsatisfactory or even ineffective at all (Zeng et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2005</xref>; Qing et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2010</xref>; Marschall et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2013</xref>; Raveh et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2013</xref>; Grandin et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2016</xref>; Cheung et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2017</xref>; Mei-jiao et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2019</xref>). For example, a pyrimidine synthesis inhibitor FA-613 without a specific target protected only 30.7% of mice from lethal influenza A virus infection when compared to the DAA drug Zanamivir (100%) in parallel (Cheung et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2017</xref>). Another two compounds, Cmp1 (Marschall et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2013</xref>) and FK778 (Zeng et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2005</xref>), which target DHODH, a rate-limiting enzyme in the fourth step of the 
 <italic>de novo</italic> pyrimidine synthesis pathway, could only inhibit the DNA virus (CMV) replication in RAG
 <sup>−/−</sup> mice, but their therapeutic effects on the upcoming diseases were unexplored. Therefore, more potent pyrimidine synthesis inhibitors, especially ones with the specific drug target, are urgent to be developed to prove whether such an HTA drug is valuable towards clinical use or has any advantages over DAA drugs in antiviral treatment.
</p>
