<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The PHS hypothesis presents new interpretations of some unsolved immunological observations. Etiological substances of disease have variable sizes and biochemical characteristics and originate from external sources or internal sources, such as from injured or infected cells. Therefore, immune cells and immune proteins seen in pathologic lesions such as neutrophils, T cells, natural killer (NK) cells, immunoglobulins, and complements are not acting by nonspecific or bystander immune stimuli such as chemokines, but rather for the purpose of host cell protection from pathogenic substances as needed in the host. Given that numerous kinds of peptides, including peptide hormone, AMPs, and intracellular peptides in proteasomes, play critical roles in the lives of organisms, as do proteins, neuropeptides, and monoamines in vivo [
 <xref rid="b73-cep-2020-00759" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>-
 <xref rid="b75-cep-2020-00759" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>], it is reasonable to assume that the main function of T cells is to control pathogenic peptides that hurt or signal the host’s target cells [
 <xref rid="b54-cep-2020-00759" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Injuries to target cells in autoimmune diseases may not be caused by specific antibodies or specific T cells against the antigens expressed on self-cells but rather by persistent aberrant immune reactions of nonspecific adaptive immune cells to substances produced by injured self-cells. The etiology of genetic diseases and cancers may involve a transformed protein or a protein deficiency in organ tissue cells or within a cell; adapted reactions such as the production of alternative or compensatory proteins in the PHS may be responsible for disease development and progression due to long-term nonspecific hyperactive reactions associated with these proteins. A “cancer organ” consists of cancer cells and normal vascular and other supportive cells of the host. In certain cancers, cancer cells may communicate with host immune cells such as macrophages and possibly T cells that have receptors for cross-talk. Blocking communication between cancer cells and immune cells can, therefore, suppress cancer cell growth [
 <xref rid="b72-cep-2020-00759" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Certain diseases, including idiopathic nephrotic syndrome, or central nervous system diseases such as prion diseases and Alzheimer disease, exhibit no adaptive immune cells or immune proteins such as immunoglobulins and complements in the initial pathologic lesions. The etiological substances in these diseases may be the size of neuropeptides. The innate immune system, which is composed of undefined immune proteins or immune peptides, may control these substances [
 <xref rid="b72-cep-2020-00759" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>].
</p>
