<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Human influenza viruses were also identified in swine in Europe: the A(H1N1) virus was isolated circa 1938, and A(H3N2) viruses were identified by serologic surveillance of swine during 1968–1970 (
 <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>10</italic>
 </xref>). The classical swine A(H1N1) virus was detected in Europe during 1950; however, the virus was not isolated until 1976 (
 <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>10</italic>
 </xref>). During 1980, swine A(H1N1) viruses were isolated in France for the first time, and in 1981, A(H3N2) viruses were also isolated from swine. Both subtypes circulated either separately or jointly in the same geographic areas. During 1987 in Brittany, France, when these subtypes were co-circulating among swine in the surrounding region, A(H1N2) viruses were isolated (
 <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>12</italic>
 </xref>). These viruses were reassortants of classical swine A(H1N1) and human-like swine A(H3N2) viruses that had circulated since the 1980s (
 <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>12</italic>
 </xref>). In 1994, A(H1N2) viruses were isolated from swine in Great Britain for the first time. Unlike the A(H1N2) viruses previously circulating in Asia and Europe, these A(H1N2) viruses appeared to have undergone triple reassortment, inheriting genes from 3 parent sources: the hemagglutinin (HA) from human A(H1N1) viruses that circulated during 1980–1986, the NA from swine A(H3N2) viruses (a reassortant virus), and the avian-like swine A(H1N1) viruses that had emerged in swine in Europe during 1979 (
 <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>13</italic>
 </xref>). Whereas the A(H1N2) variants that emerged in France during the 1980s remained localized, the A(H1N2) virus found in the United Kingdom subsequently spread to mainland Europe and became endemic among European swine (
 <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>13</italic>
 </xref>,
 <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>14</italic>
 </xref>).
</p>
