<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our study provides important information on the vector competence of both sylvatic and domestic populations of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and three sylvatic species of 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> while some aspect could be considered as minor limitations. First, due to limited number of specimens available we were not able to test 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>furcifer</italic> with the African DENV strains after an early experiment performed with DENV-4 and DENV-3 strains respectively from Haiti and Barbados. For the same reason we also limited the experiment with 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>furcifer</italic>, 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>taylori</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>luteocephalus</italic> at 15 dpbm only. Furthermore, only the RT-PCR was used to detect DENV genomes whether infectious particles or not for 2 reasons: i) the purpose of this article is to show the competence of the vector and we have been focused on the detection of DENV in the different compartments of the mosquitoes and in the saliva. As we have shown that the virus reached the saliva, it implies that the vector is competent ii) In our experience with other viruses, (West Nile, Usutu), we have noticed that RT-PCR and infectious viral particles are generally very consistent and concordant in their conclusions and trends [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007043.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007043.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Such a trend has also been confirmed on C6/36 cells for other virus [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007043.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Despite the relevance of the capillary feeding method for virus transmission assessment there is no proof of salivation activity for each tested individual. However, as the use of animals has many limitations, it is currently the best alternative technique [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007043.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007043.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], successfully used over years with different media like defibrinated blood [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007043.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], mineral or immersion oils [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007043.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007043.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], foetal bovine serum [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007043.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] to measure virus transmission. One way to assess the presence of saliva could be the detection of saliva components like protein or carbohydrates. Such an approach will require, however, a larger volume of media for saliva collection to achieve the different analysis without compromising virus detection. During our experiments, no DENV-susceptible laboratory mosquito strain was used as control. In our knowledge, there is no unique mosquito strain that can serve as a single control for each of the DENV serotypes and genotypes. Beyond the current scope of the study, future experiments would take into account this aspect by integrating at least one laboratory susceptible mosquito strain for each DENV serotype.
</p>
