<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0080">3-Chymotrypsin like Protease or Main protease (M
 <sup>pro</sup>) is one of the two crucial proteolytic enzymes that help in cleaving the replicase polyprotein 1ab in SARS-CoV-2. The M
 <sup>pro</sup>, which is also known as non-structural protein 5 (nsp5), is 306 amino acid long and is translated from the Orf1ab of viral RNA genome
 <xref rid="b0335" ref-type="bibr">[67]</xref>. M
 <sup>pro</sup> is known to cleave the replicase polyprotein at 11 specific sites, the recognition sites being Leu-Gln
 <sub>↓</sub>(Ser, Ala, Gly), to release 12 nsps (nsp4, nsp6-16) that are essential for viral replication as well as viral assembly 
 <xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0335" ref-type="bibr">[67]</xref>. Structurally, M
 <sup>pro</sup> is a dimer, and each monomer has three domains- domain I, which includes residues 8-101, domain II which includes residues 102-184 and domain III, which includes residues 201-303. The domains II and III are connected through the loop region that includes 185-200 residues. The substrate-binding site containing the catalytic dyad (Cys145-His41) is located between domain I and domain II 
 <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. The functional importance of the enzyme in the life cycle of SARS-CoV-2 and the fact that no human proteases possess similar cleavage recognition site makes M
 <sup>pro</sup> appealing target for drug discovery. Zhang et al. reported the optimization of α-ketamides for activity against the M
 <sup>pro</sup> of SARS-CoV-2 
 <xref rid="b0340" ref-type="bibr">[68]</xref> (
 <xref rid="f0055" ref-type="fig">Fig. 11</xref> ). The lead compound 
 <bold>1</bold> was found to be active against the SARS-CoV M
 <sup>pro</sup> in picomolar concentration 
 <xref rid="b0345" ref-type="bibr">[69]</xref>. However, short half-life in plasma and unfavorable pharmacokinetic profile of compound 
 <bold>1</bold> prevented further development and study. In order to improve its pharmacokinetic profile, the amide linkage between 
 <italic>P</italic>2-
 <italic>P</italic>3 was replaced with a pyridine ring for improved metabolic stability, and the cinnamoyl moiety was replaced with a butyloxycarbonyl (BOC) group for increased solubility and reduced plasma protein binding. However, the better pharmacokinetic profile met with a decreased activity against the M
 <sup>pro</sup> of SARS-CoV-2 of compound 
 <bold>2</bold> (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 2.39 µM) when compared with compound 
 <bold>1</bold> (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.18 µM). In the next modification, 
 <italic>P</italic>2 cyclohexyl moiety was replaced with a smaller cyclopropyl moiety in order to improve the antiviral activity. The resulting compound 
 <bold>3</bold> inhibits M
 <sup>pro</sup> of SARS-CoV-2 with an IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 0.67 µM. Further, compound 
 <bold>3</bold> effectively inhibited the replication of SARS-CoV-2 in Calu3 cells, while compound 
 <bold>4</bold> formed by the removal of the BOC group was almost inactive, emphasizing that the BOC group is indispensable. The X-ray crystal structure of compound 
 <bold>3</bold> with SARS-CoV-2 M
 <sup>pro</sup> is depicted in 
 <xref rid="f0060" ref-type="fig">Fig. 12</xref> . Compound 
 <bold>3</bold> also had a favorable pharmacokinetic profile 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>, suggesting it as an ideal lead for further development.
</p>
