<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0085">Jin et al. developed a strategy encompassing structure-based drug design, virtual screening, and high throughput screening to repurpose existing drugs or agents to target M
 <sup>pro</sup> of SARS-CoV-2 
 <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. N3 (
 <xref rid="f0065" ref-type="fig">Fig. 13</xref> ) was designed based on computer-aided drug design to target the M
 <sup>pro</sup> of SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV 
 <xref rid="b0355" ref-type="bibr">[71]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0360" ref-type="bibr">[72]</xref>. Since M
 <sup>pro</sup> is highly conserved among coronaviruses, compound N3 was also tested against M
 <sup>pro</sup> of SARS-CoV-2, and it was found to be a potent inhibitor of M
 <sup>pro</sup>. Enzyme kinetics studies revealed compound N3 as an irreversible inhibitor. The X-ray crystal structure of compound N3 in the binding pocket of SARS-CoV-2 
 <sup>Mpro</sup> is shown in 
 <xref rid="f0065" ref-type="fig">Fig. 13</xref>. Based on the crystal structure of SARS-CoV-2 M
 <sup>pro</sup> with N3, a virtual screening study identified cinanserin, a serotonin antagonist, as a promising antiviral candidate. Cinanserin exhibited activity against SARS-CoV-2 M
 <sup>pro</sup>
 <italic>in vitro</italic> (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 125 µM). A high-throughput screening study consisting of approved drugs, natural products, and clinical drug candidates was performed to identify hit compounds against SARS-CoV-2 M
 <sup>pro</sup>. The top six compounds, along with their IC
 <sub>50</sub> values, are depicted in 
 <xref rid="f0070" ref-type="fig">Fig. 14</xref> . These compounds were evaluated for the potential to inhibit the replication of SARS-CoV-2 in Vero E6 cells. Ebselen (also called PZ 51, DR3305, and SPI-1005, is a synthetic organoselenium drug molecule with anti-inflammatory, antioxidant and cytoprotective activity) and N3 with half-maximal Effective Concentration (EC
 <sub>50</sub>) values of 4.67 and 16.77 µM, respectively were found to be the most potent compounds. Ebselen has low cytotoxicity, and its safety has been evaluated in a previous clinical trial 
 <xref rid="b0365" ref-type="bibr">[73]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0370" ref-type="bibr">[74]</xref>, making it an ideal candidate for further development.
</p>
