<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The disparity of SARS‐CoV‐2 testing coverage in different countries is much discussed but the reasons are sometimes rather opaque. There are many tests available (e.g., see 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.finddx.org/covid-19/pipeline/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.finddx.org/covid-19/pipeline/</ext-link>), so one bottleneck would appear to be a limitation in authorized testing facilities. Scaling up testing in existing official centres requires not only acquisition of the appropriate instrumentation and reagents, but also of competent personnel disposing of the necessary expertise, which may constitute a bottleneck. However, it is abundantly clear that the instrumentation and expertise needed to carry out SARS‐CoV‐2 testing are widespread in academic research laboratories, as is the eagerness of many research groups to contribute to efforts to combat the pandemic. While issues of safety, quality control, logistics, data reporting and security and so on, need to be addressed, a failure in some countries to harness early in the crisis the expertise and enthusiasm of young researchers to fulfil a key need and, with it, the opportunity to acquire data that could have resulted in responses that saved lives, is regrettable. Paradoxically, while there have been frantic efforts to open new hospital facilities to accommodate COVID‐19 patients, and to recruit the health professionals needed to operate them, there has been an indiscriminate closing of research institutes capable of carrying out diagnostic work, and thus of identifying infected and, importantly for frontline health professionals, non‐infected individuals.
 <list list-type="bullet" id="emi15029-list-0002">
  <list-item id="emi15029-li-0002">
   <p>
    <italic>Rapidly developing pandemics necessitate rapid responses. Getting diagnostics and testing facilities up and running that are able to handle large numbers of samples are key to efforts to manage the disease. Crisis preparedness demands not only formulation of strategies to enable rapid scale up official facilities, but also advance identification of relevant available resources outside of the health system, and strategies of how to promptly and effectively harness them</italic>.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
