<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Furthermore, there is less than 100% overlap between any two sample runs, whether biologic runs or technical replicates of the same sample. Alternate multiplex assays that target specific proteins have been developed and include the MyriadRBM
 <sup>®</sup> and Luminex
 <sup>®</sup> platforms. Many of these are limited to fewer than 100 proteins that can be simultaneously assayed and measured, although a few, such as those offered by RayBiotech
 <sup>®</sup>, are reported to detect and measure several hundred proteins. Thus, at the time we initiated these studies, we selected an aptamer-based assay reported to reliably detect and measure more than 1000 proteins. These slow-off-rate modified aptamers (SOMAmers
 <sup>®</sup>) were developed by SomaLogics, Inc., (Boulder, CO, USA) [
 <xref rid="B18-viruses-11-01028" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-11-01028" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-11-01028" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], and have been used to examine cancer biomarkers [
 <xref rid="B45-viruses-11-01028" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], Alzheimer′s disease biomarkers [
 <xref rid="B46-viruses-11-01028" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] and biomarkers in IAV-infected clinical nasal secretions [
 <xref rid="B47-viruses-11-01028" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Our pilot studies with the first available version, capable of detecting 1128 proteins, reliably measured differences in influenza PR8-infected A549 cells over a time course. We subsequently used the next-generation SOMAscan version 1.3, which measures &gt;1300 proteins, to measure Zika virus-induced proteomic alterations in Vero cells [
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-11-01028" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] and in U251 astrocytoma cells [
 <xref rid="B48-viruses-11-01028" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Application of this targeted aptamer-based approach, which was designed primarily to detect low-abundance proteins, thus provides a beneficial complementary approach to the non-biased MS-based approaches that tend to measure more abundant proteins. Comparative analyses of dysregulated proteins we identified in this study to proteins identified in one of our earlier MS-based studies [
 <xref rid="B10-viruses-11-01028" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-viruses-11-01028" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-viruses-11-01028" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] showed generally good agreement. Two proteins (ISG15 and β-2-microglobulin) were identified as upregulated by both methods, 75 proteins were determined to not be significantly regulated by both techniques and no proteins were identified as significantly upregulated by one method, but significantly downregulated by the other. Thus, this newer aptamer-based multiplexed system, designed primarily to detect and measure lower abundant proteins, provides complementary data to the more commonly-used MS-based approaches and to assay numerous proteins not normally detected by quantitative MS.
</p>
