<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The current study assayed 2–3 biologic replicates of five different IAV strains, each compared to mock-infected samples (a total of 14 samples). These virus strains represent a lab-adapted H1N1 strain (PR8), a mild seasonal H1N1 strain related to the A/New Caledonia/20/1999-like clinical isolate (RV733), the 2009 H1N1 pandemic strain (pdm09), and two strains that show significantly higher pathology in human patients; the H5N1 “Bird flu” and the H7N9 strain. All tested virus strains affected the A549 cellular proteome, upregulating some proteins and downregulating other proteins. Although none of the 1310 measurable common cellular proteins was significantly dysregulated by all five viruses, some proteins were similarly dysregulated by multiple viruses. For example, CCL5 was upregulated by PR8, H5N1 and H7N9, and PGAM1 was significantly downregulated by pdm09, H5N1 and H7N9. The five viruses generated three overall patterns of dysregulation, at least as measured by the 1310 proteins that can be assayed by the SOMAscan. PR8 caused an overall general activation, primarily of antimicrobial inflammatory and immune response, as reflected by a large upregulation of more than a dozen proteins, including ISG15, STAT1, OAS1 and downregulation only of PPID. PR8 is a highly lab culture-adapted strain passaged multiple times in mice that is highly virulent in mice, but extremely attenuated in humans. RV733 and pdm09 had very little effect in our A549 cells, as we found in a previous quantitative MS study [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-11-01028" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], and are relatively low virulence, despite being well adapted to growth in humans. Both the H5N1 and H7N9 viruses, which demonstrate the third pattern (significant downregulation of many more proteins than the other strains, particularly in the antimicrobial response, cardiovascular, and post-translational modification networks), and significant downregulation of many common proteins, are poorly adapted to humans because of their receptor specificity, but when successfully delivered into the lower human respiratory tract, they can be highly virulent. This more profound proteomic effect by these avian-derived viruses also was observed in quantitative transcriptomic [
 <xref rid="B49-viruses-11-01028" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] and MS studies [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-11-01028" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].
</p>
