<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The number of positive CHIKV IgM ELISA test results was unexpectedly high. As the results could not be confirmed with IFA, a technique which is considered to be more specific, interference with malaria was suspected based on our experience. Indeed, false-positive reactions as a result of polyclonal B-cell activation is a phenomenon that we experienced before with ZIKV ELISA [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007047.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The detection of 
 <italic>Plasmodium</italic> by PCR in the CHIKV ELISA positive/IFA negative samples strongly supported this hypothesis. The use of IFA for IgM detection may result in false-positive reactions although the risk is limited in case of experienced readers [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007047.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Cross-reaction of anti-CHIKV antibodies with antibodies against other members of the Semliki-forest serogroup, notably O’nyong nyongvirus, could not be excluded as no neutralization assays were performed. ZIKV was not suspected to be circulating in the area and indeed, no RT-PCR positive cases were found. YFV was actively circulating in the region at the time of study, transgressing the border with Angola [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007047.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], but we did not detect any RT-PCR positive case. Detecting YFV and ZIKV only based on RT-PCR diagnostics could have resulted in an underestimation of acute ZIKV and YFV infections. However, ZIKV and YFV IgM testing was not done, because almost 80% of the patients included in this study presented in the first four days after the onset of fever, which is the period with the highest probability to detect the virus with molecular methods and there are several shortcomings with the IgM testing for these viruses [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007047.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007047.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Nowadays, there is evidence that in urine samples ZIKV is longer detectable by ZIKV PCR, but at the time of study this was not known. Thus, no such samples were collected [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007047.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>].
</p>
