<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is generally assumed that all biological populations experience changes in their environments, at least occasionally. The frequency of environmental turnover can affect which phenotypic variants within a population are favored by natural selection, thus dictating whether the population is relatively homogeneous versus heterogeneous (polymorphic) for genetic variation underlying these phenotypes. Frequent environmental turnover may present differing targets for selection, whereby the relative fitness of certain phenotypes are favored in some environments, but the relative performances of these variants are disfavored in other environments (Buckling, Kassen, Bell, &amp; Rainey, 
 <xref rid="ece36287-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>; Kassen, 
 <xref rid="ece36287-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>). In this way, an interaction between the tempo of environmental change and the mutations underlying fitness traits may cause a population to harbor greater versus lesser standing genetic variation. Stochastic environmental changes may be particularly challenging for evolving populations, because mismatches between variants and the selective environments can cause genetic variation to accumulate and yet prove insufficient to fuel adaptation (i.e., inability for one or more variants to experience sustained positive selection across varying environments causes adaptation to “stall out,” and increases vulnerability to extinction) (Bürger and Lynch, 
 <xref rid="ece36287-bib-0066" ref-type="ref">1995</xref>; Donaldson‐Matasci, Lachmann, &amp; Bergstrom, 
 <xref rid="ece36287-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>; Lande &amp; Shannon, 
 <xref rid="ece36287-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">1996</xref>; Botero, Weissing, Wright, &amp; Rubenstein, 
 <xref rid="ece36287-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). Thus, stochastic (unpredictable) environments can cause genetic variance to increase in a population over time, without mean fitness improvement (maladaptation). In contrast, selection in a constant environment should cause relatively lower standing genetic variation to be present in an adapting population. Beyond the expected difference in standing variation, the fixation of alleles in a population successfully adapting to its environment should cause its genetic architecture to diverge from a population that is maladapted. By definition, the underlying genetic basis of phenotypic traits that improve fitness (i.e., adaptations) constitutes genetic architecture; therefore, populations that share recent common ancestry but are adapted versus maladapted to their environments should necessarily diverge in genetic architecture, as well as differ in standing variation.
</p>
