<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8">Affordable, accessible and acceptable healthcare for all sections of society is the need of the hour. Meeting the health needs of population of over seven billion people, majority of which reside in developing/underdeveloped countries where the population just cannot afford costly healthcare, has necessitated the revival of traditional systems of medicine and the development of cost-effective and pragmatic strategies for the masses. Besides, the disease preventive as well as curative aspects of Indian herbal medicine, its safety and efficacy proved over thousands of years, have made it a preferred choice amongst the masses. The Indian system of medicine, Ayurveda, has evolved as a result of years of medical practice with medicinal plants in humans. India is endowed with extremely rich biodiversity and is home to innumerable medicinal and aromatic plant species which have been used extensively to prevent and/or cure diseases. Similarly, other alternative systems of health like Siddha, Unani and Homoeopathy are now officially recognized, and a ministry known as AYUSH – Ayurveda, Yoga and Naturopathy, Unani, Siddha and Homoeopathy – has been set up. In view of the huge population of India, it is imperative to develop cost-effective and sustainable health solutions for the public at large. Only one particular system of medicine cannot meet the health challenges posed by the burgeoning population. It is the author’s firm belief that we have to consider the rich, Indian traditional systems of medicine for both their preventive and therapeutic aspects and utilize them for meeting the health challenges of our country. Besides, treatments for all diseases are not available in the allopathic system of medicine. The undesirable side effects of modern medicines, the mounting costs of conventional hospital-based healthcare and the emergence of lifestyle-related diseases are some of the reasons for the population to consider alternative simpler and cheaper forms of treatment. Effective and holistic treatment for several diseases like cancer, AIDS, emerging and reemerging bacterial, fungal and viral diseases, Alzheimer’s, Parkinson’s and several emerging and reemerging diseases are still not available in modern systems of medicine leading to more and more patients taking recourse to alternative therapies for improving the quality of life. Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> enumerates the reason why recourse to herbal medicine is the natural choice for sustainable, affordable and acceptable healthcare for the population.
</p>
