<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The NAIs (oseltamivir carboxylate, zanamivir, and peramivir) were dissolved in sterile distilled water, and aliquots were stored at −20°C until use. A fluorescence-based NA inhibition assay with the fluorogenic substrate 2′-(4-methylumbelliferyl)-α-D-N-acetylneuraminic acid (MUNANA; Sigma-Aldrich, St Louis, MO) was used to determine the 50% inhibitory concentration (IC
 <sub>50</sub>) values [
 <xref rid="pone.0190877.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0190877.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Briefly, viruses were standardized to equivalent NA enzyme activity in the linear range of the curve and were mixed with various concentrations of NAI (ranged from 0.05 to 5000 nM in the final reaction mixture) in 96-well flat-bottom black opaque plates (Corning Costar, NY). The virus-NAI mixture was incubated at 37°C for 30 min prior to the addition of MUNANA and then incubated with substrate (100 μM final concentration) at 37°C for 30 min. The reaction was terminated by the addition of the stop solution (0.1 M glycine in 25% ethanol, pH 10.7). Fluorometric determinations were quantified with a Synergy 2 multi-mode microplate reader (BioTek Instruments, Winooski, VT) based on the release of the fluorescent product 4-methylumbelliferone (4-MU) using excitation and emission wavelengths of 360 and 460 nm, respectively. The IC
 <sub>50</sub>s of viruses were determined using the curve-fitting model in GraphPad Prism 5 software (GraphPad Software, La Jolla, CA). The phenotypic NAI susceptibility of influenza A and B viruses was evaluated based on the fold change in their IC
 <sub>50</sub> values when compared to those of susceptible viruses from the same NA subtype/lineage, as previously described by the WHO Influenza Antiviral Working Group [
 <xref rid="pone.0190877.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The inhibition was categorized as “normal” (a ≤ 10-fold change for influenza A and a ≤ 5-fold change for influenza B viruses); “reduced” (a 10–100-fold change for influenza A and a 5–50-fold change for influenza B viruses); or “highly reduced” (a ≥ 100-fold change for influenza A and a ≥ 50-fold change for influenza B viruses).
</p>
