<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>HW is a triple exponential smoothing method which involves exponentially decreasing the weights of observations over time, such that oldest observations have the smallest weight. The forecast is continuously revised according to the most recent observations. HW incorporates three components: a level term, a trend term, and a seasonality term, respectively, defined by the smoothing constants α, β, and γ. HW can be applied to raw time series containing trend and seasonality. All the data available before 31-12-2015 were used for model training. The data available after December 31st, 2015 were used for model validation and for the estimation of model prediction performance. The training data contained data for periods from 2 to 7 years and the validation data contained data for periods from 7 to 12 months, depending on the length of syndrome TS. Optimal HW parameters were determined through minimization of the squared prediction error (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Model fit was evaluated using the autocorrelation and partial autocorrelation functions of the residuals (ACF and PACF, respectively), normality Q-Q plot, and the root-mean-squared error (RMSE). ACF is the linear dependence of a variable on itself at two points in time and PACF is the autocorrelation between two points in time after removing any linear dependence between them (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). ACF and PACF were used to find any remaining repeated patterns in the model residuals. RMSE is a measure of the difference between the values predicted by a model and the values actually observed in the real data (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). This criterion was calculated for the differences between the observed and the predicted values within both the training period (RMSE
 <sub>t</sub>) and the validation period (RMSE
 <sub>v</sub>). In both cases, the predictive performance of the model were better when the RMSE was lower. The alarm thresholds tested for evaluating event detection performance were based on constant values multiplied with the standard error of the predicted value for each week (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). The following constant values were used: 0.05, 0.1, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 2.5, 3, 3.5, 4, 4.5.
</p>
