<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Animal viruses must pass through a series of highly selective evolutionary bottlenecks to become established in the human population [
 <xref rid="pone.0206926.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. First, the host species barrier selects for viruses that establish successful infections in exposed humans [
 <xref rid="pone.0206926.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0206926.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The next bottleneck selects for viruses capable of relatively efficient human-to-human transmission. This efficiency can be measured by the pathogen’s basic reproduction number, 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub>, defined as the mean number of secondary infections propagated by an initial case in an immunologically naïve population. Selection for variants with higher 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> values produces viruses capable of more sustained transmission within the new human population [
 <xref rid="pone.0206926.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. During this process, two discrete thresholds can be defined: first, whether or not an animal virus can infect humans, and second, whether or not a zoonotic infection can be transmitted between humans. To supplement knowledge on the first threshold, animal-to-human spillover, several data-driven models have been used to predict undiscovered zoonotic viruses, potential vectors [
 <xref rid="pone.0206926.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0206926.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], and animal reservoirs [
 <xref rid="pone.0206926.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0206926.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. With regards to the second threshold, a descriptive statistical analysis by Geoghegan 
 <italic>et al</italic> found that human transmissibility was generally associated with low host mortality, chronic infection, non-segmented genomes, and the lack of an insect vector [
 <xref rid="pone.0206926.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].
</p>
