<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par44">A well-suited P1 mimetic to target trypsin- and furin-like PCs is the 4-amidinobenzylamide group (4-Amba). The 4-Amba anchor makes numerous polar interactions to residues at the bottom and exit of the S1 pocket (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">11.5</xref>) but exhibits no preference for special trypsin-like serine proteases. Within this inhibitor type, an improved selectivity for individual family members can partially achieved only via their P2, P3, and/or P4 residues. All substrate analogue structures strictly require a P2 amino acid in 
 <sc>l</sc>-configuration, whereas a 
 <sc>d</sc>-configured P3-residue is often preferred. Its side chain can address the characteristic distal S3/4 binding pocket above Trp215, which is found and mostly well-defined in all trypsin-like serine proteases. In contrast, the side chain of a natural 
 <sc>l</sc>-configured P3 residue is directed toward the solvent and makes fewer binding contributions. Interestingly, the backbone of the P3 residue is involved in a short antiparallel β-sheet interaction with a highly conserved glycine in position 216 of the protease domain, irrespective of an 
 <sc>l</sc>- or 
 <sc>d</sc>-configuration of the P3 amino acid. So far, no crystal structures of TTSPs involved in HA cleavage, like TMPRSS2, TMPRSS4, or HAT, are available. However, countless crystal structures of this inhibitor type in complex with numerous other trypsin-like serine proteases have been elucidated. As an example, Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">11.5</xref> shows the binding mode of the substrate analogue inhibitor H-
 <sc>d</sc>-hTyr-Ala-4-Amba (
 <bold>10</bold>) (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">11.6</xref>) in complex with trypsin, indicating the characteristic binding pockets (Maiwald et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR127">2016</xref>). This inhibitor type could be refined following a well-established prodrug strategy that has been used for the development of the orally available thrombin inhibitor ximelagatran (Gustafsson et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">2004</xref>). The conversion of the P1-amidine (p
 <italic>K</italic>
 <sub>a</sub> = 11.5) into a hydroxyamidine (p
 <italic>K</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>a</italic>
 </sub> = 5.2) reduces the strongly basic character of the 4-Amba group and improves the bioavailability of the inhibitors. An enzyme system found in the liver and other organs (kidney, lung, brain, and intestine) consisting of cytochrome b5, a NADH-dependent cytochrome b5 reductase, and a P450 enzyme is involved in the reduction of the N-hydroxylated compounds (Clement 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2002</xref>). 
</p>
