<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The oral cavity houses the second largest microbiota in the human body and can include bacteria, fungi, viruses, and archaea (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Dewhirst et al., 2010</xref>). As a large number of opportunistic pathogens and a variety of antibiotic resistance genes have been detected in the calculus of ancient human remains by analyzing the microbial DNA contained within them, it is supposed that the oral cavity, an ecological reservoir for potential pathogens, is involved in local and systemic diseases (
 <xref rid="B127" ref-type="bibr">Warinner et al., 2014</xref>). The main bacterial genera, by abundance, present within the normal oral cavity include 
 <italic>Neisseria</italic>, 
 <italic>Corynebacterium</italic>, 
 <italic>Leptotrichia</italic>, 
 <italic>Streptococcus</italic>, 
 <italic>Prevotella</italic>, 
 <italic>Veillonella</italic>, 
 <italic>Fusobacterium</italic>, and 
 <italic>Capnocytophaga</italic> (
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2014</xref>). The dominant genera of healthy lungs include 
 <italic>Streptococcus</italic>, 
 <italic>Fusobacterium</italic>, 
 <italic>Pseudomonas</italic>, 
 <italic>Veillonella</italic>, 
 <italic>Prevotella</italic>, and 
 <italic>Capnocytophaga</italic> (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Beck et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Dickson and Huffnagle, 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B134" ref-type="bibr">Wypych et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B110" ref-type="bibr">Shen et al., 2020</xref>), colonizing the oral cavity as well. Microbiota that have migrated from the oral cavity, rather than those from the nasal flora, is likely to be an important source of microbiota in the lungs under normal conditions (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Bassis et al., 2015</xref>). Multiple studies have shown that lung microbiota are more similar to those in the oropharynx, than those in the air, nasopharynx or lower digestive tract (
 <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr">Segal et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B121" ref-type="bibr">Venkataraman et al., 2015</xref>). It was demonstrated that acellular bronchoalveolar lavage samples from half of healthy individuals are enriched with oral taxa (
 <xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr">Segal et al., 2016</xref>), providing further evidence for the relationship between the microbial community in the lungs and the oral cavity. Additionally, many human bacterial pathogens can also colonize the respiratory tract of healthy individuals asymptomatically (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Arora et al., 2015</xref>). The oral microbiome could be a driving force for bacteriome shifts by regulating mucosal immunity, which directly or indirectly affects pathogenicity (
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2019</xref>).
</p>
