<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One important constraint for the use of ICI in patients with concomitant virus hepatitis for treatment of cancer is the possible occurrence of immune-mediated hepatotoxicity, a frequent irAE caused by ICI. This notion is particularly troublesome, as an immune-mediated hepatitis may pose a significant diagnostic challenge in patients with underlying viral or autoimmune hepatitis.
 <xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30–32</xref> Pu 
 <italic>et al</italic>
 <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> recently published a comprehensive review on 186 cancer patients with concurrent HBV or HCV infection who had received ICI treatment.
 <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> About 20% of patients developed an increase of hepatic transaminases which was higher than those reported in ICI-treated cancer patients without concurrent viral hepatitis.
 <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> All grade 3 or 4 toxicities were reversible by means of antiviral treatment or corticosteroids without necessitating a discontinuation of ICI. Importantly, no negative influence on infection status was reported in patients receiving corticosteroids.
 <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> It should be mentioned, however, that ICI should be withhold once an irAE is encountered requiring immunosuppressive drugs; but, ICI may be resumed once the irAE has resolved. Importantly, the incidence of other adverse events in this particular patient population was not significantly increased when compared with ICI-treated cancer patients without chronic viral hepatitis. Based on a recent publication reviewing the available data on the use of ICI in cancer patients with hepatitis, it is recommended that all patients scheduled to receive ICI should be screened for HBV and HCV, and in patients who are tested positive, prophylactic antiviral treatment is indicated. Unfortunately, however, it is currently unclear for how long the prophylactic treatment should be continued. Primary prophylaxis should also be considered in patients with chronic HBV infection, if not already on treatment. Liver function tests and viral load should routinely be monitored in virus positive patients.
 <xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34 35</xref>
</p>
