<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par47">Treatment is supportive, with no FDA-approved specific antiviral therapy available. Experimental vaccines and treatments for Ebola are under development, but they have not yet been fully tested for safety or effectiveness [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Mortality remains very high.
 <list list-type="simple">
  <list-item>
   <label>3.</label>
   <p id="Par48">
    <italic>What is the management of patients who develop acute liver failure due to non-hepatotropic virus infection?</italic>
   </p>
   <p id="Par49">Acute liver failure is defined by elevation in liver enzymes, an INR &gt;1.5, and development of encephalopathy in someone without known underlying liver disease. It is associated with rapid progression and very high mortality. The first step towards appropriate management is prompt transfer of the patient to the nearest transplant center. These patients are preferably admitted to the critical care unit, and should have close frequent monitoring of sensorium and the basic chemistry panel. Their management is very similar to management of other patients with non-acetaminophen-associated liver failure and the use of 
    <italic>N</italic>-acetylcysteine may also have a role [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].
   </p>
   <p id="Par50">Management of advanced encephalopathy is arguably the most challenging in acute liver failure. Management is aimed at reducing intracranial pressure. When sedation is indicated, propofol is the preferred agent as it reduces brain edema [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>].
   </p>
   <p id="Par51">Early transplant consideration and evaluation offer the best chance at survival in patients with acute liver failure. Even with appropriate management, mortality remains high. Prior to transplantation, most series suggested less than 15 % survival. Currently , overall short-term survival (1 year) including those undergoing transplantation is greater than 65 % [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>4.</label>
   <p id="Par52">
    <italic>Do the non-hepatotropic viruses cause chronic disease or result in an elevated risk of liver cancer?</italic>
   </p>
   <p id="Par53">None of the non-hepatotropic viruses, with the possible exception of PV-B19, has been shown to cause chronic liver disease. PV-B19 has been postulated as a rare and unusual etiology of chronic hepatitis. This observation is based on identification of viral DNA from the hepatocytes years after the original infection. However, the extent to which it results in actual fibrosis and chronic damage is unclear. Furthermore, interest has focused on a possible effect of co-infection with PV-B19 on the natural history of chronic hepatitis B and C [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Similarly, none of the above viruses have been associated with liver cancer.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
