<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Among the various methods to impede viral transmission, vaccines are widely heralded as one of the most effective medical interventions. Indeed, since the pivotal discovery by Edward Jenner over two hundred years ago, vaccination has seen tremendous success in reducing the burden of viral diseases such as polio, yellow fever, measles, mumps, rubella, hepatitis A, hepatitis B, and influenza [
 <xref rid="B7-viruses-12-00520" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-viruses-12-00520" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. However, perhaps the greatest testament to their success is the eradication of smallpox in 1980 [
 <xref rid="B9-viruses-12-00520" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. According to the World Health Organization (WHO), vaccination now saves over 2.5 million lives annually and prevents even more cases of illnesses and serious disabilities [
 <xref rid="B10-viruses-12-00520" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Moreover, taking into account both treatment costs and lost productivity due to death and disability, vaccines are estimated to provide billions of dollars’ worth in cost savings between 2011 and 2020 [
 <xref rid="B11-viruses-12-00520" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In addition, at high enough coverage, vaccination can impart both individual and community protection in the form of herd immunity, safeguarding those who are legitimately incapable of receiving immunization. On the other hand, reduced vaccine coverage threatens to cause a resurgence of vaccine-preventable diseases, including measles, mumps, and pertussis [
 <xref rid="B12-viruses-12-00520" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. With such accolades, vaccination is widely considered as the crowning achievement of public health, and the WHO touts it as the most cost-effective method to prevent infectious diseases. Given their remarkable track records, vaccination is likely to remain a cornerstone of antiviral strategies, especially with the increasing prevalence of epidemic viral diseases.
</p>
