<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Using a hybrid of these classifications it is possible to identify groups of individuals based on race, ethnicity, and socioeconomic status that are at particular risk for specific neglected infections of poverty. In this paper I review the prevalence of the major neglected diseases of poverty in the US This analysis was conducted in January 2008 using the online database PubMed 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-US1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref> for 1972–2007 with the Medical Subject Headings (MSHs) “neglected diseases”, “poverty”, the specific geographic regions and racial, ethnic, and socioeconomic groups listed above 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Glasmeier1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Holt1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Murray1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, and the specific diseases listed as NTDs on the 
 <italic>PLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases</italic> journal scope page 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-4" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, as well as major congenital infections associated with impaired child development including cytomegalovirus (CMV) infection, toxoplasmosis, and syphilis. I also reviewed reference lists of identified articles and hand-searched reviews. I report here either previously published estimates of the number of cases of each neglected infection, or I provide a range of estimates based on reported prevalence rates among selected communities multiplied by published estimates of the population at risk having similar socioeconomic, racial, and ethnic demographics (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0000256-t002">Table 2</xref>). For some neglected infections, particularly the soil-transmitted helminth infections, no new surveys have been reported since the 1980s. Some of the regional and national prevalence estimates were modified from a chapter in my recently published book on neglected tropical diseases 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Hotez4" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>.
</p>
