<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<notes notes-type="COI-statement">
 <sec id="FPar3">
  <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
  <p id="Par61">Trial was registered (NCT02654613) and subsequently approved by the biomedical research ethics committee (BREC), University of Kwa-Zulu Natal (BF108/14). Gateway permission from the Department of Health to conduct the study at the clinics and also access patient records has been obtained. Signed written informed consent will be obtained from the participants to be interviewed. These participants include the health staff working at the clinics. This study will not require any direct patient contact with research staff; rather, the research staff will work with the clinic staff to implement the interventions. Data collected for analysis purposes will be de-identified and not contain personal information. This is in order to protect the privacy of the study participant by maintaining anonymity and ensuring confidentiality is achieved so that no harm comes to the study participants. Beneficence will be attained through provision of study findings for improved TB-HIV integration and reduced burden of the aforementioned diseases. The database and program files will be made available for review by authorized persons, e.g., study statisticians, institutional review board, study investigators, etc. Also, during the study period and few years after, cabinets containing study administered forms will remain locked. Access will be enabled if needed to allow responsible staff perform required data management and any other relevant function.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar4">
  <title>Consent for publication</title>
  <p id="Par62">Not applicable.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar5">
  <title>Competing interests</title>
  <p id="Par63">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar6">
  <title>Publisher’s Note</title>
  <p id="Par64">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
 </sec>
</notes>
