<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Previous research has demonstrated a link between these structural factors and women’s sexual health outcomes in many African settings. The integration of SRH services can improve a women’s uptake of both family planning and HIV services, as well as improve her satisfaction and continued engagement with care (
 <xref rid="czx101-B1" ref-type="bibr">Adamchak 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2010
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="czx101-B4" ref-type="bibr">Church and Mayhew 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="czx101-B14" ref-type="bibr">Kennedy 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2010
 </xref>). There is substantial evidence that GBV and male relationship control can both directly and indirectly increase a women’s risk of HIV though non-protected forced sex, and through the downstream effects of violence such as future risky sex, less protective powers, and substance use (
 <xref rid="czx101-B18" ref-type="bibr">Maman 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2000
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="czx101-B6" ref-type="bibr">Dunkle 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2004
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="czx101-B13" ref-type="bibr">Jewkes 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2010
 </xref>). Adolescent girls’ economic opportunity and access to resources has also been shown to be associated with sexual health outcomes; for example providing young women loans, cash-transfers, or vocational training can decrease sexual risk taking, drug use, engagement in transactional sex, and increase condom use (
 <xref rid="czx101-B7" ref-type="bibr">Erulkar and Chong 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="czx101-B34" ref-type="bibr">Ssewamala 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2010
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="czx101-B3" ref-type="bibr">Bandiera 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2012
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="czx101-B32" ref-type="bibr">Rotheram-Borus 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2012
 </xref>). Finally, research has also shown that interventions to improve girls’ school attendance through cash transfers, reduced fees and/or social support, have decreased the risk of HIV infection, reduced dropout rates, early pregnancy, and adolescent marriage rates (
 <xref rid="czx101-B5" ref-type="bibr">Duflo 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2006
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="czx101-B10" ref-type="bibr">Hallfors 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2011
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="czx101-B2" ref-type="bibr">Baird 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2012
 </xref>). Although there are certainly other relevant social and structural factors that influence AGYW’s HIV outcomes, only those factors that were found in the NSPs targets are represented in this paper. Categories are mutually exclusive, where all identified targets that met criteria are represented in only one category. 
</p>
