<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par72">It is currently acknowledged that viral contamination of recreational water presents a high risk of infection and is considered a significant public health hazard. Published studies, summarized in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">7.2</xref>, have addressed the assessment of virus bioburden in water environmental samples. The most commonly found viruses in aquatics environments are enteric viruses, such as Enterovirus, Rotavirus and Norovirus, Adenovirus and Hepatitis Virus A and C. Begier and coworkers have correlated swimming in polluted seawater with enterovirus infection (Begier et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2008</xref>). For enteroviruses, the most common mode of transmission is the fecal-oral route, although aerosol transmission has also been reported. In a similar manner, drinking water contaminated with virus, such as Norovirus, also presents a risk for human health, highlighting the importance of good hygiene practices with respect to water storage, Shin and Sobsey suggested that water chlorination could inactivate enteric viruses (Shin &amp; Sobsey, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2008</xref>). Sample concentration is a critical step in viral diagnosis, since the number of viral particles in water is generally very low, which often results in false results if samples are tested directly using PCR (Katayama et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2002</xref>). Therefore, some authors choose an adsorption–elution method, followed by ultrafiltration, to concentrate the viruses, before nested-PCR or quantitative Real Time PCR. In severally contaminated environments such as hospital wastewater treatment plants, Prado and coworkers utilized PCR/RT-PCR, quantitative real-time PCR (qPCR) and genome sequencing, after sample concentrations techniques, to assess the presence of viruses associated with human pathologies such as acute gastroenteritis and hepatitis (Prado et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2011</xref>). In intermediate contaminated environments, such as urban and bathing waters the assessment of microbial hazards with potential public health risk associated with viral contamination also preferentially utilizes nucleic acid amplification methodologies, after sample concentration. 
</p>
