<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In recent decades, different types of HSV vaccines, including inactivated vaccines, peptide vaccines containing various antigenic structures, and replication‐deficient vaccines, have been investigated for their efficacy and safety,
 <xref rid="rmv2054-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">9</xref> and these vaccines have been found to enable both cytotoxic T lymphocyte (CTL) responses in animals and neutralizing antibody production that blocked viral entry into cultured cells in classic neutralization assays.
 <xref rid="rmv2054-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2054-bib-0146" ref-type="ref">146</xref> However, a clinical trial of these vaccine candidates suggested that there were no clinical protective effects on human subjects, even though the immune response induced in rodent animal models was identified as being capable of protecting against viral attack.
 <xref rid="rmv2054-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">9</xref> This finding seems to suggest that the designed vaccine‐induced immune response, which was mainly based upon the antigenic structure of viral surface glycoproteins, might not target various virus‐encoded proteins that play roles in viral pathogenesis. Importantly, this characterized pathological process presents not only as vesicle lesions in epithelial and/or mucosal tissues but also as a modified phenotype of innate immune cells, including DCs and ILCs. The immune response elicited by HSV vaccine candidates based on viral glycoproteins cannot be restimulated by various antigenic molecules from virus‐encoded proteins that are expressed transiently at different stages of infection, and antibodies and CTLs specific for viral surface proteins cannot control various pathological lesions triggered by the interactions of many viral molecules with cellular molecules in tissues. Furthermore, if the characterized pathogenesis of HSV infection is recognized as a systematic dynamic outcome of the interactions between virus‐encoded molecules and cellular components, effective vaccine‐induced immunity would comprise not only neutralizing antibodies specific for viral surface protein‐binding receptors and/or specific CD8 cytotoxic T‐cell subsets in local tissues but also an antibody profile capable of neutralizing various viral molecules that enable interactions with host cells and a specific CTL response against infected cells presenting various viral antigens. However, to achieve this type of vaccine‐mediated immunity, the design for the HSV vaccine would be required to achieve the objectives presented below (Figure 
 <xref rid="rmv2054-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>): 
 <list list-type="order" id="rmv2054-list-0001">
  <list-item id="rmv2054-li-0047">
   <p>The vaccine candidate should have a viral replication cycle that mimics the HSV replication cycle but is substantially weaker and sufficiently long to ensure the activation of the local innate immune system and the subsequent activation of adaptive immunity.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="rmv2054-li-0048">
   <p>The vaccine candidate should be capable of inducing the expression of the main viral molecules with pathological effects and exposing them to the host immune system.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="rmv2054-li-0049">
   <p>The vaccine candidate should be designed to be readily taken up by antigen presenting cells, including DCs and/or ILCs and macrophages, without interference with antigen presentation processes or induction of cellular apoptosis events.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="rmv2054-li-0050">
   <p>The vaccine candidate should efficiently remove viral molecules with serious pathological effects and be unable to lead to pathological lesions in host tissues.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="rmv2054-li-0051">
   <p>Ideally, the vaccine candidate should itself possess no neurotropic infectivity, as described by Richards et al in a recent publication.
    <xref rid="rmv2054-bib-0095" ref-type="ref">95</xref>
   </p>
   <p>To satisfy these biological requirements in a vaccine candidate, a complex antigenic structure or an attenuated strain integrated with mutated structural genes could be generated with molecular techniques.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
