<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Rainfall and temperatures are known to have an impact on the dynamics of vector populations, and RVF virus can be transmitted by a large range of vectors species with different bio-ecologies [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The dynamics of rainfall and temperature may therefore result in a complex RVF vector multi-population dynamics for which no data are available in our case; and attempting to account for this without data would only increase the model uncertainty. In addition, studies on RVF vectors (
 <italic>Culex pipiens</italic> and 
 <italic>Aedes taeniorhynchus</italic>) showed that temperature above 26°C increased virus transmission rates [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], while in Mayotte the average temperature varies between 25°C and 35°C [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], potentially allowing transmission year-round. If data on vector population dynamics were available, and if the ecosystem studied could bear cooler temperatures, both temperature and rainfall should be accounted for. Here, we used NDVI as a proxy for vector habitat and therefore vector density in common with many previous RVF studies did [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Since Mayotte has not reported any NDVI anomalies as in the Horn of Africa [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], using monthly NDVI was the most relevant parameter to use. Furthermore, no previous dynamic models have used RVF transmission as a direct function of NDVI [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], although NDVI is used in most spatial modelling works [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Our model allowed quantifying of a functional relationship between NDVI and transmissibility for RVF, with the highest 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>s</italic>
 </sub> value being 2.19, falling within the range of previously estimated 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> at 1.19 (95%CI [1.18–1.21]) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>] in a theoretical endemic setting; or 1.18 (range 0.5–2.1) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>], and 1.17 (range [0–3.68]) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] in an epidemic context. Finally, our model offers a benchmark for exploring RVF transmissibility without vector data, and should be tested in ecosystems with different NDVI dynamics.
</p>
