<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We assumed that animals were at equal risk of acquiring infection and becoming seropositive across species and age-groups. Indeed, in Mayotte all animals regardless of age and species are raised outdoors, and we therefore assumed that they were at equal risk of being exposed to mosquito bites. In addition, while some studies found differences in serological prevalence between livestock species [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>], a number of serological studies conducted in different study areas across Africa, such as Mozambique, Senegal, Tanzania, Kenya and Madagascar, did not show any difference in seroprevalence between livestock species during an epidemic or inter-epidemic period [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Finally, due to the island’s small size and the limited spatial variation of the ecosystem [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]; but also since herds are small (about 5–7 animals) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], and herds from all communes had been affected by RVF, we did not need to account for spatial heterogeneity. This also allowed implementing model fitting in a data-scarce environment. Stratifying per location would have resulted in data points supported by fewer samples, increasing uncertainty and precluding model fitting. In addition, since our livestock population did not experience the classical symptoms of RVF (waves of abortions and high mortality in newborn), disease-induced mortality was not explicitly modelled. Sub-clinical forms were common for RVF in Mayotte, as well as in the neighbouring Union of Comoros and Mozambique [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Also, sheep, the most susceptible species to clinical symptoms, only represents 3–4% of the livestock population of the island. Finally, in the absence of vector data, nor evidence on human-to-animals RVF transmission, we assumed that the import of infectious animals was the most likely virus introduction pathway, although the introduction through infectious vectors and infectious humans cannot be ruled out.
</p>
