<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Huhehaote and Bayannaoer Districts are located in the central and western parts of Inner Mongolia, respectively. Both belong to a semi-arid or arid zone. Until the 1990s, epizootiologic surveys had not shown the presence of hantaviruses circulating in rodents and infecting humans in these districts (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">
  <italic>14</italic>
 </xref>). The first HFRS cases were reported in the Huhehaote District in 1995 and in the Bayannaoer District in 1999. In the Bayannaoer District, a relatively large HFRS outbreak occurred in 2005 and 2006, with 95 and 75 cases reported, respectively. The ecology of central and western Inner Mongolia differs from that of the northeastern part. In the central and western parts, 
 <italic>A. agrarius</italic> mice are absent, and 
 <italic>R. norvegicus</italic> rats are abundant. Consequently, a high number of human hantavirus infections are registered. Since the 1980s, the incidence of HFRS has been high in the provinces of Hebei and Shanxi (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">
  <italic>2</italic>
 </xref>
 <italic>,</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">
  <italic>5</italic>
 </xref>
 <italic>,</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">
  <italic>6</italic>
 </xref>
 <italic>,</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">
  <italic>22</italic>
 </xref>
 <italic>–</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">
  <italic>24</italic>
 </xref>), which share borders with central Inner Mongolia (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). Particularly, the annual number of HFRS cases reported in Hebei Province was more than 4,000 during 1990–2002 (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">
  <italic>6</italic>
 </xref>). 
 <italic>R. norvegicus</italic> rats were the predominant reservoir; hence, SEOV was prevalent in the provinces of Hebei and Shanxi (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">
  <italic>2</italic>
 </xref>
 <italic>,</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">
  <italic>5</italic>
 </xref>
 <italic>,</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">
  <italic>22</italic>
 </xref>
 <italic>–</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">
  <italic>24</italic>
 </xref>).
</p>
