<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Packaging of the viral genome into virus particles requires flavivirus capsid to interact with both the ER membrane (with prM and E proteins present) and with the genome. In addition to the disordered basic tails of flaviviral capsid, of interest is the large hydrophilic region on the bottom surface of each flavivirus capsid protein comprised of C-terminal domains of the dimer [
 <xref rid="B47-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. This face consists primarily of basic amino acids, lysine (K) and arginine (R). As shown by others, capsid appears to indiscriminately bind a range of nucleic acids 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> including either single or double stranded RNA or DNA, suggesting non-specific interactions with the phosphate backbone [
 <xref rid="B15-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. However, the N-terminal domain of flavivirus capsids, unresolvable by crystallography, is flexible and also highly positively charged. Disordered, basic peptide tails are highly common in nucleic-acid binding proteins with roles in RNA or DNA compaction or packaging such as the lysine-rich eukaryotic histone tails [
 <xref rid="B50-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] or arginine-rich motifs in viral capsid proteins from icosahedral non-enveloped viruses [
 <xref rid="B51-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Similarly, in flavivirus capsid, the disordered basic tail is implicated in the packaging of viral genome. Alanine scanning of the conserved basic regions within the N-terminal domain (first 18 residues) of the DENV capsid resulted in very slow propagation of virus due to the release of fewer virus particles compared to wild-type [
 <xref rid="B45-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Interestingly, these regions only needed be basic, and were not amino acid sequence specific. Thus, although the sequences of the N-terminus are not precisely conserved among flaviviruses, the two positively charged motifs/regions are.
</p>
