<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The last two decades have seen considerable advancement in the statistical methods available to fit dynamic models to empirical data, especially in the field of infectious diseases (Becker &amp; Britton 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">1999</xref>). An increasingly popular approach is to use a Bayesian framework, which offers several advantages. First, all model parameters follow probability distributions rather than being treated as fixed quantities. This enables measures of parameter uncertainty to be generated. Second, the Bayesian framework allows prior information (e.g. parameter ranges obtained from available data sources, such as published papers) to be incorporated into the model structure. This is somewhat controversial as poor choices of priors can unduly influence the final estimates. However, where reliable information is available, a careful use of priors can help to ensure that the parameter estimates obtained are realistic. Indeed, certain combinations of parameter values that fall outside of meaningful biological ranges might happen to produce a perfect fit to the data by virtue of the mathematical properties of the model, but the use of prior information can help maintain parameters within biologically appropriate ranges. Third, in the Bayesian framework, any missing information in the data (e.g. due to incomplete observations or long time intervals between repeated measurements) can be treated as extra parameters in the model, and estimated as part of the model fitting process (O'Neill &amp; Roberts 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b57">1999</xref>; Clark &amp; Bjørnstad 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">2004</xref>). Recent methods have also been developed to deal with missing information within a frequentist framework (Ionides 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42">2006</xref>). Other new techniques, such as approximate Bayesian computation, provide a natural framework to estimate parameters in stochastic ecological models (Hartig 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">2011</xref>), which are particularly relevant for infectious disease dynamics.
</p>
