<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0195">BM2 is a type III transmembrane protein that provides a proton channel function essential for the intracellular release of vRNPs from late endosomes. BM2 consists of a short 7 amino acid ectodomain, a 19 amino acid transmembrane domain and a cytosolic domain of 83 amino acids, and it exists in the form of a homotetramer. BM2 is a functional homolog with the IAV M2 protein to which it has little sequence identity apart from a conserved 19-HxxxW-23 proton channel motif. BM2 was recently shown to efficiently complement the multi-cyclic growth of a recombinant M2-deficient influenza A virus, which was otherwise confined to a single cycle infection. BM2 differs from the M2 protein in being insensitive to channel blockers such as amantadine resulting in natural resistance of type B influenza viruses to this first generation class of anti-influenza compounds. The resistance to amantadine was explained by differences in the interior part of the proton channel, which is covered by polar amino acids and not hydrophobic residues as in the case of the IAV M2 protein, as well as by a reduced size of the channel pore. Apart from serving as a proton channel BM2 protein has also important morphogenic activity since recombinant viruses with C-terminal BM2 deletions of as little as six amino acids displayed irregularly formed virions and the virus was strongly attenuated in its replication ability. The large cytosolic BM2 domain adopts a coiled-coil tetramer. Biochemical analyzes showed that the C-terminus of BM2 is important for efficient membrane association of the M1 protein in flotation centrifugation, as well as incorporation of M1 and vRNPs into virion particles. Within the cytosolic BM2 domain, there is an electrostatic interaction with a positive charged N-terminal part (residues 44–71) and a negative C-terminus (72−103), the latter of which has been suggested to bind to the IBV M1 protein. From these analyzes, a model emerges in which the BM2 protein is a central factor that recruits viral RNPs and the M1 protein to virion assembly sites as a prerequisite for efficient budding. Whether BM2 also contributes to scission of virus particles from the plasma membrane as described for M2 for IAV remains to be investigated.</p>
