<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Administrative controls guide—among other work practice controls—training and best practices including decontamination methods to prevent exposure to respiratory diseases. In addition, policies should direct a medical surveillance plan for healthcare workers and first responders, logistics for acquiring and storing needed materials required during an outbreak, and logistics for managing needed personnel. While this paper is not meant to detail all appropriate administrative controls needed for public health during a disease outbreak, two points should be emphasized. First, in the context of emerging diseases, administrative controls must optimally be put into place in anticipation of an outbreak or a pandemic rather than after a disease has already become established. Lessons learned from the SARS pandemic provide ample information for helping design administrative controls leaving sufficient flexibility for adaptation to different pathogens and regional needs.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>
 </sup> Second, the importance of personnel training cannot be emphasized enough. Even if sufficient PPE is available it becomes useless if personnel are not trained in proper donning and doffing procedures. Improper PPE use was likely a contributing factor in superspreading hospital events during the SARS and MERS outbreaks.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref51">51</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref69">69</xref>
 </sup> In the 2003 SARS epidemic 20.5% of all healthcare providers treating SARS patients in Hong Kong hospitals became infected, and 36.7% in a Canadian hospital episode.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref69">69</xref>
 </sup> The incorrect removal of PPE, for example, gloves, not only endangers hospital personnel and first responders and their patients but also plays a role in spreading disease in other facilities such as nursing homes, airports, and grocery stores. Thus, instead of offering protection, PPE without guided training can instill a false sense of security and accomplish the opposite, the expansion of an outbreak.
</p>
