<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23">Indeed, contagious contact necessarily represents the material realities of a physically connected world transcribed in their most extreme form (of potentially deadly connection or touch), where innumerable numbers of creatures and things are connected through the veritable tissues of air, atmosphere, and, indeed, seas of microbial organisms all connecting and comprising the spaces between us. However, as we have alluded to, this physical connectedness cannot but come with the burden of its own concomitant existential (and therefore spiritual, metaphysical, emotional, and symbolic) angst. Our volume seeks to represent this duality. To do anything otherwise risks building arguments on a set of misleading binaries. The point of this volume, therefore, is not to draw the lines between material and metaphorical contagion—a line which any thinking critic must acknowledge has been blurry since the formation of the concept itself. No physical contagious contact arises without epistemological (and therefore, at least partially psychological and symbolic) recourse to its human, animal, or environmental source, and no reference to metaphoric contagion can exist without a concept of literal contagious disease.
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn9">9</xref> One is no more “real” than the other. Figurative contagion describes “real” influence and not only shapes our perception of reality but also has material effects. Said differently, contagion is about “ideas becoming flesh and flesh becoming ideas” (Pelling 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2001</xref>, p. 5). Even the explicit and intended use of the term as metaphor rather than description of a biological entity or process is, as Martin Pernick observes, historically contingent. In Greek and Roman times, for instance, the influence of religion, ideas, and love was thought to influence physical health (Pernick 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2002</xref>). Moreover, the case has been made that such social and cultural influences have immunosuppressive effects (Blas and Sivasankara Kurup 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2010</xref>). These perhaps seemingly discrete ontologies are, in fact, mutually constitutive, a foundational logic of the volume at hand, and we are firmly convinced that the possibilities which emerge from it urgently bear exploration.
</p>
