<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8">Nevertheless, the medical golden age of antibiotics became challenged with HIV in the 1980s and 1990s and, of course, most recently with zoonotic influenzas, the 2014 EVD outbreak, and antibiotic-resistant bacteria. And, perhaps ironically, the characterization of the autism “epidemic” by the “anti-vaxx” movement has ushered in the resurgence of highly infectious childhood diseases that had been controlled by vaccines for some time. It is no surprise, then, that infectious discourse paradoxically continues to intrinsically structure contemporary society even as much of industrialized society imaginatively constructs itself as beyond the pale of infection and serious contagious threats. Contagion is a “cultural logic,” to use Fredric Jameson’s terms. If for Jameson, postmodernism was the cultural logic of a mode of capitalistic rationality, then contagion is a logic that serves dividing practices that subtend hermetic subjectivities, the distinction between self and other, and the supremacy and autonomy of the human. Often, this takes a biopolitical valence, based on what Foucault calls “racism,” (but which might more aptly be termed a hierarchy of life), where the human biological continuum is fragmented and categorized into those who are made to live at the expense of others who are allowed to die. On the one hand, Western cultures in many ways perceive that they have moved beyond contagious disease; on the other, they remain threatened by “foreign” and “emerging” diseases. Furthermore, they expand the biological notion of contagion as a way to understand threats to seemingly all aspects of life. In this capacity, contagion still threatens certain lives whether it be by way of suicidality, chronic diseases such as cancer or obesity, or physical and financial productivity. In spite of First-World nationalism that imagines its subjects as immune to the threat of infectious disease, our post-postmodern, post-human, post-natural society nevertheless retains the structural paradigms of contagion and infection in discourses beyond biomedicine. We are strikingly not post-contagion.</p>
