<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Drug treatment for most viral diseases is limited, and relies primarily on symptomatic treatment and supportive care with no attempt to impair virus propagation. This approach rests on the notion that viruses are cellular parasites that employ cellular processes to reproduce, and hence any attempt to target their propagation is likely to be toxic to the host cells as well. Therefore, few anti-viral drugs are available with a sufficient level of safety. In addition, anti-viral drugs must be highly effective, as incomplete inhibition of the virus infection may enable selection of drug-resistant virus strains that can cause an even greater threat. Accordingly, most anti-viral compounds target viral enzymes, such as proteases
 <xref rid="b12-rmmj-11-3-e0023" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="b35-rmmj-11-3-e0023" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> and replication enzymes.
 <xref rid="b36-rmmj-11-3-e0023" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="b37-rmmj-11-3-e0023" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> New anti-viral drugs, some of which are still under development, focus on blocking attachment of the virus to the host cell, preventing its entry into cells and virion uncoating, inhibiting regulatory functions, or targeting the viral RNA.
 <xref rid="b38-rmmj-11-3-e0023" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> Potential drugs with such activities can be identified by using purified viral proteins in high-throughput mechanism-based experimental screens. Computational approaches, based on the atomic structure of the target molecule, enable virtual screening and design of new drugs. In addition, a comprehensive understanding of the molecular interactions between the virus and the host cell, together with whole-genome sequencing and methods to block gene expression, enables identification of cellular gene products that are essential for virus replication, and which can be used as targets for treatment without damaging the host. Obviously, any new compound has to reach appropriate bioavailability and pharmacokinetics with no toxic effects.
</p>
