<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Genetic variants in the major histocompatibility complex antigen loci (HLA) are well-known to influence host susceptibility to infectious disease (
 <xref rid="B149" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>). So far, only a limited number of studies have looked for an association between HLA haplotypes and genetic susceptibility or resistance to SARS coronavirus infection. However, an impact of HLA haplotypes may identify some of the unexplained differences in disease severity and mortality observed across different countries and different population ethnicities (
 <xref rid="B150" ref-type="bibr">150</xref>–
 <xref rid="B154" ref-type="bibr">154</xref>). Allele typing of 37 probable SARS patients in Taiwan identified an association between HLA-B
 <sup>*</sup>4601 and SARS-CoV infection (
 <xref rid="B155" ref-type="bibr">155</xref>); however, this was not confirmed in a study of 90 serologically confirmed SARS-CoV patients in Hong Kong (
 <xref rid="B156" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B157" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>). The latter study instead identified an association between the HLA-B
 <sup>*</sup>0703 and HLA-DRB1
 <sup>*</sup>0301 genotypes and the development of SARS (
 <xref rid="B157" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>). In terms of the current pandemic, we might predict that genetic variations in the HLA molecules resulting in decreased binding specificities for SARS-CoV-2 peptides may confer a more severe COVID-19 disease course (
 <xref rid="B158" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>). Zhao et al. (
 <xref rid="B159" ref-type="bibr">159</xref>) investigated the relationship between ABO blood group and COVID-19 susceptibility in 2,173 Chinese patients. Interestingly, being of blood group A represented a higher risk for developing COVID-19 disease, whilst having blood group O was associated with a lower infection risk. A similar risk pattern for ABO blood groups has also been reported for the 2003 SARS-CoV outbreak (
 <xref rid="B160" ref-type="bibr">160</xref>); however, the exact mechanism of how blood group antigens might affect susceptibility remains to be clarified.
</p>
