<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="fig-6" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.7954/fig-6</object-id>
 <label>Figure 6</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Motif switching.</title>
  <p>An example of motif switching events observed in avian HA protein. The alignment region shown is from position 168 to 179, comprising of four overlapping nonamer positions. At the nonamer position 168–176 (with 2,349 protein sequences aligned at the position), the nonatype KKDNAYPTI containing the amino acid (aa) “A” at position 172 (172A) is the predominant sequence, and thus, the index, while the nonatype KKNSTYPTI containing the aa “T” at the corresponding position (172T) is the second most predominant sequence, and thus, the major variant. The nonamer position also included multiple nonatypes of minor and unique variants (two nonatypes shown: a minor and a unique variant; the remaining 67 nonatypes not shown). In the subsequent nonamer position (169–177), the nonamer containing aa 172A remained as the index, but with a reduced incidence because a small fraction (five sequences) of the index (from the preceding position 168–176) split into four different nonatypes because of a variant amino acid in each, as a result of the position shift, which contributed to the occurrence of one new minor and three new unique variants at the current focal nonamer position (169–177). Meanwhile, the nonamer containing aa 172T, which was the major variant at the preceding position, remained as major variant at the current focal nonamer position, but with an increase in its incidence because two nonatypes (a minor variant of two copies and a unique variant) from the preceding nonamer position (168–176) merged with the major variant at the current focal position 169–177. Nonetheless, the major variant of the preceding position also underwent a split, where one copy became a new unique variant at the current focal position. In the next nonamer position (170–178), an index switching event is observed, where the nonamer containing aa 172A has significantly dropped in incidence to be downgraded from the previous index rank to now as a major variant, and replaced by the nonamer containing aa 172T (previously the major variant) as the new index. As many as 217 copies (552 − 335;∼39%) of the former index sequence were split into different variant motifs, thus decreasing the incidence of the sequence. Although the nonamer containing aa 172T also split into other variants, the incidence drop was less (∼16%), leaving it as the sequence with the highest incidence and thus the predominant index. In the subsequent nonamer position (171–179), another index switching event occurred, which witnesses a reversal of the previous switch, where now the nonamer containing aa 172A is back as the index and the nonamer containing aa 172T is back as the major variant. This was due to the merger of a significant copy number of different minor and unique variants with the major variant (nonamer containing aa 172A), and thus, resulting in an increase in its incidence at the current focal position 171–179 and becoming the predominant index. At the current focal position, it was also observed that variants can be gained from a motif classified as “None” (due to indel) at the preceding position. Similarly variants can become loss, classified as “None” if the position shift introduced an indel.</p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="peerj-08-7954-g006" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
