<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par30">IVDB provides access to additional tools such as (i) the Sequence Distribution Tool, which provides global geographical distribution of a given viral genotype as well as correlates its genomic data with epidemiological data, and (ii) the Quality Filter System, which according to their sequence content (coding sequence [CDS], 5’untranslated region [5’UTR], and 3’UTR) and integrity (complete [C] or partial [P]) categorizes a given viral nucleotide sequence into either of the seven categories of C1 to C4 and P1 to P3, respectively. NCBI-IVR is the most widely used and cited online resource. With NCBI-IVR, the given viral genomic sequences can be annotated using a genome annotation tool and Flu ANnotation (FLAN) tool. Additionally, large phylogenetic trees may be constructed and can be visualized in aggregated form with sub-scale details (Bao et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2007</xref>; Bao et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2008</xref>; Zaslavsky et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">2008</xref>). IRD provides tools for genomic and proteomic intervention, immune epitope prediction and surveillance data for viral nucleotide sequences (Squires et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">2012</xref>). Furthermore, this resource is also equipped with tools that provide insight into host-pathogen interactions, type of virulence, host range and a correlation of sequence variation and these processes. There are other repositories available: Global Initiative on Sharing Avian Influenza Data (GISAID) consortium that mediated the EpiFlu database and FluGenome database that exclusively provides genotyping of influenza A virus and aids in detecting reassortments taking place in divergent lines (Lu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2007</xref>). Furthermore, reassortment events in influenza viruses exclusively can be identified by a program GiRaF (Graph-incompatibility-based Reassortment Finder) that can be downloaded (Nagarajan and Kingsford 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2011</xref>). Another distinct repository, Influenza Sequence and Epitope Database (ISED), provides viral sequences and epitopes from Asian countries; the information could be exploited to understand and study evolutionary divergence and migration of strains (Yang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">2009</xref>). The web server ATIVS (Analytical Tool for Influenza Virus Surveillance) provides an antigenic map for conducting surveillance and selection of vaccine strains by scrutinizing the serological data of haemagglutinin sequence data of influenza A/H3N2 viruses and influenza subtypes (Liao et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2009</xref>). There is another online repository OpenFluDB (an isolate-centred inventory), where information of an isolate such as virus type, host, date of isolation, geographical distribution, predicted antiviral resistance, enhanced pathogenicity or human adaptation propensity may be obtained (Liechti et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2010</xref>). For influenza viruses, primers and probes can be designed using the Influenza Primer Design Resource (IPDR) (Bose et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2008</xref>). Further, prospective influenza seasonal epidemics or pandemics can be predicted using a stochastic model, FluTE (Chao et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2010</xref>) (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">23.2</xref>).
</p>
