<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This study only investigated the short-term associations between influenza infection and hospitalisations occurring in the same week, with the burden of longer-term sequelae unable to be estimated. The choice of knots for the smoother of time in our GAM model may have influenced our results. We took a conservative, a priori approach for the choice of knots, which led to some residual autocorrelation, but avoided overfitting the smoother to the observed data. Nevertheless, the sensitivity analysis comparing results between our modelling approach and a more conventional harmonic regression model showed that the results were similar. Further, our choice of knots provided a reasonable level of independence in the model residuals compared with a greater and a lower degree of smoothing and with the harmonic model. Checking of this modelling assumption is often absent from influenza attribution studies. A disadvantage of the harmonic regression model [
 <xref rid="pone.0230705.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] may be that it requires an assumption that all non-influenza diseases that contribute to the diagnosis category being studies have perfect seasonality when aggregated. This is unlikely given that influenza circulated at varying times and with varying epidemic sizes each year. Another limitation is that we were unable to control for other respiratory pathogens, such as respiratory syncytial virus (RSV). RSV laboratory results are not systematically monitored in Australia. This may have led to some misattribution of RSV hospitalisations to influenza [
 <xref rid="pone.0230705.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. However, a southern hemisphere study from South Africa on influenza and RSV-attributable mortality found that inclusion or exclusion of RSV did not substantially alter the influenza results [
 <xref rid="pone.0230705.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Our model fit may have been improved if we had access to hospitalisation data that excluded planned admissions, thus leading to a hospitalisation time series that better reflected acute illness in the population. We were unable to examine influenza A subtypes or influenza B lineages, because subtype is only available for a small proportion of influenza notifications. Due to sparse notification data in some years, we were unable to include age-specific notifications in the age-specific models. Nevertheless, all-age epidemic patterns should reasonably reflect age-specific time series.
</p>
