<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As depicted in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>, in the NASBA process, three enzymes and two primers work together to exponentially amplify a target viral RNA. Primer 1 (P1) carries at its 5′ end T7 RNA polymerase promotor region and at its 3′ end, P1 carries sequence that is complementary to a target viral RNA sequence. Primer 2 (P2) carries a sequence complementary to cDNA strand. The amplification reaction begins with the production of cDNA copy of the viral RNA by RT using P1. RNase H degrades the viral RNA from RNA-DNA hybrid molecules. Then, RT synthesizes dsDNA molecules using P2 and the released DNA strand. Finally, T7 RNA polymerase uses dsDNA molecules as templates to transcribe many viral RNA copies. The above cycle is repeated several times, resulting in the accumulation of many viral RNA copies and ds DNA molecules. The amplified product can either be detected by gel electrophoresis at the end of the assay or in real time using molecular beacon [
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Transcription-based amplification methods have several advantages, for example, they do not require a thermal cycler, so developing countries and budget-restricted laboratories can afford to perform the assays, they have rapid kinetics (requires fewer cycles), and they produce a single-stranded RNA product that is suitable for detection by various techniques [
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Transcription-based amplification methods are suitable for the diagnosis of human viral infections caused by RNA viruses. They can amplify viral genomic RNA, messenger RNA, or ribosomal RNA [
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Ayele et al. [
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] developed NASBA assay that uses gag-based molecular beacons to distinguish between HIV-1 subtype C (C and C′) circulating in Ethiopia. The assay demonstrated high levels of sensitivity and specificity for both beacons (90.5% sensitivity and 100% specificity for the C beacon and 100% sensitivity and 95.2% specificity for the C′ beacon) by considering sequencing as gold standard for genotyping. Moore et al. [
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>] also used NSABA for the detection of influenza A H5N1 virus in clinical specimens with a LoD of 10 RNA copies/
 <italic>μ</italic>l along with the same sensitivity as RT-PCR and average turnaround time of 4 hours. The NASBA assay was also used for the detection of dengue viral RNA with LoD of 1 PFU/ml for all of 4 dengue virus serotypes, no cross-reaction with JEV, and turnaround time of 3 hours [
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Ender et al. [
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] used TMA for screening of blood donations for HIV-1 and HCV RNA. The TMA assay had LoDs of 16.2 IU/ml for HIV-1 and 3.5 IU/ml for HCV. A multiplex NASBA assay was used for simultaneous detection of HIV-1 and HCV in plasma samples. The LoD of the assay for both HIV-1 and HCV was determined to be 1000 copies/ml and no cross-reactions with other selected viruses [
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Swenson and his colleagues [
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>] used real-time TMA for the detection of HSV-1 and HSV-2 in lesion swab specimens with overall sensitivities of 98.2% and 99.4%, respectively, and specificity of 97.8% and 94.5%, respectively, compared to culture. In one study, real-time NASBA assay was more sensitive than the conventional RT-PCR in the detection of norovirus. In this study, RT-PCR detected 10 pg of standard viral RNA, while the real-time NASBA assay could detect 100 fg of standard viral RNA [
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. These data indicate that the assays are sensitive, specific, and cost-effective for the detection of human infection by RNA viruses.
</p>
