<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>HNMs comprise a family of materials that share a nanostructured hard core and a tunable surface chemistry. In this contribution, we have methodically reviewed different HNMs for antiviral properties. HNMs can have antiviral properties 
 <italic>per se</italic>, blocking the viral replication and diffusion, or their antiviral properties can be tailored, playing with surface chemistry. HNMs can be used to block viral entry and arrest infection at the early stage. The mechanisms rely on different actions including breaking of capsid disulfide bonds (
 <italic>e</italic>.
 <italic>g</italic>., noble metal nanoparticles), capsid oxidation (
 <italic>e</italic>.
 <italic>g</italic>., CuONPs), mimicking of cell surface (
 <italic>e</italic>.
 <italic>g</italic>., carbon NMs), or mechanical disruption (
 <italic>e</italic>.
 <italic>g</italic>., AuNPs or graphene). Surface functionalization additionally confers a higher specificity and pharmacological activity toward the targeted virus. In particular, the high local concentration of ligands on functionalized HNM surface imparts a high multivalent effect, enhancing the viral trapping efficiency of NMs. Interestingly, HNMs that show an intrinsic antiviral activity can further enhance their antiviral efficacy 
 <italic>via</italic> surface functionalization. Some antiviral HNMs are good photosensitizers (
 <italic>e</italic>.
 <italic>g</italic>., CuONPs) or exert photothermal activity (
 <italic>e</italic>.
 <italic>g</italic>., carbon NMs), thus their antiviral activity can be trigged by light stimulation. More importantly, most of the settled strategies target common viral entry mechanisms and can be adopted to fight a wide viral spectrum. HNMs have been also applied as antiviral agents by their interaction with host cells. HNMs are able to block viral replication machinery in host cells (
 <italic>e</italic>.
 <italic>g</italic>., CNTs and fullerenes), inhibiting endogenous enzyme activity. Additionally, HNMs can be explored for the delivery of antiviral molecules, showing a better antiviral activity and reducing side effects 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>. Some HNMs can also regulate the ROS homeostasis of host cells, reduce apoptosis, and enhance host cell survival during the infection. Finally, we have reviewed the role of HNMs on immunity. In particular, HNMs can stimulate the innate immune response, mainly inducing overexpression of interferon and cytokines. This effect can alert sentinel cells and generally warn the immune system of the infection. HNMs can be also used for the activation of the adaptive immune response, foreseeing vaccination. Due to the similar size of a virus, functionalized HNMs with antiviral molecules (virus-like particles) can enhance their immunogenicity.
</p>
