<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Oropouche virus (OROV) is one of the most important arthropodborne orthobunyaviruses (
 <italic>Bunyaviridae</italic>, 
 <italic>Orthobunyavirus</italic>) (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">
  <italic>1</italic>
 </xref>) that infect humans; it causes an acute febrile illness called Oropouche fever (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">
  <italic>2</italic>
 </xref>). OROV was originally reported in Trinidad in 1955, when the prototype virus strain was isolated from the blood of a febrile patient and from a pool of 
 <italic>Coquillettidia venezuelensis</italic> mosquitoes (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">
  <italic>3</italic>
 </xref>). In Brazil, OROV was initially described in 1960, when it was isolated from a sloth (
 <italic>Bradypus tridactylus</italic>) captured near a forest area during the construction of the Belém-Brasilia highway, and from a pool of 
 <italic>Ochlerotatus serratus</italic> mosquitoes captured nearby (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">
  <italic>4</italic>
 </xref>). More than one-half million persons have been infected with OROV, which makes this virus a public health threat in tropical and subtropical areas of Central and South America (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">
  <italic>5</italic>
 </xref>). OROV genome consists of 3 partite, single-stranded, negative-sense RNAs, named large (L), medium (M), and small (S) RNA. These RNAs are predicted to encode a large protein (L: polymerase activity), viral surface glycoproteins (Gc and Gn), and nonstructural NSM protein, as well as both nucleocapsid (N) and NSS proteins (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">
  <italic>1</italic>
 </xref>). Complete nucleotide sequences have been determined for all 3 RNA segments (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">
  <italic>6</italic>
 </xref>
 <italic>–</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">
  <italic>8</italic>
 </xref>), and previous studies of the molecular biology of the N gene (SRNA) of 28 different OROV strains indicated the existence of 3 genotypes, designated I, II, and III (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">
  <italic>6</italic>
 </xref>).
</p>
