<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0210">Over the past few decades, there was an urge to discover the root cause of coronavirus infections not only in animals but in humans as well. Currently, COVID-19 has emerged as the most intense and petrifying viral infection to be handled by the human race. According to 
 <xref rid="bb0825" ref-type="bibr">WHO (2020b)</xref>, major concern among public health throughout the world and many countries have taken precautionary measures against the virus, and Government officials in all countries continue to make efforts to minimize human contact by facilitating countrywide shutdowns of public places as well as various steps have been initiated to ensure the safety of the people, like social distancing and self-quarantine which limits our social interactions (
 <xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">Balachandar et al., 2020</xref>). This will reduce the risk of spreading the COVID-19 to people by breaking the transmission chain and the influx of new COVID-19 cases in a given time period. Total confirmed cases throughout the world are 4,16,686 and total number of confirmed deaths are 18,589 (
 <xref rid="bb0820" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2020a</xref>) as on 26th March 26, 2020 and in India 581 cases (
 <xref rid="bb0340" ref-type="bibr">ICMR, 2020</xref>) have been identified to be positive for this COVID-19 and 11 death cases in India as on 25th March 2020 (20:00 IST). More cases are likely to be identified in the coming days in India. This increase in infection was mainly due to the ability of this virus to recombine, mutate, block the immune system of the host cells and infect multiple species as well as cell types. Moreover, discovering the gene pool of SARS-CoV-2 may help accelerate the production of drugs and vaccines. Further, analyzing and understanding the role of non-structure and accessory proteins encrypted in this virus will aid us in understanding its mechanism of action. Also, acquiring an in-depth framework of its unique RNA replication process will enable us to find a breakthrough point to understand the host immunological response. Our review suggests the importance of a few Indian medicinal plants that have been used for several decades in the treatment of various respiratory conditions. It highlights the pathways that the plant-based medicines may target to reduce the disease burden. Thus, proactive investments in researches based on Indian medicinal plant derived vaccines or drugs to treat COVID-19 would emerge as a source of light to overcome this fatal infection.
</p>
