<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0270">The MISMS project was initiated in 2001 to build global research capacity for the study of influenza viruses using computational methods (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://misms.net" id="intr0005" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://misms.net</ext-link>, 
 <xref rid="tb0005" ref-type="boxed-text">Box 1</xref> ). The acronym originally referred to the Multinational Influenza Seasonal Mortality Study, although the program quickly expanded beyond mortality studies. MISMS has a mission to promote research, training and inform policy, more specifically (i) to characterize the global epidemiological and evolutionary dynamics of influenza in different host species, and (ii) to empower influenza researchers globally to study influenza and inform policymaking in their own countries. Towards this end, 18 technical training workshops were conducted on six continents during 2007–2018. These workshops focus on reviewing the state of influenza research and epidemiology in different global regions, and hands-on teaching of time series analysis of contemporary and historical outbreaks, control measures, mathematical transmission models, and phylogenetic approaches (
 <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> ). MISMS supports interdisciplinary approaches by fostering collaborations between historians, demographers, ecologists, evolutionary biologists, vaccine manufacturers, microbiologists, epidemiologists, and policy-makers, as evidenced by the rich diversity of publications (
 <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> ).
 <boxed-text id="tb0005">
  <label>Box 1</label>
  <caption>
   <title>Why have RAPIDD and MISMS workshops been so successful?</title>
  </caption>
  <p id="par0005">Since 2007, 
   <underline>RAPIDD</underline> has sponsored 118 workshops on topics ranging from gain-of-function experiments to the latest developments in particle filtering methods. These workshops have had a remarkable track record of enabling constructive syntheses of current frontiers in the science of disease modeling, and in spurring innovation and analysis of case studies to advance those frontiers. They also have earned a strong reputation in the field as important venues for scientific discourse. Here we summarize distinctive elements of those workshops that we believe have contributed to their success.
   <list list-type="simple" id="lis0005">
    <list-item id="lsti0005">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="par0010">Lightweight and nimble proposal process, steered by two generous and visionary scientists that had deep expertise in the field. The program ‘let a thousand flowers bloom’ by accepting workshop proposals on a rolling basis with a two-page initial proposal. For promising proposals, program leadership then iterates with proposers to refine the focus on RAPIDD goals, ensure solid deliverables, and optimize the participant list.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="lsti0010">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="par0015">Small size and balanced composition. Research workshops are generally kept to 10–20 participants, to ensure free-flowing and natural discussion. Age structure is key, with emphasis on including junior scientists (especially postdocs) so there are people with the time and incentive to do follow-up work.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="lsti0015">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="par0020">Flexible structure. Adapt meeting structure to meet scientific needs. Some workshops focus on conceptual or methodological issues, others on particular disease systems. Some of the best workshops had a central theme combined with data in hand and time to analyze it.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="lsti0020">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="par0025">Keep workshops short (typically 1.5–3 days) and maximize the value of in-person meetings. Pre-workshop teleconferences (among leaders or the whole group) help to reach consensus on goals and scope, so talks are on target and preliminary work can get done. Avoid overloading the schedule with formal talks, to ensure ample time for discussion and breakout groups; some participants can act as synthesizers or reactors rather than giving talks. Relaxed interactions on a hike or at a pub usually pay off.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="lsti0025">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="par0030">Designed for follow-through. Before the meeting, specify deliverable and timelines, and identify who will lead these efforts (often RAPIDD postdocs or workshop organizers). Get key pieces such as data sets and foundational analyses in place beforehand. Require workshop reports within a few months, summarizing the scientific content of the meeting, progress toward deliverables, and new opportunities that have emerged. Support follow-up when warranted, including ‘working meetings’ of project leaders, but also be prepared to stop threads that are not productive or not aligned with program priorities.</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
  <p id="par0035">Since 2005, 
   <underline>MISMS</underline> has convened 18 training workshops on all 5 continents and trained several hundreds of scientists on computational methods for infectious diseases. The unique characteristics of these workshops include:
   <list list-type="simple" id="lis0010">
    <list-item id="lsti0030">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="par0040">The primary output of these workshops is technology transfer; i.e. capacity building in infectious disease analytics. Participants are not expected to become modeling experts after a short workshop, but instead they should understand principles of data analysis and modeling (to the point that they are able to understand a disease modeling article).</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="lsti0035">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="par0045">MISMS workshops are typically regionally-focused and organized in tandem with a local university, research institute, or ministry of health. Regional participants are identified based on an exhaustive PubMed search (especially in early years of the MISMS program), word-of-mouth, and existing MISMS contacts (particularly as the program matured). Public health experts from WHO, CDC, and local institutions, are always invited.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="lsti0040">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="par0050">Workshops are sometimes organized in conjunction with a larger influenza scientific meeting to decrease travel costs and optimize participation.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="lsti0045">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="par0055">Weeklong workshops include 2 days of general scientific session and 3 days of hands-on training. The general session is meant to expose the state of the art of influenza epidemiology in the region and highlight success stories in influenza modeling and MISMS collaborations. The hands-on training session demonstrate methods in time series analysis, transmission models, and evolutionary analyses.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="lsti0050">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="par0060">Workshops are open to scientists and public health experts who do not have prior training in infectious disease modeling, e.g. veterinarians, clinicians, virologists, lab technicians, policy makers, etc.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="lsti0055">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="par0065">Flexible travel support for participants based on abstract selection process; focus on participants bringing data that may be amenable to modeling, those who have a clear training plan, and those from underserved areas.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="lsti0060">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="par0070">Training portion of the workshop is limited to 30 participants, for 5–8 faculty, to facilitate one-on-one interactions.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="lsti0065">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="par0075">Participants are encouraged to bring their own data; at least a day is devoted to small-group analyses of these data. Sample datasets are always available for demonstration purposes and for those unable to bring data (or with sparser datasets).</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="lsti0070">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="par0080">While the workshops are focused on influenza, participation is open to scientists working on related infectious diseases, recognizing that relevant (or specific) influenza data may be scarce in some countries, and that computational skills are cross-cutting.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="lsti0075">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="par0085">Workshop deliverables include joint publications and supplementary issues that spur collaborative work (for instance, Supplementary issues on Big Data for Infectious Disease Surveillance or Historical Pandemics (
      <xref rid="bib0545" ref-type="bibr">Simonsen, Viboud et al. 2011</xref>; 
      <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">Bansal, Chowell et al. 2016</xref>; 
      <xref rid="bib0530" ref-type="bibr">Simonsen et al., 2016</xref>))
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="lsti0080">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="par0090">Similarly to RAPIDD, there is opportunity for follow-up beyond the workshop, primarily via longer visits to NIH for more extensive training with MISMS staff, and occasionally, through remote collaborations. Workshops can also be organized in the same region a few years later to gauge progress. MISMS staff provides support for completion of analytical work and manuscripts, where workshop participants are recognized as first authors.</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
  <notes notes-type="alt-text" specific-use="for-accessibility" id="at0025">
   <p>Alt-text: Box 1</p>
  </notes>
 </boxed-text>
</p>
