<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015">New species of human viruses are still being identified, at a rate of three or four per year. Viruses make up about two-thirds of all new human pathogens. These new viruses differ widely in their importance, ranging from the rare and mild illness due to Menangle virus to the devastating public health impact of Human immunodeficiency virus 1 (HIV-1). On the contrary, a highly significant overrepresentation has been given by most human pathogen species of bacteria, fungi, or helminthes. Actually, it was the discovery of the HIV in the early 1980s that initiated a worldwide awareness and research interest in emerging novel viral pathogens (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Anderson and Tong, 2010</xref>). Over the past several decades, new outbreaks of infections have led to the discovery of a diverse array of highly pathogenic viruses mainly those belonging to the Filoviridae, Arenaviridae, Bunyaviridae, Paramyxoviridae, Coronaviridae, Flaviviridae, Togaviridae, and Hepeviridae families. Some examples include BK virus, JC virus, Merkel cell polyomavirus (MCV or MCPyV), severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome virus (SFTSV), hantavirus (HTNV), and Sin Nombre virus (
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Bebber et al., 2007</xref>). Following the fatal cases of Lujo virus in southern Africa in 2008 (
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Briese et al., 2009</xref>), another arena virus, the Lassa virus, was first reported in Nigeria in 1969, reemerged in Guinea, Liberia, and Mali in 2009, Ghana in 2011, and Benin in 2014. Human metapneumovirus was first identified in the Netherlands in 2001 and was subsequently linked to an acute lower respiratory tract infection in children, similar to respiratory syncytial virus (RSV). Recently, in 2013, a novel avian influenza A strain (H7N9) of “bird flu” in China (
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Wolfe et al., 2004</xref>) and the Middle East respiratory syndrome related Coronavirus (MERS)-CoV have been identified (
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Corman et al., 2012</xref>). Of note, while 2015 was threatened by the reemergence of the Ebola virus, 2015/2016 has been challenged with the resurgence of the Zika virus (ZIKV). Despite substantial advancements in the understanding of the biology of pathogens, the breakthrough in prevention, their effects on public health and the global economy, and the emergence of novel pandemic viruses remains an enduring puzzle. The intricate “host–pathogen–environment” relationship remains the key to understanding the emergence/reemergence of pathogenic versus ecological approach to study the diversity of human viruses (defined as viruses for which there is evidence of natural infection of humans) (
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Jones et al., 2008</xref>). First, the temporal, geographical, and taxonomic patterns in the discovery of human viruses need to be described and co related. Second, the processes by which new human viruses emerge need to be understood. There are a number of definitions of “emergence.” All the stages of the process by which a virus shifts from not infecting humans at all to becoming a major human pathogen need to be understood. As experiences with HIV-1 and new variants of influenza A (and also with novel animal pathogens such as canine parvovirus) show, this shift can occur rapidly, over time scales of decades, years, or even months. Not all newly identified human virus species are “new” in the sense that they have only recently started to infect humans; many of them have been present in humans for a considerable time but have only recently been recognized (
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Cleaveland et al., 2007</xref>). Moreover, the “species” itself is an imprecise designation, especially in influenza-like viruses where different serotypes can have different epidemiologies and health impacts. Indeed, the demarcation between genus, species complex, species, and serotype (or other designations of subspecific variation) can be somewhat arbitrary (
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Cleaveland et al., 2001</xref>). Nonetheless, a study of currently recognized “species” is a natural starting point for attempts to characterize and interpret patterns of virus diversity. A comprehensive knowledge of important emerging/reemerging viral infections worldwide with their possible origins, evolution, natural reservoirs, human adaptations, and risk factors needs to be developed for individual novel agents for a better insight of the biologic and evolutionary mechanisms (
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Keeling and Rohani, 2008</xref>) (
 <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4.1</xref> ). 
</p>
