<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <bold>
  <italic>i) Consensus sequence generation.</italic>
 </bold> Bioinformatic pipelines were run on the same laptop used for sequencing. A RABV version of the ARTIC network open-source bioinformatics pipeline ( 
 <xref rid="ref-60" ref-type="bibr">Quick 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017
 </xref>) was used to generate consensus sequences for each barcoded sample ( 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3B</xref>). Briefly, raw files were basecalled with the latest ONT software at the time (Albacore or Guppy) and demultiplexed with Porechop using stringent settings to select reads with barcodes at both ends of the read. Demultiplexed reads were then mapped with BWA ( 
 <xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Li &amp; Durbin, 2009</xref>) to a reference genome chosen according to the country of origin (Tanzania/Kenya: Genbank accession no. 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/KF155002" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">KF155002</ext-link>; Philippines: Genbank accession no. 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/KX148260" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">KX148260</ext-link>). Prior to variant calling, primer sequences were trimmed using their genome coordinates and their genome coverage normalised. Variants were called using Nanopolish ( 
 <xref rid="ref-100" ref-type="bibr">Loman 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015
 </xref>), which uses MinION signal-level data to “polish” the genome assembly. Consensus sequences were generated under the condition that non-overlapping primer binding sites and sites for which coverage was &lt;20X were masked by ambiguity code N. Illumina reads were processed according to a previously described method ( 
 <xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">Brunker 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015
 </xref>). Briefly, Genome Analysis Toolkit ( 
 <xref rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr">Poplin 
  <italic>et al.,</italic> 2017
 </xref>) was used to identify high quality SNPs using filters on strand bias (FS&gt;60, SOR&gt;4), mapping quality (MQ&lt;40, MQRankSum≤12.5), read position (ReadPosRankSum≤8), and depth of coverage (DP&lt;5). Consensus sequences were produced with a 75% majority basecall rule. Raw and processed sequence data files were stored locally on the laptop’s internal hard drive or external SSDs. Data was transferred to University of Glasgow servers for storage and backup on return to the UK.
</p>
