<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>ZIKV emerged in an immunologically naive population and spread rapidly throughout the Americas, with the consequent impact on human health [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007622.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. In the upcoming years it is unlikely that the region will experience similar peaks of GBS due to ZIKV infection given the build-up of population immunity against this arbovirus [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007622.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. However, other emerging pathogens, including different arboviruses and influenza strains [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007622.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>], may trigger increases in the incidence of GBS. In the future, in addition to background GBS-triggering foodborne infections, we expect GBS incidence to be cyclical as attack rates of arboviral infections fluctuate seasonally as well as in response to population immunity. Foodborne infections are often cited as the most common GBS trigger, responsible for between 25% and 50% of GBS cases worldwide [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007622.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Of eight studies included in this review that examined 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>jejuni</italic> as an antecedent infection to GBS, only two found a positive association. On the island of Curaçao, authors found a positive temporal association between 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>jejuni</italic> infections and GBS in pre-ZIKV years (1987–1999) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007622.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. In Veracruz, Mexico, 75% of GBS patients tested positive for 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>jejuni</italic> infection in 2017 (after the peak of ZIKV) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007622.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Studies in Aruba, Brazil, and Colombia–all except the one from Aruba were conducted during the ZIKV epidemic–found no association between 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>jejuni</italic> infection and GBS [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007622.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007622.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007622.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007622.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007622.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007622.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. A study in Brazil found respiratory infections to be present in 27% of GBS patients compared to 7% with gastrointestinal infections in pre-ZIKV years (1995–2002) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007622.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Although examining the role of foodborne infections was outside the scope of this research, this limited evidence suggests that temporal increases in GBS incidence during ZIKV in LAC are not associated with 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>jejuni</italic> infection. With more robust GBS surveillance and increased awareness, the region would be better prepared to monitor fluctuations in GBS incidence in the future. Although this review focused on GBS in endemic populations, incidence of neurological conditions in other regions might be impacted by international travelers returning from areas with ZIKV and other arboviral disease transmission, or with a sexual partner who returned from such areas [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007622.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0007622.ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>].
</p>
