<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<boxed-text id="BB1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
 <caption>
  <title>Executive summary</title>
 </caption>
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) was first reported in China and currently poses a serious challenge worldwide. The pneumonia was caused by a novel coronavirus named SARS-CoV-2.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>More than 1,347,804 cases of COVID-19 and 74,596 deaths have been reported as of April 7, 2020 according to data from Johns Hopkins Resource Center.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>SARS-CoV-2 belongs to 
    <italic>Betacoronavirus</italic>, a large genus of viruses prevalent in nature. SARS-CoV-2 has 82% nucleotide identity with human SARS-CoV and 96% nucleotide identity with bat SARS coronavirus (SARSr-CoV-RaTG13).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>The fatality rate of COVID-19 has been approximately 3.4% and the R0 has ranged from 1.4 to 6.4. Compared with previous coronavirus outbreaks, COVID-19 has been reported to have a lower mortality rate and more rapid transmissibility and caused severe acute respiratory syndrome similarly to SARS.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>The main symptoms are fever, cough, shortness of breath, leukopenia and pneumonia.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Diagnostic laboratory testing of COVID-19 includes hematology testing, nucleic acid testing, viral genome sequencing and serology testing. To date, no specific antiviral drugs or vaccines for COVID-19 have been developed. Therefore, empirical antiviral drugs (lopinavir/ritonavir, favipiravir, oseltamivir, zanamivir and peramivir, arbidol), antibiotic drugs (moxifloxacin, levofloxacin, linezolid), chloroquine/hydroxychloroquine, glucocorticoids, monoclonal anti-inflammatory antibody (tocilizumab), have been used to treat SARS-CoV-2 infection. Traditional Chinese medicines are also used for therapy during infection with SARS-CoV-2.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>This review is presented in the hope of helping the public effectively recognize and combat COVID-19 and to provide a reference for future studies or outbreaks.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</boxed-text>
