<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The authors Brunker 
 <italic>et al.</italic> have described and advocate a rapid in-country sequencing of whole virus genomes to inform rabies elimination programmes using Tanzania, Kenya and the Philippines as sites of testing of this technology. Whereas genomic surveillance is not being used in Africa and Asia and as we know this is due to limited infrastructure, costs, supply chains and other logistical challenges. This may change as the global scientific community has adopted the zero human deaths by 30. This may result is a shift in funding for this elimination programme as regional blocks may support this programme to be in line with global goals for the elimination of rabies. With this surveillance approach, regional members will be able to differentiate rabies variants from other wildlife, distinguish ongoing transmissions from incursions as well as identifying sources of incursions. The authors described sequencing and bioinformatics pipelines and validation process. Protocols for sample-to-sequence and a general purpose for analysis, interpretation and management of rabies virus genome data are available making the approach described here appealing to regional laboratories and members states. The concept of a portable, low-cost sequencer (lab-in-a suitcase is interesting). Overall, the manuscript is well written and I have very few issues that require clarification: 
 <list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
   <p>Para 4 - please explain what is meant by disease can circulate for extended periods at low levels in the context of rabies.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>In many of these countries, there are rabies virus repositories that date to many years back. What would the authors such laboratories in terms of sequencing to inform rabies elimination programmes?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>The samples were collected by field officers, in actual fact a varied number, Kenya=10, Tanzania=24 and the Philippines=52. Do these numbers in any way indicate how good the different countries are in collecting and submitting samples? If so, how can this be improved so that whole genome sequencing of viruses truly reflects the rabies situation in the countries?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>On page 5, the authors indicated that samples were processed in settings with varying infrastructure and resources - samples were confirmed using different methods from RIDT, to dRIT and the FAT. Can the authors shed more light on the antibody preparation used in the dRIT and also the FAT in the Philippines? What was the correlation between the results obtained by these laboratories and the sequencing?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>In the description of the Trizol method on page 5 - 50-100g should read 50-100mg.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Page 7 - please indicate the number of archived and tested samples to give the reader a sense of the sample numbers.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>On page 7, the authors indicated that extracted RNA was reverse transcribed first with the Protoscript II kit and later Lunascript RT Supermix - was the rationale only to use reduced volumes or they were other considerations?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>I think the technology described in this manuscript is useful for the Asia and Africa, particularly as the global community move towards rabies elimination human mediated dog rabies. Some of the outputs have been taken up by Kenya, Tanzania and the Philippines. How do the authors intend to disseminate such important technologies (particularly on minimising cross-contamination in sequencing runs, preparation of sequencing libraries and bioinformatics training) for this purpose to other regions of the two continents (if any)?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>On page 10 - one salivary gland sample (amend).</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Page 11 - Variations in quality of brain tissues was observed and generally influenced sample preparation times - what would the authors advise on sample collection in general to overcome this problem?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>How do the authors plan to overcome the bottlenecks experienced with bioinformatics and data management?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>The authors indicated that prior knowledge about circulating RABV diversity in an area is important - and we know many countries on the African and Asian continents do not have this knowledge. How do the authors hope that member states on these continents can circumvent this issue?</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
