<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>OMVs had been introduced as a part of novel vaccine formulations carrying antigenic proteins eliciting protective responses in animal models from diverse microorganisms such as 
 <italic>N. meningitis</italic> B, 
 <italic>Vibrio cholera</italic>, 
 <italic>Salmonella Typhimurium</italic>, 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, 
 <italic>Gallibacterium anatis</italic>, 
 <italic>Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>, 
 <italic>Chlamydia trachomatis</italic>, 
 <italic>Shigella spp</italic>., and 
 <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B35-vaccines-07-00046" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-vaccines-07-00046" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-vaccines-07-00046" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-vaccines-07-00046" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-vaccines-07-00046" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-vaccines-07-00046" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-vaccines-07-00046" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. LPS in the outer surface of OMVs acts as a self-adjuvant that induces humoral and cellular immunity. Therefore, OMVs vaccines may be used without extra adjuvant to increase the immunogenicity and produce antiviral innate immune responses against various influenza virus infections via activation of macrophages [
 <xref rid="B42-vaccines-07-00046" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-vaccines-07-00046" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-vaccines-07-00046" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Despite that the exact role of LPS in the context of OMVs vaccines requires further investigations, high amounts of LPS could be a drawback due to its known endotoxicity and ability to induce excessive secretions of pro-inflammatory cytokines [
 <xref rid="B45-vaccines-07-00046" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Therefore, several ongoing investigations aim to produce genetically detoxified and less reactogenic LPS to improve OMV safety [
 <xref rid="B42-vaccines-07-00046" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-vaccines-07-00046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-vaccines-07-00046" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Additionally, modified bacterial strains such as ClearColi™ BL21(DE3), which do not trigger LPS-related immune response, can be applied for OMV production [
 <xref rid="B48-vaccines-07-00046" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>].
</p>
