<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Previous studies have focused on ACE2 in host cells and its partner molecule TMPRSS2. Although progress has been made in determining the structures and binding domains and in drug screening, it is unclear whether there are other receptors on the host cell membrane for S protein binding, which reminds us of the challenges of identifying drug targets for SARS‐CoV‐2. Therefore, as a result of in‐depth study, another receptor was discovered recently to be involved in SARS‐CoV‐2 infection. CD147, usually referred to as extracellular MMP inducer (EMMPRIN) or basic immunoglobulin (Basigin), is a transmembrane glycoprotein belonging to the immunoglobulin family, which is closely associated with many disease processes, such as tumour progression, plasmodium invasion, and virus infection (Lu et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>; Nguyen &amp; Kamil, 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0072" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>; Zhang et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0114" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). Previous studies showed that CD147 can promote the entry of SARS‐CoV into host cells, while the CD147‐antagonistic peptide (AP)‐9 has high binding activity to effectively prevent SARS‐CoV infection of HEK293 cells (Chen et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>). Due to the similar genetic sequences, virus structures, and clinical characteristics of SARS‐CoV‐2 and SARS‐CoV, CD147 may be a potential target for the treatment of SARS‐CoV‐2. To test this hypothesis, Wang et al. used SARS‐CoV‐2‐infected Vero E6 cells to detect the localization and binding status of CD147 and S protein during infection and observed that the S protein and CD147 were present mainly in the viral inclusion bodies of Vero E6 cells by immuno‐electron microscopy (Wang, Chen et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0095" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). During the experiment, a surface plasmon resonance (SPR) assay confirmed the interaction between CD147 and the S protein via the receptor binding domain, and the affinity constant was 1.85 × 10
 <sup>−7</sup> M. Moreover, a coimmunoprecipitation (Co‐IP) assay again confirmed the interaction between CD147 and the S protein. These data indicated that SARS‐CoV‐2 may also enter the host cell through binding to the CD147 receptor. However, further research is needed to confirm that CD147 acts as a co‐receptor, a secondary receptor or an equally important new receptor. Additionally, whether the combined treatment is better than alternative treatment needs to be confirmed by additional in vivo and in vitro experiments. Thus, targeting CD147 provides a new therapeutic strategy worth exploring and extending further. Meplazumab, a commonly studied humanized anti‐CD147 antibody for treating malaria, is reported to effectively prevent viruses from entering human host cells through binding to the CD147 receptor by abolishing CD147 activity. An in vitro study showed a good therapeutic effect against the virus in a dose‐dependent manner, with a 50% maximal effect concentration (EC
 <sub>50</sub>) of 24.86 μg·ml
 <sup>−1</sup> and IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 15.16 μg·ml
 <sup>−1</sup>. Meanwhile, a clinical trial has achieved satisfactory effects, indicating that CD147 is indeed a novel potential therapeutic target for treating SARS‐CoV‐2 and that meplazumab should be considered a promising drug after larger experimental research investigation and clinical trial verification (Bian et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Moreover, previous research and the development of original antibody drugs targeting the CD147 receptor, such as metuximab, metuzumab, and meplazumab, all indicate that these drugs show good safety in preclinical research and clinical administration (Chen et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>; Li, Xi et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>; Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0097" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>). Additionally, the tissue distribution specificity of CD147 in tumour tissues, inflamed tissues and pathogen‐infected cells, indicates relatively low cross‐reactivity with normal cells (Kosugi, Maeda, Sato, Maruyama, &amp; Kadomatsu, 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0046" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Su &amp; Yang, 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0088" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). Therefore, the route of viral entry involving CD147 suggests a novel potential target with promising druggability for specific anti‐SARS‐CoV‐2 drug (such as metuximab, metuzumab, and meplazumab) verification and exploration.
</p>
