<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>What we have attempted to do is to show the possible limitations to the dominant humanist approach to the COVID‐19 pandemic. We have asked the questions, ‘what might be contributed to human moral reflection if the human is decentralized; what do we gain in terms of normative leverage points if we move away from anthropocentrism in order to think the dynamism of the whole?’ We have argued that the humanist cosmopolitan approach itself constricts what it is possible for us to think, and thus constricts where it is possible for us to imagine points of intervention. The distinction between and unilateral preference for organisms (viruses, animals, humans), inorganic beings (viruses and technics), and engineered artifacts (technologies) seems inadequate to the realities COVID‐19. When thinking of COVID‐19 as a viral problem, or a problem of viral mutation, or a problem of public health, or as a problem amenable to nation‐state control, or as a legislative problem amenable to cosmopolitanism, or as problem of the failures of technocapitalism, one is limited by the places where normative interventions can find a footing. The reality of viroid life is not solely a question of the N protein, or the S protein, or RNA viral mutation; it is also a question of wet markets, and cultural values, and technocapitalist apparatuses, on which viroid life rides. In fact, this rather simple virus, SARS‐CoV‐2, now rides on a larger evolutionary scale, mediated in part by culture, by law, by technology; and even on the cosmopolitan philosophy held by modern natation states. Its own survival depends, not directly on the metal, or on the machines, but on the shifting boundary points between a variety of systems. We have argued then that by an appeal to non‐humanist (and thus, non‐normative) ways of thinking, we can catch a larger glimpse of the vast multivalency of the problem, and possibly even of novel places for human normativity to gain purchase.</p>
