<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The DNA fragment was obtained by cleavage of the modified plasmid pGEM7(f+) (Promega) carrying oligonucleotide inserts with pseudosymmetric sequences by restrictases NcoI and ApaI (
 <xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">Grokhovsky et al., 1998</xref>). In addition, the DNA fragment contained a segment of OriS DNA with the 5′-CTTCGCCCTAATAATATATATATATTGGGTCGAAGTGCGAACGC-3′ sequence carrying an A + T-rich segment and binding sites I and II for UL9 helicase. Radiolabelling at the 3′-end of this DNA fragment was carried out using [
 <italic>α</italic>-
 <sup>32</sup>P]dATP (Izotop, Moscow), nonlabeled dNTP and the Klenow fragment of 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> DNA polymerase I. The isolation procedure was performed in 5% polyacrylamide gel (
 <xref rid="R62" ref-type="bibr">Sambrook, Fritsch, &amp; Maniatis, 1989</xref>). Footprinting of DNA complexes with bis-netropsins was performed using the previously described procedure (
 <xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">Grokhovsky et al., 1998</xref>). Briefly, 10 µl of the DNA solution (∼10
 <sup>4</sup> Bq) in 10 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5) and .5 M NaCl pH 6.0 were mixed with 10 µl of the ligand solution in H
 <sub>2</sub>O. After cooling to 0°C, 20 µl of the DNase I solution in 10mM Tris-HCl (pH 6.0), .25 M NaCl and 5 mM MnCl
 <sub>2</sub> were added and the mixture was incubated for 3 min at 0°C. The reaction was stopped by adding 85 µl of a solution containing .15M NaCl, 50mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 10mM EDTA and 10 µg/ml tRNA. After phenol extraction and precipitation with ethanol, the DNA was washed with 70% ethanol, dried and dissolved in 1 µl of 95% formamide containing 15mM EDTA, .05% bromphenol blue and .05% xylenecyanol FF. The resulting solution was heated for 1 min at 90 °C, cooled down rapidly and applied onto 6% denaturing polyacrylamide gel (40-cm strips of gradient thickness of .15–.45 mm) (
 <xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">Grokhovsky et al., 1998</xref>). Electrophoresis was carried out for 60 min at 2500 V. Prior to exposure, the gel was fixed in 10% acetic acid and dried on a γ-methacrylpropyloxysilane-treated glass plate (LKB, Sweden).
</p>
