<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Parasit Vectors</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Parasit Vectors</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Parasites &#x00026; Vectors</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1756-3305</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7296759</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">4181</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-020-04181-4</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Age-structured vectorial capacity reveals timing, not magnitude of within-mosquito dynamics is critical for arbovirus fitness assessment</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mayton</surname><given-names>E. Handly</given-names></name><address><email>emayto1@lsu.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tramonte</surname><given-names>A. Ryan</given-names></name><address><email>ryan.tramonte@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wearing</surname><given-names>Helen J.</given-names></name><address><email>hwearing@unm.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2806-1131</contrib-id><name><surname>Christofferson</surname><given-names>Rebecca C.</given-names></name><address><email>rcarri1@lsu.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.64337.35</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0662 7451</institution-id><institution>Department of Pathobiological Sciences, School of Veterinary Medicine, </institution><institution>Louisiana State University, </institution></institution-wrap>Baton Rouge, LA USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.266832.b</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2188 8502</institution-id><institution>Departments of Biology and Mathematics &#x00026; Statistics, </institution><institution>University of New Mexico, </institution></institution-wrap>Albuquerque, NM USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.64337.35</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0662 7451</institution-id><institution>Center for Computation and Technology, </institution><institution>Louisiana State University, </institution></institution-wrap>Baton Rouge, LA USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>15</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>310</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Transmission dynamics of arboviruses like Zika virus are often evaluated by vector competence (the proportion of infectious vectors given exposure) and the extrinsic incubation period (EIP, the time it takes for a vector to become infectious), but vector age is another critical driver of transmission dynamics. Vectorial capacity (VC) is a measure of transmission potential of a vector-pathogen system, but how these three components, EIP, vector competence and vector age, affect VC in concert still needs study.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">The interaction of vector competence, EIP, and mosquito age at the time of infection acquisition (Age<sub>acquisition</sub>) was experimentally measured in an <italic>Aedes aegypti-</italic>ZIKV model system, as well as the age-dependence of probability of survival and the willingness to bite. An age-structured vectorial capacity framework (VC<sub>age</sub>) was then developed using both EIP<sub>Min</sub> and EIP<sub>Max</sub>, defined as the time to first observed minimum proportion of transmitting mosquitoes and the time to observed maximum proportion of transmitting mosquitoes.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">The within-mosquito dynamics of vector competence/EIP were not significant among treatments where mosquitoes were exposed at different ages. However, VC<sub>age</sub> revealed: (i) age-dependence in vector-virus interactions is important for transmission success; (ii) lower vector competence but at shorter EIPs was sufficient for transmission perpetuation; and (iii) R<sub>0</sub> may be overestimated by using non-age-structured VC.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">The results indicate that ultimately the temporal component of the virus-vector dynamics is most critical, especially when exposure occurred at advanced mosquito age. While our study is limited to a single virus-vector system, and a multitude of other factors affect both vector competence and mosquito mortality, our methods can be extrapolated to these other scenarios. Results indicate that how &#x02018;highly&#x02019; or &#x02018;negligibly&#x02019; competent vectors are categorized may need adjustment.<graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="13071_2020_4181_Figa_HTML" id="MO1"/></p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Extrinsic incubation period</kwd><kwd>EIP</kwd><kwd>Vector competence</kwd><kwd><italic>Aedes aegypti</italic></kwd><kwd>Vectorial capacity</kwd><kwd>Zika</kwd><kwd>Arbovirus</kwd><kwd>Mortality</kwd><kwd>Biting rate</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000057</institution-id><institution>National Institute of General Medical Sciences</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>R01GM122077</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Christofferson</surname><given-names>Rebecca C.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par10">The transmission dynamics of arboviruses such as Zika virus (ZIKV) are evaluated over several characteristics, namely vector competence and the extrinsic incubation period (EIP). <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> is the primary vector of ZIKV and several studies have evaluated its competence to transmit the virus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Vector competence is the ability of a mosquito to acquire and ultimately transmit a virus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. The time it takes for this process to occur is referred to as the extrinsic incubation period (EIP) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Vector competence and EIP are interrelated measures of the proportion of vectors that become infectious given exposure and the time it takes for a vector to become infectious given exposure, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Thus, EIP can be described as the temporality of vector competence and has been used to evaluate the relative fitness of arbovirus systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. In addition, EIP and vector competence are influenced by many parameters including vector species, mosquito-immune system, microbiota fauna, discrete populations within species, and environmental factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p><p id="Par11">Indeed, changes in arbovirus fitness and thus transmission dynamics have been predicated on altered vector competence, especially as a critical component of vectorial capacity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The composite of vector competence and EIP into a single, dynamic measure allows for a more comprehensive understanding of this process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Not all mosquitoes that are exposed will be able to transmit (vector competence) and the time it takes for those mosquitoes that will transmit is not a constant (EIP), and so understanding this composite over several days post-infection is critical [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>].</p><p id="Par12">Vectorial capacity (VC) was derived as a measure of transmission potential of a vector-borne pathogen by a competent vector, and incorporates both vector competence and EIP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. VC is the vector-centric component of the basic reproduction number (R<sub>0</sub>), and VC represents the number of secondary cases resulting from the introduction of a single infectious human individual per infectious day of that human index case [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. VC is given by:<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$VC = \frac{{ma^{2} bp^{N} }}{{ - { \ln }\left( p \right)}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13071_2020_4181_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where &#x02018;m&#x02019; is the density of mosquitoes relative to humans, &#x02018;a&#x02019; is the biting rate, &#x02018;b&#x02019; is the vector competence of the mosquito for a particular virus, &#x02018;N&#x02019; is the extrinsic incubation period, and &#x02018;p&#x02019; is the daily probability of mosquito survival [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. And R<sub>0</sub> is given by:<disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$R_{0} = \frac{c}{r}*VC$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13071_2020_4181_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where &#x02018;r&#x02019; is the human recovery rate, or the reciprocal of the average human infectious period, and &#x02018;c&#x02019; is the probability of transmission from the human to the vector given contact. R<sub>0</sub> is a threshold parameter, whereby an R<sub>0</sub> value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1 is not expected to sustain transmission and an R<sub>0</sub> value&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;1 is likely to result in an outbreak [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].</p><p id="Par13">VC uses an average daily probability of survival to calculate the probability of a mosquito living through the EIP (p<sup>N</sup>) and p<sup>N</sup>/(&#x02212;&#x02009;ln(p) represents the expected infectious days given N and p [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. It is intuitive how mortality could impact transmission, but most studies address mortality based on a constant age at which the mosquito acquires the infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Mathematical modeling studies have addressed age structure with respect to EIP or bite-structure, but no studies have empirically investigated all three processes simultaneously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Thus, herein, we experimentally test the hypothesis that transmission dynamics of arboviruses are as or more affected by time as a function of age <italic>versus</italic> time as a function of days post-infection. We further develop an age-structured vectorial capacity equation (VC<sub>age</sub>) to quantify these potential effects.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><p id="Par14">We first wanted to determine if age and/or prior blood meals affected the within-mosquito viral dynamics, as well as various life traits of the mosquito. To that end, we designated three treatment groups: YOUNG, OLDER and S.OLDER. The YOUNG group was offered an infectious blood meal at approximately 5&#x000a0;days post-emergence (dpe). The OLDER group was offered a non-infectious blood meal at 5&#x000a0;dpe and then an infectious blood meal 1&#x000a0;week later (12&#x000a0;dpe). The S.OLDER group was not offered a prior, non-infectious blood meal, but a single infectious blood meal at approximately 12&#x000a0;dpe (to match the OLDER timing). S refers to sugar, which was done in order to distinguish the absence of a blood meal at 5&#x000a0;dpe. All non-infectious blood meals are referred to as &#x0201c;mock&#x0201d; blood meals, as they contain non-infectious cell culture media in place of infectious media.</p><sec id="Sec3"><title>Virus and mosquitoes</title><p id="Par15">ZIKV strain PRVABC59 (Asian lineage), originally isolated from a human patient in Puerto Rico in 2015, was provided by Dr Barbara Johnson at the USA Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (GenBank: KU501215). The viral stock was passaged three times in Vero cells before passage on Vero cells for mosquito exposure. Supernatant was collected 3&#x000a0;days post-inoculation and titer determined as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. The titer of ZIKV was verified by qRT-PCR at approximately 8&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>7</sup> plaque forming units (pfu)/ml, matched across all exposure experiments. Virus used for mosquito exposure was never frozen, as this has been shown to negatively affect vector competence when compared to freshly cultured virus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Colony <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> (Rockefeller) were provided by Dr Daniel Swale of the LSU Entomology Department, Baton Rouge, Louisiana, USA. To isolate the effect(s) of age, mosquitoes were maintained at constant conditions with 16:8&#x000a0;h light:dark periods, approximately 80% humidity (monitored using a digital RH monitor), and at 28&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C constant temperature. Mosquitoes were supplied with a 10% sucrose water solution after emergence <italic>via</italic> soaked cotton pledgets, which were replenished every 24&#x000a0;h. Sucrose solution was removed 24&#x000a0;h before experiments and was again provided after blood feeding/mock starvation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Blood-feeding and oral exposure of <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic></title><p id="Par16">Infectious and non-infectious blood meals were prepared with ZIKV-infected cell culture supernatant and non-infected cell culture supernatant, respectively. Whole bovine blood in Alsever&#x02019;s solution (Hemostat Labs, Dixon, CA, USA) was used in a 2:1 blood to supernatant ratio [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Mosquitoes were fed <italic>via</italic> the Hemotek membrane feeding system (Hemotek, Blackburn, UK) for 45&#x000a0;min, after which mosquitoes were cold anesthetized and blood-fed females were placed into clean cartons until further treatment. Because starvation and cold anesthetization could affect mortality rates, every treatment was subjected to the same schedule of each of these conditions. For example, all groups were starved 24&#x000a0;h prior to days 5 and 12 post-emergence, regardless of whether that group would receive a blood meal. In addition, not only were blood-fed mosquitoes cold anesthetized and moved to a new carton, but other groups that did not feed on that schedule were treated the same in order to mimic these conditions and control for these factors. The experimental design is depicted in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Within-mosquito kinetics</title><p id="Par17">In order to determine if the timing of the infectious blood meal affected the within-mosquito viral kinetics, mosquitoes were sampled at 5, 8 and 11&#x000a0;days post-infection (dpi) to test for infection and dissemination across all groups (sample sizes are provided in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1). Mosquito legs and bodies were placed into separate tubes containing 900&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l BA-1 diluent media and BBs. Samples were then homogenized twice at 25&#x000a0;Hz for 3 min using a Qiagen Tissuelyzer (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany). RNA was extracted (5&#x000d7; MagMax 96 Viral RNA Isolation Kit; Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA) and tested for the presence of viral RNA <italic>via</italic> qRT-PCR (SuperScript III One-Step RT-PCR System; Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) as in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Each treatment was repeated a total of three times and data was averaged over these replicates. Differences among the treatment groups for infection and dissemination rates were tested by a chi-square test for multiple proportions on 5, 8 and 11&#x000a0;dpi.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Transmission assay</title><p id="Par18">To directly assess transmission potential, 20 mosquitoes per treatment were force-salivated. Briefly, ZIKV-exposed mosquitoes were immobilized on ice before removing legs and wings. Mosquitoes were then placed on double-sided tape, and the proboscis of each mosquito was placed into a pipette tip containing 35&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l FBS with 3&#x000a0;mmol/l ATP for 30&#x000a0;min, as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Contents of the pipette tip were ejected into 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l BA-1 diluent and stored at &#x02212;&#x02009;80&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C before testing (see below).</p><p id="Par19">Mosquitoes from the two OLDER groups were sampled at 5, 8 and 11&#x000a0;dpi, as well as 16&#x000a0;dpi to represent the end of the mortality study (28&#x000a0;dpe). In order to characterize the EIP across the mosquito&#x02019;s lifetime, mosquitoes in group YOUNG were sampled at 5, 8 and 11&#x000a0;dpi, as well as additional days post-infection in order to match the age at which the older groups were sampled. Thus, by adding 7 to the time points in the older groups, we additionally sampled the YOUNG group at 12, 15 and 18&#x000a0;dpi, as well as 23&#x000a0;dpi which corresponds to the oldest time point of 28 days old. Samples were tested for the presence of viral RNA in saliva using the techniques described above [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Differences among the treatment groups&#x02019; transmission rates were tested by Chi-square test for multiple proportions at each sampling timepoint.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Mortality study</title><p id="Par20">Mortality studies were performed for the same three treatments (YOUNG, OLDER, and S.OLDER). We added additional mock blood meal controls (that is, accounting for any infectious blood meal-associated alteration of mortality) where a mock blood meal was used in place of infectious blood meals. The three controls were: (i) a mock blood meal at 5&#x000a0;dpe (M.Y) to correspond to the YOUNG treatment; (ii) a mock blood meal at 5&#x000a0;dpe, followed by another mock blood meal at 12&#x000a0;dpe (M.M) to correspond to the OLDER two blood meal treatment; and (iii) a mock blood meal at 12&#x000a0;dpe (S.M) to correspond to the S.OLDER, one blood meal treatment. An additional negative control treatment was performed where the mosquitoes were never blood-fed (S). All treatments were cold anesthetized at 5 and 12&#x000a0;dpe, regardless of whether they were offered a blood meal so that all mosquitoes experienced the same treatment, and mosquito density per carton was kept relatively constant with an average of 47 mosquitoes/carton (range 36&#x02013;58). Each mortality treatment was repeated a total of three times and data are averages of the three replicates.</p><p id="Par21">Cartons were checked daily and, when present, dead mosquitoes were counted and removed up to 28&#x000a0;dpe (approximately 1&#x000a0;month), as this has been shown to be the upper limit of field survival of <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> and is similar to the range used in Tesla et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Only mosquitoes that took all offered blood meals were included in the mortality analyses.</p><p id="Par22">To test for differences in mortality rates among treatments, Kaplan-Meier survival analyses were conducted and the average time to death (TTD) was estimated. Daily mortality estimates relative to age were then predicted using best fits in R (version 3.5.2) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Determining age-structured willingness to probe</title><p id="Par23">One of the most influential parameters for determining transmission dynamics of vector-borne pathogens is the biting rate (because it impacts vector-host transmission in both directions). Biting rate is sometimes parameterized as the reciprocal of the number of days between feeds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. This assumes that the waiting time between bites is exponentially distributed, and we make this assumption for three biting rates: 0.5 (once every two days); 1 (once a day); and 2 (twice a day) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. However, we wanted to determine if the willingness of the mosquito to probe was affected by (i) timing of infectious blood meal and/or (ii) age of the mosquito [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. While mosquito biting is a function of many factors, it has been shown that heat cues are sufficient to initiate host-seeking behaviors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. We use this to determine the willingness or probability of a mosquito probing, which can lead to transmission [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>].</p><p id="Par24">Ten to twelve mosquitoes per each ZIKV-infected treatment (YOUNG, OLDER and S.OLDER) were placed in individual, clear plastic canisters (Bioquip, Rancho Dominquez, CA, USA) 24&#x000a0;h before being provided a blood meal <italic>via</italic> a membrane feeder using 1&#x000a0;ml discs with 800&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l of blood (Hemotek, Blackburn, UK). This was done at the same dpi schedule as the vector competence studies above. Willingness to bite was assessed using a two-tiered approach by a single observer to control for observation bias. First, mosquitoes were observed through the clear canister for their general position in the canister and secondly, the disc was removed to determine if they were on or near the mesh at the top of the canister. In all cases, these two methods of observation matched. That is, if a mosquito was observed to be at the blood meal prior to disc removal (looking through the canister), it did not move to the bottom of the canister upon disc removal.</p><p id="Par25">This observation was performed at 1, 20 and 45&#x000a0;min post-placement of the disc and the disc was replaced between observation time points. Thus, a mosquito was assessed as &#x0201c;landed&#x0201d; and recorded as &#x0201c;1&#x0201d; if the female was at the top of the canister at any of the observation times. The female was otherwise classified as &#x0201c;not landed&#x0201d; and coded as &#x0201c;0&#x0201d; if she was at the bottom of the canister for all three observation times. We then calculated the probability of biting (Z) as a function of age. Z(age) was determined by fitting the proportion of mosquitoes that landed or fed at least once a day using a self-starting non-linear least squares regression:<disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$Z\left( {age} \right) = s + \left( {g - s} \right){ \exp }( - \exp \left( h \right)*\left( { - age} \right))$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">age</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>exp</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mo>exp</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13071_2020_4181_Article_Equ3.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where &#x02018;s&#x02019; is the asymptote, &#x02018;g&#x02019; is the zero-response parameter, and &#x02018;h&#x02019; is the logarithmic rate constant. Comparison of probing differences among treatments was assessed both per day post-infection as well as per mosquito age by Kruskal-Wallis test.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Age-structured vectorial capacity and R<sub>0</sub></title><p id="Par26">We re-formulated the vectorial capacity equation to estimate VC as a function of the age at which the mosquito acquires an infectious blood meal, redefining the parameters with respect to age at the time of acquisition of infection. We define Age<sub>acquisition</sub> as the age at which a mosquito acquires an infection (the day of taking the infectious blood meal) and Age<sub>transmission</sub> as the age at which the mosquito subsequently transmits (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>):<disp-formula id="Equ4"><label>4</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$Age_{transmission} = Age_{acquisition} + EIP$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">transmission</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">acquisition</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13071_2020_4181_Article_Equ4.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Vector age at time of infection acquisition determines transmission opportunity. Uninfected mosquitoes (black, left) acquire an infection at Age<sub>acquisition</sub> (black vertical lines) and after a certain EIP (black dashed lines), a proportion will become infectious (red, right), but for a certain period of time (red horizontal lines) that is dependent on Age<sub>acquisition</sub></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13071_2020_4181_Fig1_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p><p id="Par27">In VC<sub>age</sub>, &#x02018;m&#x02019; is still the mosquito-to-human density and, for illustrative purposes, held constant here at 1. The parameters z<sub>acquisition</sub> and z<sub>transmission</sub> are the probability of a mosquito biting at age of acquisition and age at time of transmission, respectively. The traditional calculation of p<sup>N</sup> represents the probability of a mosquito living through a fixed number of days N, the EIP, and p<sup>N</sup>/(&#x02212;&#x02009;ln(p)) represents the expected infectious days given N and p [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. In the context of an age-dependent vectorial capacity framework, we can calculate a more precise probability of surviving based on the day the mosquito obtained an infection and the cumulative survival probability to Age<sub>transmission</sub> where the cumulative probability of living through the EIP given Age<sub>acquisition</sub> is given by:<disp-formula id="Equ5"><label>5</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$p\left( {surviving \, to \, Age_{transmission} } \right) = \mathop \prod \limits_{j = 1}^{{Age_{transmission} }} p_{j}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">transmission</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">&#x0220f;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">transmission</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13071_2020_4181_Article_Equ5.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where &#x02018;p<sub>j</sub>&#x02019; is the probability of daily survival on day <italic>j</italic> post emergence. We further estimate the infectious period (L) in an age-structured way by numerically deriving L:<disp-formula id="Equ6"><label>6</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$L = TTD - Age_{transmission}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M12" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">transmission</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13071_2020_4181_Article_Equ6.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where TTD is the average time-to-death derived from the experimental mortality study.</p><p id="Par28">Using the data from our experimental studies, we calculated Age<sub>transmission</sub> for two scenarios: EIP<sub>min</sub> and EIP<sub>max</sub> from our observed transmission data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>], and calculated VC<sub>age</sub> as:<disp-formula id="Equ7"><label>7</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$VC_{age} = mb\left( {z_{acquisition} a} \right)\left( {z_{transmission} a} \right)\left( {\mathop \prod \limits_{j = 1}^{{age_{transmission} }} p_{j} } \right)L$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M14" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">age</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">acquisition</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">transmission</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mo movablelimits="false">&#x0220f;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">transmission</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13071_2020_4181_Article_Equ7.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par29">VC is a component of R<sub>0</sub>, which also includes the average infectious period of the human and the probability of transmission from the human to the vector. For illustrative purposes, we calculated R<sub>0</sub> using both the traditional calculation of VC (Eq.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="">1</xref>), as well as VC<sub>age</sub>. We made the following assumptions: mosquito density is held constant at m&#x02009;=&#x02009;1; the average infectious period of the human is 5&#x000a0;days (r<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]; and the average probability of transmission from human to vector is parameterized experimentally as the average proportion of mosquitoes that develop a midgut infection given exposure (c). From these data, we can calculate the value of VC needed to push R<sub>0</sub> above this threshold. We use this value as a &#x0201c;threshold&#x0201d; to compare VC<sub>age</sub> across treatment groups and with the traditional VC measures.</p><p id="Par30">All statistics and subsequent graphics were performed and generated using R version 3.5.2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. All packages used are provided in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Text S1. All functions and function parameters used to fit the data and obtain age-dependent distributions of these parameters are given in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S2. Goodness-of-fit was assessed either through AIC (for non-linear models) or <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> for linear models.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Within-mosquito dynamics are more affected by time as a function of age <italic>versus</italic> days post-infection</title><p id="Par31">We first wanted to determine if the age at which a mosquito is offered an infectious blood meal and acquires the ZIKV infection (Age<sub>acquisition</sub>) impacted the within-vector kinetics of the mosquito. To do this, we looked at infection, dissemination, and transmission of the three treatments in the context of days post-infection. We found no significant difference in the infection (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05) or dissemination rates (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05) across all treatments (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1). However, when direct age comparisons are made, the effect of Age<sub>acquisition</sub> on infection becomes obvious (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The average rate of infection of mosquitoes given exposure was 78.2% across all treatments and days post-infection (95% confidence interval: 74.3&#x02013;82.0%).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Infection and dissemination rates in the context of mosquito age. Despite no significant effect of treatment on infection and dissemination rates when assessed over days post-infection, Age<sub>acquisition</sub> has an obvious impact on the timing of these processes</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13071_2020_4181_Fig2_HTML" id="MO10"/></fig></p><p id="Par32">When we evaluated the proportion transmitting in terms of days post-exposure (5, 8 and 11 only) none of the treatments were transmitting on days 5 or 8&#x000a0;dpi. On day 11, the transmission rates were 5%, 10% and 15% in groups OLDER, S.OLDER and YOUNG, respectively. These differences were not statistically significant using the Chi-square test for proportions (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.5) (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1).</p><p id="Par33">However, when we investigated mosquitoes from group YOUNG at time points that age-matched OLDER and S.OLDER treatments (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), the YOUNG group achieved a maximum transmission of 45% at 28&#x000a0;days old (23&#x000a0;dpi) <italic>versus</italic> only 15% for the S.OLDER group and 10% for the OLDER group at 28 days old (16&#x000a0;dpi).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Transmission rates for each day post-infection (dpi) and corresponding mosquito age for each of the three treatment groups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Treatment</th><th align="left">dpi (day post-infection)</th><th align="left">Age (day post-emergence)</th><th align="left">% Transmission (<italic>n&#x02009;</italic>=20)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="7">YOUNG</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">10</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">13</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">15</td></tr><tr><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">17</td><td align="left">15</td></tr><tr><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left">18</td><td align="left">23</td><td align="left">35</td></tr><tr><td align="left">23</td><td align="left">28</td><td align="left">45</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4">OLDER</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">17</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">23</td><td align="left">5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">28</td><td align="left">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4">S.OLDER</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">17</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">23</td><td align="left">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">28</td><td align="left">15</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par34">We define the EIP<sub>max</sub> as the earliest EIP (days post-infection) where the maximum proportion of mosquitoes are transmitting, and we define the EIP<sub>min</sub> as the earliest EIP where the proportion of mosquitoes transmitting is minimal, but greater than 0. EIP values at different vector competence levels have been used to evaluate the vectorial capacity for malaria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. For the YOUNG group, EIP<sub>max</sub> was 23 dpi at 45%, and EIP<sub>min</sub> was 11&#x000a0;dpi at 15%. For the OLDER group, EIP<sub>max</sub> was 16&#x000a0;dpi at 10% and EIP<sub>min</sub> was 11&#x000a0;dpi at 5%. For the S.OLDER group, EIP<sub>max</sub> was 16&#x000a0;dpi at 15% and the EIP<sub>min</sub> was 11&#x000a0;dpi at 10%.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Mortality of <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> is modestly affected by timing of infectious blood meal</title><p id="Par35">When each infectious treatment was compared to a matching non-infectious control group, the only significant difference in average time to death (TTD) was between the S.OLDER and S.M treatments, with an estimated difference in TTD of two days (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S3). Of interest, the non-blood-fed sugar-only controls died significantly faster than any of the blood-fed treatments with an average TTD of 19.6&#x000a0;days (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S3), which has been previously shown [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>].</p><p id="Par36">Pairwise comparisons of the ZIKV-exposed treatments determined that group YOUNG had a significantly longer average time to death (TTD) when compared to groups OLDER and S.OLDER, though this difference was modest (0.6 and 1.4&#x000a0;days, respectively) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The TTD for the YOUNG group was 25.9&#x000a0;days, 25.3 days for the OLDER group, and 24.5&#x000a0;days for the S.OLDER group. This corresponds to average daily survival probabilities of 0.962, 0.961 and 0.960 for the YOUNG, OLDER and S.OLDER groups, respectively. Predicted daily survival rates were generated for the YOUNG group using a non-linear fit and a linear model was fit to the OLDER and S.OLDER groups. The parameters of these models and goodness-of-fit assessments are given in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S2, and the observed and predicted values are shown in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S2 for all three treatment groups. Additional comparisons were made among the treatment and control groups, detailed in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Text S2, Figure S3 and Table S3.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Survival curves of female <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> by treatment. Each line represents the combined data from three replicates per treatment: YOUNG (gold line), OLDER (green line), and sugar-OLDER (S.OLDER, red line). Average time to death of treatment, YOUNG was significantly, but modestly, longer than treatments OLDER and S.OLDER</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13071_2020_4181_Fig3_HTML" id="MO11"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Age-dependence of willingness to probe</title><p id="Par37">There was no significant difference in the willingness to probe based on treatment (YOUNG, OLDER and S.OLDER) at each day post-infection <italic>via</italic> the Kruskal-Wallis test, but there was a significant effect of age (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). We then were able to fit a daily probability of probing based on age (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Observed and predicted probabilities of daily biting. The observed daily biting frequencies (dots) from the laboratory experiments and the fitted daily predictions (green curve)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13071_2020_4181_Fig4_HTML" id="MO12"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>VC<sub>age</sub> framework for assessing transmission as a function of age and effect on R<sub>0</sub></title><p id="Par38">To calculate VC<sub>age</sub>, we used treatment-group specific average TTD and predicted daily probabilities of survival (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S4) and the overall daily prediction of willingness to bite in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>. Since biting rate (the number of bites per day) is a field-derived parameter, we calculated VC<sub>age</sub> over three biting rates: 0.5 (once every 2 days), 1 (once a day), and 2 (twice a day) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. For comparison, we calculated the traditional VC using the average life-dependent traits determined experimentally above, EIP<sub>min</sub> and EIP<sub>max</sub>, and the biting rates referenced above. These VC values are given in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, along with corresponding values for R<sub>0</sub>. In the absence of published data regarding the probability of human to mosquito ZIKV transmission success, we used the average infection rate from our experimental data (78.2%) to parameterize human to mosquito transmission, recognizing that this model system used a high dose of ZIKV titer, although such titers in individuals are not unheard of [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>].<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Traditional VC calculations for EIP<sub>min</sub> and EIP<sub>max</sub> for each treatment group (calculated according to Eq.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="">1</xref>) and corresponding R<sub>0</sub> (according to Eq.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="">2</xref>)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Treatment</th><th align="left">EIP</th><th align="left">Biting rate</th><th align="left">VC</th><th align="left">R<sub>0</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6">YOUNG</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">EIP<sub>max</sub></td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">19.06</td><td align="left">74.52</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">4.77</td><td align="left">18.65</td></tr><tr><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">1.19</td><td align="left">4.65</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">EIP<sub>min</sub></td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">10.11</td><td align="left">39.53</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">2.53</td><td align="left">9.89</td></tr><tr><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">0.632</td><td align="left">2.47</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6">OLDER</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">EIP<sub>max</sub></td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">4.03</td><td align="left">15.76</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1.01</td><td align="left">3.95</td></tr><tr><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">0.978</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">EIP<sub>min</sub></td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">6.49</td><td align="left">26.98</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1.62</td><td align="left">6.33</td></tr><tr><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">0.41</td><td align="left">1.60</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6">S.OLDER</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">EIP<sub>max</sub></td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">7.65</td><td align="left">29.91</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1.91</td><td align="left">7.47</td></tr><tr><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">0.48</td><td align="left">1.88</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">EIP<sub>min</sub></td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">6.25</td><td align="left">24.44</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1.56</td><td align="left">6.10</td></tr><tr><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">0.39</td><td align="left">1.52</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>YOUNG group</title><p id="Par39">To achieve an R<sub>0</sub> of 1, the vectorial capacity needed to be at or above 0.256. When parameterized with EIP<sub>max</sub>, the VC<sub>age</sub> at a biting rate of 0.5 (once every 2 days) did not achieve this minimal value, but at biting rates of once or twice per day, VC<sub>age</sub> was sufficient to push R<sub>0</sub> over the threshold of one (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). We next determined the window of opportunity, which encompasses the days post-emergence when a mosquito acquires an infection and which results in VC<sub>age</sub> values where R<sub>0</sub> would be greater than one. The window of opportunity when we parameterized VC<sub>age</sub> with EIP<sub>max</sub> indicated that a virus must be acquired within the first 2&#x000a0;days post-emergence when the bite rate was twice or once per day (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Interestingly, when parameterized with EIP<sub>min</sub>, all bite rates reached sufficient VC<sub>age</sub> values. The window of opportunity was 14 days post-emergence for a bite rate of twice a day, 12&#x000a0;days post-emergence for a bite rate of once a day, and 7&#x000a0;days post-emergence for a bite rate of once every 2&#x000a0;days (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Even at its highest, VC<sub>age</sub> indicates that traditional VC calculations are likely overestimates.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Vectorial capacity calculations using VC<sub>age</sub>. VC<sub>age</sub> values (y-axis) depend on the age at acquisition (x-axis). Each curve calculated based on pre-determined bite rates of 2 (yellow line), 1 (blue line), and 0.5 (black line) for (left) EIP<sub>max</sub> of the YOUNG group,&#x02009;=&#x02009;45% at 23&#x000a0;dpi, and (right) EIP<sub>min</sub> of the YOUNG group&#x02009;=&#x02009;15% at 11&#x000a0;dpi. The dotted line represents the lower limit of VC where below this threshold, R<sub>0</sub> is less than 1</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13071_2020_4181_Fig5_HTML" id="MO13"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>OLDER and S.OLDER groups</title><p id="Par40">For both the OLDER and S.OLDER groups, the infectious blood meal occurred at 12&#x000a0;days post-emergence, which was outside the window of opportunity for VC<sub>age</sub> in all but one scenario (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S4). Only at a bite rate of twice daily did the OLDER group achieve the minimum VC<sub>age</sub> of 0.256 on or after Age<sub>acquisition</sub> of 12 days-old, and only when parameterized with the EIP<sub>min</sub>. The window of opportunity for this scenario was days 12&#x02013;13 post-emergence.</p><p id="Par41">With these vector age-dependent traits, both EIP and vector competence would need to be altered significantly to achieve a VC<sub>age</sub>&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;0.256 at 12&#x000a0;days post-emergence for other scenarios. For example, we consider a hypothetical EIP<sub>max</sub> of EIP<sub>50</sub> (the time it takes for 50% of exposed mosquitoes to transmit) and a hypothetical EIP<sub>min</sub> of EIP<sub>10</sub> to demonstrate how these group-specific mortality rates and the age structure of willingness to bite interact to drive vectorial capacity above the threshold in the context of Age<sub>acquisition</sub> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. The S.OLDER group would need a maximum EIP<sub>50</sub> of 12&#x000a0;dpi or 11&#x000a0;dpi for biting rates of twice and once daily, respectively, and 8&#x000a0;dpi for a biting rate of once every 2&#x000a0;days. For the OLDER group, the maximum EIP<sub>50</sub> would need to be 13, 12, or 11&#x000a0;dpi for biting rates of twice or once daily, or once every 2&#x000a0;days, respectively. With the EIP<sub>min</sub>, similar maximum EIPs were noted of 12 and 9&#x000a0;dpi for biting rates of twice or once daily, respectively. For both the OLDER and S.OLDER groups, with a hypothetical EIP<sub>min</sub> of 10%, VC<sub>age</sub> never got above the threshold needed to get R<sub>0</sub> at or above 1.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par42">Prediction of vector-borne disease spread remains difficult, as transmission of vector-borne disease is a dynamic, multifaceted system. This includes life traits of the mosquito, environmental factors, and vector-virus interactions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. Here we demonstrate through a combination of experimental and computational methods that mosquito age at the time of pathogen acquisition is a powerful driver of transmission potential due, in large part, to the age-dependence of daily mortality and biting habits. Further, these drivers lead to differences in the estimates of R<sub>0</sub>.</p><p id="Par43">Our study, which focused upon the age at the time of infectious blood meal, showed no significant impacts on the vector competence of colony <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> for ZIKV. While a recent study did show there were significant effects of multiple blood meals on vector competence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>], we delivered the second blood meal at a much longer interval (7&#x000a0;days <italic>versus</italic> 3&#x000a0;dpi in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]), which likely plays a role in this disparate finding and indicates that there may be age-dependence in this phenomenon as well. However, this hypothesis is outside the scope of the present study. In our mortality study, we did observe a modest difference in TTD. We also observed a very short TTD in mosquitoes only given sugar with no blood meal. We chose not to pursue these effects, as the differences in TTD were modest and the impacts of no blood meal have been previously observed.</p><p id="Par44">The technology for determining the age structure of natural mosquito populations in the field is currently still in development. For example, a study using near-infrared spectroscopy was able to predict the age of female <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> &#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x000a0;days, indicating that determining the age structure of a mosquito population is possible, and that such technology could be refined for field studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. Further, mid-infrared spectroscopy had varying, but some promising results in determining the age structure of <italic>Anopheles</italic> mosquitoes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. As these technologies are pursued and refined, there will be a need for ways to understand and quantify age-dependent interactions among vector competence, EIP, mosquito lifespan, and biting behavior [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>].</p><p id="Par45">The methodologies in this study highlight the need to understand the quantitative interaction between vector competence, mosquito mortality, and age at time of infection acquisition. Thus, we anticipate that this methodology could be used to explore other important modifiers of vector competence and mosquito mortality and the interaction of the two, such as innate mosquito immunity response to infection, adult and larval microbiome, as well as other extrinsic factors known to affect these traits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Several recent studies have focused on environmental factors such as temperature, and found that temperature not only affects vector competence of many arboviruses, especially in <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>, but also several life traits of the mosquito [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. This means that transmission is ultimately impacted by the interactions of all of these temporally dependent processes, and future studies should consider the age structure when assessing these impacts. Studies have also shown the impact of vector species, in particular the difference between field-derived and laboratory strains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Here, we used a laboratory strain of <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic>, which has been shown to vary in its competence when compared to a field-derived strain. Future use of VC<sub>age</sub> could highlight these differences, as well as differences among various arbovirus-arthropod systems.</p><p id="Par46">Our results demonstrate the importance of age structure when evaluating the fitness of a mosquito-virus system and indicate that R<sub>0</sub> may be overestimated when it is not considered. This framework further shows that how within-mosquito arbovirus fitness is measured, often by comparing proportions of transmitting mosquitoes at arbitrary time points, is not sufficient. Here, when the Age<sub>acquisition</sub> was advanced, the difference in hypothetical EIPs necessary for the system to succeed was not very different. For example, in the OLDER and S.OLDER groups, there was only one day difference between the EIP<sub>min</sub> and EIP<sub>max</sub> needed for success at biting rates of 2 and 1, though these quantities represented a difference of 40% in the proportion of mosquitoes transmitting. The same trend was demonstrated in the YOUNG group where EIP<sub>min</sub> resulted in longer windows of opportunity compared to EIP<sub>max</sub>. Additionally, when the minimum time to transmission is shorter, a larger portion of the mosquito population contributes to transmission, because VC<sub>age</sub> implicates older mosquitoes in this scenario given no significant reduction in mortality due to extrinsic factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. Thus, VC<sub>age</sub> reveals that the temporality of the within-mosquito arbovirus dynamics is more impactful than the ultimate magnitude of this widely used fitness measure. More investigations into the earlier and minimal transmission rates, such as at earlier time points that we did not consider, may be warranted to quantify fully the contribution of lower but faster dissemination profiles in arbovirus systems.</p><p id="Par47">A study by Althouse et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>] also found that the temporality of transmission from non-human primates was sometimes more impactful than the magnitude of the viremia leading to transmission to the mosquito. They proposed a &#x0201c;tortoise-and-the-hare&#x0201d; (TatH) model to describe this relationship between arboviral viremia profiles in non-human primates and the predicted transmission success to vectors, showing that the strategy of &#x0201c;slow and steady&#x0201d; viremia, i.e. lower levels for longer periods, resulted in higher predicted transmission success of arboviruses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. This same TatH model recently described macro-transmission dynamics in Colombia, where it was demonstrated that slow burn-in epidemics actually resulted in cumulatively more cases and higher R<sub>0</sub> values than in initially explosive outbreaks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. Vector competence is a continuous process over time, and as such, EIP<sub>min</sub> and EIP<sub>max</sub> are not independent measures. Thus, vector competence profiles with higher transmission rates at earlier times (&#x0201c;hare strategy&#x0201d;) will always be more fit than lower proportions at the same EIP. However, this study demonstrates that in systems where the maximum measured vector competence is low, but the time to minimum transmission is short (&#x0201c;tortoise strategy&#x0201d;) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>], there is still a good chance the system will succeed. VC<sub>age</sub> also suggests that how arbovirus phenotypes are compared and ranked, and perhaps even how the field identifies &#x02018;highly&#x02019; or &#x02018;negligibly&#x02019; competent vectors, may need adjustment in the context of mosquito age.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par48">We demonstrate that mosquito age may not affect experimentally determined infection, dissemination, or transmission rates when assessed in the traditional days post-infection manner. However, when we consider mosquito mortality, EIP, and vector competence in the context of a more holistic measure of transmission potential, vectorial capacity, and further adjust VC for the effect of age at the time of mosquito infection, we demonstrate that age can be an important factor, and that how some arbovirus fitness measures are assessed may need reconsideration.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec19"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="13071_2020_4181_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 1: Figure S1.</bold> Illustration of main treatment design for vector competence experimentation. <bold>Table S1.</bold> Infection and dissemination rates for each day post-infection (dpi) and corresponding mosquito age for each of the three ZIKV treatments. <bold>Table S2.</bold> Modeled fits of parameters, the type of model, and the parameter values. <bold>Figure S2.</bold> Observed and predicted daily probabilities of survival for the three treatment groups. <bold>Text S1.</bold> R packages used in the study. <bold>Text S2.</bold> Comparison of mortality of <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> with respect to bloodmeals. <bold>Figure S3.</bold> Mortality curves for all treatments and associated controls. <bold>Table S3.</bold> Mean time to death and sample size for ZIKV-infection treatments and unexposed controls used in the mortality study. <bold>Figure S4.</bold> Demonstration of the VC<sub>age</sub> for the two treatments exposed at older ages.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>EIP</term><def><p id="Par5">extrinsic incubation period</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ZIKV</term><def><p id="Par6">Zika virus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VC</term><def><p id="Par7">vectorial capacity</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>dpe</term><def><p id="Par8">days post-emergence</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>dpi</term><def><p id="Par9">days post-infection</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1186/s13071-020-04181-4.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to thank Dr. Barbara Johnson for providing our viral strain, as well as Dr. Daniel Swale for providing us with mosquito eggs. We would like to thank all our laboratory colleagues for putting up with the hogging of freezer space to hold all of the samples generated for this study. And last but not least, we&#x02019;d like to thank Aesop for his apparently ubiquitously applicable fable.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>EHM and RCC conceived and designed the study. EHM, ART and RCC performed the experiments. EHM, HJW and RCC carried out data analysis and interpretation. EHM, HJW and RCC wrote the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This study was funded through NIH/NIGMS R01GM122077.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>All data generated or analyzed during this study are included in this published article and its additional file.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par49">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par50">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par51">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costa-da-Silva</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ioshino</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Araujo</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kojin</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Zanotto</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Laboratory strains of <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> are competent to Brazilian Zika virus</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>e0171951</fpage><?supplied-pmid 28187183?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28187183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roundy</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Azar</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Leal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Variation in <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> mosquito competence for Zika virus transmission</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><year>2017</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>625</fpage><lpage>632</lpage><?supplied-pmid 28287375?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28287375</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chouin-Carneiro</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Vega-Rua</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vazeille</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yebakima</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Girod</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Goindin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Differential susceptibilities of <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> from the Americas to Zika virus</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e0004543</fpage><?supplied-pmid 26938868?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26938868</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Musso</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gubler</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zika virus</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source><year>2016</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>524</lpage><?supplied-pmid 27029595?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27029595</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valderrama</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez-Verges</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interaction of Flavivirus with their mosquito vectors and their impact on the human health in the Americas</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2017</year><volume>492</volume><fpage>541</fpage><lpage>547</lpage><?supplied-pmid 28499872?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28499872</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciota</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dissecting vectorial capacity for mosquito-borne viruses</article-title><source>Curr Opin Virol</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>112</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><?supplied-pmid 26569343?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26569343</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christofferson</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mores</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Wearing</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bridging the gap between experimental data and model parameterization for chikungunya virus transmission predictions</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>214</volume><issue>Suppl. 5</issue><fpage>S466</fpage><lpage>S470</lpage><?supplied-pmid 27920175?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27920175</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohm</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Barreaux</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefevre</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rethinking the extrinsic incubation period of malaria parasites</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors</source><year>2018</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>178</fpage><?supplied-pmid 29530073?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29530073</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bellan</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The importance of age dependent mortality and the extrinsic incubation period in models of mosquito-borne disease transmission and control</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e10165</fpage><?supplied-pmid 20405010?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20405010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maciel-de-Freitas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Koella</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lourenco-de-Oliveira</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lower survival rate, longevity and fecundity of <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> (Diptera: Culicidae) females orally challenged with dengue virus serotype 2</article-title><source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg</source><year>2011</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>452</fpage><lpage>458</lpage><?supplied-pmid 21700303?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21700303</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Godfray</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatem</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gething</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Vectorial capacity and vector control: reconsidering sensitivity to parameters for malaria elimination</article-title><source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg</source><year>2016</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>117</lpage><?supplied-pmid 26822603?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26822603</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Christofferson</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasquez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mores</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Wearing</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling mosquito-borne disease spread in U.S. urbanized areas: the case of dengue in Miami</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>e0161365</fpage><?supplied-pmid 27532496?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27532496</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goindin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Delannay</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramdini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustave</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fouque</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parity and longevity of <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> according to temperatures in controlled conditions and consequences on dengue transmission risks</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e0135489</fpage><?supplied-pmid 26258684?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26258684</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Houk</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Reeves</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intrinsic factors affecting vector competence of mosquitoes for arboviruses</article-title><source>Annu Rev Entomol</source><year>1983</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>262</lpage><?supplied-pmid 6131642?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6131642</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Souza-Neto</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonizzoni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> vector competence studies: a review</article-title><source>Infect Genet Evol</source><year>2019</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><?supplied-pmid 30465912?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30465912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lounibos</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Invasiveness of <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> and vectorial capacity for chikungunya virus</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>214</volume><issue>Suppl. 5</issue><fpage>S453</fpage><lpage>S458</lpage><?supplied-pmid 27920173?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27920173</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Macdonald</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><source>The epidemiology and control of malaria</source><year>1957</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garrett-Jones</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prognosis for interruption of malaria transmission through assessment of the mosquito&#x02019;s cectorial capacity</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1964</year><volume>204</volume><fpage>1173</fpage><lpage>1175</lpage><?supplied-pmid 14268587?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14268587</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bagny</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Delatte</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Quilici</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fontenille</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Progressive decrease in <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> distribution in Reunion Island since the 1900s</article-title><source>J Med Entomol</source><year>2009</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>1541</fpage><lpage>1545</lpage><?supplied-pmid 19960710?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19960710</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsetsarkin</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanlandingham</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>McGee</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A single mutation in chikungunya virus affects vector specificity and epidemic potential</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2007</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>e201</fpage><?supplied-pmid 18069894?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18069894</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vazeille</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Moutailler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Coudrier</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rousseaux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Khun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huerre</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Two chikungunya isolates from the outbreak of La Reunion (Indian Ocean) exhibit different patterns of infection in the mosquito, <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic></article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2007</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>e1168</fpage><?supplied-pmid 18000540?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18000540</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kilpatrick</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Meola</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Moudy</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Temperature, viral genetics, and the transmission of West Nile virus by <italic>Culex pipiens</italic> mosquitoes</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2008</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>e1000092</fpage><?supplied-pmid 18584026?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18584026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ciota</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vector-virus interactions and transmission dynamics of West Nile virus</article-title><source>Viruses</source><year>2013</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>3021</fpage><lpage>3047</lpage><?supplied-pmid 24351794?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24351794</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moudy</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Meola</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Morin</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebel</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A newly emergent genotype of West Nile virus is transmitted earlier and more efficiently by <italic>Culex</italic> mosquitoes</article-title><source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source><year>2007</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>370</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17690414?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17690414</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dye</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The analysis of parasite transmission by bloodsucking insects</article-title><source>Annu Rev Entomol</source><year>1992</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><?supplied-pmid 1539935?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1539935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruckert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebel</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How do virus-mosquito interactions lead to viral emergence?</article-title><source>Trends Parasitol</source><year>2018</year><volume>34</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>310</fpage><lpage>321</lpage><?supplied-pmid 29305089?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29305089</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Silveira</surname><given-names>IDD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatila-Ferreira</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chouin-Carneiro</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Van den Wouwer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The impact of the age of first blood meal and Zika virus infection on <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> egg production and longevity</article-title><source>PLoS One.</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>e0200766</fpage><?supplied-pmid 30048481?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30048481</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christofferson</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mores</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating the magnitude and direction of altered arbovirus transmission due to viral phenotype</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e16298</fpage><?supplied-pmid 21298018?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21298018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Statics and dynamics of malaria infection in <italic>Anopheles</italic> mosquitoes</article-title><source>Malar J</source><year>2004</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>13</fpage><?supplied-pmid 15180900?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15180900</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Massad</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vectorial capacity, basic reproduction number, force of infection and all that: formal notation to complete and adjust their classical concepts and equations</article-title><source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source><year>2012</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>564</fpage><lpage>567</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22666873?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22666873</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dye</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vectorial capacity: must we measure all its components?</article-title><source>Parasitol Today</source><year>1986</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15462840?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15462840</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Battle</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ross, macdonald, and a theory for the dynamics and control of mosquito-transmitted pathogens</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e1002588</fpage><?supplied-pmid 22496640?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22496640</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garrett-Jones</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Shidrawi</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Malaria vectorial capacity of a population of <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic>: an exercise in epidemiological entomology</article-title><source>Bull World Health Organ</source><year>1969</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>545</lpage><?supplied-pmid 5306719?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5306719</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Styer</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mosquitoes do senesce: departure from the paradigm of constant mortality</article-title><source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source><year>2007</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>117</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17255238?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17255238</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Novoseltsev</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name><name><surname>Michalski</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Novoseltseva</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yashin</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An age-structured extension to the vectorial capacity model</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e39479</fpage><?supplied-pmid 22724022?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22724022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rock</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Age- and bite-structured models for vector-borne diseases</article-title><source>Epidemics</source><year>2015</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><?supplied-pmid 26342239?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26342239</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawiecki</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayton</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Dutuze</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Goupil</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Langohr</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Piero</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tissue tropisms, infection kinetics, histologic lesions, and antibody response of the MR766 strain of Zika virus in a murine model</article-title><source>Virol J</source><year>2017</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>82</fpage><?supplied-pmid 28420392?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28420392</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ciota</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bialosuknia</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zink</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Brecher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrbar</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrissette</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of Zika virus strain and <italic>Aedes</italic> mosquito species on vector competence</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><year>2017</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1110</fpage><lpage>1117</lpage><?supplied-pmid 28430564?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28430564</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pesko</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Alto</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Mores</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reduced infection in mosquitoes exposed to blood meals containing previously frozen flaviviruses</article-title><source>Virus Res.</source><year>2007</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>227</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17686541?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17686541</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tramonte</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Christofferson</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigating the probability of establishment of Zika virus and detection through mosquito surveillance under different temperature conditions</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2019</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>e0214306</fpage><?supplied-pmid 30921386?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30921386</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tesla</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Demakovsky</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mordecai</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonds</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngonghala</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Temperature drives Zika virus transmission: evidence from empirical and mathematical models</article-title><source>Proc Biol Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>285</volume><fpage>20180795</fpage><?supplied-pmid 30111605?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30111605</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">R Development Core Team. R: a language and environment for statistical computing. Vienna: R Foundation for Statistical Computing; 2018. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.R-project.org/">https://www.R-project.org/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paaijmans</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Cator</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Temperature-dependent pre-bloodmeal period and temperature-driven asynchrony between parasite development and mosquito biting rate reduce malaria transmission intensity</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e55777</fpage><?supplied-pmid 23383280?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23383280</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christofferson</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mores</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Wearing</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterizing the likelihood of dengue emergence and detection in naive populations</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors</source><year>2014</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>282</fpage><?supplied-pmid 24957139?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24957139</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zermoglio</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Robuchon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonardi</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandre</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazzari</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What does heat tell a mosquito? Characterization of the orientation behaviour of <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> towards heat sources</article-title><source>J Insect Physiol</source><year>2017</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><?supplied-pmid 28479122?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28479122</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Styer</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Albright</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mosquitoes inoculate high doses of West Nile virus as they probe and feed on live hosts</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2007</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1262</fpage><lpage>1270</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17941708?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17941708</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A rodent malaria, <italic>Plasmodium berghei</italic>, is experimentally transmitted to mice by merely probing of infective mosquito, <italic>Anopheles stephensi</italic></article-title><source>Parasitol Int</source><year>2002</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11880224?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11880224</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dubrulle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mousson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Moutailler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vazeille</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Failloux</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chikungunya virus and <italic>Aedes</italic> mosquitoes: saliva is infectious as soon as two days after oral infection</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>e5895</fpage><?supplied-pmid 19521520?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19521520</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paaijmans</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanford</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Warmer temperatures reduce the vectorial capacity of malaria mosquitoes</article-title><source>Biol Lett</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>465</fpage><lpage>468</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22188673?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22188673</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kucharski</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Funk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Eggo</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mallet</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Edmunds</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilles</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transmission dynamics of Zika virus in island populations: a modelling analysis of the 2013&#x02013;14 French Polynesia outbreak</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e0004726</fpage><?supplied-pmid 27186984?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27186984</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Styer</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Minnick</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mortality and reproductive dynamics of <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> (Diptera: Culicidae) fed human blood</article-title><source>Vector Borne Zoonotic Dis</source><year>2007</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17417961?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17417961</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perkasa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yudhaputri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Haryanto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayati</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma&#x02019;roef</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Antonjaya</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Isolation of Zika virus from febrile patient, Indonesia</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>924</fpage><lpage>925</lpage><?supplied-pmid 27088970?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27088970</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waggoner</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gresh</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballesteros</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tellez</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Soda</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Viremia and clinical presentation in Nicaraguan patients infected with Zika virus, chikungunya virus, and dengue virus</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>1584</fpage><lpage>1590</lpage><?supplied-pmid 27578819?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27578819</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carrington</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Armijos</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambrechts</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fluctuations at a low mean temperature accelerate dengue virus transmission by <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic></article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><year>2013</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e2190</fpage><?supplied-pmid 23638208?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23638208</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alto</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiggins</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Eastmond</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zirbel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lounibos</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diurnal temperature range and chikungunya virus infection in invasive mosquito vectors</article-title><source>J Med Entomol</source><year>2018</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>224</lpage><?supplied-pmid 29040730?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29040730</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muttis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Balsalobre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuchuy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mangudo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciota</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Factors related to <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> (Diptera: Culicidae) populations and temperature determine differences on life-history traits with regional implications in disease transmission</article-title><source>J Med Entomol</source><year>2018</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>1105</fpage><lpage>1112</lpage><?supplied-pmid 29659944?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29659944</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrlich</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Magalhaes</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bransfield</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Successive blood meals enhance virus dissemination within mosquitoes and increase transmission potential</article-title><source>Nat Microbiol</source><year>2020</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>247</lpage><?supplied-pmid 31819213?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31819213</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sikulu-Lord</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Milali</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wirtz</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hugo</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dowell</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Near-infrared spectroscopy, a rapid method for predicting the age of male and female wild-type and <italic>Wolbachia</italic> infected <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic></article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e0005040</fpage><?supplied-pmid 27768689?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27768689</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sikulu-Lord</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayagaya</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name><surname>Devine</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dowell</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Churcher</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monitoring the age of mosquito populations using near-infrared spectroscopy</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>5274</fpage><?supplied-pmid 29588452?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29588452</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonzalez Jimenez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Babayan</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Khazaeli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Walton</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Reedy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prediction of mosquito species and population age structure using mid-infrared spectroscopy and supervised machine learning</article-title><source>Wellcome Open Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>76</fpage><?supplied-pmid 31544155?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31544155</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hugo</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Churcher</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>OTW</given-names></name><name><surname>Devine</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mosquito age grading and vector-control programmes</article-title><source>Trends Parasitol</source><year>2020</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><?supplied-pmid 31836285?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31836285</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Onyango</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bialosuknia</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathias</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Vigneron</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Increased temperatures reduce the vectorial capacity of <italic>Aedes</italic> mosquitoes for Zika virus</article-title><source>Emerg Microbes Infect</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><?supplied-pmid 31894724?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31894724</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Althouse</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanley</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The tortoise or the hare? Impacts of within-host dynamics on transmission success of arthropod-borne viruses</article-title><source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2014.0299</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26150665?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26150665</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pena-Garcia</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name><name><surname>Christofferson</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correlation of the basic reproduction number (R0) and eco-environmental variables in Colombian municipalities with chikungunya outbreaks during 2014&#x02013;2016</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><year>2019</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>e0007878</fpage><?supplied-pmid 31697681?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31697681</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goddard</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Reisen</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vector competence of California mosquitoes for West Nile virus</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><year>2002</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1385</fpage><lpage>1391</lpage><?supplied-pmid 12498652?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12498652</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>