<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0560">The main results of the study here, based on case study of COVID-19 outbreak in Italy, can explain and generalize the factors determining transmission dynamics of Coronavirus disease in regions with polluting industrialization. In particular, 
 <list list-type="simple" id="l0095">
  <list-item id="li0225">
   <label>○</label>
   <p id="p0565">The acceleration of transmission dynamics of COVID-19 has a high association with air pollution of cities measured with days exceeding the limits set for PM
    <sub>10</sub> or ozone.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="li0230">
   <label>○</label>
   <p id="p0570">
    <italic>Cities having more than 100 days of air pollution (exceeding the limits set for PM</italic>
    <sub>
     <italic>10</italic>
    </sub>
    <italic>or ozone), they have a very high average number of infected individuals</italic> (about 3600 infected individuals on 7th April 2020), whereas cities having less than 100 days of air pollution, they have a lower average number of infected individuals (about 1000 infected individuals).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="li0235">
   <label>○</label>
   <p id="p0575">
    <italic>Hinterland cities</italic>, with high number of average days exceeding the limits set for PM
    <sub>10</sub>, have a very high number of infected people on 7th April 2020 (arithmetic mean is about 2200 infected individuals, with average polluted days more than 80 days per year). 
    <italic>Coastal cities,</italic> also having days exceeding the limits set for PM
    <sub>10</sub> or ozone, have an arithmetic mean of about 940 infected individuals, with average polluted days about 60 per year. In addition, 
    <italic>coastal cities</italic> have an average higher intensity of wind speed (about 12 km/h) than hinterland cities (8 km/h) and statistical analysis reveals a negative coefficient of correlation between number of infected individuals and of wind speed (
    <italic>r</italic> &gt; −31%, 
    <italic>p</italic>-value &lt; 0.05): in fact, wind speed and other climate factors can clean air from pollutants that are associated with transmission dynamics of Coronavirus disease.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="li0240">
   <label>○</label>
   <p id="p0580">Air pollution in Italian cities under study seems to be a more important predictor in the initial phase of transmission dynamics (on 17th March 2020, b
    <sub>1</sub> = 1.27, 
    <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) than human-to-human transmission (b
    <sub>2</sub> = 0.31, 
    <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Subsequently, the factor of air pollution reduces intensity of the diffusion of Coronavirus infection (on 7th April 2020 b′
    <sub>1</sub> = 0.81, 
    <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) also because of indirect effect of lockdown, whereas coefficient of human-to-human transmission does not change (b′
    <sub>2</sub> = 0.31, 
    <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01). 
    <italic>This result reveals that accelerated transmission</italic>
    <italic>dynamics of COVID-19 is due to</italic>
    <italic>the mechanism of air pollution-to-human transmission in addition to human-to-human transmission</italic>.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="li0245">
   <label>○</label>
   <p id="p0585">To minimize future epidemics similar to COVID-19, the max number of days per year that Italian provincial capitals and other cities with polluting industrialization can exceed the limits set for PM
    <sub>10</sub> (particulate matter 10 μm or less in diameter) or for ozone, considering their meteorological conditions, has to be less than 
    <italic>50 days</italic>.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
