<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0590">Hence, high concentration of nitrogen dioxide and particulate air pollutants emitted by motor vehicles, power plants, and industrial facilities in North Italy seems to be a platform to support the diffusion of viral infectivity (
 <xref rid="bb0360" ref-type="bibr">Groulx et al., 2018</xref>), increase hospitalizations for respiratory virus bronchiolitis (cf., 
 <xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">Carugno et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0575" ref-type="bibr">Nenna et al., 2017</xref>), increase asthma incidence and other respiratory disorders (
 <xref rid="bb0495" ref-type="bibr">Liao et al., 2011</xref>) and induce damages to the immune system of people (
 <xref rid="bb0340" ref-type="bibr">Glencross et al., 2020</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr">Beelen et al. (2013)</xref> report the need to draw attention to the continuing effects of air pollution on health of people. A socioeconomic strategy to prevent future epidemics similar to the COVID-19 is also the reduction of pollution with fruitful environmental and health effect by rationalizing of manufacturing industry in a perspective of sustainable development and by de-industrializing polluting activities in the geographical development of capitalism. De-industrialization of polluting industries and sustainable development impose often huge social costs in the short term for people, households, and families but they have long-run benefits for human societies. Studies show that public and environmental health policy interventions have the potential to reduce morbidity and mortality in Europe (cf., 
 <xref rid="bb0640" ref-type="bibr">Raaschou-Nielsen et al., 2013</xref>). In fact, the improvements of air quality have been accompanied by demonstrable benefits to human health. 
 <xref rid="bb0615" ref-type="bibr">Pope et al. (2009)</xref> report that PM
 <sub>2.5</sub> concentrations fell by a third from the early 1980s to the late 1990s across major US metropolitan areas, with each 10 μg/m
 <sup>3</sup> reduction associated with an increase in life expectancy of 0.61 years. Because of health problems of polluting industrialization, 
 <xref rid="bb0745" ref-type="bibr">Wei et al. (2020)</xref> suggest different air pollution regulations in regions having varied geographical and climatic conditions, and different bio aerosol pollution. In particular, 
 <xref rid="bb0745" ref-type="bibr">Wei et al. (2020)</xref> suggest that different air quality strategies should be applied in inland and coastal cities, e.g., coastal cities need start bioaerosol risk alarm during moderate pollution when severe pollution occurs in inland cities. 
 <xref rid="bb0365" ref-type="bibr">Guo et al. (2019)</xref> argue that haze pollution is a serious environmental problem affecting cities, proposing a sustainable urban planning directed to improve public respiratory health. In brief, the long-term benefits of sustainable economic development are basic for the improvement of environment, atmosphere, air quality and especially health of population as well as for the reduction of possible factors determining accelerated diffusion of viral infectivity and Coronavirus diseases in winter and fall seasons (
 <xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">Blackaby, 1978</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">Bluestone and Harrison, 1982</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0600" ref-type="bibr">Pike, 2009</xref>).
</p>
