<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0595">These findings here are consistent with correlational studies that health effects of air pollution exposure can extend beyond cardiopulmonary systems, affecting diffusion of epidemics similar to COVID-19. Hence, it is important to reinforce empirical evidence related to association between air pollution and inter-related factors of the transmission dynamics of viruses similar to COVID-19, to help policy makers to develop proactive strategies for the control of environment, reduction of air pollution and polluting industrialization, and to prevent the diffusion of future Coronavirus diseases. The complex problem of epidemic threats has to be treated with a proactive approach of 
 <italic>dissolution</italic>: it means to redesign the strategies and protocols to cope with future epidemics in such way as to eliminate the conditions that caused accelerated diffusion of COVID-19, thus enabling nations to do better in the future than the best it can do today (
 <xref rid="bb0005" ref-type="bibr">Ackoff and Rovin, 2003, pp. 9–10</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">Bundy et al., 2017</xref>). This study reveals interesting results of transmission dynamics of COVID-19 outbreak given by 
 <italic>two mechanisms</italic> that may have accelerated the diffusion of viral infectivity in Italy: air pollution-to-human transmission and human-to-human transmission that create dangerous interaction over time and space. However, these conclusions are tentative. There are several challenges to such study, particularly in real time. Sources may be incomplete, or only capture certain aspects of the on-going outbreak dynamics; there is need for much more research in to the complex relations between diffusion of Coronavirus diseases, levels of air pollution, meteorological factors, immune systems of population and other determinants within and between countries. Overall, then, in the presence of polluting industrialization of cities and mechanisms of diffusion of viral infectivity also based on air pollution -to-human transmission (
 <italic>airborne viral infectivity diseases</italic>), this study must conclude that a comprehensive strategy to prevent future epidemics similar to COVID-19 has 
 <italic>also</italic> to be designed in environmental and socioeconomic terms, that is in terms of sustainability science and environmental science, and 
 <italic>not only</italic> in terms of biology, medicine, healthcare and health sector.
</p>
