<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The variables included were the point prevalence of stockouts of a set of HIV commodities in the visited sites. A stockout was defined as no physical availability of the selected commodity in the facility pharmacy at the time of the survey visit. A complete first-line ART regimens consist of three active ingredients. Sometimes, two or more active ingredients are combined into a single tablet (also called a fixed-dose combination) to reduce the pill burden and improve adherence [
 <xref rid="pone.0191294.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. We have written the fixed-dose-combinations as the names of the active ingredients separated with a hyphen, and we have written the formulations with only one active ingredient as separate words. We selected the following ARVs for analysis: the two fixed-dose-combinations for first-line adult treatment; Tenofovir-Lamivudine-Efavirenz (TDF-3TC-EFV) and Zidovudine-Lamivudine-Nevirapine (AZT-3TC-NVP), and the Tenofovir-Lamuvidine (TDF-3TC) combination tablets commonly used as a first-line regimen (with Nevirapine) or a second-line regimen (with Lopinavir/ritonavir). These regimens were selected because at least 90% of ART patients in Kinshasa are treated with one of the included ART formulations [
 <xref rid="pone.0191294.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. We also assessed the availability of tablets of cotrimoxazole (CTX) for adults, which contain a combination of the antibiotics sulfamethoxazole and trimethoprim, and of Determine™ HIV-1/2 rapid diagnostic tests (HIV test) [
 <xref rid="pone.0191294.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In case of stockouts, we registered the duration until the day of the survey visit and, in cases of ART stockouts, the solutions the facility would propose to patients needing the unavailable ART. We differentiated between giving no ART at all (ask to return later, refer to another facility) and substitution with another formulation or regimen. High-burden facilities were those that reported more than 200 patients on ART and low-burden facilities those that reported 200 or fewer patients on ART in March 2015 according to the national database.
</p>
