<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Odessa, Ukraine, was one of the first locations where TRIP was implemented. Ukraine has a large HIV-infected population (estimated to be 240,000 people as of 2019 [
 <xref rid="B16-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]), but only 4 (out of 27 total) administrative regions account for &gt;50% of HIV cases in the country: Odessa, Kyiv, Dnipro and Donetsk. Odessa is thought to be the “birthplace” of the HIV epidemic in Ukraine and the post-soviet territories [
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], and it still has one of the highest HIV prevalence levels in various risk groups in Ukraine (i.e., 13% in MSM and 28% in PWID in 2015) [
 <xref rid="B18-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Overall, Kyiv and Odessa share similar HIV epidemiological profiles and have experienced a similar number of HIV prevention interventions, other than TRIP. They were the first cities in which treatment started being offered to patients upon diagnosis in 2014, even though it is still not a universal practice in Ukraine. Since 2013, in both cities, a case management approach to linkage to care has been introduced for PWID: peer outreach workers help newly diagnosed HIV-positive PWID to register with local AIDS Centres and start antiretroviral treatment. During 2012–2013 the “Project Protect” intervention was implemented in both cities, which offered the PWID community education about the danger of acute HIV infection [
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. According to our previous estimates, Odessa and Kyiv were also some of the main sink (receiving infections) locations for HIV spatial dissemination associated with the recent military conflict in the east of Ukraine [
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Neither city displayed a decline in the annual number of newly HIV diagnosed people in 2016–2019, while the annual number of performed HIV tests also grew [
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].
</p>
