<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="discussion"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?OLF?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Lancet Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Lancet Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Lancet. Infectious Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1473-3099</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1474-4457</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier Ltd.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7470735</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S1473-3099(20)30451-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(20)30451-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Group B streptococcus vaccines: one step further</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au10"><name><surname>Berner</surname><given-names>Reinhard</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Pediatrics, University Hospital Carl Gustav Carus, Technische Universit&#x000e4;t Dresden, Dresden 01307, Germany</aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>3</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>3</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Elsevier Ltd</copyright-holder><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article related-article-type="article-reference" id="d33e235" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/S1473-3099(20)30478-3"/></article-meta></front><body><p id="para10">In <italic>The Lancet Infectious Diseases</italic>, Judith Absalon and colleagues<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> report on a phase 1/2 clinical trial evaluating the safety, tolerability, and immunogenicity of a vaccine composed of capsular polysaccharide conjugated to cross-reactive material 197 (CRM<sub>197</sub>) and directed against six capsular polysaccharide serotypes of group B streptococcus (GBS). These serotypes (Ia, Ib, II, III, IV, and V) account for the vast majority of isolates causing invasive GBS disease worldwide&#x02014;in neonates as well as in adults.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> The authors report that three different doses of this hexavalent vaccine formulated with or without aluminium phosphate as its adjuvant were safe and well tolerated in healthy, non-pregnant, adult volunteers. The vaccine elicited a robust immune response for at least 6 months.</p><p id="para20">It is a good point in time to report some success with a GBS vaccine. In the era of COVID-19 and the worldwide anticipation of a severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) vaccine, it might appear as if vaccine development works as in the proverb that states that where there's a will, there's a way. For GBS vaccines, progress has been very difficult. In the 1980s, pioneers Carol Baker and Dennis Kasper started to investigate polysaccharide-based GBS vaccines. In 1988, they showed that maternal immunisation against GBS is feasible, but immunogenicity of GBS polysaccharide-based vaccines was weak.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> In 1996, a phase 1 trial with conjugate vaccines prepared with GBS type-specific capsular polysaccharide coupled to protein antigens induced stronger immune responses than capsular polysaccharide alone.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> Although more than 20 years have elapsed since then, unfortunately no GBS vaccine has been licensed. In the meantime, pneumococcal, meningococcal, and <italic>Haemophilus influenza</italic>e type b conjugate vaccines have all been licensed. Several phase 1 and 2 studies of GBS vaccines have been done, including that by Absalon and colleagues.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> The results often are very encouraging&#x02014;as in this study&#x02014;but the next steps that are urgently needed, including studies in pregnant women, analysing the passive antibody transfer to the neonate, and subsequently assessing protection against disease, are often not taken.</p><p id="para30">There is an urgent need for a global strategy to protect the most vulnerable population&#x02014;neonates and young infants up to age 3 months&#x02014;against this sometimes devastating disease, which can cause neonatal GBS sepsis and meningitis, and which is an unresolved challenge, especially in low-income countries. GBS is estimated to cause more than 300&#x02008;000 cases of neonatal disease annually, resulting in roughly 90&#x02008;000 infant deaths worldwide.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> GBS is also associated with maternal sepsis, stillbirths and preterm births, and severe neurological impairment among patients who survive neonatal meningitis. Intrapartum antibiotic prophylaxis has substantially reduced the incidence of early onset GBS disease in high-income countries that have implemented this strategy; however, this strategy is not feasible in many low-income and middle-income countries. Moreover, intrapartum antibiotic prophylaxis will not protect against late-onset GBS disease, which in most cases is transmitted postnatally. By contrast, a vaccine given to pregnant women to stimulate passive transplacental transfer of protective antibodies has the potential to reduce maternal disease, adverse pregnancy outcomes, and newborn early onset and late-onset disease. Maternal IgG is actively transported across the placenta, providing passive immunity. Of course, the risks and benefits of maternal vaccination must always be carefully weighed and analysed, and protection of the mother and the fetus must be prioritised.</p><p id="para40">The next step would then be doing efficacy studies, which for a GBS vaccine candidate is a difficult task. It would require large numbers of immunised mothers because of the low incidence of neonatal GBS disease. It has therefore been proposed that alternative options to vaccine licensure should be explored. Recent studies suggest that maternal capsular antibody thresholds could be used as immunological correlates of protection. Thus, a regulatory approved correlate of protection and safety evaluation in mothers, fetuses, and infants are needed.<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> After the vaccine is licensed, phase 4 studies would then have to follow to evaluate vaccine effectiveness.</p><p id="para50">Beyond conjugate vaccines, which have some limitations, surface proteins, as candidate vaccines with or without being coupled to the capsular polysaccharide, might broaden protection against invasive GBS disease. However, the immunogenic potential of pilus island and other GBS surface proteins, which has been shown in animal-model studies, could not be confirmed by association analysis of maternal antibody concentration and invasive GBS disease in infants.<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> Therefore, the study by Absalon and colleagues is particularly important and encouraging. The hexavalent conjugate vaccine covers the majority of invasive serotypes worldwide. Serotype replacement should be kept in mind as a potential problem, but should not hamper further steps. In these days of the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic, when awareness of the paramount importance of vaccine development is as high as ever, the time has come to initiate the required studies designed to prove immunogenicity of a hexavalent vaccine in pregnant women, diaplacental transfer of antibodies, and protection of neonates from disease, disability, or death.</p><p id="para60">
<fig id="f10"><graphic xlink:href="fx1_lrg"/><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Flickr/NIAID</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions></fig>
</p></body><back><ref-list id="bibl10"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Absalon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Segall</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Block</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Safety and immunogenicity of a novel hexavalent group B streptococcus conjugate vaccine in healthy non-pregnant adults: a phase 1/2, randomised, placebo-controlled, observer-blinded trial</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><year>2020</year><comment>published online Sept 3.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(20)30478-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nanduri</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Petit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Smelser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of invasive early-onset and late-onset group B streptococcal disease in the United States, 2006 to 2015: multistate laboratory and population-based surveillance</article-title><source>JAMA Pediatr</source><volume>173</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>233</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30640366</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Francois Watkins</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>McGee</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Schrag</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of invasive group B streptococcal infections among nonpregnant adults in the United States, 2008&#x02013;2016</article-title><source>JAMA Intern Med</source><volume>179</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>479</fpage><lpage>488</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30776079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Z&#x000fc;rn</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hufnagel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Monecke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Berner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microarray analysis of group B streptococci causing invasive neonatal early- and late-onset infection</article-title><source>Pediatr Infect Dis J</source><volume>39</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>449</fpage><lpage>453</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32091495</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rench</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hays</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasper</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunization of pregnant women with a polysaccharide vaccine of group B streptococcus</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>319</volume><year>1988</year><fpage>1180</fpage><lpage>1185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3050524</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref60"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kasper</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Paoletti</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wessels</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immune response to type III group B streptococcal polysaccharide-tetanus toxoid conjugate vaccine</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><volume>98</volume><year>1996</year><fpage>2308</fpage><lpage>2314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8941648</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref70"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Carreras-Abad</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Doare</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Group B streptococcus: trials and tribulations</article-title><source>Pediatr Infect Dis J</source><volume>38</volume><issue>suppl 1</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>S72</fpage><lpage>S76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31205250</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref80"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vekemans</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Crofts</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of immune correlates of protection on the pathway to licensure, policy decision and use of group B streptococcus vaccines for maternal immunization: considerations from World Health Organization consultations</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><volume>37</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>3190</fpage><lpage>3198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31031031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref90"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Le Doare</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kampmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Vekemans</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serocorrelates of protection against infant group B streptococcus disease</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><volume>19</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>e162</fpage><lpage>e171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30683467</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fabbrini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rigat</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinaudo</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The protective value of maternal group B streptococcus antibodies: quantitative and functional analysis of naturally acquired responses to capsular polysaccharides and pilus proteins in European maternal sera</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><volume>63</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>746</fpage><lpage>753</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27402816</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack><p>I was part of the EU-funded (7th Framework Programme) project DEVANI (Design of a Vaccine to Immunize Neonates Against GBS Infections through a Durable Maternal Immune Response) for which Novartis Vaccines and Diagnostics was part of the project team.</p></ack></back></article>