<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>HPAIV infection in humans occurs sporadically in Asia, Africa, Europe, and the Middle East.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr1-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
 </sup> As of October 2018, there have not been any reported cases of human H5N1 infection in the USA, but one case was reported in Canada in 2014 from a person who had recently traveled from China.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr94-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>
 </sup> HPAIV H5 virus infection in humans can initially present as an uncomplicated seasonal influenza infection with clinical signs of fever, body aches, and upper respiratory tract symptoms.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr1-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr95-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>
  <xref rid="bibr96-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr"/>–
  <xref rid="bibr97-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>
 </sup> However, the infection eventually progresses into a lower respiratory tract infection. The infection can progress to become severe pneumonia, multi-organ failure, encephalitis, and septic shock.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr1-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr95-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr96-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>
 </sup> The incubation period for H5N1 virus infection is estimated to be 7 days, but is more commonly 2–5 days after exposure. In the rare cases where human-to-human transmission occurred the incubation period varied from 3–4 days to 2–10 days. Variability in this incubation period can possibly reflect the level of viral shedding, exposure, and immunological factors.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr98-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>
 </sup> A reported pediatric case with H5N1 virus infection presented with fever, diarrhea, and seizures, which progressed to a coma and eventually developed into encephalitis. The patient had contracted the virus from his sister 2 weeks earlier who also suffered from encephalitis and died. Neither patient presented with any respiratory symptoms.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr99-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>
 </sup> The severity of the illness varies with the virus clade, age of the patient, and other unknown genetic factors. Rapid disease progression following AIV infection occurs in the majority of human cases. Extrapulmonary complications that arise from H5 viral infections include cardiac failure, kidney failure, encephalitis, muti-organ failure, and intravascular coagulation.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr97-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr100-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>
  <xref rid="bibr101-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr"/>–
  <xref rid="bibr102-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>
 </sup> Human-to-human transmission of avian H5N1 virus has been recorded in several households, but is often limited.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr95-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr96-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>
 </sup> Transmission usually results from close intimate contact and/or care of a family member infected with H5N1 viruses. Surveillance by RT-PCR of contact patients led to the detection of mild cases of infection in older adults and an increased number of seropositive families in northern Vietnam.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr103-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
