<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0020">In the 20th-century infectious diseases were responsible for the largest number of premature death and disability worldwide. The Spanish flu occurred in the beginning of the previous century (
 <xref rid="bb0295" ref-type="bibr">Taubenberger and Morens, 2006</xref>; 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/features/1918-flu-pandemic/index.html" id="ir0020" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.cdc.gov/features/1918-flu-pandemic/index.html</ext-link>). It is estimated that one-third of the world’s population (500 million individuals) was infected and has symptoms during the 1918–19 pandemic (
 <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>A). The disease was one of the deadliest of all influenza pandemics. It was estimated that at least 50 million individuals died following the infection. The impact of this pandemic was not restricted to the first quarter of the 20th century since almost all cases of influenza A were caused by mutated versions of the 1918 virus. While we will not cover the virologic or immunological aspect of influenza infection, it is important to understand the purpose of this chapter why the pandemic occurred. The 1918 flu pandemic happened during World War I where proximity, bad hygiene, and unusual mass movement (troops and population) helped the spread of the virus. Even the United Stated reported more than 600,000 death in its country despite the distance. Many of the countries involved in the war “failed” to communicate on the death toll caused by influenza. This was purposely kept silence in order to sustain public morale. While this could be understood on a military aspect, it has deadly consequences as the virus would come in other waves. At that time, viruses were not known yet and diagnostic, prevention and treatments were very limited. As such, people would suffer from influenza virus itself (flu illness) and its consequences such as lung infection by bacteria (pneumonia) in susceptible individuals. This shows how poor communication and wrong usage of pandemics data could affect millions of lives. Since then, progresses have been made in order to follow influenza A pandemics. Since 1952, the World Health Organization’s Global Influenza Surveillance and Response System (GISRS) have been monitoring the evolution of influenza viruses. It also serves as a global alert mechanism for emerging viruses with pandemic potential as observed in 1918. We now better understand the factors that influence transmission (
 <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>B). Influenza is just one of the various pandemics we have been through. In fact, besides influenza, smallpox, tuberculosis, and cholera are constant threats (
 <xref rid="bb0165" ref-type="bibr">Holmes et al., 2017</xref>). Improving the hygiene conditions and vaccination campaigns have been very effective means to reduce the spread of infections. There are different cases of viral spread, for instance, there is constant follow-up on polio cases as three countries still report cases while WHO has the mission to eradicate it completely. The 21st century has already seen emerging pandemic infectious such as SARS (severe acute respiratory syndrome), MERS (Middle East respiratory syndrome), Ebola, and Zika viruses. By controlling infections, we can reduce premature death as well as infection-driven diseases such as cirrhosis (hepatitis B), liver cancer (hepatitis C), stomach cancer (
 <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic>), or worsening of conditions such as cardiovascular and respiratory (influenza A). Because we cannot always rely on medicine to develop rapidly vaccines or other treatments, the best prevention is to detect early possible pandemics and stop the transmission. By blocking transmission, we could eventually also reduce the mutation of the viruses and thus keep the virus in a stage that vaccines could help fight.
</p>
