<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recently, our studies on chimeric ZIKV clones between an epidemic Brazilian strain of ZIKV BeH819015 (hereafter called BR15) and a historical African strain MR766 highlighted an important role of two structural proteins prM/M, and E in ZIKV ability to infect human cells [
 <xref rid="B16-cells-08-01444" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-cells-08-01444" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-cells-08-01444" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-cells-08-01444" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. We further showed that they contribute to the initiation of viral infection. Analysis of chimeric viruses indicated that C-prM region plays a role in triggering cell death by ZIKV and E protein is associated with viral attachment to host cells during early infection [
 <xref rid="B23-cells-08-01444" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-cells-08-01444" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Flavivirus E proteins usually contain two 
 <italic>N</italic>-glycosylation sites at position E-56 and E-154. The first site is lacking in ZIKV E protein and contribution of the second site in ZIKV viral cycle, including in the mosquito vector, has been recently highlighted [
 <xref rid="B25-cells-08-01444" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. N-linked glycosylation of the E protein was shown to be an important determinant of ZIKV virulence in a mouse model of viral encephalitis [
 <xref rid="B22-cells-08-01444" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-cells-08-01444" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. In invertebrate vectors, ZIKV bearing an unglycosylated E protein was attenuated in its capacity to replicate in 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> [
 <xref rid="B27-cells-08-01444" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Although a 
 <italic>N</italic>-glycosylation site is highly conserved among flaviviruses, which suggests of its biological importance, E proteins could remain unglycosylated as it has been observed in some ZIKV strains. To date, the exact mechanism by which the 
 <italic>N</italic>-glycosylation motif region of the E protein contributes to ZIKV infectivity still remains elusive. In the present study, we further characterised structural protein contribution in ZIKV infectivity by focusing on the ZIKV E protein. Our goal was to determine whether three E residues—Ile152, Thr156, and His158 (hereafter called as E-152/156/158 residues)—which surround the Asn154 composing the 
 <italic>N</italic>-glycosylation site NDT, may have any effect on ZIKV’s ability to infect human cells.
</p>
