<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As an atypical strain with mutations and genetic reassortment, emergence of the novel H7N9 AIVs in China raises concerns regarding new vaccine development and drug resistance. The influence of animal infections on human disease propagation places a large burden on health systems and animal trade controls to prevent the virus spreading via travelers and animal movement. Although AIVs usually do not infect people, rare cases of human infection with these viruses have been reported.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr53-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>
 </sup> Regarding the transmission route, H7N9 AIVs have been found to cause human infection, mainly from poultry to humans. Infected birds can shed H7N9 AIVs in secretions like saliva, mucous, and feces, which can lead to human infection via mucosal surfaces of the eyes, nose, and mouth or through inhalation of droplets and dust containing the virus. Unprotected exposure to H7N9 AIVs from infected birds is currently considered the main risk factor and transmission route. The role of poultry farms, live animal markets, and retailers might be key in the spread of disease, as well as inadequate biosafety measures and poor handling of sick or dead animals. However, some laboratory-confirmed human cases lack evidence of a history of direct contact with animals, indicating the possibility of human-to-human transmission.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr53-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr149-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>
 </sup> To date, several studies have predicted and compared the route of poultry-to-human or human-to-human transmitted efficiency of H7N9 AIVs using the reproduction number (R);
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr43-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr56-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr120-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr140-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr150-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">150</xref>
 </sup> The R is a key indicator of transmission intensity estimated by fitting the number of poultry-to-human and from human-to-human infections into mathematical models. The data of these studies showed that the estimated R value for an H7N9 outbreak was below the epidemic threshold required for sustained human-to-human transmission, indicating that an H7N9 human-to-human pandemic is unlikely to occur and most cases of H7N9 AIV infection are owing to poultry-to-human transmission. Virlogeux et al.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr149-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>
 </sup> recently used an ecological model to evaluate animal-to-human and human-to-human transmission of H7N9 during the first three epidemic waves in China; the authors indicated that there was a significant decrease in the incidence of H7N9 cases after live poultry market closures in several major cities of China. Accordingly, it can be concluded that although H7N9 human-to-human transmission might be possible, the major transmission route of H7N9 AIVs remains via poultry-to-human.
</p>
