<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <title>ABSTRACT</title>
 <p>Ebola virus (EBOV) infections result in aggressive hemorrhagic fever in humans, with fatality rates reaching 90% and with no licensed specific therapeutics to treat ill patients. Advances over the past 5 years have firmly established monoclonal antibody (MAb)-based products as the most promising therapeutics for treating EBOV infections, but production is costly and quantities are limited; therefore, MAbs are not the best candidates for mass use in the case of an epidemic. To address this need, we generated EBOV-specific polyclonal F(ab′)
  <sub>2</sub> fragments from horses hyperimmunized with an EBOV vaccine. The F(ab′)
  <sub>2</sub> was found to potently neutralize West African and Central African EBOV 
  <italic>in vitro</italic>. Treatment of nonhuman primates (NHPs) with seven doses of 100 mg/kg F(ab′)
  <sub>2</sub> beginning 3 or 5 days postinfection (dpi) resulted in a 100% survival rate. Notably, NHPs for which treatment was initiated at 5 dpi were already highly viremic, with observable signs of EBOV disease, which demonstrated that F(ab′)
  <sub>2</sub> was still effective as a therapeutic agent even in symptomatic subjects. These results show that F(ab′)
  <sub>2</sub> should be advanced for clinical testing in preparation for future EBOV outbreaks and epidemics.
 </p>
 <p>
  <bold>IMPORTANCE</bold> EBOV is one of the deadliest viruses to humans. It has been over 40 years since EBOV was first reported, but no cure is available. Research breakthroughs over the past 5 years have shown that MAbs constitute an effective therapy for EBOV infections. However, MAbs are expensive and difficult to produce in large amounts and therefore may only play a limited role during an epidemic. A cheaper alternative is required, especially since EBOV is endemic in several third world countries with limited medical resources. Here, we used a standard protocol to produce large amounts of antiserum F(ab′)
  <sub>2</sub> fragments from horses vaccinated with an EBOV vaccine, and we tested the protectiveness in monkeys. We showed that F(ab′)
  <sub>2</sub> was effective in 100% of monkeys even after the animals were visibly ill with EBOV disease. Thus, F(ab′)
  <sub>2</sub> could be a very good option for large-scale treatments of patients and should be advanced to clinical testing.
 </p>
</abstract>
