<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Influenza virus vaccine effectiveness ranged from 19% to 48% during the past three influenza seasons (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). During the 2013–2014, 2014–2015, and 2015–2016 seasons, a number of issues emerged that called into question the effectiveness of the only FDA-approved LAIV in the U.S. market (no evidence of similar problems appears to have existed in other markets where the same vaccine is approved). Although such issues appear to have been resolved for the 2017–2018 season and alternative LAIVs approved for other markets (based on the A/Leningrad and B/USSR MDV strains) do not seem to have faced similar issues, there is a need for the development of novel LAIV strategies that will likely impact the future development of influenza virus vaccines. In general, weakened (attenuated) forms of viral pathogens offer the longest-lasting protection because they produce multidimensional responses by stimulating the humoral and cellular arms of the immune system. The IAV 
 <italic>att</italic> component in the QIV studied here, based on the internal gene segment constellation of the Ty/04 strain, contains mutations found in the A/Ann Arbor MDV-A (PB2 S265 and PB1 E391, G581, and T661). These mutations can confer an 
 <italic>att</italic> phenotype on some, but not all, IAV strains, as we have previously shown (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). However, the incorporation of the HA epitope tag at the C terminus of PB1, along with the 
 <italic>ts</italic> mutations (
 <italic>ts</italic> + HA tag = 
 <italic>att</italic>) resulted in attenuation 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>. The IAV 
 <italic>att</italic> strains that we have produced so far are remarkably stable and show optimal safety and protective profiles when used as monovalent vaccines. The most widely used MDV-As (A/Leningrad/and A/Ann Arbor) were isolated nearly 60 years ago. Over this period, IAVs have continued to evolve and reassort and have accumulated mutations on relevant cytotoxic T lymphocyte (CTL) epitopes that differ from those in the MDV-A internal backbones (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Altering the gene constellation of MDV-A would require further preclinical and clinical testing. Thus, a major advantage of our strategy is the possibility to impart the 
 <italic>att</italic> phenotype to virtually any IAV strain. We favored the Ty/04 
 <italic>att</italic> backbone because it carries the potential to act as a universal 
 <italic>att</italic> backbone for use in avian and mammalian species, including humans. To be used in humans, however, a complementary IBV 
 <italic>att</italic> strategy is highly desirable. For that reason, we incorporated an IBV PB1 gene segment carrying the G580 and A660 mutations and the C-terminal HA tag and established that it resulted in attenuation of the B/Bris strain. We further demonstrated that the B/Bris 
 <italic>att</italic> strain was stable, safe, and immunogenic and protected mice against lethal IBV challenge. The modifications of the IBV 
 <italic>att</italic> are unique to our virus and are not shared with the B/Ann Arbor or B/USSR MDV-B.
</p>
