<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">Drug repurposing (or drug repositioning) is the method of assigning a new medical indication for an existing drug. The repositioned drug might be currently on the market for other medication, withdrawn due to adverse effects or proved to be less efficacious. As a matter of fact, most of the drug repositioning emerged as a result of beneficial side effects (by serendipity); however, current efforts to attain repurposing are accomplished in a more systematic way (Naveja et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">2016</xref>). Nowadays, the problem of antimicrobial drug resistances poses a growing threat to global public health and demands newer or repositioned drugs. With regard to utilizing already FDA-approved drugs for another indication, the entities can be used for treating the new indication without any further structural modification of the compound at hand (though dosing and formulation could be modified) (Savoia 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">2016</xref>; Klug et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2016</xref>). The case of Ebola virus outbreak in West Africa that reached to a scale not ever seen in history was the greatest public health emergency. Antibody-based therapy was proved effective in a macaque model and had been used to treat few patients; however, the supply of the drug was quite limited. Therefore, drug repurposing was the best option to come up with an old drug with new indication to speed up the discovery and development of anti-Ebola virus drugs for the treatment of patients with Ebola virus infection. As a result, initial drug repurposing screen subsequently provided 53 approved drugs with Ebola virus-like particle entry-blocking activity including the macrolide antibiotics azithromycin and clarithromycin, which block bacterial protein synthesis (Kouznetsova et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2014</xref>). Finally, six antibiotics which inhibit Ebola virus infection (azithromycin, erythromycin, spiramycin, dirithromycin, maduramicin, clarithromycin) were selected for anti-Ebola activity out of 3828 FDA-approved drugs (Veljkovic et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111">2015</xref>). There was no herbal therapy for Zika virus infection; however recently, two antiviral agents have been approved by FDA for Zika virus infection (Cheng et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2016</xref>). It is important to design or develop a therapeutic approach to overcome Zika virus infection with a special focus on drugs targeting the virus helicase protein, nucleosides, inhibitors of NS3 protein, small molecules, methyltransferase inhibitor and repurposed drugs. Repurposed drugs such as chloroquine, azithromycin and niclosamide are used for the treatment of Zika virus infection (Munjal et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2017</xref>). New studies revealed that Alzheimer’s drugs may moderate Zika virus-mediated neuronal damage. So, Alzheimer’s disease drugs which overstimulate N-methyl-d-aspartate receptors (NMDARs) lead to damage neuronal death interlinked with Zika virus infection. Therefore, blocking of NMDAR channels with memantine and/or other antagonists helps to lessen the neuronal damage associated with Zika virus infection, which act as a pre-approved drug from the Food and Drug Authority (FDA) which need more clinical trials (Sirohi and Kuhn 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">2017</xref>).
</p>
