<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>According to a World Health Organization (WHO) report in 2018, there are approximately 38 million people living with HIV/AIDS in the world, the largest number being in Africa, with 25.7 million [
 <xref rid="B1-pathogens-09-00432" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The WHO’s goal is to identify 90% of HIV patients, treat 90% of those identified and virally suppress 90% of those treated by 2020 [
 <xref rid="B2-pathogens-09-00432" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Hepatitis C virus (HCV) and hepatitis B virus (HBV) have affected 71 million and 257 million people worldwide, which can lead to cirrhosis and liver cancer, respectively. Removing these viruses, which requires significant economic and sanitary capital, will prevent more than 1.2 million deaths worldwide annually [
 <xref rid="B3-pathogens-09-00432" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-pathogens-09-00432" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. HCV has the highest prevalence in the Eastern Mediterranean region, followed by the European region, with a prevalence of 2.3% and 1.5%, respectively. It varies from 0.5% to 1% in other areas. HBV is most prevalent in the Western Pacific and African regions, with values of 6.2% and 6.1%, respectively. The lowest prevalence is reported in the US, with a value of 0.7% [
 <xref rid="B5-pathogens-09-00432" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Viral hepatitis elimination program has been adapted by WHO in 2016 [
 <xref rid="B6-pathogens-09-00432" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In line with this global program, several countries are working towards this elimination platform [
 <xref rid="B7-pathogens-09-00432" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. In this program, engagement of high-risk groups and marginal populations has been highlighted [
 <xref rid="B8-pathogens-09-00432" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-pathogens-09-00432" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The efficient implementation of prevention and control measures incorporated in this program, requires detailed insight on the epidemiology of hepatitis viruses and other viral infectious agents circulating in these cohorts [
 <xref rid="B9-pathogens-09-00432" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].
</p>
