<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par45">RNA was extracted from PBMCs with the RNeasy Mini Kit (QIAGEN, Hilden, Germany) according to the manufacturer’s recommendations and stored at − 80 °C. Sequencing libraries were prepared with the TruSeq RNA Library Prep Kit v2 (Illumina, San Diego, CA) according to the low sample (LS) protocol and with 1 μg input mass. Libraries were quantified by qPCR using the KAPA Library Quantification Kit (KAPA Biosystems, Wilmington, MA) on a Roche 480 LightCycler (Roche, Basel, Switzerland); their size distributions were measured on a Fragment Analyzer using the Standard Sensitivity NGS Fragment Analysis Kit (Advanced Analytical Technologies, Ankeny, IA). Libraries were diluted to 2 nM in dilution buffer and combined with equimolar input into 4 sequencing pools (14 libraries per pool). Paired-end sequencing (2 × 100 bp) was performed at the Genomics Core Facility (Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai) on the Illumina HiSeq 2500 instrument with TruSeq SBS V3 chemistry according to the manufacturer’s instructions (Illumina, Inc., San Diego, CA). Each pool was run on one lane of a High Output flowcell. The raw sequencing reads were aligned to the human hg19 genome using star aligner (version 2.4.0 g1) guided by the Ensembl transcriptomic annotation model of GRCh37.70. After read alignment, featureCounts [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] was used to quantify expression at the gene level. Genes with at least 5 reads in at least 4 samples were considered expressed and hence retained for further analysis. The gene level read counts data was normalized using the trimmed mean of M-values normalization (TMM) method [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] to adjust for sequencing library size differences. Normalized read counts were further adjusted for batch effect using a linear model. The residuals from the regression model were used for downstream analysis. Differentially expressed genes were determined between acute and convalescent blood samples using linear models together with empirical Bayes statistics from the LIMMA R package [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. DEGs were considered significant with a fold change (FC) cutoff of |FC| ≥ 2 and an FDR-corrected 
 <italic>p</italic> value of 0.05 or less.
</p>
