<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Lastly, the interactions of hormones and the immune system contributing to both the outcome of pregnancy and female susceptibility to viral infections should be further studied. Female reproduction is regulated predominately by estrogen, progesterone, luteinizing hormone, and follicular stimulating hormone. These sex hormones contribute significantly to the shift in immune function that occurs over the three trimesters of pregnancy. Pregnant women have a unique immunological profile modulated by the sex hormones required to maintain pregnancy, namely progesterone and estrogens. Insufficient progesterone production has been associated with infertility and recurrent miscarriages [
 <xref rid="B143-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">143</xref>,
 <xref rid="B144-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>], whereas estrogens have also been implicated in inducing CD4
 <sup>+</sup> CD25
 <sup>+</sup> T regulatory cells (T
 <sub>regs</sub>) and are critical for maintaining tolerance within the maternal–fetal interface [
 <xref rid="B145-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>]. Progesterone also upregulates the activity of uterine T
 <sub>regs</sub>, which act as suppressors of inflammatory immune subsets, particularly NK cells and macrophages resident to the endometrium [
 <xref rid="B146-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>]. Thus, hormonal regulation of pregnancy and immune signaling are delicately balanced to protect fetal development. However, this balance can be disrupted by viral pathogens that cross placental barrier. For example, Littauer and colleagues demonstrated that influenza virus infection disrupts progesterone production and upregulates inflammatory mediators such as cyclooxygenase-2 and prostaglandins, resulting in preterm birth and miscarriages [
 <xref rid="B147-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>]. Furthermore, using an animal model, the same group reported that viral load was negatively associated with progesterone concentration, and reduced progesterone expression was correlated with preterm birth in influenza virus-infected pregnant mice [
 <xref rid="B148-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>]. Administration of progesterone to female mice following influenza A (H1N1) virus infection reduced immunopathological changes and improved lung epithelial cell regeneration, although it did not reduce viral load [
 <xref rid="B149-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>].
</p>
