<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0415">MV suppresses PBMC proliferation to mitogens after MV resolution, and this continues for several weeks (
 <xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 49.4B</xref>).
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>20</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>31</sup>
 </xref> IL-2 supplementation can improve, but not fully restore, this responsiveness. This suggests that defective IL-2 expression is in part responsible for this proliferative defect.
 <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>50</sup>
 </xref> Cell cycle arrest in G1 after 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> infection with MV is a recognized cause of hyporesponsiveness to mitogens.
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>42</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref> MV RNA can persist in PBMCs for months after MV resolution
 <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>54</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>55</sup>
 </xref> and may reduce mitogen proliferation, although this has not been established. The receptor used by wild-type MV to infect cells, CD150, is a dual function co-receptor for lymphocyte activation, and enhances IFN-γ expression.
 <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref> However, MV binding to CD150 can also downregulate receptor expression.
 <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>59</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>60</sup>
 </xref> T cell signaling through the MV glycoprotein complex of H and F1-F2 in the membranes of virions or MV-infected cells
 <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref> may also contribute to immunosuppression. This inhibitory signal prevents T cell S-phase entry for several days, and is independent of cell death, membrane fusion, soluble inhibitor production, or T cell infection.
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>52</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>61</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>62</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref> Thus, there is a delay in cell cycle progression and an accumulation of T cells in the G0/G1 phase.
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>52</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>66</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>67</sup>
 </xref> The mechanism by which H/F1-F2 suppresses mitogen-induced proliferation is unknown, but it is associated with MV-induced interference of T cell activation of phosphoinositide 3-kinase (PI3K) in T cells, or IL-2 receptor ligation.
 <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>68</sup>
 </xref> IL-2 added to MV-treated cells activates signal transducer and activator of transcription 3 (STAT3) but fails to activate Akt kinase, which is required for cell cycle progression.
 <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>69</sup>
 </xref> The modulatory effects of MV with glycoprotein complexes, and the downstream consequences of this interaction, have recently been summarized.
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>10</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref> While the relevance of these processes to the 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> suppression of T cell lymphoproliferation remains to be identified. The combination of the established mechanisms leading to post-MV infection immunosuppression, and those that remain to be elucidated, cause, in select individuals, severe and on occasion, fatal secondary infection with other microbes.
</p>
