<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3">
 <label>Table 3</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Selected Human Infectious Diseases</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1_lrg.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <fn id="tspara0035">
   <p>Variables that relate to their potential for eradication. (Top) Selected infectious diseases that have either been eradicated, are now being targeted for eradication, or are being significantly controlled by public health and medical or veterinary actions. (Bottom) Human infectious diseases that are currently considered non-eradicable but for which some important disease aspects could potentially be eliminated with existing tools (e.g., eliminating human rabies without or before eradicating rabies in wild animals). The information is based on published data reflecting 2008 determinations (
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cartercenter.org" id="intref0020" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.cartercenter.org</ext-link>), supplemented by additional widely available publications. Columns show disease features that favor eradicability (blue circles), are of uncertain relevance to eradicability (yellow), or are expected to make eradication more difficult or impossible (red). Some of these features (e.g., ease of detecting disease and immunity, seasonality in tropical versus temperate climates) are subjective and situationally variable; see text and references for the individual diseases.
   </p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="tspara0040">
   <p>
    <sup>∗</sup>Sterile immunity for life refers to the ability of a natural infection or vaccine to induce a type and degree of immunity that prevents infection/reinfection and eliminates carriage and transmissibility to others and to animal and environmental reservoirs.
   </p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
