<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Vesicular stomatitis virus (VSV) is a zoonotic 
 <italic>Vesiculovirus</italic> of veterinary importance in the family 
 <italic>Rhabdoviridae</italic>, which infects domesticated cattle, horses, and swine, and whose definitive natural host reservoir remains unclear (Rozo‐Lopez, Drolet, &amp; Londoño‐Renteria, 
 <xref rid="ece36287-bib-0053" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). The virus is transmitted between hosts via insect vectors, such as mosquitoes, sand flies, black flies, and biting midges, as well as through direct contact (Lyles &amp; Rupprecht, 
 <xref rid="ece36287-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>; Rozo‐Lopez et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36287-bib-0053" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). In addition, VSV provides a biological model for studying generalities of RNA virus evolution (Elena et al., 2001; Holland et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36287-bib-0067" ref-type="ref">1991</xref>; Morley, Sistrom, Usme‐Ciro, 
 <xref rid="ece36287-bib-0047" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Remold, Rambaut, &amp; Turner, 
 <xref rid="ece36287-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>; Turner &amp; Elena, 
 <xref rid="ece36287-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>; Turner, Morales, Alto, &amp; Remold, 
 <xref rid="ece36287-bib-0068" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Williams et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36287-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). VSV has an ~11kb negative‐sense ssRNA genome, encoding 5 proteins: the nucleocapsid (N) protein that tightly encapsidates the genomic RNA, phosphoprotein (P), and large (L) protein which make up the polymerase, glycoprotein (G) involved in cell‐surface binding and infection initiation via membrane fusion, and matrix (M) protein important for virion formation and inhibition of host antiviral gene expression (Rose &amp; Whitt, 
 <xref rid="ece36287-bib-0069" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>). In laboratory tissue culture, replication of wild‐type VSV on baby hamster kidney (BHK) cells is roughly equal at temperatures ranging from 28°C to 37°C, with virus populations achieving equivalent sizes in these environments (Alto &amp; Turner, 
 <xref rid="ece36287-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>).
</p>
