<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="d1e1585">We manually checked the fractal analysis results for each of the images analyzed for the best fit in the intermediate scale for accurate estimation of the D values with minimal bias. Of all the 55 images analyzed, we found for the 14 images the quality of fit over this range is relatively poor. In order to investigate how the ROI of the images influences the fit and hence the D estimates, we re-analyzed those 14 images by adjusting the ROI such that it includes the details of the viral features plus small contribution from the extracellular background. Results showed that a small change in the ROI in reference to the original one improves the quality of fit. 
 <xref rid="figA.1" ref-type="fig">Fig. A.1</xref> shows an example of fractal analysis applied to one of the CoV particle images (shown in 4th column, 
 <xref rid="fig2a" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2a</xref>) with two different ROIs (115 x 115 pixels and 125 x 125 pixels): a small increase in ROI slightly improves the quality of fit. The D values of both the datasets (original dataset of the 55 D values, and the same data set except with the 14 D values revised after introducing the change in ROI) are then subjected to the ANOVA and MANOVA analyses for testing the statistical significance of the changes induced by the ROI. On comparing the MANOVA test results for both the data sets (
 <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> for the original data set and 
 <xref rid="figA.2" ref-type="fig">Fig. A.2</xref> for the changed data set), we found the nature of dependence of viral features for classifying the nCoV particles is similar to that presented earlier, i.e., our primary results. This is evidenced from the similar estimates of the p-values: relatively large p-values for the shape and spike obtained separately, and small p-value for their interaction (
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="d1e1607" display="inline" altimg="si27.svg">
   <mrow>
    <msub>
     <mrow>
      <mi mathvariant="normal">p</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mrow>
      <mi mathvariant="normal">shape</mi>
      <mo>∗</mo>
      <mi mathvariant="normal">spike</mi>
     </mrow>
    </msub>
    <mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mo>
    <mn>0</mn>
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mn>0915</mn>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>, 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="d1e1630" display="inline" altimg="si28.svg">
   <mrow>
    <msub>
     <mrow>
      <mi mathvariant="normal">p</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mrow>
      <mi mathvariant="normal">shape</mi>
     </mrow>
    </msub>
    <mi mathvariant="normal">M</mi>
    <mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mo>
    <mn>0</mn>
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mn>4067</mn>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>, 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="d1e1651" display="inline" altimg="si29.svg">
   <mrow>
    <msub>
     <mrow>
      <mi mathvariant="normal">p</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mrow>
      <mi mathvariant="normal">spike</mi>
     </mrow>
    </msub>
    <mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mo>
    <mn>0</mn>
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mn>5558</mn>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>, see MANOVA Table in 
 <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> of the main text; 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="d1e1675" display="inline" altimg="si30.svg">
   <mrow>
    <msub>
     <mrow>
      <mi mathvariant="normal">p</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mrow>
      <mi mathvariant="normal">shape</mi>
      <mo>∗</mo>
      <mi mathvariant="normal">spike</mi>
     </mrow>
    </msub>
    <mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mo>
    <mn>0</mn>
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mn>0882</mn>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>, 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="d1e1698" display="inline" altimg="si31.svg">
   <mrow>
    <msub>
     <mrow>
      <mi mathvariant="normal">p</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mrow>
      <mi mathvariant="normal">shape</mi>
     </mrow>
    </msub>
    <mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mo>
    <mn>0</mn>
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mn>4177</mn>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>, 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="d1e1717" display="inline" altimg="si32.svg">
   <mrow>
    <msub>
     <mrow>
      <mi mathvariant="normal">p</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mrow>
      <mi mathvariant="normal">spike</mi>
     </mrow>
    </msub>
    <mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mo>
    <mn>0</mn>
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mn>3099</mn>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>, MANOVA Table in 
 <xref rid="figA.2" ref-type="fig">Fig. A.2</xref>). This comparison suggests that the influence of the ROI on the primary results presented is not statistically significant. Similar conclusions emerge from both the data sets when they are interpreted in terms of the relative changes in D values obtained.
</p>
