<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par43">This is an open-label cluster randomized controlled trial where the cluster is defined as the group of clinic(s) under the same PHC clinic supervisor, where each of the 16 PHC clinic supervisors may oversee between 3 and 5 PHC clinics. Cluster randomization was chosen for practical reasons because the study will be carried out in pragmatic settings involving 40 PHC clinics within the King Cetshwayo district (formerly called uThungulu) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>] and Ugu districts in KwaZulu-Natal, South Africa. A total of 11.1 million people (19.9% of the South African population) live in KwaZulu-Natal [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. The province has the highest TB-HIV disease burden in South Africa with an estimated TB-HIV co-infection rate of 70% [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. The two districts were selected because they are rural with high burden of TB, HIV, and TB-HIV co-infection, despite TB and HIV treatment services in accordance with current guidelines being available [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. In 2016, 82.3% of TB-HIV co-infected patients were initiated on ART in KwaZulu-Natal, slightly lower than the national ART initiation rate of 84.5% [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. King Cetshwayo district, located on the northern coast of KwaZulu-Natal, has a population of 937,793, with approximately 80% living in rural settings [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Similarly, Ugu district, situated in southern KwaZulu-Natal has 86% of its population of 750,214 living in rural areas [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. The in-hospital case fatality rate due to TB-HIV co-infection in both King Cetshwayo district (38.4%) and Ugu district (38.8%) remains high despite ART availability [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. In 2015, over a quarter of all deaths in KwaZulu-Natal, irrespective of age or gender, were caused by TB (15.5%) or HIV (12.2%). PHC clinics offer community level frontline services and chronic care for all health ailments, including TB and HIV. Patient level data for these diseases are routinely captured electronically [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>].
</p>
