<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Existing knowledge about spillover infection dynamics is generally very patchy. While many studies have been sufficient to establish the public health importance of the spillovers in a local context, many important puzzles remain, particularly when considering larger scales [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSTB20120228C27">27</xref>]. For example, bat lyssaviruses have been associated with fatal human encephalitis on almost every continent, while outbreaks or cases of encephalitis caused by henipaviruses have been confirmed in Australia, Southeast Asia and South Asia. Until recently, this distribution of outbreaks was expected as henipaviruses were thought to be confined to Australasia, southern Asia and Madagascar [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSTB20120228C28">28</xref>]. However, the discovery of henipaviruses in Africa [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSTB20120228C29">29</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSTB20120228C30">30</xref>] greatly increases the geographical range for the potential spillover to humans and other animals, adding to the recognized threats of lyssaviruses and filoviruses from bats in Africa [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSTB20120228C16">16</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSTB20120228C19">19</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSTB20120228C31">31</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSTB20120228C35">35</xref>]. Indeed, spillover in Africa may already be occurring; encephalitis often goes undiagnosed and defining its causality is not straightforward [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSTB20120228C36">36</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSTB20120228C37">37</xref>]. Studies increasingly demonstrate that cerebral malaria is often over-diagnosed and rabies under-diagnosed [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSTB20120228C38">38</xref>], as henipavirus or other unknown viral diseases might be. As recent reports of widespread seroprevalence to Ebola Zaire in healthy villagers in Gabon underline [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSTB20120228C39">39</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSTB20120228C40">40</xref>], some preconceived notions regarding the diagnosis, surveillance and potential for emergence of ‘feared’ pathogens are open to challenge. Knowledge of the infection dynamics of these pathogens in their natural hosts is essential to increase our understanding of spillover dynamics and to assess fully the implications for, and the protection of, public health.
</p>
