<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Host-vector-virus transmission systems are dynamic and typically evolve over time, and this seems to be occurring within the WNV-transmission system. As indicated, the invading virus acquired and retained at least one significant mutation that may have enhanced vector competence and perhaps transmission dynamics under warm [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B158-viruses-05-02079">158</xref>], but not necessarily moderate [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B159-viruses-05-02079">159</xref>] temperatures. In California, experimental infections of House Finches [an important maintenance host] comparing the replicative fitness phenotype of the invading WNV 2003 strain carrying a temperature sensitive allele [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B160-viruses-05-02079">160</xref>] against WNV isolates from four biomes made in 2007-2008 indicated that the founding strain has been replaced by more competitive strains as the virus invaded areas of California such as the Los Angeles Basin and the Central Valley where amplification in corvid populations was important for transmission (Worwa 
 <italic>et al.</italic>, unpublished). Interestingly, there seems to be little concurrent selection for viral change in replicative fitness in House Finches from the SE deserts or for replication within the vector, 
 <italic>Cx. tarsalis</italic>. In addition, repeated estimates of the ID
 <sub>50</sub> (virus dose required to infect 50% of exposed mosquitoes) among field 
 <italic>Culex</italic> populations for the NY99 strain of WNV during the invasion of California [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B161-viruses-05-02079">161</xref>] indicated that there was minimal concurrent change in the vector competence of 
 <italic>Cx. tarsalis</italic> and 
 <italic>Cx. pipiens</italic> complex field populations and that these changes were not associated with outbreaks of human disease. In contrast, progressive sweeps through susceptible avian species populations seem to have selected for resistant phenotypes. This notion was supported by reduced viremia and mortality among House Sparrows and House Finches during successive experimental infection studies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B103-viruses-05-02079">103</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B123-viruses-05-02079">123</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B126-viruses-05-02079">126</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B162-viruses-05-02079">162</xref>] (Worwa et al. unpublished). Among birds submitted by the public during the 2010–2011 seasons, these two species also showed a greater frequency of chronic than acute infections as indicated by qRT-PCR Ct scores at necropsy, indicating the frequent natural survival of acute infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B129-viruses-05-02079">129</xref>]. In addition, American crows have been collected with WNV antibody and some dead crows have shown elevated qRT-PCR Ct scores, perhaps indicating they also survived acute infection and died of other causes when chronically infected [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B129-viruses-05-02079">129</xref>]. Collectively, these data may indicate adaptive changes in avian populations that could reduce the efficiency of transmission unless offset by increases in the virus’s ability to infect vector populations. However, regardless of these apparent trends, the dramatic resurgence of WNV during 2012 certainly indicated that the WNV-transmission system has remained sufficiently intact throughout much of the USA to support widespread epidemic transmission.
</p>
