<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par51">In light of the major contribution of widespread coagulopathy and thrombosis to poor outcomes in COVID-19, the use of prophylactic doses of low-molecular-weight heparin (LMWH) has emerged as a valuable strategy for preventing the development of venous thromboembolisms. In a report from China published in preprint form, administration of LMWH to patients with COVID-19 improved indices of coagulation dysfunction and reduced levels of IL-6 (ref.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR234">234</xref>
 </sup>). As recommended by the International Society on Thrombosis and Haemostasis, the management of COVID-19- associated coagulopathy with LMWH should be accompanied by close monitoring of platelet counts, fibrinogen and the prothrombin time for the early diagnosis of bleeding
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR235">235</xref>
 </sup>, although bleeding seems to be rare in patients with COVID-19 (ref.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR236">236</xref>
 </sup>). A more promising approach than LMWH may be the serine protease inhibitor nafamostat mesylate, which is under investigation in four different clinical trials
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR237">237</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR240">240</xref>
 </sup>. This agent has short-acting anticoagulant effects and can limit viral infection and replication by inhibiting TMPRSS2 (ref.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR241">241</xref>
 </sup>). That fact TMPPRSS2 is a valuable therapeutic target in COVID-19 has been shown by an open-label randomized clinical trial documenting that early administration of oral bromhexine, a TMPPRSS2 inhibitor, reduces ICU admission, intubation and mortality
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR242">242</xref>
 </sup>. Alternatively, inhibition of platelet aggregation may represent another therapeutic avenue for patients with COVID-19. In support of this proposal, a small clinical trial conducted in China and published in preprint form showed that prophylactic anti-coagulation therapy supplemented by the anti-platelet drug dipyridamole prevented the progression of COVID-19 to severe stages of the disease by significantly increasing platelet and lymphocyte counts and decreasing D-dimer levels
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR243">243</xref>
 </sup>. Notably, through virtual screening of an approved drug library, dipyridamole was also found to suppress SARS-CoV-2 replication in vitro
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR243">243</xref>
 </sup>. Despite these promising findings, available clinical data suggest that anti-coagulation therapies might have only a partial effect on coagulopathy and thromboembolism in severe forms of the disease
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR244">244</xref>
 </sup>. For this reason, additional therapeutic interventions are needed to attenuate endothelial cell dysfunction and thromboembolic complications
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR145">145</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
