<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A number of reports have been devoted to comparative studies of the anti-influenza effectiveness of polysaccharides from several families of algae [
 <xref rid="B81-marinedrugs-17-00373" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. Song et al. [
 <xref rid="B82-marinedrugs-17-00373" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>] assessed 
 <italic>Grateloupia filicina</italic> (family Rhodophita), 
 <italic>Ulva pertusa</italic> (family Chlorophyta), and 
 <italic>Sargassum qingdaoense</italic> (Ochrophyta) in their studies. The yield of polysaccharide was 19.7% (
 <italic>G. filicina</italic>, GFP), 12.1% (
 <italic>U. pertusa</italic>, UPP), and 7.2% (
 <italic>S. qingdaoense</italic>, SQP). The content of sulphate groups in the polysaccharide was also different: 13.54% in UPP, 19.89% in GFP, and 5.64% in SQP. The structure of all three polysaccharides was established, and their biological activities were investigated in vivo and in vitro. The safe concentration for SQP and UPP was 5 mg/mL, and for GFP this was 2.5 μg/mL. The in vitro antiviral effects were evaluated against the H9N2 influenza virus. In the hemagglutination test, the most active were UPP and SQP. Under the action of these polysaccharides, the titer of influenza B virus decreased significantly. GFP was the most active in reducing virus replication and SQP was the least active. The most effective dose of the polysaccharide was 20 µg/mL. Using real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR), it was shown that the expression of the H9N2 gene was significantly reduced under the influence of the studied polysaccharides. The best inhibitory effect was observed with a GFP dose of 20 µg/mL. In the same study, the authors showed that all three polysaccharides had immunomodulatory potential as the studied polysaccharides were active in the spleen lymphocyte proliferation test. The greatest activity in this test was shown by SQP, the effect of which was dose-dependent. Maximum values were obtained when using the sulphated polysacchrides at a dose of 500 µg/mL. In the experimental group of mice treated with the polysaccharide, the levels of IFN-γ and IL-4 were significantly increased (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). All polysaccharides increased numbers of CD3+ and CD4+ lymphocytes in the blood compared to controls, but only SQP increased the level of CD8+ cells. Thus, the best effect was obtained with the polysaccharide of the brown alga 
 <italic>S. quingdaoense,</italic> especially at a dose of 50 mg/kg. The authors attributed this phenomenon to the presence of fucose residues in its structure, which play a significant role in immunomodulation [
 <xref rid="B83-marinedrugs-17-00373" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. The content of fucose in the PCA was 0.02, 0.05, and 1% for UPP, GFP, and SQP, respectively. The authors also observed immunological phenomena as such the proliferation of spleen cells and the humoral immune response, connected with the presence of fucose in these preparations. The more pronounced suppression of the replication of the influenza virus by the GFP polysaccharide was explained by the higher content of sulphate groups in the structure of this polysaccharide [
 <xref rid="B84-marinedrugs-17-00373" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>,
 <xref rid="B85-marinedrugs-17-00373" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. The authors suggest the use of all three polysaccharides as a potential alternative to vaccination, as well as to suppress the replication of the influenza virus.
</p>
