<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV S protein trimers can be self-assembled with the removal of nonionic detergent during the purification process to form NPs. Mice vaccination with these NPs induces high level of neutralizing antibodies, which increased significantly with adjuvants such as aluminum hydroxide (15-fold) or Matrix M1 (68-fold) [
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Adjuvants might also improve safety and immunogenicity with MERS-CoV vaccine [
 <xref rid="B123" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>]. Additionally, virus-like particles (VLPs), which are structurally similar to virus particles, but without a viral genome, are commonly used in vaccine development [
 <xref rid="B124" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>,
 <xref rid="B125" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>]. VLPs of MERS-CoV (MERS-CoV-LPs) have been developed via coexpression of S, E and M proteins in insect cells and consequent self-assembly of S protein-displaying NPs (100–200 nm) from cultured cells by mechanical extrusion [
 <xref rid="B126" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>]. Slight modification of these NPs with SARS-CoV-2 S protein enables NPs to attach ACE2 receptors instead of DPP4, stimulating the immune system. Another self-assembly of MERS-CoV-RBD fused with VP2 structural protein gene of canine parvovirus in insect cells produces RBD-displaying chimeric VLPs (50 nm), which are able to express RBD [
 <xref rid="B127" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>]. Thus, mice vaccination induced RBD-specific immune responses and the antisera could protect cells from MERS-CoV entry. Instead of insect cell as an eukaryotic host, bacterial expression systems can be used in nanovaccine assembly processes due to cost–effectiveness and simplicity [
 <xref rid="B128" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>,
 <xref rid="B129" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>]. Self-assembled NPs of MERS-CoV antigens (such as RBD of S protein) have been developed in bacterial systems using ferritin as a molecular scaffold [
 <xref rid="B128" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. RBD of S protein was fused with RNA-interaction domain and bacterioferritin to be expressed in 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> in a soluble form. Moreover, Chaperna (Chaperone + RNA) function can exploited for folding and assembly of ferritin monomers into Chaperna-based NPs, inducing mice immunization against CoV by interfering with binding of RBD to DPP4 receptor [
 <xref rid="B128" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. Bacterioferritin has the ability to self-assemble into octahedral nanocages, which are used as a delivery system with chemical refolding to avoid aggregation during viral antigens assembly [
 <xref rid="B130" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>,
 <xref rid="B131" ref-type="bibr">131</xref>]. Furthermore, self-assembled polypeptide NPs (25 nm) have been functionalized with SARS B-cell epitopes from the HRC1 of S protein to result in native trimeric conformation and produce very specific antibodies [
 <xref rid="B132" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>].
</p>
