<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0010">Influenza epidemics cause significant morbidity and mortality every year in older adults and those with underlying medical conditions. Influenza infections resulted in 48.8 million illnesses, more than 22.7 million medical visits, 959,000 hospitalizations, and 79,400 deaths during the 2017–2018 season in the US alone.
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref> Although vaccination is the most cost-effective preventive strategy against influenza infections, antiviral agents, specifically neuraminidase inhibitors, are the drugs of choice to treat influenza viral infections.
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>2</sup>
 </xref> To have the antiviral effects, oseltamivir, the neuraminidase inhibitor, needs to be administered within 48 h of diagnosis and given twice a day for 5 days or once daily for 10 days for those who come in contact with flu-infected patients. Recently, a new drug, baloxavir marboxil, marketed as Xofluza, which inhibits influenza viral polymerase, was approved to treat influenza infections, almost two decades after the approval of oseltamivir.
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref> Similar to oseltamivir, Xofluza needs to be administered within 48 h of influenza diagnosis. However, drug resistance has been a major issue with neuraminidase inhibitors, and a majority of circulating viruses during 2008 became resistant to oseltamivir prior to the 2009 pandemic.
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Circulation of drug-resistant strains of H1N1 and H3N2 against not only neuraminidase inhibitors but also against the newly introduced polymerase subunit inhibitor, Xofluza, have been reported.
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> The emergence of drug-resistant strains is of major concern because a severe epidemic or a pandemic with a drug-resistant strain can result in severe morbidity and a large number of deaths.
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>15</sup>
 </xref> Hence developing novel antiviral strategies is an immediate public health need.
</p>
