<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0175">In 2019, Kim et al. (
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2019</xref>) focused on the role of bisbenzylisoquinoline alkaloids extracted from 
 <italic>Stephania tetrandra.</italic> Previous studies demonstrated that three variants of these compounds have effect on different viruses. In particular, tetrandrine (TET) has effect on herpes simplex and dengue viruses (
 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Hu et al., 1997</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Liou et al., 2008</xref>); fangchinoline (FAN) has effect on HIV-1 (
 <xref rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr">Wan et al., 2012</xref>) and cepharanthine (CEP), possesses anti-viral activity against HIV-1 (
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Baba et al., 2001</xref>), herpes simplex (
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2004</xref>) and Ebola viruses (
 <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">Sakurai et al., 2015</xref>). The authors tested the same molecules against HCoV-OC43 infected MCR-5 cells (
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2019</xref>). These treatments showed that TET, FAN and CEP, inhibited cell death induced by HCoV-OC43 (at IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 0.33 ± 0.03, 1.01 ± 0.07, and 0.83 ± 0.07 μM, respectively). Moreover, all the three compounds suppressed the expression of S and N proteins and the viral replication (
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2019</xref>). In particular, the authors treated cells with TEN, FAN, and CEP at 24, 12, 6, and 3 h before HCoV-OC43 infection, during infection, and at 12, 24, and 48 h post-infection. They found that the three compounds had high antiviral activity from 3 h before the infection with HCoV-OC43. On the other hand, the treatments at 48 h post-infection revealed that the viability of cells was similar to that of the untreated group, for all the compounds, suggesting no antiviral effects after 48 h. Therefore, the authors suggested that TET, FAN, and CEP have antiviral activities in the range from 3 h before, to 48 h post HCoV-OC43 infection. These results indicate that three compounds are most effective at the early stages of the HCoV-OC43 life cycle. Moreover, the authors investigated the effects of the compounds on viral replication. They quantified the abundance of viruses in the supernatants and cell lysates by measuring the RNA levels of S and N proteins, revealing their decrease when comparing treated with non-treated cells.
</p>
