<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0075">RNA dependent RNA Polymerase (RdRp) is an enzyme that is responsible for the replication of RNA from an RNA template. RdRp is one of the nsp (nsp-12) that play an essential role in the life cycle of RNA viruses like hepatitis C virus, Zika virus, and coronaviruses 
 <xref rid="b0285" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0290" ref-type="bibr">[58]</xref>. In SARS-Cov-1 RdRp (nsp-12) functions as a tripartite polymerase complex with nsp-7 and nsp-8. The nsp7 and nsp8 activate and confer processivity to the RNA-synthesizing activity of nsp12. This tripartite polymerase complex further associates with nsp-14, which confers proofreading exonuclease function 
 <xref rid="b0295" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>. Remarkably, RdRp of SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 share 96% sequence similarity 
 <xref rid="b0300" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>. Therefore, it is very likely that the agents that target RdRp of SARS-CoV might also target the RdRp of SARS-CoV-2. Some of the compounds that target RdRp of SARS-CoV include favipiravir, ribavirin, penciclovir, galidesivir, remdesivir, among others (
 <xref rid="f0045" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref> ) 
 <xref rid="b0305" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>. Recently, ribavirin, favipiravir, penciclovir, and remdesivir were shown to inhibit SARS-CoV-2 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>, probably due to their inhibitory activity towards RdRp 
 <xref rid="b0310" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>. Several computer-aided molecular modeling studies have been done to find potential candidates that target RdRp of SARS-CoV-2. Elfiky et al. evaluated the effectiveness of antiviral agents to bind to SARS-CoV-2 RdRp through a combination of homology modeling and molecular modeling studies 
 <xref rid="b0315" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref>. The structures of the antiviral agents, along with their docking scores in kcal/mol, are given in 
 <xref rid="f0050" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref> . Datta et al. constructed a model of SARS-CoV-2 RdRp using sequence alignment and homology modeling and screened the model against antiviral drugs. Beclabuvir, an HCV RdRp inhibitor, was shown to bind effectively to SARS-CoV-2 with a docking score of −9.95 kcal/mol and inhibition constant of 51.03 nM 
 <xref rid="b0320" ref-type="bibr">[64]</xref>. Recently, the structure of RdRp of SARS-CoV-2 was resolved in complex with nsp-7 and nsp-8 by the cryo-EM 
 <xref rid="b0325" ref-type="bibr">[65]</xref>. The overall architecture of the SARS CoV-2 nsp12/nsp7/nsp8 complex was observed to be similar to the RdRp complex of SARS-CoV-1. Binding of remdesivir diphosphate, the RdRp inhibitor under clinical trials for the treatment of COVID-19, to SARS CoV-2 nsp12, was investigated based on modeling with sofosbuvir bound to hepatitis C virus (HCV) ns5b. The nsp12 of the SARS CoV-2 virus showed the highest similarity with the Apostate of ns5b. Sofosbuvir, a nucleoside prodrug, targets HCV ns5b polymerase and selectively binding catalytic site of the HCV polymerase. Sofosbuvir has been approved for the treatment of chronic HCV infection 
 <xref rid="b0330" ref-type="bibr">[66]</xref>. The catalytic site of SARS CoV-2 nsp13 shows remarkable structural similarity to HCV ns5b polymerase. The antiviral RdRp inhibitors (
 <xref rid="f0045" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>) are likely to target SARS CoV-2 RdRp and are excellent drug candidates for the treatment of COVID-19.
</p>
