<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recently, we provided evidence of arbovirus exposure in non-human primates in Western Kenya forests [
 <xref rid="B14-insects-11-00342" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. However, no isolates of CHIKV were obtained from mosquitoes of those regions during the current study, conducted at a similar time period. In fact, despite screening over 14,000 mosquitoes from 12 forest sites for evidence of either mammalian or insect-specific viruses, we found little evidence of arboviral infection in specimens from forested areas in Kenya, despite some of the mosquitoes collected being known vector species elsewhere (see below). Only one of the forest sites sampled (nearest to Nairobi) yielded virus-positive mosquitoes, with detection of six 
 <italic>Orthobunyavirus</italic> isolates, and one same pool of mosquitoes also being flavivirus positive, indicating co-infection status with that pool. The 
 <italic>Orthobunyavirus</italic> genus has the greatest species diversity of known virus genera, with widely distributed arthropod-borne viruses found in both hemispheres. Bunyaviruses are capable of infecting a wide range of vertebrate hosts, and include some important viral pathogens, which cause diseases of veterinary and human concern [
 <xref rid="B37-insects-11-00342" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-insects-11-00342" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Elsewhere in Kenya, numerous bunyaviruses have been detected, with evidence in both mosquitoes and livestock [
 <xref rid="B39-insects-11-00342" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-insects-11-00342" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-insects-11-00342" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Most 
 <italic>Orthobunyavirus</italic> activity in Kenya has been detected in the Northeast region, which is dry ecosystem, with little forested habitat except alongside the Tana River. Flaviviruses elsewhere have spilled over from their enzootic cycle—for example, WNV has frequently left its bird–mosquito transmission cycle to infect horses and humans (dead-end hosts) via a bridge-vector mosquito, resulting in neurological infections [
 <xref rid="B42-insects-11-00342" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Regarding the likelihood of false negatives during screening, it is possible that low-level viral RNA exists within mosquitoes. However, the passaging of samples within cell culture was expected to amplify infectious viral particles to a detectable level should they exist.
</p>
