<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To discuss some of the more notable vector species within sylvatic sites of Kenya, we highlight (i) 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> (
 <italic>stegomyia</italic>) spp., e.g., 
 <italic>Aedes africanus</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae. vittatus</italic>, which are arboreal mosquitoes found to be competent for CHIKV transmission [
 <xref rid="B43-insects-11-00342" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], and associated with a number of other alpha- and flavi-viruses [
 <xref rid="B44-insects-11-00342" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], and 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> as a key vector of CHIKV, YFV, DENV (although the latter was only detected at one forest site). (ii) 
 <italic>Aedes cumminsi</italic> is believed to be a vector of Spondweni virus and RVFV [
 <xref rid="B45-insects-11-00342" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], and an isolate of Middleburg virus was made from a pool of 
 <italic>Ae. cumminsi</italic> from forests in Senegal (Robin, 1969). (iii) 
 <italic>Culex</italic> spp. are often associated with WNV transmission and represented a large proportion of the mosquitoes collected, in particular 
 <italic>Cx. vansomereni</italic> (&gt;58% of catches in our study). This species was found to be a competent vector of WNV in the laboratory [
 <xref rid="B46-insects-11-00342" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. (iv) In neighboring Uganda, 
 <italic>Ae. tarsalis</italic> and 
 <italic>Coq. fuscopennata</italic> (both found in the study here) were sources of Pongola virus, which can cause febrile illness in humans [
 <xref rid="B47-insects-11-00342" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. (v) 
 <italic>Anopheles</italic> spp. are generally associated with transmission of malaria. However, 
 <italic>An. funestus</italic> and 
 <italic>An. gambiae</italic> are also vectors of ONNV, and this genera of mosquito is increasingly detected with arboviruses; transmission capability requires determination [
 <xref rid="B9-insects-11-00342" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. That a bunyavirus was detected here in a male 
 <italic>An. funestus,</italic> suggests that vertical transmission is occurring as a mechanism for virus persistence.
</p>
