<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Zika virus is mainly transmitted to humans through mosquito-borne vectors (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Vanlandingham et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Zanluca and Dos Santos, 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Kauffman and Kramer, 2017</xref>), though some human-to-human transmission has also been reported (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Song et al., 2017</xref>). Phylogenetic analyses of ZIKV identified African and Asian lineages, with the Asian lineage being responsible for the epidemics detected thus far (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al., 2016</xref>). These analyses have raised as yet unanswered questions. Firstly, given that it was initially identified almost 60 years ago, why is the virus only causing human epidemics now? Secondly, despite being initially isolated from Africa, why do ZIKV strains of the African lineage not cause epidemics? Thirdly, which viral factors are responsible for the severity of infection and subsequent congenital abnormalities? When the virus was first isolated, it was reported that it was non-virulent until its seventeenth passage in Swiss albino mice, suggesting that the virus may have to undergo several bouts of purifying selection to adapt to a new host (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Dick, 1952</xref>). The fact that data on Africa lineages is lacking further complicates our understanding of this virus, with Wetsman suggesting that the widely used African strain MR766 may not be truly representative of the original isolate (
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Wetsman, 2017</xref>). Wetsman also indicated that Asian strains have a more pronounced effect on the expression of genes involved in DNA replication and repair in neural cells than African strains. A phylogenetic analysis of ZIKV strains responsible for recent epidemics in Asia has further suggested that they have undergone several amino acid substitutions during either circulation in hosts or vectors, giving rise to several biological phenotypes (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al., 2016</xref>).
</p>
