<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Zika virus has biological similarities to other flaviviruses, such as West Nile virus, Japanese encephalitis virus (JEV) and dengue virus. ZIKV has an approximately 11 kb positive-stranded RNA genome, with untranslated regions flanking the 5′ and 3′ ends of its open reading frame. The genome is translated into structural proteins [capsid (C), precursor membrane (prM), and envelope (E)] and non-structural (NS) proteins (NS1, NS2A, NS2B, NS3, NS4A, NS4B, and NS5) [reviewed in (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2018</xref>)]. The NS proteins are mainly responsible for evasion of the host’s cellular innate immune response and for viral replication (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2017</xref>). The structural proteins are involved in the assembly of infectious virions and successful ingress and egress of host cells (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2008</xref>). ZIKV virion assembly involves: (i) prM interaction with E protein in the endoplasmic reticulum; (ii) encapsulation of the RNA genome with C protein and coverage with a lipid bilayer containing a prM-E protein complex to form immature virions; and (iii) cleavage of prM protein into M protein by furin or furin-like protease in the 
 <italic>trans</italic>-Golgi network before release of mature virions (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Pierson and Diamond, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2018</xref>). The prM proteins protect E proteins from premature fusion in the low-pH conditions during transportation in the 
 <italic>trans</italic>-Golgi network. Prior to virion release from the cell, cleavage of prM to M protein results in release of the 
 <italic>pr</italic> peptide, allowing rearrangement of E proteins into homodimers and facilitating virion maturation. Recent studies have revealed that ZIKV has a similar structure to other known flaviviruses (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Kostyuchenko et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Sirohi et al., 2016</xref>). A conserved region of prM protein has been identified among flaviviruses that has been shown to be critical for viral assembly (
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Yoshii et al., 2012</xref>). Therefore, inhibiting the function of prM during the viral lifecycle may incapacitate ZIKV infectivity and pathogenicity. ZIKV prM and E proteins are being used as antibody-activating epitopes in most of the ZIKV vaccines currently undergoing clinical trials (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2018</xref>). This short review seeks to highlight recent advances in our understanding of the role of ZIKV prM protein in virus pathogenicity and its use in vaccine development.
</p>
