<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>ZIKV transmission is closely connected to the abundance of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic>, so changes in the efficacy of vector control may coincide with shifting prevalence of ZIKV and other 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic>-transmitted viruses. Historically, vector control has affected the global ecology of YFV and DENV transmission. In 1901, aggressive vector control reduced YFV cases more than 50-fold in a single year, from 1,400 cases in 1900 to 37 cases in 1901 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005135.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], with similar results during construction of the Panama Canal [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005135.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Following World War II, the widespread availability of the pesticide DDT shifted public health responses to YFV from primarily emergency action to a large scale 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> eradication program in Central and South America [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005135.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. These efforts successfully eliminated 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and reduced outbreaks of YFV and DENV in large areas of the Americas from 1946 to 1970 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005135.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005135.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. A victim of their own success, vector control programs declined in the late 20th century [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005135.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], contributing to the dramatic resurgence of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and DENV incidence [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005135.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005135.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Further, the unregulated use of insecticides to control DENV outbreaks has since allowed widespread resistance to develop in 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic>, exacerbating existing problems with modern vector control even amidst growing concerns about pesticide use [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005135.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Clearly, effective and coordinated vector control is necessary to suppress mosquito populations and, by extension, epidemics of arboviruses.
</p>
