<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A number of authors have attempted to characterise the time taken to translate basic research findings into clinical practice; a review by Morris 
 <italic>et al</italic>
 <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> identified a number of studies reporting the time taken to translate health research, concluding that 17 years was the most likely estimate despite wide variation in definitions and marked differences in the time periods studied and approaches to data collection. However, few researchers have considered trends in drug development timeframes. Keyhani 
 <italic>et al</italic>
 <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> considered the time taken from the Investigational New Drug (IND) Application (a step required by the US Food and Drug Administration (FDA) prior to testing in humans
 <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>) to the filing of a New Drug Application
 <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> and subsequent FDA approval (the latter time points representing the regulatory review process). For all new drugs approved in the USA from 1992 to 2001, the authors found no increase in the time taken to conduct clinical trials prior to filing a New Drug Application (median 5.1 years) and a decrease in the time taken for the subsequent regulatory review and approval. Kaitin and DiMasi
 <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> considered a much longer time frame (1980–2009) and also found a decrease in time taken for regulatory review by the FDA. However, they found an increase in the clinical trial periods prior to filing (increasing from a mean 5.7 years for drugs approved in the USA 1980–1984, to 6.4 years for those approved 2005–2009) and concluded that this was due, in part, to increasing numbers of central nervous system and antineoplastic agents with very long average development times. However, the clinical trial periods prior to filing (ie, from IND application to filing a New Drug Application) for HIV antiviral agents also increased from a mean 2.3–5 years, and clinical trial periods for other anti-infective agents (including other antiviral drugs) increased from 4.2 to 6.6 years. More recent data on drug intervention trials registered with ClinicalTrials.gov suggests that trial lengths may have reduced in recent years (from 2 years for trials beginning in 2005 to 1.3 years for those beginning in 2009), but this trend was considerably less marked for industry sponsored trials, which are more likely to support the approval of new drugs.
 <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>
</p>
