<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Identified inhibitors of IE2-dependent transactivation do not inhibit IE1-dependent transactivation and are thus specific to IE2 not IE1 function [
 <xref rid="B364-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">364</xref>,
 <xref rid="B382-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">382</xref>,
 <xref rid="B383-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">383</xref>]. IE1′s function as an IFN antagonist has been targeted for drug discovery via a modular cell-based screening platform designed to identify compounds that inhibit a viral IFN antagonist choice [
 <xref rid="B373-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">373</xref>]. The platform utilizes two reporter cell-lines that provide a simple method to detect activation of IFN induction or signalling via an EGFP gene placed under the control of the IFN-β or an ISRE-containing promoter, respectively. IE1 counteracts type I IFN signalling by binding directly to STAT2 thereby preventing the ISGF3 transcription factor from binding ISRE elements in the promoters of ISGs (see 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec3dot4-viruses-12-00110">Section 3.4</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B225-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">225</xref>]. Therefore, a derivative of the IFN signalling reporter cell-line expressing IE1 was generated that blocks EGFP expression upon IFN signalling pathway activation. This reporter cell-line was used to screen a 16,000 compound library to identify compounds that release the IE1-imposed IFN response block and hence restore EGFP expression [
 <xref rid="B373-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">373</xref>]. Two hit compounds, StA-IE1-2 and StA-IE1-3, were identified and demonstrated to be potent inhibitors of HCMV replication [
 <xref rid="B373-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">373</xref>]. Compound characterization revealed that, instead of identifying anticipated IE1 IFN antagonist function inhibitors that target at the protein level, the compounds act at the mRNA level and interfere with IE1/2 transcription. The likely explanation is that IE1 expression was driven by MIEP sequences in the lentiviral vector used to create the IE1 reporter cell-line derivative. StA-IE1-2 and -3 are therefore also described in 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec6dot7-viruses-12-00110">Section 6.7</xref> concerning inhibition of IE gene expression. Despite the unexpected results, the assay platform had previously been used to identify compounds that specifically target the IFN antagonist function of Respiratory Syncytial Virus non-structural protein 2 [
 <xref rid="B373-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">373</xref>]. To the best of our knowledge, no other IE1-specific drug discovery screens have been undertaken.
</p>
