<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our risk perception is shaped by heuristics and more influenced by friends’ recommendations than mass media channels such as newspapers and television. Nevertheless, mass media have a tremendous importance in influencing individual behaviour probably because of the concept of the wisdom of the crowds, that is, the many are smarter than the few. Mass media is influenced by commercial trends, politics and the journalistic practice, for example, an article could appear in the first page in large characters or towards the end of the newspaper in a minor section; moreover, there is a journalistic tendency to draw attention to certain features of an issue while minimising attention to others. Social media is strongly influenced by our social constrains. Robin Dunbar and collaborators have found that social networks have a cognitive limit for emotional closeness of about 150 members (albeit with significant variance around this value); within a 150-people layer, there are those you know as persons. Beyond 150, we know people only as categories; interactions are defined by rules, not personal knowledge. Kin are given preference in the network where individuals from large families have fewer friends, and there are strong same-sex preferences. Kin networks are usually more dense than friend networks, suggesting that family links are less fragile than friends (reflecting the say that blood is not water) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. There is a widespread belief that social media have increased the amount and quality of information but also background rumours. Facebook, Twitter and other social websites have boosted the public awareness of disease outbreaks but also make it more difficult to separate facts from fiction. Many WHO experts have pointed out that social media are mixed blessing in epidemics. WHO officials reported that during the H1N1 swine flu that swept the world in 2009/2010, one of the Internet rumours was increasing your salt intake can help, consequently boosting a counteraction by WHO about the dangers of taking too much salt. Two important differences with respect to mass media are represented by specific information social networks for patients such as the website 
 <italic>PatientsLikeMe</italic> and flu tracker phone or Internet-based networks which act as a quick alarm network and continuous coverage statistics on the evolution of an epidemic front. The website 
 <italic>PatientsLikeMe</italic> acts as a quick self-diagnose based on symptomatic similarity and drug performance evaluation social network. The drawbacks could be mis-diagnoses and less personalised treatment (an individual takes the same drugs that have well performed for other patients disregarding his/her special conditions and past history of treatments). Although observational studies cannot meet the rigid standard of randomised clinical trials, they provide an opportunity to collect possibly useful data by capturing patients’ conditions. There is more trust in people with similar conditions and the heuristics of imitating likewise people. A recent work reported that a person’s overall web literacy predicts their behaviour to a significant extent. Especially for people with lower web literacy, the extent to which a web page’s declared ideological perspective was consistent with their own was very important for whether a person decided to believe the information posted on that web page. In [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>] the authors have proposed a susceptible (S)-infected (I)-hospitalised (H)-recovered (R) model where the media function is incorporated into the model using an exponentially decreasing function:
</p>
