<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>IFA was used for the diagnosis of SARS. The assay showed 100% sensitivity and 100% specificity in the detection of anti-SARS-CoV IgG in human serum samples when compared to RT-PCR [
 <xref rid="B150" ref-type="bibr">150</xref>]. Madhusudana et al. [
 <xref rid="B152" ref-type="bibr">152</xref>] developed IFA for the detection of anti-rabies virus antibodies in human serum and CSF. When compared to the mouse neutralization test, the assay demonstrated a sensitivity of 97.2% and a specificity of 97.9%. IFA was also used for direct detection of HSV antigen in clinical specimens with sensitivity of 84.6% and specificity of 95.7%, compared to the tissue culture method [
 <xref rid="B151" ref-type="bibr">151</xref>]. Moreover, IFA was applied for subtyping of influenza A virus with 100% agreement to RT-PCR [
 <xref rid="B153" ref-type="bibr">153</xref>]. IFA was also used for the detection of EBV [
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] and as a confirmatory test for HIV-1 [
 <xref rid="B154" ref-type="bibr">154</xref>]. Concerning DFA, in one study, it showed 60% sensitivity and 96% specificity in the detection of pandemic influenza A (H1N1) pdm09 in children when compared to RT-qPCR [
 <xref rid="B149" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>]. In another study, DFA showed high specificity (99–100%) in comparison to RT-qPCR for the detection of RSV in children [
 <xref rid="B155" ref-type="bibr">155</xref>]. IFA-based commercial test kit (Anti- ZIKV IIFT) is available, developed by Euroimmun AG (Germany), for the detection of ZIKV infection. The assay uses the complete ZIKV particles as antigen. Consequently, cross-reactivities with antibodies against viruses of the flavivirus family can occur. De Ory et al. [
 <xref rid="B156" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>] evaluated the performance of the assay using 126 positive and 102 negative samples. The assay showed 96.8% sensitivity and 72.5% specificity. OXOID Limited (UK) developed DFA-based kit (IMAGEN influenza virus A and B test) for the detection and differentiation of influenza A virus and influenza B virus in human specimens. The assay uses FITC labeled anti-influenza A virus or influenza B virus monoclonal antibodies. The assay has 100% sensitivity and 100% specificity, compared to the cell culture method.
</p>
