<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0160">In order to account for different levels of clinical detail collected at the ETUs, we constructed a family of prognostic models that range from models requiring only clinical signs/symptoms or age and viral load, to more complex models incorporating a mixture of laboratory data, signs/symptoms, and observational assessments from experienced health providers. The discriminative capacity of the models is robust across the training set and two independent validation sets, with AUCs ranging from 0.75 up to 0.80. Furthermore, these models recapitulate several findings reported earlier in the literature and also reveal further associations between mortality and clinical signs/symptoms. The most informative predictors of EVD outcome are patient age and viral load, and models incorporating just these two variables exhibit good performance. Occurrence of jaundice or bleeding at initial presentation are important predictors of death, but both have low incidence at triage among the patients in the IMC cohort of only 5%. In contrast, more widespread EVD manifestations such as dyspnea, dysphagia, and asthenia at triage have a much weaker correlation with mortality. Even though fever is a non-specific symptom with no predictive power, body temperature at triage is informative by increasing specificity in the predictions. The performance of models incorporating the clinical wellness score is at least comparable or superior to the more detailed models including individual clinical features deemed as the most predictive in our variable selection process. This is a particularly interesting result in our study, since it suggests that machine learning approaches, when properly designed and implemented, and applied on rich-enough data, could approximate the clinical intuition that physicians acquire through their experience in the field. Conversely, this also provides evidence that good bedside intuition can very effectively integrate the individual indicators of the patient's clinical status into an overall health assessment of great predictive power. These models may be useful in emergency situations when the appropriate experience is unavailable or under-developed.</p>
