<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>On January 2, 2003, a hospital in Heyuan city, Guangdong Province, reported two strange cases of severe pneumonia, which were then transferred to a larger hospital for further treatment. Several days later, seven medical staff members in the department that treated these patients developed symptoms. Retrospective investigation found that a hospital in Foshan had treated a similar case on November 25, 2002 [Supplementary Figure 2A]. This patient developed symptoms on November 16, 2002, and subsequently, five family members also developed symptoms. This indicated that SARS-CoV emerged with high human-to-human transmission capability, characterized by familial and medical staff infections.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
  <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]
 </sup> An investigation of family clustering identified 35 clusters involving 105 patients, in families with two or more family members in Guangzhou. The largest cluster was derived from a female patient. A total of 91 persons were infected due to visiting or nursing the female patient, and two of these people died
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]
 </sup> [Supplementary Figure 2B]. This indicated that the super virus spreader emerged at the earliest stage of the outbreak, confirming the high infection capability of the virus.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
  <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]
 </sup> Subsequent case investigations also showed that SARS-CoV had the capability to multiply and continuously undergo human-to-human transmission [Supplementary Figure 2C]; at least four generations of cases were identified from one original patient. Among the clusters of cases, healthcare workers were common victims.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]
 </sup> As of April 13, 2003, a total of 48 medical institutions had medical staff with SARS-CoV infection, and 33 medical institutions in Guangzhou reported a total of 283 cases. The incidence among medical staff in the respiratory care department of a university affiliated hospital in Guangzhou was 61.7% (29/47), that is, more than half of the medical staff were infected while treating their patients.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]
 </sup>
</p>
