<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our hierarchical phylogeographic estimates indicate that pairs of locations that are closer to each other tend to be involved in more extensive virus exchange on average. The time to travel between locations has previously been suggested the shape the geographic distribution of human viruses [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007976.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007976.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007976.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>] and railways have been suggested to play a role in the spread of HIV-1 in Central Africa [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007976.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Yet, the spatial distribution of subtype D most likely results from a single founder viral strain being introduced into Uganda. Although no subtype D 
 <italic>pol</italic> data are available from the north of the DRC, 
 <italic>env</italic> data indicate that subtype D is relatively prevalent in Bwamanda and Kisangani [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007976.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007976.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], with the latter being the closest DRC city to Uganda. Once introduced to Uganda, HIV-1 rapidly became established in the country, most likely spreading within structured transmission networks [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007976.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Socio-historical factors may have played an important role in the establishment HCV epidemics in the DRC during the 1950s [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007976.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], so it is possible that similar factors in Uganda [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007976.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>] may have facilitated the rapid expansion of subtype D in the country. With the advent of next generation sequencing and rapid generation of complete full genomes, we expect that data sets resulting from a larger and denser sampling will allow for a more detailed analysis of the historical and contemporaneous drivers of HIV-1 spread in Sub-Saharan Africa [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007976.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1007976.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>].
</p>
