<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Yellow fever virus is a mosquito-borne 
 <italic>Flavivirus</italic> that mainly persists in a sylvatic transmission cycle between forest mosquitoes (primarily 
 <italic>Haemagogus janthinomys, Hg. leucocelaenus</italic> and 
 <italic>Sabethes chloropterus</italic> in South America) and non-human primates, and occasionally spills over into human populations [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180335C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. In some settings, these spillover events lead to onward human epidemics in an urban transmission cycle between humans and 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180335C9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Spillover of yellow fever requires the virus to be transmitted locally, mosquito vectors to acquire the virus from infected non-human vertebrate hosts, survive the extrinsic incubation period, and feed on human hosts, and human hosts to be susceptible to infection following exposure. These events require distributions of reservoirs, vectors and humans, their interactions, and immune dynamics to align in space and time. In humans, yellow fever is the most severe vector-borne virus circulating in the Americas [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180335C10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], with an estimated fatality rate for severe cases of 47% [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180335C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. While no urban transmission of yellow fever has occurred in the Americas since 1997 [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180335C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] and in Brazil since 1942 [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180335C15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], a large epidemic began in December 2016 in Minas Gerais and by June 2018 had caused 2154 confirmed cases and 745 deaths [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180335C16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Despite these large case numbers, molecular and epidemiological evidence suggests that human cases were caused by spillover from the sylvatic cycle, rather than urban transmission [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180335C11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], most recently in areas previously believed to be free of yellow fever.
</p>
