<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0185">Zhao et al. studied the structural basis of antibody protection by passively transferring mouse-derived ZIKV-specific mAbs to C57Bl/6 mice prior to ZIKV challenge (
 <xref rid="bb0360" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al., 2016</xref>). They observed reduced viremia (by ~ 1–2 logs) and complete clinical protection as measured by weight loss and mortality. Sapparapu et al. isolated a panel of human mAbs isolated from subjects previously infected with ZIKV (
 <xref rid="bb0280" ref-type="bibr">Sapparapu et al., 2016</xref>). One of the mAbs, ZIKV-117, recognized a quaternary epitope on the E protein dimer-dimer interface. This specific mAb when administered to pregnant mouse dams, prior to ZIKV challenge, significantly reduced virus recovery from low to undetectable levels in placenta and fetal brain vs. dams receiving a control mAb. Our study described herein is in line with the Zhao and Sapparapu studies in that transferred ZIKV-specific antibody significantly protects against viral infection but may not provide sterilizing immunity. Taken together, these studies support ZIKV-specific antibody as a CoP against ZIKV infection and pathogenesis. The necessary level of ZIKV-specific nAb that must be achieved to prevent viral replication and protection of the developing fetus, even in animal models, is unknown. In part, it is difficult to directly compare animal study results due to different strains of mice used, different strains of ZIKV used for challenge, and the measure of neutralizing antibody by different assay methods. In our study, a log NT
 <sub>50</sub> serum antibody titer of approximately 125 was required for protection against weight loss, morbidity, and mortality. Studies are in progress to compare the ZIKV RVP luciferase-based assay used in this study to the standard Plaque Reduction Neutralization Test (PRNT) to determine correlation and bias between the assays. Shan et al., has developed a high throughput assay for ZIKV and dengue virus diagnosis that indirectly addresses this issue (
 <xref rid="bb0290" ref-type="bibr">Shan et al., 2017</xref>). Their assay utilizes luciferase viruses to quantify the neutralizing antibody titers in a 96-well format and found that neutralization titers derived from the ZIKV luciferase-based assay were on the average 2.5-fold higher than those derived from the corresponding ZIKV plaque assay. Further animal studies will be informative when evaluating the level of viremia the fetus can be exposed to vs. clinical outcome, but it may be that a vaccine strategy will be required that prevents any viremia to be truly effective against fetal injury.
</p>
