<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?OLF?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Travel Med Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Travel Med Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Travel Medicine and Infectious Disease</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1477-8939</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1873-0442</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier Ltd.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7128549</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S1477-8939(20)30074-0</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tmaid.2020.101607</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101607</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>COVID-19: Zoonotic aspects</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>Tauseef</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">Department of Epidemiology and Health Statistics, School of Public Health, Southeast University, Nanjing, 210009, China</aff><aff id="aff2">Key Laboratory of Environmental Medicine Engineering, Ministry of Education, School of Public Health, Southeast University, Nanjing, China</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Muhammad</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff3">Department of Genetics, Centre for Human Genetics, Hazara University Mansehra, Khyber Pakhtunkhwa, Islamic, Pakistan</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Haroon</surname></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff4">College of Life Science, Northwest University, Xian, China</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Musa</surname><given-names>Taha Hussein</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff5">Department of Epidemiology and Health Statistics, School of Public Health, Southeast University, Nanjing, 210009, China</aff><aff id="aff6">Key Laboratory of Environmental Medicine Engineering, Ministry of Education, School of Public Health, Southeast University, Nanjing, China</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name><surname>Nasir</surname><given-names>Saima</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff7">Allama Iqbal Open University, Islamabad, Islamic, Pakistan</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>Jin</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff8">Department of Epidemiology and Health Statistics, School of Public Health, Southeast University, Nanjing, 210009, China</aff><aff id="aff9">Key Laboratory of Environmental Medicine Engineering, Ministry of Education, School of Public Health, Southeast University, Nanjing, China</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name><surname>Bonilla-Aldana</surname><given-names>D.Katterine</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff10">Incubator in Zoonosis (SIZOO), Biodiversity and Ecosystem Conservation Research Group (BIOECOS), Fundaci&#x000f3;n Universitaria Aut&#x000f3;noma de las Am&#x000e9;ricas, Sede Pereira, Pereira, Risaralda, Colombia</aff><aff id="aff11">Public Health and Infection Research Group, Faculty of Health Sciences, Universidad Tecnol&#x000f3;gica de Pereira, Pereira, Colombia</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8"><name><surname>Rodriguez-Morales</surname><given-names>Alfonso J.</given-names></name><email>arodriguezm@utp.edu.co</email><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff12">Public Health and Infection Research Group, Faculty of Health Sciences, Universidad Tecnol&#x000f3;gica de Pereira, Pereira, Colombia</aff><aff id="aff13">Grupo de Investigaci&#x000f3;n Biomedicina, Faculty of Medicine, Fundaci&#x000f3;n Universitaria Aut&#x000f3;noma de las Am&#x000e9;ricas, Pereira, Risaralda, Colombia</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. Public Health and Infection Research Group, Faculty of Health Sciences, Universidad Tecnol&#x000f3;gica de Pereira, Pereira, Risaralda, Colombia. <email>arodriguezm@utp.edu.co</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>27</day><month>2</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>2</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><elocation-id>101607</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>2</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>19</day><month>2</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>2</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Elsevier Ltd</copyright-holder><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>2019-New coronavirus</kwd><kwd>Outbreak</kwd><kwd>Transmission</kwd><kwd>China</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p content-type="salutation">Dear Editor</p><p id="p0010">Coronaviruses can cause severe diseases in humans and animals, as has been stated recently by Biscayart et al. [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. China has experienced several viral outbreaks in the last three decades; avian influenza outbreak in 1997, severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) in 2003 [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], and severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome (SFTS) in 2010 [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In China, yet another pathogenic human coronavirus outbreak was reported in the city of Wuhan, Hubei province. Wuhan is an urban town located in the central part of China. It is one of the significant transportations and business hubs. In 2018, the city comprised of a population of approximately 11.9 million, and one of the seventh most populous Chinese city [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p><p id="p0015">On December 12, 2019, the Wuhan Municipal Health Commission (WMHC) reported 27 individuals infected by a new coronavirus designated initially as 2019-novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV), and later as Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) by the World Health Organization (WHO). Of the reported cases, seven were critically ill and had a history of exposure with the Seafood Wholesale Market.</p><p id="p0020">An early study conducted in January 2020, among 41 patients (median age 49 years), positive for SARS-CoV-2 infection (the causative agent of COVID-19), found that half of them had underlying diseases, including diabetes 20%, cardiovascular disease 15%, and hypertension 15%. Their symptoms were mainly fever 98%, cough 76%, and fatigue 44%. The COVID-19 severe complications in such patients included respiratory distress syndrome 29%, RNAaemia 15%, acute cardiac injury 12%, and other secondary infections. Of the total infected patients, 32% were admitted to an Intensive Care Unit (ICU). The death rate was 15% [<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p id="p0025">Emerging viruses that spread to humans from an animal host are proven to be some of the deadliest diseases known [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. COVID-19 is thought to be transmitted from the animals, though it has not yet been clear exactly from which animal, however the animals have been the sources of transmission as described in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>
. The recent finding shows that SARS-CoV-2 is 96% identical to a bat coronavirus [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. We aimed to discuss the zoonotic transmission of SARS-CoV-2 to humans.<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Potential transmission cycles of SARS-CoV2 (formerly 2019nCoV).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p><p id="p0030">In the last few weeks, the number of cases has been increased and pose a threat to public health. The region Wuhan is the potential hotspots of coronavirus infection in China. Daily, the number of cases has been significantly increased, and be tracked at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://gisanddata.maps.arcgis.com/apps/opsdashboard/index.html#/bda7594740fd40299423467b48e9ecf6" id="intref0010">https://gisanddata.maps.arcgis.com/apps/opsdashboard/index.html#/bda7594740fd40299423467b48e9ecf6</ext-link>. The overall case fatality rate has been stable for weeks less than 3%. However, an increased number of cases in China and outside posed an international emergency. Therefore, countries with limited resources prepared and strengthen the disease surveillance system to report and diagnose any case of COVID-19.</p><p id="p0035">Coronaviruses were identified in the mid-1960s and known to infect humans and other animals, including birds and mammals. Epithelial cells in the respiratory and gastrointestinal tract are the primary target cells. Due to these characters, viral shedding occurs via these systems and transmission can occur through different routes, i.e., fomites, airborne or fecal-oral. To date, seven coronaviruses have been shown to infect humans. Common human coronaviruses <italic>Betacoronavirus</italic> HCoV-OC43 and HCoV-HKU1, as well as Alphacoronavirus HCoV-229E, cause common colds and severe lower respiratory tract infections in infants and elderly, while <italic>Alphacoronavirus</italic> HCoV-NL63 is found to be a significant cause of (pseudo) croup and bronchiolitis in children [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p><p id="p0040">New zoonotic coronaviruses have emerged and caused outbreaks in humans; SARS-CoV (2002, <italic>Betacoronavirus</italic>, subgenus <italic>Sarbecovirus</italic>), and MERS-CoV (2012, <italic>Betacoronavirus</italic>, subgenus <italic>Merbecovirus</italic>). In late 2019, a novel coronavirus related to a cluster of pneumonia cases in Wuhan, China (2019-nCoV), was identified. After that the disease designed as COVID-19. The SARS-CoV-2 is closely related to SARS-CoV and genetically clusters within <italic>Betacoronavirus</italic> subgenus <italic>Sarbecovirus</italic> [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p><p id="p0045">An early study conducted by Li and colleagues reported that of the total 425 patients&#x02019; (median age was 59 years) highest number of cases, 55% had a history of Seafood Wholesale Market. Besides, 56% of patients were male, and the mean incubation period was 5.2 days. The Seafood market located at Wuhan, where different types of wild (snakes and marmots) and domesticated (poultry and bats) animals were sold illegally. Thus, suggested the disease may be transmitted from animals to humans (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). Till now, the specific source and reservoir of SARS-CoV-2 are not explicitly known yet.</p><p id="p0050">During the COVID-19 outbreak, although earlier transmissions were from the animals after reporting four individuals from Seafood Wholesale Market, all other transmissions are believed to be from human to human (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). This mode of transmission was so active that within a few days, it flew to other countries. A recent study identified human to human transmission of COVID-19. A Chinese (Shanghai resident) between January 19, 2020 and January 22, 2020 had visited Germany. During her stay in Germany, she developed no signs and symptoms of COVID-19, but she was tested positive after came back to China on January 26, 2020. On January 24, 2020, a 33 years old German businessman became ill had chills, sore throat, and myalgias. The patient history showed that he had a meeting with a Chinese business partner on 20 and January 21, 2020. Later, on January 28, 2020, another three employees at the company were found positive for COVID-19.</p><p id="p0055">Animal to human transmission can be reduced more quickly as compared to humans [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. In the recent outbreak, transmission from humans to humans increased many folds due to annual celebrations in China during which the movement of the masses increased allot. Human to human transmission can happen in several ways. It can be through the droplets from the cough or sneeze, surfaces of public transport, restaurants, and other public places (toilets, elevators, bus stops).</p><p id="p0060">As have occurred in the past with other zoonotic conditions [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], the spillover of a new coronavirus, SARS-CoV-2, is now significant. Originating in bats, current and previous coronaviruses, such as SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV, are a matter of concern in the interaction between animals and humans, with the future concern of new epidemics in China and abroad.</p><sec id="sec1"><title>Author contributions</title><p id="p0065">Conceptualization: TA and MK. Data curation: TA. Writing&#x02014;original draft preparation: TA. Writing&#x02014;review, and editing: TA, MK, H, THM, SN, DKB-A, and AJR-M. Supervision and funding acquisition: JH.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Ethical approval</title><p id="p0070">Approval was not required.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Funding source</title><p id="p0075">This study was financially supported by Jiangsu Provincial Six Talent Peak, grant number WSN&#x02010;002. The funder had no role in study design, data collection, drafting of the manuscript, and submission.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title><p id="p0080">
<bold>Tauseef Ahmad:</bold> Writing - original draft. <bold>Muhammad Khan:</bold> Writing - review &#x00026; editing, Writing - original draft. <bold>Haroon:</bold> Writing - review &#x00026; editing. <bold>Taha Hussein Musa:</bold> Writing - review &#x00026; editing. <bold>Saima Nasir:</bold> Writing - review &#x00026; editing. <bold>Jin Hui:</bold> Writing - review &#x00026; editing. <bold>D.Katterine Bonilla-Aldana:</bold> Writing - review &#x00026; editing. <bold>Alfonso J. Rodriguez-Morales:</bold> Writing - review &#x00026; editing, Writing - original draft.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="p0085">All authors report no potential conflicts. All authors have submitted the Form for Disclosure of Potential.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biscayart</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Angeleri</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lloveras</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaves</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlagenhauf</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez-Morales</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The next big threat to global health? 2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV): what advice can we give to travellers? - interim recommendations January 2020, from the Latin-American society for Travel Medicine (SLAMVI)</article-title><source>Trav Med Infect Dis</source><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101567</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodriguez-Morales</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonilla-Aldana</surname><given-names>D.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balbin-Ramon</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paniz-Mondolfi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabaan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sah</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>History is repeating itself, a probable zoonotic spillover as a cause of an epidemic: the case of 2019 novel Coronavirus</article-title><source>Inf Med</source><volume>28</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>5</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodriguez-Morales</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramirez-Jaramillo</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patino-Barbosa</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bedoya-Arias</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henao-SanMartin</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murillo-Garcia</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome - a bibliometric analysis of an emerging priority disease</article-title><source>Trav Med Infect Dis</source><volume>23</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>98</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>F.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Are we ready for the new fatal Coronavirus: scenario of Pakistan?</article-title><source>Hum Vaccines Immunother</source><year>2020</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>3</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bastola</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sah</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez-Morales</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lal</surname><given-names>B.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ojha</surname><given-names>H.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The first 2019 novel coronavirus case in Nepal</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><volume>20</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32057299</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>None.</p></ack></back></article>