<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Dealing with outbreaks and emergencies efficiently and promptly would require a very robust governance mechanism where the roles and responsibilities of each stakeholder are clearly laid out. Research must be responsive to affected communities and the officials must ensure appropriate, expedient and flexible mechanisms
 <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>. The framework would also facilitate close oversight, appropriate monitoring to entail activities such as adequacy of informed consent, adherence to approved protocols, collection of adverse events, ensuring the integrity of the collected research data, appropriateness of participant selection. A clear organizational chart defining responsibilities and flow of information with all stakeholders would help clarify right at the beginning, on who conducts, or who reviews the protocol scientifically and who monitors the study, or appoints Data and Safety Monitoring Board to function independently. An enabling network which can share, communicate, support, issue advisories, handle media concerns, reduce panic in the public and be effective in controlling the crisis in a time-bound manner can be of great value in an outbreak situation. It will cover provisions for data collection and analysis while ensuring that the conflicts of interests are managed. Since it is not possible to predict the region for outbreak or its extent in advance to support prior planning, holistic, well informed, and fast-track approaches at the central level are critical. Dealing with an outbreak may require an inter-ministerial master plan involving not only MoHFW but also other Ministries, Departments and Agencies. In ICMR, the Division of Epidemiology and Communicable Diseases has developed action plan in consultation with expert groups. The responsibilities of multiple stakeholders including those of sponsors, industry, NGOs, government and others must be clearly defined
 <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>. A governance framework for rapid response with collaborative planning and coordination can help define responsibilities of each stakeholder, encourage judicious use of resources, better planning and coordination to control the infection
 <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>.
</p>
