<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack id="ack0010">
 <title>Acknowledgements</title>
 <p>We thank Daniela Sartori for manuscript editing.</p>
 <p>The San Matteo Pavia COVID-19 Task Force: R. Bruno, M. Mondelli, E. Brunetti, A. Di Matteo, E. Seminari, L. Maiocchi, V. Zuccaro, L. Pagnucco, B. Mariani, S. Ludovisi, R. Lissandrin, A. Parisi, P. Sacchi, SFA Patruno, G. Michelone, R. Gulminetti, D. Zanaboni, S. Novati, R. Maserati, P. Orsolini, M. Vecchia(ID Staff); M Sciarra, E. Asperges, M. Colaneri, A. Di Filippo, M. Sambo, S. Biscarini, M. Lupi, S. Roda, TC Pieri, I. Gallazzi, M. Sachs, P. Valsecchi(ID Resident); S. Perlini, C. Alfano, M. Bonzano, F. Briganti, G. Crescenzi, AG Falchi, R. Guarnone, B. Guglielmana, E. Maggi, I. Martino, P. Pettenazza, S. Pioli di Marco, F. Quaglia, A. Sabena, F. Salinaro, F. Speciale, I. Zunino (ECU Staff Emergency Care Unit); M. De Lorenzo, G. Secco, L. Dimitry, G. Cappa, I. Maisak, B. Chiodi, M. Sciarrini, B. Barcella, F. Resta, L. Moroni, G. Vezzoni, L. Scattaglia, E. Boscolo, C. Zattera, MF Tassi, V. Capozza, D. Vignaroli, M. Bazzini (ECU Resident Emergency Care Unit); G. Iotti, F. Mojoli, M. Belliato, L. Perotti, S. Mongodi, G. Tavazzi (Intensive Care Unit); G. Marseglia, A. Licari, I. Brambilla (Pediatric Unit); DBarbarini, A. Bruno, P. Cambieri, G. Campanini, G. Comolli, M. Corbella, R. Daturi, M. Furione, B. Mariani, R. Maserati, E. Monzillo, S. Paolucci, M. Parea, E. Percivalle, A. Piralla,F Rovida, A. Sarasini, M. Zavattoni (Virology Staff); G. Adzasehoun, L. Bellotti, E. Cabano, G. Casali, L. Dossena, G. Frisco, G. Garbagnoli, A. Girello, V. Landini, C. Lucchelli, V. Maliardi, S. Pezzaia, M. Premoli (Virology Technical staff); A. Bonetti, G. Caneva, I. Cassaniti, A. Corcione, R. Di Martino, A. Di Napoli, A. Ferrari, G. Ferrari, L. Fiorina, F. Giardina, A. Mercato, F. Novazzi, G. Ratano, B. Rossi, IM Sciabica, M. Tallarita, E. Vecchio Nepita (Virology Resident); M. Calvi, M. Tizzoni (Pharmacy Unit); C. Nicora, A. Triarico, V. Petronella, C. Marena, A. Muzzi, P. Lago (Hospital Management).</p>
</ack>
