<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In general morbilliviruses are transmitted horizontally by the respiratory route or by contact with oral, respiratory, and ocular fluids and exudates containing the virus [
 <xref rid="B95-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>,
 <xref rid="B156-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>]. Close contact between affected and susceptible animals is probably required due to the relative fragility of enveloped PDV in the external environment. For the same reason, transmission by fomites is probably not common. The highly aggregated nature of seal haul out sites would certainly predispose them to aerosolized virus from infected conspecifics [
 <xref rid="B157-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>]. Depending on the species, seals aggregate seasonally for breeding and molting which would also favor transmission of a highly infectious respiratory virus. It is noteworthy that epidemics or outbreaks of PDV among harbor seals in both Europe and New England began in spring during the pupping/breeding season or at winter haulout sites [
 <xref rid="B41-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="B158-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>]. Other modes of horizontal transmission are also possible based on the distribution of PDV antigen in epithelia of the urinary tract and skin but these are probably relatively unimportant [
 <xref rid="B51-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B88-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. Transplacental transmission of morbilliviruses has been documented in dogs and is likely in cetaceans [
 <xref rid="B159-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">159</xref>,
 <xref rid="B160-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">160</xref>,
 <xref rid="B161-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">161</xref>]. However, while abortion and stillbirth were features of the harbor seal 1988 and 2002 epidemics, vertical transmission has not yet been documented in pinnipeds.
</p>
