<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The built environment (BE) is the collection of environments that humans have constructed, including buildings, cars, roads, public transport, and other human-built spaces (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Since most humans spend &gt;90% of their daily lives inside the BE, it is essential to understand the potential transmission dynamics of COVID-19 within the BE ecosystem and the human behavior, spatial dynamics, and building operational factors that potentially promote and mitigate the spread and transmission of COVID-19. BEs serve as potential transmission vectors for the spread of COVID-19 by inducing close interactions between individuals, by containing fomites (objects or materials that are likely to carry infectious diseases), and through viral exchange and transfer through the air (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). The occupant density in buildings, influenced by building type and program, occupancy schedule, and indoor activity, facilitates the accrual of human-associated microorganisms (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Higher occupant density and increased indoor activity level typically increase social interaction and connectivity through direct contact between individuals (
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) as well as environmentally mediated contact with abiotic surfaces (i.e., fomites). The original cluster of patients were hospitalized in Wuhan, China, with respiratory distress (December 2019), and approximately 10 days later, the same hospital facility was diagnosing patients outside the original cohort with COVID-19. It is presumed that the number of infected patients increased because of transmissions that potentially occurred within the hospital BE (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). The increased exposure risk associated with high occupant density and consistent contact was demonstrated with the COVID-19 outbreak that occurred on the Diamond Princess cruise ship in January 2020 (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Current estimates of the contagiousness (known as the R0) of SARS-CoV-2, have been estimated from 1.5 to 3 (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). R0 is defined as the average number of people who will contract a disease from one contagious person (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). For reference, measles has a famously high R0 of approximately 12 to 18 (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>), and influenza (flu) has an R0 of &lt;2 (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). However, within the confined spaces of the BE, the R0 of SARS-CoV-2 has been estimated to be significantly higher (estimates ranging from 5 to 14), with ∼700 of the 3,711 passengers on board the Diamond Princess (∼19%) contracting COVID-19 during their 2-week quarantine on the ship (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). These incidents demonstrate the high transmissibility of COVID-19 as a result of confined spaces found within the BE (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). With consideration to the spatial layout of the cruise ship, the proximity of infected passengers to others likely had a major role in the spread of COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>).
</p>
