<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Phylogenetics provides an insight into the HIV network structure including its transmission dynamics [
 <xref rid="pone.0172473.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Use of dated sequence data, coupled with demographic and clinical information allows to model characteristics of the epidemics including population-based patterns of HIV transmission [
 <xref rid="pone.0172473.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Dated sequence analyses from cohorts with known and unknown infection time, showed that early infection was associated with onward transmissions in 25–50% of cases [
 <xref rid="pone.0172473.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0172473.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0172473.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0172473.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. For above-mentioned purposes HIV-1 partial 
 <italic>pol</italic> sequences obtained from routine genotyping assays have been successfully used. Characterizing populations forming transmission networks allows to target interventions to the ones at risk. Using phylogeny relationship between various viral strains may be established with identification of closely interrelated subsets—phylogenetic clusters [
 <xref rid="pone.0172473.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Typically, a cluster contains all taxa—in case of HIV analyses patient derived sequences—descending from the similar lineage or ancestry [
 <xref rid="pone.0172473.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Using these clusters chronology of the spread viral clades spread may be visualized. Typically clusters are defined by the genetic discane between analyzed sequences and/or statistical support (bootstrap) within the inferred tree [
 <xref rid="pone.0172473.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0172473.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0172473.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In HIV medicine clustering dynamics may reflect changing patient mobility and allows to assess the efficacy of ART as prevention strategy [
 <xref rid="pone.0172473.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0172473.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0172473.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].
</p>
