<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>ANP32A and ANP32B are small 
 <underline>a</underline>cidic 
 <underline>n</underline>uclear 
 <underline>p</underline>hosphoproteins (ANPs) that are attributed to a plethora of cellular functions (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>), including chromatin remodeling (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), apoptosis (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>), transcription regulation (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), and intracellular transport (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). ANP32 proteins are approximately 250 amino acids in length and contain an N-terminal leucine-rich repeat (LRR) region, a central domain, and an unstructured low-complexity acidic region (LCAR) at the C terminus. ANP32 proteins have been associated with influenza A polymerase function. A nuclear fraction containing ANP32A and ANP32B was shown to enhance the synthesis 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> of vRNA from a short cRNA template (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Knockdown of ANP32A or ANP32B in human cells reduced polymerase activity measured in minigenome reporter assays, as well as synthesis of viral RNA in infected cells (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Direct interactions of ANP32 proteins with the RdRp or RNP have been documented but do not completely correlate with function (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). The difference between avian and mammalian ANP32A proteins has been suggested to account for host range restriction of avian influenza strains in mammalian cells, and much of the work to date has focused on the avian orthologues, particularly those from chickens (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>).
</p>
