<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="pone.0162112.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0162112.g003</object-id>
 <label>Fig 3</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Spatiotemporal dynamics of dissemination of HIV-1 B
   <sub>CAR</sub> clades circulating in the Caribbean and Brazil.
  </title>
  <p>A) Time-scaled Bayesian MCMC tree of 
   <italic>pol</italic> PR/RT sequences of HIV-1 B
   <sub>CAR</sub> lineages from Brazil (n = 97) and the Caribbean (
   <italic>n</italic> = 258), and subtype D reference sequences (
   <italic>n</italic> = 10) from the Democratic Republic of Congo. Branches are colored according to the most probable location state of their descendent nodes as indicated in the legend at right. Colored boxes indicate the positions of major B
   <sub>CAR</sub> clades detected in Brazil, Jamaica and Trinidad and Tobago. Branch lengths are depicted in units of time (years). The tree was automatically rooted under the assumption of a relaxed molecular clock. B) Lines between locations represent branches in the Bayesian MCC tree along which location transitions occurred and were colored according to the location of origin (see the legend at left). Maps were created from templates obtained from d-maps.com (Caribbean: 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://d-maps.com/carte.php?numcar=1389&amp;lang=en" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://d-maps.com/carte.php?numcar=1389&amp;lang=en</ext-link>; South America: 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://d-maps.com/carte.php?numcar=2313&amp;lang=en" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://d-maps.com/carte.php?numcar=2313&amp;lang=en</ext-link>; and Brazil: 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://d-maps.com/carte.php?numcar=4843&amp;lang=en" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://d-maps.com/carte.php?numcar=4843&amp;lang=en</ext-link>). AC: Acre; AM: Amazonas; AP: Amapá; CD: Democratic Republic of Congo; ES: Espírito Santo; GO: Goiás; HISP: Hispaniola; JM: Jamaica; MA: Maranhão; MG: Minas Gerais; MS: Mato Grosso do Sul; PA: Pará; PI: Piauí; RJ: Rio de Janeiro; RR: Roraima; RS: Rio Grande do Sul; SP: Sao Paulo; TO: Tocantins; TT: Trinidad and Tobago.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="pone.0162112.g003" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
