<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Today we know that rabies infections represent only one extreme of cross-species infections between bats and humans. It can be described as a single infection “spillover” event, hence the very low number of cases. Were it not for the dreaded consequences of this disease, it would probably not attract medical attention. A major barrier against viral spillover between species is the species barrier. Unfortunately, this concept is more a time confirmed empirical medical concept than a much investigated experimentally phenomenon. What leads to breaches in this barrier? One could imagine that spillovers occur primarily between species with high ecological contact rates. Alternatively, the height of the barrier might be determined by host genetics factors. Streicker and colleagues (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2010</xref>) have addressed this question by sequencing the nucleoprotein gene in nearly 400 rabies viruses isolated from 23 bat species. They identified 43 unambiguous cross-species infections. Their observations amount to one trans-species for every 73 within-species transmission events. These authors also observed that the intensity of the trans-species transmission declined continuously with the genetic difference between donor and recipient species. Transmission increased less with the extent of geographical overlap between species habitats. The authors concluded that the vast majority of the trans-species infections of bats with rabies virus are evolutionary dead-ends. From these data it appears that this highly mutable RNA virus does not represent a major concern for introduction of a bat virus into the human population. Can this relatively assuring conclusion be generalized to other viruses of bats? Unfortunately, the answer is No. In subsequent paragraphs, we will recognize cross-infections from bats that led to transient outbreaks (e.g. Nipah virus infections) and even sustained epidemics with the potential of endemic establishment (e.g. SARS corona virus) in the human population. There is another reason not to be complacent with bat rabies. Virologists from the Pasteur Institute in Paris, where Louis Pasteur had developed the first rabies vaccine, had sequenced many lyssaviruses (how rabies virus is called taxonomically) isolated from carnivoran and chiropteran (“finger-wings”, the systematical name of bats) hosts. The phylogenetic tree of the surface glycoprotein which is responsible for receptor recognition revealed seven genotypes (Badrane and Tordo 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2001</xref>). The long branches on the tree were all bat viruses. Genotype 1, the classical rabies group, was found in bats and carnivoran mammals. The carnivoran rabies viruses were all small twigs on the glycoprotein tree suggesting recent introduction. Using the tree, the authors deduced two spillover events, one into raccoons and another, independent event into the other carnivores (dog, fox, wolf, skunk, mongoose) which then spread worldwide without much diversification. Using molecular clock arguments, the authors dated this spillover to the time of the decline of the Roman Empire. They explained the fact that rabies was already described in cuneiform tablets in Mesopotamia 4,000 years ago by the hypothesis that this represented a spillover event with a rabies virus which became in the meanwhile extinct. In an even bolder hypothesis, the Pasteur authors speculated that bats had acquired the lyssaviruses from their insect prey. Indeed, rhabdoviruses are a prominent insect pathogen and another rhabdovirus, Mokola virus (known from two human case reports) was also isolated from an insectivorous mammal (this time a shrew) and this virus could be propagated on insect cells. According to the Pasteur scientists the spillover from insects to bats might have occurred 10,000 years ago.
</p>
