<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We fit the equation above to the frequency distribution of the total number of autochthonous infections (secondary and later generations) generated from each simulated introduction (by resident, visitor or mosquito). Distributions were defined by all independent introductions summed over 250 20-year runs of a given parameter scenario. In this analysis we jointly varied 
 <italic>p</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>esv</italic>
 </sub> (0.001, 0.01, 0.1), 
 <italic>mig</italic> (0, 0.08, 0.16) and vector production (based on observation in each of the 8 2-block patches followed 2007–2009). In each simulation mean annual birth rate varied randomly in the 0.5–0.20 interval, with random variation in each across household (+/- 0.05). We use Kolmogorov-Smirnov (KS) statistics to determine the best-fitting power-law exponent 
 <italic>a</italic> for each parameter scenario. This procedure computes the maximal distance (D) between the cumulative distribution frequency (CDF) of the data (the agent based model results) and the fitted model (
 <italic>x</italic>
 <sup>
  <italic>-a</italic>
 </sup>), based on the equation 
 <inline-formula id="pone.0144451.e001">
  <alternatives>
   <graphic xlink:href="pone.0144451.e001.jpg" id="pone.0144451.e001g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="M1">
    <mrow>
     <mi>D</mi>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mi>m</mi>
     <mi>a</mi>
     <msub>
      <mi>x</mi>
      <mrow>
       <mi>x</mi>
       <mo>&gt;</mo>
       <msub>
        <mi>x</mi>
        <mrow>
         <mi>m</mi>
         <mi>i</mi>
         <mi>n</mi>
        </mrow>
       </msub>
      </mrow>
     </msub>
     <mrow>
      <mo>|</mo>
      <mrow>
       <msub>
        <mi>S</mi>
        <mrow>
         <mrow>
          <mo>(</mo>
          <mi>x</mi>
          <mo>)</mo>
         </mrow>
        </mrow>
       </msub>
       <mo>−</mo>
       <msub>
        <mi>P</mi>
        <mrow>
         <mrow>
          <mo>(</mo>
          <mi>x</mi>
          <mo>)</mo>
         </mrow>
        </mrow>
       </msub>
      </mrow>
      <mo>|</mo>
     </mrow>
    </mrow>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
 </inline-formula>, where 
 <italic>S(x)</italic> is the CDF of the model output and 
 <italic>P(x)</italic> the CDF of the fitted model that best fit the data in the region 
 <italic>X&gt;Xmin [
  <xref rid="pone.0144451.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]
 </italic>. Comparison of 
 <italic>D</italic> across parameter scenarios provides a relative measure of how well they fit power law distributions, although it does not assign statistical significance to the parameter 
 <italic>α</italic>. The exponent 
 <italic>α</italic> gives a relative measure of the frequency of large relative to small outbreaks generated by a particular parameter combination.
</p>
