<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>When the E
 <sub>CW</sub> increases, the same airway driving pressure can generate different P
 <sub>L</sub> levels.
 <sup>(</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>
 </sup>
 <sup>)</sup> Nonetheless, the prediction of changes in P
 <sub>L</sub> from the airway driving pressure has shown satisfactory results.
 <sup>(</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>
 </sup>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>
 </sup>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>
 </sup>
 <sup>)</sup> Chiumello et al. observed an acceptable correlation between the two variables (r
 <sup>2</sup>: 0.737 and r
 <sup>2</sup>: 0.656, at 5 and 15cmH
 <sub>2</sub>O PEEP, respectively), determining that an airway driving pressure higher than 15cmH
 <sub>2</sub>O satisfactorily predicts pulmonary stress above the proposed limits for a protective ventilation with an area under the ROC curve of 0.864 (95% confidence interval: 0.801 - 0.929).
 <sup>(</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>
 </sup>
 <sup>)</sup> Such a finding corroborates a retrospective analysis in which the airway driving pressure showed a strong linear correlation with the transpulmonary driving pressure.
 <sup>(</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>
 </sup>
 <sup>)</sup> In turn, in a 24-hour follow-up, the patients who maintained high values of both airway and transpulmonary driving pressure had higher mortality, showing that the decrease in airway driving pressure exclusively responds to the improvement in the mechanical conditions of the lung.
 <sup>(</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>
 </sup>
 <sup>)</sup> Therefore, in a general population of patients with ARDS, the chest wall effect on the respiratory system mechanics is negligible.
 <sup>(</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>
 </sup>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>
 </sup>
 <sup>)</sup>
</p>
