<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A longer term risk factor is the gradual spatial creep of viruses due to transmission to previously uninfected species whose habitat spatially overlaps that of known infected species. For example 
 <italic>P. vampyrus</italic> are known hosts of NiV. They are not found outside of Asia, according to IUCN red list (see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-06-02084-f002">Figure 2</xref>), but have been reported in the Shaanxi region of China, close to where 
 <italic>M. daubentonii</italic> have also been recorded [
 <xref rid="B12-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. 
 <italic>M. daubentonii</italic> are also known to be present across Europe and there is a report of henipavirus antibodies in three of four 
 <italic>Myotis</italic> bat species at a location in Yunnan Province, southern China in 2006 and 2007. This included nine of 79 
 <italic>M. daubentonii</italic> bats [
 <xref rid="B67-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Although pteropid bats are not widespread in China, henipaviruses could be introduced to China by other susceptible bat species whose habitats and ranges overlap those of pteropid bats in neighbouring countries. This raises the question of whether henipaviruses could eventually emerge in European bats. However, there are a number of additional factors that may delay and/or prevent this from occurring, such as mountainous areas providing geographical barriers to interaction of neighbouring bat populations. Indeed according to the IUCN redlist the populations of 
 <italic>M. daubentonii</italic> in China and Europe are not contiguous. It would be interesting to know if bats in south-east Asia migrate in a north-westerly direction to the same regions as those migrant European bat species to give a “virus cross-roads”. The risk of EU bat infection with MARV due to overlapping species populations is potentially higher than NiV, due to shorter geographical distances, 
 <italic>R. aegyptiacus</italic> are already present in some European countries where their range may overlap with some migratory European bat species, and the fact that some African fruit bat species (e.g., 
 <italic>E. helvum</italic>) migrate large distances, although generally within the Sub-Saharan African continent [
 <xref rid="B150-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">150</xref>]. However, MARV has not been isolated from any bats in Cyprus or indeed Northern Africa, although there have been few published reports of attempts to find MARV outside its normal range. Additionally, MARV has not been isolated from as many different bat species as henipaviruses, so the risk of virus transfer between species may be more limited. This may reflect the ubiquity of molecular receptors for henipaviruses among mammal species.
</p>
