<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par9">Practitioners and researchers in the midst of overwhelming COVID-19 outbreaks are calling for new ways of looking at such pandemics, with an emphasis on human behavior and holistic consideration [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. While, in effect, any scientific model could be used to frame SARS-CoV-2 and COVID-19 to generate hypotheses and insights, some models are especially well-suited to thinking about pandemics and to expand comprehensive thinking beyond traditional — albeit useful — ways of looking at viral outbreaks. Pandemics are frequently characterized by intense focus on the evolution, transmission, survival, and pathogenic impact of the virus itself — indeed development of treatments and immunizations rely on understanding these biological elements. Viral outbreaks, however, are also characterized by more socio-behaviorally-oriented public health efforts aimed at reducing and eliminating exposure to the virus and prevention of morbidity and mortality once infected [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. These public health and behavioral efforts involve different forms of science and points-of-view, generally, than do those efforts attempting to understand the virus’ natural history. Often missing from scientific thinking around pandemics are the multi-leveled, complex notions surrounding social and cultural determinants of health and behavior, which focus beyond the individual and their cells to systematic and structural elements in society that additionally contribute to disease and its spread. Engulfing social determinants are power and economic relationships and processes, at micro and macro levels, that subsequently realign causal attention from individuals as the pandemic’s focus of control to larger population aggregations. All of these intersecting dimensions are overlapping, dynamic, and changing. But, whether or not an individual person dies from COVID-19 relates — in part — to them being exposed in the first place (a largely social-environmental phenomenon), the voracity of the virus pitted against one’s cells (a largely bio-pathogenic process), and the ability for that pathogenic process to be interrupted or attenuated (a mix of social and biological processes, including health care systems and practices).
</p>
