<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Over the past four decades, the global emergence and resurgence of arboviruses has become a burgeoning public health crisis. Dengue virus (DENV; family 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic>, genus 
 <italic>flavivirus</italic>), which began reappearing globally in the late 20th century, more than quadrupled in reported incidence from the 1980s–2000s and now causes an estimated 96 million symptomatic cases yearly [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005135.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0005135.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In 2013, chikungunya virus (CHIKV; family 
 <italic>Togaviridae</italic>, genus 
 <italic>alphavirus</italic>) emerged for the first time in the Americas in St. Martin, causing 1.8 million suspected and confirmed cases in the region [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005135.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. In 2015, Brazil confirmed the first case of locally acquired Zika virus (ZIKV; family 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic>, genus 
 <italic>flavivirus</italic>) infection in the Americas [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005135.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The ZIKV epidemic has since caused over 500,000 suspected and confirmed cases in 40 countries and territories in the Americas [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005135.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005135.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0005135.g001">Fig 1</xref>). Many ZIKV cases have likely gone unreported due to the initial low reporting, high proportion of asymptomatic cases (&gt;80%) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005135.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], and diagnostic challenges (including overlapping symptoms and immunological cross-reactivity with DENV, which is also a flavivirus). Since ZIKV and DENV antibodies are structurally similar, antibody cross-reactivity between ZIKV and DENV may even enhance ZIKV infection (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0005135.g002">Fig 2</xref>) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005135.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Mutations in the ZIKV genome may also contribute to ZIKV infection [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005135.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. As of now, mutations have been identified but none have been linked to the rapid spread of ZIKV or the severity of its complications [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005135.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], including microcephaly and Guillain-Barré syndrome (GBS) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005135.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005135.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. With strikingly similar paths of arrival and spread through the Americas, the ongoing DENV, CHIKV, and ZIKV epidemics represent a dangerous new pattern of arbovirus emergence and resurgence that demands renewed focus on the global ecology of vector transmission.
</p>
