<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>HIV-1 
 <italic>pol</italic> sequences were first analyzed using REGA HIV-1 Subtyping Tool–Version 3.0 (dbpartness.stanford.edu:8080/RegaSubtyping/stanford-hiv/typingtool/) for preliminary classification. Reference sequences were obtained from the Los Alamos National Laboratory HIV sequence database (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hiv.lanl.gov/components/sequence/HIV/search/search.html" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.hiv.lanl.gov/components/sequence/HIV/search/search.html</ext-link>). Alignments, composed by query and reference sequences, were built using the CLUSTAL method implemented in the AliView software [
 <xref rid="pone.0230878.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], followed by manual editing through BioEdit software [
 <xref rid="pone.0230878.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The nucleotide substitution models for each alignment were inferred by adopting the maximum likelihood (ML) statistical approach with the Bayesian information criterion implemented the MEGA 7 software [
 <xref rid="pone.0230878.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The general time-reversible plus gamma correction (G) and the proportion of invariant sites (I) (GTR + G + I) was the main evolutionary model selected for all alignments. Phylogenetic inferences were performed using maximum likelihood (ML) methods (PhyML) using Seaview version4 [
 <xref rid="pone.0230878.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Support branches’ values were computed with the approximate likelihood-ratio test (aLRT) based on the Shimodaira-Hasegawa-like test (SH-test) with Nearest neighbor interchange (NNI) algorithm selected for the tree search. Topologies of the phylogenetic trees were compared with those generated by the Neighbor-Joining (NJ) method under Kimura 2-parameter model with tree topology statistical support evaluated by 1000 replicates (bootstrap) using MEGA 7 software. The phylogenetic trees were visualized with Figtree version 1.4.3 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree/</ext-link>). Reference sequences used for phylogenetic analysis are described in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0230878.s001">S1 Material</xref>.
</p>
