<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This study shows that Singapore experienced a significant reduction in the dengue FOI between 1960 and 1990, followed by a steadily low FOI. The phenomenon is corroborated by the 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="kwz110ImEq36">
   <msub>
    <mrow>
     <mi>R</mi>
    </mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mn>0</mn>
    </mrow>
   </msub>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> estimates for the same period. The 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="kwz110ImEq37">
   <msub>
    <mrow>
     <mi>R</mi>
    </mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mn>0</mn>
    </mrow>
   </msub>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> estimate in Singapore is lower than estimates reported in other endemic places. For example, 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="kwz110ImEq38">
   <msub>
    <mrow>
     <mi>R</mi>
    </mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mn>0</mn>
    </mrow>
   </msub>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> has been estimated to be 1.35 or more in Thailand, Sri Lanka, and Brazil (
 <xref rid="kwz110C26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). A reduction in FOI could be due to an aging population in which the birth rate decreased very significantly and life expectancy increased, resulting in increased herd immunity due to fewer susceptible new births and a concurrent increase in immune individuals as a proportion of the population (
 <xref rid="kwz110C33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Indeed, Singapore has seen a rapidly aging population in the last 4 decades. However, there has been a reduction in seroprevalence in Singapore despite the changing age structure. Not surprisingly, the relatively small reduction in the overall prevalence of dengue does not corroborate with the large drop in age-specific prevalence seen through the same period. Together, these findings suggest that the lowering of the transmission rate indicated by FOI estimates is not mainly driven by a change in age structure, that the reduction in the FOI cannot solely be attributed to changing demographics, and that the evolving age structure may have prevented a more drastic decrease in seroprevalence. Singapore’s stringent vector prevention and control regime, which has continued to evolve to respond to the increasing challenge and involves the community in reducing levels of the vector (
 <xref rid="kwz110C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>), is one possible explanation for some of the reduction in transmission risk.
</p>
