<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0090">- 
 <bold>Interleukins</bold> are a family of cytokines involved in immune cells differentiation and activation. They mediate the traffic of immune cells to the site of the infection, induce the increase of the acute phase signaling, activate epithelial cells and mediate the production of secondary cytokines [
 <xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Among them, Interleukin-6 (IL-6) deserves a more extensive discussion in view of its involvement in the coronavirus-induced cytokine storm. IL-6 is crucially involved in acute inflammation due to its role in regulating the acute phase response [
 <xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. It is produced by almost all stromal cells and B lymphocytes, T lymphocytes, macrophages, monocytes, dendritic cells, mast cells and other non-lymphocytic cells, such as fibroblasts, endothelial cells, keratinocytes, glomerular Mesangial cells and tumor cells [
 <xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The production of this cytokine is increased by IL-1β and tumor necrosis factor (TNF- α) [
 <xref rid="bib0115" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. IL-6 may also be responsible for the activation of T helper 17 (TH17) cells in the dendritic cell-T cell interaction [
 <xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In COVID-19 affected patients, a high TH17 cells activation could result from a virus-driven increased production of IL-6 by the immune system. IL-6 plays a key role in the pathogenesis of the cytokine storm owing to its pleiotropic properties. Several studies showed that the serum levels of IL-6 are increased in COVID-19 patients and that its circulating levels are positively related to disease severity [
 <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0125" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0130" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. For this reason, high serum IL-6 levels were suggested as predictors for disease severity [
 <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0140" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Indeed, in animal models of SARS-CoV infection, the inhibition of the transcription factor of IL-6 and, in turn of its production, was associated with reduced mortality [
 <xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].
</p>
