<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015">Two reports [
 <xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] describe conjunctival congestion or conjunctivitis in patients with confirmed COVID-19, and those with SARS-CoV-2-positive serologies had ocular secretions with the virus (
 <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> ). This suggests that SARS-CoV-2 can cause an inflammation of 
 <bold>conjunctiva</bold> that lines the inside of the eyelid and covers the white part of the eye, causing redness and itchiness in the eye. However, correlations between conjunctivitis and COVID-19 could also be confounded by co-correlation with unobserved factors. The pathomechanistic link between SARS-CoV-2 infection and conjunctivitis is not clear yet either. Nevertheless, further studies highlighted the importance of recognizing possible early ocular manifestations and suggested to stay highly vigilant to recognize the early manifestation of COVID-19 including consideration of viral conjunctivitis as a possible presentation [
 <xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. We suspect that the conjunctivitis cases caused by SARS-CoV-2 are underestimated for several reasons: (i) not necessarily all patients with conjunctivitis but without typical COVID-19 symptoms (cough, fever, respiratory symptoms) will be clinically evaluated. Though irritating, conjunctivitis rarely affects vision and many will opt for self-treatment of symptoms. We also have to take into account that often patients with symptoms of conjunctivitis associated with mild systemic symptoms (mild fever or cough) take measures to quarantine and will never be medically evaluated. (ii) To date, we have no data regarding how many patients with conjunctivitis (who did or did not attend the eye emergency department) developed COVID-19 in the following days. (iii) During the COVID-19 epidemic, ophthalmologists may have to deal with patients affected by conjunctivitis of other nature and have no guidelines on how to make a differential diagnosis.
</p>
