<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18">Several authors already focused on BVDV spread at a regional scale, using either a statistical or a mechanistic approach. Using statistical modelling, both neighbourhood contacts and trade movements were highlighted as contributing to virus spread at large scale with contrasted results in dairy vs. beef cattle herds [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Combining statistical analyses and mechanistic modelling, the impact of the dynamical trade network on BVDV spread was particularly investigated, pointing out the role of purchasing young animals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. It was shown that strategies regulating animal trade should target either high-movement farms [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>] or specific productive systems [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] to achieve efficient control. However, the respective contribution of both routes to new herd infections was not assessed neither related to herd characteristics. Although both within and between-herd infection dynamics were explored accounting for neighbourhood contacts and animal movements [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], herd heterogeneity and actual trade movements were not incorporated in that study which considered a homogeneous and rather small metapopulation of herds, a situation in which trade movements were shown to largely overpass neighbourhood contacts in explaining BVDV spread and persistence. Very recently [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], available data from the Irish eradication programme were reviewed and the expected added-value of modifying the current control strategy was quantified using an expert system model derived from a model developed in [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. The authors proposed an original model of BVDV spread at large scale, but did not focus on the investigation of virus propagation and persistence within and between populations, which thus remains quite poorly documented at such scales.
</p>
