<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There are a number of limitations of our study. First, we used serologic data to infer the occurrence of A(H3N2) infections based on 4-fold or greater rises in HAI titers, but this approach may have missed some infections [
 <xref rid="pone.0197504.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0197504.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Some A(H3N2) infections are associated with low rises in HAI titers [
 <xref rid="pone.0197504.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], and therefore we may have underestimated the cumulative incidence of infections. Second, we relied on self-reported vaccination status, and we investigated the serologic data for evidence of rises in HAI titers against A(H1N1) and A(H3N2) all together which might be indicative of vaccination rather than infection. There were no participants in epidemics 1 to 4 having such a result. These were excluded from the estimation of cumulative incidence of infections, but we may have failed to identify vaccinations in a small number of other participants. Third, our participants may not be representative of the general population because of biases in participation. We did enroll using random digit dialing to select potential participants at random from the population, but the response rate was low. Self-reported vaccination coverage in our participants was considerably higher than the general population, and we excluded vaccinated participants when estimating the cumulative incidence of infection. Fourth, the study rounds of sera did not neatly bracket each A(H3N2) epidemics and we were not able examine the two small A(H3N2) epidemics in 2011 and early 2014, or A(H3N2) infections that occurred outside the four major epidemics that we identified in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0197504.g001">Fig 1</xref>. Epidemics overlapping study rounds may underestimate or overestimate the number of infections in the epidemic following or preceding the study rounds, respectively. We are actively developing statistical techniques that can characterize these smaller epidemics with these irregular follow-up timings. Finally, we did not examine A(H1N1) or B in this study, because our focus was on A(H3N2), but cross reactive antibodies to these strains may have affected titers to A(H3N2).
</p>
