<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Flaviviruses are enveloped positive sense single-stranded RNA (+ssRNA) viruses that package their ~11 kb genome into individual virus particles that are approximately 50 nm in diameter [
 <xref rid="B2-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The virions enter the cell via receptor-mediated endocytosis and fuse with the endosomal membrane, releasing viral nucleocapsid into the cytoplasm [
 <xref rid="B1-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Uncoating is complete when the genome is released from the capsid proteins. The viral genome contains a single open reading frame that must be translated at the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) membrane as a viral polyprotein [
 <xref rid="B6-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] to generate the viral proteins including the RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRP) required for genome replication (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pathogens-09-00042-f001">Figure 1</xref>A). Thereafter, the positive sense genome can be either used to generate a negative-sense template or for translation. Both during and after translation into the ER membrane, the polyprotein is processed to produce 10 viral proteins: three structural (capsid: C, pre-membrane: prM, and envelope: E), as well as seven non-structural proteins (NS1, NS2A, NS2B, NS3, NS4A, NS4B, and NS5). This yields three soluble viral proteins in the cytoplasm: C, NS3 (protease/helicase), and NS5 (RdRP with methyl-transferase activity) as indicated by red boxes in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pathogens-09-00042-f001">Figure 1</xref>B. Following synthesis of nascent positive-sense genome in the cytoplasm, the RNA is encapsidated into nucleocapsid particles which begin budding into the ER lumen. These particles traverse through the secretory pathway, undergoing furin-mediated cleavage of prM to produce mature virus particles that are expelled from the cell via exocytosis (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pathogens-09-00042-f001">Figure 1</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B6-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].
</p>
