<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As a highly specialized organ present only during mammalian pregnancy, the placenta creates an environment that is suitable for fetal growth and development through tight regulation and coordination. The placenta, which is located at the interface between the mother and the fetus, takes on a broad range of functions, such as respiration, excretion, and protection, and gives rise to different cell types during the developmental process to carry out its duties. The placenta is comprised of both maternal and fetal tissues, which are derived from the endometrium and chorionic sac, respectively, and the intervillous space located between the two regions contains placental villi that are essential for maternal–fetal exchange [
 <xref rid="B1-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Trophoblasts are the precursor cells that lead to human placental cells and originate from the outer layer of the blastocyst, which is a structure that forms after the embryo is fertilized and develops into the placenta surrounding the fetus contained inside [
 <xref rid="B3-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Thus, trophoblasts, among many cellular components of the placenta, are mainly responsible for placental structure and functionality. Since the placenta regulates the supply of nutrients directed towards the growing embryo, malfunctions in the placenta can result in complications such as miscarriage, stillbirth, preterm birth, and abnormalities of fetal growth and development including fetal growth restriction (FGR) and microcephaly [
 <xref rid="B4-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Furthermore, pregnancy-related complications are often caused by a combination of multiple factors involved in placental development. Therefore, greater understanding of the placenta, along with its implications in fetal development, especially on a cellular and molecular level, is necessary to address these complications.
</p>
