<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Dengue re-emerged in mainland China in 1978, after more than 30 years’ absence. Since then, outbreaks and epidemics have been reported from time to time in varying scales, mainly in south China such as in Hainan province and Guangdong province [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004473.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. In these periods, the two most severe outbreaks occurred in 1980 and 1986, before incidence rates of dengue became relatively stable and low after 1990 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004473.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. However, peak outbreaks were documented in Guangdong province again during 2013 (total 4,662 cases in mainland China, 62.08% in Guangdong province) and 2014 (total 48,162 cases, 93.83% in Guangdong province) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004473.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0004473.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Lai et al. [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004473.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] showed that the average annual incidence rate of dengue in mainland China from 1990 to 2014 was 2.2 cases per million people, while roughly calculated average annual incidence in Guangzhou reached as high as 29.14 cases per million from 2006 to 2013 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004473.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0004473.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], and 2888.57 cases per million in 2014 alone (37,305 indigenous cases [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004473.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] among 12,9368 million residents [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004473.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]). Average annual incidence rate of dengue in Zhongshan is also higher than the national level, with a rate of 30.46 cases per million people from 1990 to 2014, according to our estimate (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0004473.s003">S1 Table</xref>). In order to reduce dengue incidence in these cities, it is important to analyze the relationship of epidemics between these cities, to find any potential factor influencing the transmission of dengue and to set up an early warning system to initiate timely interventions.
</p>
