<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack>
 <title>Acknowledgements</title>
 <p>We would like to acknowledge the Epidemiology and Surveillance Division, Ministry of Health Uganda for their support during this study. We also thank the Word Health Organization, Uganda Country Office. Their tireless support in retrieving relevant records and documentation made this work possible. We also would like to thank all the national and district IDSR trainers for the job well done. This study is published with approval from the Ministry of Health Uganda.</p>
 <sec id="FPar1">
  <title>Funding</title>
  <p id="Par85">Funding for the work described in this paper was obtained from various partners and initiatives including the DFID, WHO-AFRO, the continuum of care for Reproductive Maternal Newborn Adolescent and Child Health (RMANCH), USAID, UNICEF, the Global Polio Eradication Initiative and the Central Emergency Response Fund (CERF) through the World Health Organization Country Office for Uganda. The funders however, had no role in the study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of this manuscript.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar2">
  <title>Availability of data and materials</title>
  <p id="Par86">The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available and can be obtained from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar3">
  <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate:</title>
  <p id="Par87">The study was requested by the Uganda Ministry of health. The study protocol was approved by the Uganda national task force on epidemics and PHEs and it was determined not to be human subjects’ research. We sought appointments to interview respondents via telephone calls and emails. We provided respondents with information about the study and only interviewed them after obtaining verbal consent. Respondents were informed and assured that their participation was voluntary and their refusal would not result in any negative consequences. Approval to publish this manuscript was obtained from the office of the DGHS, Ministry of Health Uganda through the commissioner, National Disease Control.</p>
 </sec>
</ack>
