<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="ppat.1007760.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1007760.g001</object-id>
 <label>Fig 1</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Characterization of the 
   <italic>in vitro</italic> anti-EV-A71 activity of MADAL385.
  </title>
  <p>
   <bold>(A)</bold> Structural formula of MADAL385. 
   <bold>(B)</bold> Concentration dependent inhibition of EV-A71 BrCr replication. RD cells were infected with EV-A71 BrCr (MOI = 0.1) for 1h in presence of the compound, after which the inoculum was removed, and cells were treated with serial dilutions of MADAL385. After 3 days, viral progeny was quantified by end-point titration. Statistical analysis was performed using the one-way ANOVA test; ****p&lt;0.0001. 
   <bold>(C)</bold> Antiviral activity of MADAL385 in the context of mCherry-EV-A71 reporter virus infection (MOI = 0.1). Images were taken with a fluorescence microscope at 24h post infection. 
   <bold>(D)</bold> Binding (left panel) and internalization (right panel) inhibition assays. The graph represents the RNA levels relative to the untreated-infected group (VC). Statistical analysis was performed using the one-way ANOVA test; ***p&lt;0.001, ****p&lt;0.0001. 
   <bold>(E)</bold> Thermo-stability assay. EV-A71 viruses, in the presence/absence of compounds (at a concentration of 50-fold 
   <italic>in vitro</italic> EC
   <sub>50</sub>: 15 μM MADAL385, 150 μM suramin and 15 μM pirodavir), were subjected to heat-inactivation at the indicated temperature for 2 min, after which the samples were cooled down on ice. Viral titers were quantified by end-point titration. Pirodavir and suramin were used as reference compounds. Statistical analysis was performed using the two-way ANOVA test in reference to the Pirodavir treament; *p&lt;0.05, ****p&lt;0.0001. Error bars represent the mean ± standard deviation (SD) of at least 2 independent experiments with three replicates.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1007760.g001" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
