<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The host innate immune system encounters upcoming infections, and this results in elevated production of various cytokines and type I interferons (IFNs). In the case of prolonged infection, hyperactivation of the immune system may also result in the development of a pro-inflammatory microenvironment, leading to adverse outcomes and even death. The induction of numerous lymphokines, such as IL-6, IL-1β, TNF-α, and CCL2, that are pro-inflammatory in nature has also been observed in the case of COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="B189" ref-type="bibr">189</xref>–
 <xref rid="B191" ref-type="bibr">191</xref>). A previous study in a MERS animal model showed that treatment with recombinant type-1 IFN (rIFN) decreased the viral RNA level in lungs with a decrease in IFN-stimulating gene expression. Early treatment with rIFN resulted in a dampening of cytokine and chemokine release that lowered the migration of neutrophils and other cells in lung (
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>). An allogenic mesenchymal stem cell-based (Remestemcel-L) therapy developed by Mesoblast, which has been previously used for inflammatory conditions and graft vs. host disease in children and adults, is now being assessed for COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="B192" ref-type="bibr">192</xref>–
 <xref rid="B194" ref-type="bibr">194</xref>). In this therapy, bone marrow-derived MSCs from the donor are grown 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and are then transfused to the recipient patients. Upon infusion, these cells exhibit anti-inflammatory activity by reducing pro-inflammatory cytokine production via the recruitment of anti-inflammatory cells in the affected tissue (
 <xref rid="B195" ref-type="bibr">195</xref>). Currently, a randomized placebo-controlled trial (NCT04371393) with 300 patients is ongoing for treating ARDS caused by COVID-19. Treatment with rIFN, inhibitors of the pro-inflammatory pathway, cytokine inhibitors such as tocilizumab, lenzilumab, and many others are still to be used in combination with other drugs for treating COVID-19. So far, there is not much evidence from clinical trials of such inhibitors with which to predict the outcome of these anti-cytokine therapies.
</p>
