<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A recent study evaluated the use of oral administration of rFeIFN-ω for the treatment of eleven client-owned, naturally FIV-infected cats with clinical signs [
 <xref rid="B108-vetsci-02-00456" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. The treatment protocol was 10
 <sup>5</sup> U/cat PO q 24 h for 90 consecutive days, administered by the cats’ owners. A historical retrospective group was used as a control for comparison (10
 <sup>6</sup> U/kg SC q 24 h on five consecutive days for three cycles), but a placebo group was not included. Treatment with oral rFeIFN-ω resulted in a significant improvement in clinical scores (e.g., oral lesions, coat appearance, body condition score, and ocular discharge) after treatment. In addition, there was no significant difference between the SC historical control group and the PO group, suggesting that oral administration of rFeIFN-ω might be a viable and less expensive alternative [
 <xref rid="B109-vetsci-02-00456" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. In a recently published study that assessed viremia, provirus load, and blood cytokine profile in naturally FIV-infected cats treated with oral rFeIFN-ω (10
 <sup>5</sup> U/cat PO q 24 h for 90 days) or with subcutaneous rFeIFN-ω (10
 <sup>6</sup> U/cat SC q 24 h for 5 consecutive days in three courses), no change in the level of viremia or in most cytokine levels was found; a placebo control group was not included [
 <xref rid="B109-vetsci-02-00456" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. The fact that virus load remained unchanged but some clinical improvement was observed in earlier studies suggests that rFeIFN-ω has an effect on secondary infections rather than on FIV itself [
 <xref rid="B94-vetsci-02-00456" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. As there are major differences in outcomes of the different studies on feline IFN-ω in FIV-infected cats. Thus, a definitive conclusion cannot be drawn without additional randomized, placebo-controlled, and double-blinded studies that include a sufficiently high number of naturally FIV-infected cats.
</p>
