<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="T0002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/21505594.2019.1697136-T0002</object-id>
 <label>Table 2.</label>
 <caption>
  <p>General principles regarding the use of antiretroviral (ARV) drugs during pregnancy.</p>
 </caption>
 <!--OASIS TABLE HERE-->
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <col width="1*" align="left"/>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">1. All pregnant women living with HIV should initiate ARV triple combination as early in pregnancy as possible, regardless of their plasma HIV RNA copy number or CD4 T lymphocyte count. 
     <italic>Earlier viral control is associated with lower risk of transmission</italic> (see 
     <xref rid="T0001">Table 1</xref>). An additional 4–6-week ﻿monotherapy is given to the neonate.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2. Maternal HIV viral load should be maintained below the limit of detection at all time points of pregnancy including antepartum and intrapartum as well as postnatally in case of breastfeeding to the neonate. Mother is encouraged to maintain the treatment after delivery even if the child is not breastfed.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">3. Whenever possible, ARV drug-resistance genotype studies should be systematically performed before starting ARV drug regimens, including in women who are ARV naive, but treatment is initiated before results and adapted secondarily if necessary.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">4. Previously treated women should continue their current regimens unless they include drugs known or suspected to be embryotoxic or new molecules for which there are no data on toxicity during pregnancy. Physicians are encouraged to visit updated guidelines. PK of some ARV changes in pregnancy; it may lead to lower plasma levels of drugs and necessitate increased dosages, more frequent dosing, boosting, or more frequent viral load monitoring.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">5. In high-income countries, it is recommended to completely avoid breastfeeding, regardless of ART and maternal viral load. In resource-limited settings, maternal ARV treatment reduces the risk of transmission through breastfeeding.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">ARV preferred choice (2019)</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">
     <italic>Mother</italic>: Two nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors (NRTIs)
     <sup>a</sup> associated with either a protease inhibitor (PI)
     <sup>b</sup> or an integrase strand transfer inhibitor (INSTI)
     <sup>c</sup>. Alternative choices are possible. In countries with limited health resources, non-nucleodide reverse transcriptase inhibitor (NNRTI)
     <sup>d</sup> as the third drug is still an option.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">During delivery: NRTI
     <sup>e</sup> perfusion, only if the maternal viral replication before delivery is not controlled. Pre-labor C section can also be discussed in this specific situation.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">
     <italic>Newborn</italic>: NRTI
     <sup>f</sup> or NNRTI
     <sup>g</sup> monotherapy during 2–6 weeks. Dual or triple combination if untreated mother or in case of maternal uncontrolled viral replication at delivery (high risk of transmission)
     <sup>h</sup>.
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <fn>
   <p>
    <sup>a</sup>ABC: abacavir + 3TC: lamivudine or TDF: tenofovir + FTC: emtricitabine.
   </p>
  </fn>
  <fn>
   <p>
    <sup>b</sup>rDRV: darunavir or rATZ: atazanavir, both boosted by ritonavir.
   </p>
  </fn>
  <fn>
   <p>
    <sup>c</sup>RTG: raltegravir or DTG: dolutegravir (DTG is contraindicated during the first trimester of pregnancy).
   </p>
  </fn>
  <fn>
   <p>
    <sup>d</sup>EFZ: efavirenz or NVP: nevirapine.
   </p>
  </fn>
  <fn>
   <p>
    <sup>e</sup>Intravenous perfusion of AZT: zidovudine.
   </p>
  </fn>
  <fn>
   <p>
    <sup>f</sup>AZT zidovudine.
   </p>
  </fn>
  <fn>
   <p>
    <sup>g</sup>NVP nevirapine.
   </p>
  </fn>
  <fn>
   <p>
    <sup>h</sup>AZT zidovudine + NVP nevirapine. Expert advice for triple therapy or in case of resistance on maternal viral isolate.
   </p>
  </fn>
  <fn>
   <p>Adapted from Ref. [
    <xref rid="CIT0020">20</xref>–
    <xref rid="CIT0022">22</xref>].
   </p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
