<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The structures of 1615 FDA approved drugs are obtained from the ZINC database. The database was then checked for redundant molecules. The three-dimensional crystal structure of SARS-CoV-2 main protease (Mpro,3CL
 <sup>pro</sup>) was collected from the RCSB Protein Data Bank (PDB) database (PDB-ID:6LU7, Resolution = 2.16 Å, Method: X-ray diffraction, Organism: Bat-SARS like coronavirus) (Zhang et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). The crystal structure of Mpro was prepared according to previously published methods for molecular docking (Islam et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Potential active site residues were specified by their vicinity to the ligand, N3 (Sekhar, 
 <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). PyRx Virtual Screening Tools incorporated with Autodock Vina was used for virtual screening (Dallakyan &amp; Olson, 
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Structural optimization of the drugs was carried out with universal force field (UFF) using the steepest descent optimization algorithm, a total of 2000 minimization steps (Ahmed et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). These drugs were converted to AutoDock ligand (PDBQT format) for docking. The grid center points were set to 
 <italic>X</italic> = −11.5693, 
 <italic>Y</italic> = 14.9663, 
 <italic>Z</italic> = 67.9041 and box dimensions (Angstrom) 
 <italic>X</italic> = 34.6857, 
 <italic>Y</italic> = 45.2264, 
 <italic>Z</italic> = 42.8980. Grid box center points and dimensions were set to target the substrate binding-binding pocket of the protein (Chen et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). The binding affinities of the drugs were measured in kcal/mol unit and sorted according to the higher negative values, which imply the best binding affinities (de Sousa et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Based on calculated binding affinities, the 31 top-ranked potential drugs were chosen for further analysis. The top-ranked drugs were then optimized by Gaussian 09 software using semi-empirical PM6 method (Frisch, 
 <xref rid="CIT0600" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). These optimized drug structures are then docked again using AutoDock Vina software and GOLD (Jones et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>) docking programs. The molecular interactions of the drugs as predicted by docking simulation were analyzed in BIOVIA Discovery Studio Visualizer (Studio, 
 <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>).
</p>
