<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our mouse vaccination results showed an increase in the avidity and magnitude of antibodies targeting the vaccine H3N2‐2013 HA, H1N1‐2009 HA and NA, and more importantly an induction of cross‐reactive H3N2‐1968 HA and H3‐stem antibodies by A‐eIIV. We further confirmed the induction of antibody cross‐reactivity by the induction of neutralising anti‐HA stem antibodies using a chimeric H9/1N3 virus.
 <xref rid="cti21107-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">22</xref> Furthermore, challenge of mice with the heterologous H3N2‐1968 virus showed substantial early recall of IgA antibodies to the site of infection. Altogether, these data reinforce the findings on the effect of the MF59 adjuvant of A‐eIIV increasing the breadth and cross‐reactivity of vaccine responses.
 <xref rid="cti21107-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">11</xref> MF59 is an oil‐in‐water emulsion that enhances the persistence of the vaccine antigens at the injection site and subsequently increases the activation of antigen‐presenting cells.
 <xref rid="cti21107-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">30</xref> We found that MF59 induces an earlier and higher expression of AID, the enzyme responsible for antibody SHM and CSR in the GC, together with Bcl6, Pax5 and c‐Myc, leading to an elevated GC reaction and magnitude of Tfh‐ and GC B‐cell responses. Because of the enhanced expression of AID and related transcription factors involved in GC development, we observed an enhancement of the avidity of cross‐reactive H3N2‐1968 HA and H3‐stem IgG by A‐eIIV, and an earlier class switch from the default IgM towards the IgG isotype, which did not occur in other vaccine groups. Expression of AID and other genes of the CSR process plays a vital role for protection from influenza infections, as AID
 <sup>−/−</sup> mice showed severe morbidity with delayed virus clearance compared with AID
 <sup>+/−</sup> mice.
 <xref rid="cti21107-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">31</xref> As these important B‐cell transcription factors are induced in the local LN by A‐eIIV and not S‐IIV, the adjuvant promotes the GC reaction, SHM and CSR to generate high‐quality antibody responses.
</p>
