<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The cellular receptors of rubella virus and most alphaviruses are not known. In Sindbis virus, laminin and the laminin receptor precursor have been identified as receptors on the surface of chicken fibroblasts, but other cellular proteins also bind the virions; in the case of rubella virus, specific phospholipids on the cell surface seem to be involved in binding the virus. The virus particles penetrate into the cells by receptor-mediated endocytosis. The interior of endocytotic vesicles (endosomes) is acidified in an energy-dependent process through the import of H
 <sup>+</sup> ions. This generates conformational changes of the viral envelope proteins which lead to the fusion of the viral envelope with the endosomal membrane, resulting in the release of the capsid. How the tight interaction of C proteins with the RNA genome is abolished is not known. However, the polarity of the positive-sense RNA allows binding of the cellular cap-binding complex via the cap structure at the 5′ terminus and the association with ribosomal subunits, which initiate translation of the sequences encoding the non-structural polyprotein. This polypeptide is synthesized on ribosomes in the cytoplasm, it associates with the ER membrane by hydrophobic amino acid sequences and the palmitoylation in the NSP1 moiety, and is cleaved by the cysteine protease present in NSP2 (alphaviruses) or p150 (rubella virus) into the individual components. As soon as the activity of the RNA-dependent RNA polymerase is present in the form of functionally active NSP4 protein, the negative-sense RNA is synthesized. In Sindbis virus, the NSP4 protein forms a complex with the uncleaved NSP polyprotein (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig001418" ref-type="fig">14.18a</xref>). The initiation occurs at the 3′ end in a highly conserved nucleotide sequence, which is located directly upstream of the poly(A) tail. In addition, nucleotides from the untranslated sequences at the 5′ terminus seem to be involved. These are partially complementary to sequences at the 3′ end and can form a partial double-stranded RNA, thus leading to circularization of the genome. Cellular proteins influence the initiation of RNA synthesis at the 3′ end: phosphorylated forms of the cellular protein calreticulin bind to the 3′ end of the rubella virus genome. The details of initiation of RNA synthesis are unknown; however, it is clear that in the further course of the replication process an RNA product which is complementary to the whole genome is generated. This process occurs on the ER membrane.
</p>
