<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par32">Rotavirus A (RVA) is the most frequent cause of severe diarrhoea in human and animal infants worldwide and remains as a major global threat for childhood morbidity and mortality (Minakshi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2005</xref>; Basera et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2010</xref>). In recent years, extensive research efforts have been done for the development of live, orally administered vaccines. In India, an orally administered vaccine ROTAVAC was also introduced after successful clinical trials in 2014 which became available to clinicians in 2016, although these vaccines will have to be scrutinized and have to be updated regularly to accommodate the emerging rotavirus genotype variations, following which molecular and genetic characterization of new circulating and emerging genotypes of rotavirus strains in humans and animals becomes necessary. Recently, a classification system for RVAs has been described by the Rotavirus Classification Working Group (RCWG) in which all the 11 genomic RNA segments are assigned a particular alphabet followed by the particular genotype number. The classification system will be helpful in explaining the importance of genetic reassortments among RVAs, host range, transfer of gene segments among two different genotypes and adaptation to different hosts. To differentiate between different gene segments of RVAs, an online web-based tool RotaC was developed by the leading researchers from Rega Institute, KU Leuven, Belgium, in 2009 (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">23.3</xref>). It’s an easy-to-use and reliable classification tool for RVAs and works on the agreement with RCWG. It’s a platform-independent tool which works on any web browser by simply going to its URL (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rotac.regatools.be/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://rotac.regatools.be/</ext-link>) and has been released without any restriction of use by academicians or anyone else. As claimed, the RotaC web-based tool will be updated regularly to reflect the established as well as newly emerging genotypes announced by the RCWG from time to time.
</p>
