<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Eighteen Arabidopsis accessions were used (
 <xref rid="plants-08-00304-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Ten accessions represented the Eurasian geographic distribution of the species and the remaining eight represented its distribution in the Iberian Peninsula, a Pleistocene glacial refuge for Arabidopsis [
 <xref rid="B62-plants-08-00304" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Plant seeds were surface-sterilized (see below) and stratified for seven days at 4 °C in pots of 15 cm of diameter, 0.43 L volume containing 3:1, peat:vermiculite mix. Afterwards, pots were moved for seed germination and plant growth to a greenhouse at 22 °C, under 16 h light. Plants were mechanically inoculated, either with 
 <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> TuMV- and CMV-infected tissue ground in 0.1 M Na2HPO4 + 0.5 M NaH2PO4 + 0.02% DIECA, or with inoculation buffer for mock-inoculated plants. Inoculations were done when plants were at developmental stages 1.05–1.06 [
 <xref rid="B63-plants-08-00304" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. After inoculation, plants were placed in two greenhouse modules: One with light intensity of 120–150 mol s/m
 <sup>2</sup> (low light), and the other with light intensity of 250–300 mol s/m
 <sup>2</sup> (high light). These conditions were chosen such that simulated light as a limiting factor [low light, 54] and no light limitation [high light, 25]. In both light conditions, plant accessions conformed two allometric groups as previously described [
 <xref rid="B25-plants-08-00304" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Since plant allometry has been repeatedly reported as a relevant factor to understand Arabidopsis tolerance to virus infection [
 <xref rid="B9-plants-08-00304" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], allometric group was considered as a factor in all analyses. For each Arabidopsis accession and light condition, seven to ten plants per virus were inoculated, and other seven were mock inoculated. All individuals were randomized in the greenhouse.
</p>
