<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several studies have, therefore, tried to demonstrate the association between influenza and SCA through laboratory confirmation of influenza infection; the results, however, did not always seem convincing. However, these are evidences deriving from case–control studies which, as such, are limited by defects (bias) of selection, confounding factors, and reduced sample size. In 1980, Pönkä 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <xref rid="suaa064-B5" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref> conducted a case–control study including a total of 49 patients with myocardial infarction (MI) subjected to the determination of the antibody titter for 22 viruses including that for Influenza A. From the results of the study, there were no significant differences in the antibody titter between patients with AMI and controls. Therefore, this limited series of cases did not confirm the hypothesis that a viral infection, including that with Influenza A virus, was associated with AMI. Macintyre 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <xref rid="suaa064-B6" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref> then designed a case–control study in which the cases were represented by subjects with AMI, while the controls were ambulatory subjects without AMI. The primary outcome measure was laboratory evidence of influenza infection. Of 559 participants, 34/275 cases and 19/284 controls were positive for laboratory virus determination for influenza virus [odds ratio (OR) 1.97; 95% CI: 1.09–3.54]; for statistical analysis; however, the flu infection was not a significant predictor for AMI. A case–control study conducted in China in 2012 showed instead that patients with AMI had, compared to controls, an OR for the determination of antibodies for Influenza A and B, respectively of 5.5 (95% CI: 1.3–23.0) and 20.3 (95% CI: 5.6–40.8). Although this study demonstrates the existence of a strong association between influenza infection and AMI, it is limited by the fact that the results derived from serological tests are less robust than those derived from the influenza virus laboratory research.
 <xref rid="suaa064-B7" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>7</sup>
 </xref> In this regard, a very recent study, published in the 
 <italic>New England Journal of Medicine</italic> in January 2018, evaluated the association between laboratory-confirmed influenza infection with highly specific methods and hospitalization for IMA. In it, Kwong 
 <italic>et al</italic>. identified 364 hospitalizations for AMI from a year before to a year after the laboratory test positive result for influenza. Winds of these hospitalizations occurred during the defined ‘risk’ interval, that is in the first 7 days from the date of detection of the flu; the remaining 344 fell in the period defined as the ‘control interval’, that is, from the year prior to the following year the risk interval. The researchers pointed out that the incidence of admission due to AMI was six times higher in the first 7 days after laboratory confirmation of the influenza infection compared to the control interval, and no increase in incidence was observed after the seventh day (the admission incidence ratio for IMA during the risk interval was 6.05; 95% CI: 3.86–9.5). Furthermore, a subgroup analysis showed that the incidence ratio was higher for more adult subjects, for Type B influenza and for patients affected by a first myocardial infarction; however, these subgroup analyses did not have sufficient statistical power to demonstrate the existence of significant differences.
</p>
