<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although most case-patients had clinically significant bleeding, few received packed red blood cells and none received whole blood. Infrequent monitoring of hematocrit and vital signs may have contributed to the late detection of hemorrhage. Instead, complete blood counts may have been ordered to monitor platelet counts. Platelet transfusions were ordered for most of the hospitalized case-patients but many died before receiving them. Guidelines generally recommend platelet transfusions be given to patients who have clinically significant bleeding; however, use of prophylactic platelet transfusions for dengue is a subject of debate 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001614-Nimmannitya1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>. Recent studies have found that in children, platelet counts are not predictive of bleeding 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001614-Lum1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001614-Malavige1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001614-Chuansumrit1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref> nor do they correlate with bleeding severity 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001614-Krishnamurti1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>. Instead, prolonged shock was found to be a risk factor for severe hemorrhage 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001614-Lum1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. In a study of 106 pediatric patients with DSS and coagulopathy, prophylactic platelet transfusions for platelet counts &lt;30×10
 <sup>9</sup> L
 <sup>−1</sup> and fresh frozen plasma did not prevent hemorrhage and may have contributed to the development of pulmonary edema resulting in increased hospital stays 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001614-Lum2" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>. Moreover, prophylactic platelet transfusions do not seem to expedite platelet recovery 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001614-Lum2" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001614-Lye1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>. Studies among adults have conflicting results; some found no association between a platelet count and bleeding 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001614-Lye1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>, while others found an association between platelet counts of 50×10
 <sup>9</sup> L
 <sup>−1</sup> or less than 20×10
 <sup>9</sup> L
 <sup>−1</sup> and bleeding 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001614-Malavige1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001614-Makroo1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>.
</p>
