<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par85">The PIP Framework does not mention the CBD but its recognition of the sovereign rights of states over the biological resources in the preamble of the PIP Framework represents an implicit recognition that states do have sovereign rights over all other pathogens. The 2016 review of the PIP Framework stated that “[t]he PIP Framework is a multilateral access and benefit sharing instrument that appears to be consistent with the objectives of the Nagoya Protocol” and recommended that it be officially recognised as such.
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn60">60</xref> The review also noted that there was no formal mechanism through which this might be achieved,
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn61">61</xref> but it is evident that the international community has accepted that the PIP Framework is a specialised ABS agreement governing the transfer of influenza viruses with human pandemic potential. That is, when sharing pandemic influenza viruses with and through the WHO (noting that the PIP Framework does not include within its scope seasonal influenza viruses), the international community chooses to do so under the terms of the PIP Framework, and not the CBD or Nagoya Protocol. By acknowledging that it is a specialised multilateral ABS instrument consistent with the Nagoya Protocol, the WHO’s review of the PIP Framework becomes an overt recognition that states have sovereign rights over all other pathogens. It also demonstrates that if the PIP Framework did not exist, the transfer of influenza viruses with human pandemic potential would “require bilateral agreements on a case-by-case basis” as per the terms of the CBD and Nagoya Protocol,
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn62">62</xref> should provider countries wish to exercise their right do so. In the ten years since Indonesia made the first claim of viral sovereignty using the language of the CBD, the WHO has, as a matter of practice, embraced and codified this concept as a new legal norm.
</p>
