<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par39">Based on the pivotal role of traditional Chinese medicines (TCM) in the treatment or prevention of many viral infections including influenza, SARS, and MERS, the application of TCM as adjuvant therapy in COVID-19 patients is highly encouraged [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. TCM has demonstrated a wide range of mechanisms that includes inhibition of 3CLpro protein (Chinese Rhubarb extracts, 
 <italic>Houttuynia cordata</italic> extract, hesperetin, etc.), inhibition of RdRp, and inhibition of inflammatory cytokines like TNF-α, IL-1β, and IL-6 (Fructus Forsythiae), thereby decreasing the severity and mortality rate of the disease [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]. In a molecular docking study by Chen and Du, five herbal compounds including scutellarin, baicalin, hesperetin, nicotianamine, and glycyrrhizin have shown potential in targeting the ACE2 receptor and exerting an antiviral effect to prevent SARS-CoV-2 infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]. Medical institutions in China have published many TCM prescriptions, and guideline in China (The Novel Coronavirus Pneumonia Diagnosis and Treatment Plan, 6th trial version) has also suggested the use of a decoction of herbal medicines for lung clearing and detoxification in the clinical treatment [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]. On February 17, The National Health Commission (NHC) of China has reported the beneficial effect of TCM in around more than 60,000 COVID-19 patients. To date, more than 50 clinical trials have registered in China for the evaluation of TCM in COVID-19. Luo, et al. has shortlisted ten most commonly used TCM in China, and they are Astragalus membranaceus, Glycyrrhizae uralensis, Saposhnikoviae divaricata, Rhizoma Atractylodis, Macrocephalae, Lonicerae Japonicae Flos, Fructus forsythia, Atractylodis Rhizoma, Radix platycodonis, Agastache rugosa, and Cyrtomium fortune J. Sm [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. Although shreds of evidence are available for the efficacy of TCM in COVID-19 patients, yet randomized clinical trials in larger populations are required to evaluate the efficacy and safety of TCM in COVID-19 patients.
</p>
