<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Logistic regression was used to analyze unadjusted (Model 1) and adjusted (Model 2) associations between arboviral infections and exposures of interest (cooks with firewood, firewood cooking frequency, kitchen location, stove type, and HAP score). In Model 2, confounders were identified 
 <italic>a priori</italic> from the literature using directed acyclic graphs [
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]: age [
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], sex [
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>], ethnic group [
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>], SES index [
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>], admission year [
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], season [
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], number of people in household [
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>], population density [
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], recruitment location, and elevation [
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. We chose not to match on age, location, and year to prevent biases associated with matching in case-control study designs [
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. We considered linear, quadratic, and cubic forms of age and SES index. Since most of the cooking in Guatemala is done by women [
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], we also looked to see whether there were interactions between sex and the exposures of interest on arboviral infections in Model 2. Tolerance values were used to assess collinearity among all independent variables. Hosmer-Lemeshow tests were used to assess goodness-of-fit of adjusted models. Odds ratios (OR) described the magnitude of associations between arboviral infection and exposures of interest. Statistical significance, defined as p&lt;0.05, was evaluated through the Chi-square test. ORs, 95% confidence intervals, and p-values were reported. All analyses were conducted using SAS V.9.4 (SAS Institute, Inc., Cary, North Carolina).
</p>
