<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There are several reviews of FMD models in the literature [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], but it is perhaps not surprising that many of these are focussed on the large-scale UK epidemic in 2001, which in many aspects was responsible for pioneering a step-change improvement in these tools. Consequently, most of the models related to FMD transmission were designed for use in countries where the disease is not endemic, where control measures are implemented to contain a single virus incursion into a naive population and recover FMD-free status as quickly as possible. However, in endemic settings, different factors play a critical role in virus circulation and require consideration such as waning of natural immunity or vaccine-induced immunity, and frequent disease re-introduction as well as the potential involvement of wildlife reservoirs [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Consequently, it is difficult or even wrong to extrapolate the experience in one country to another one as farming practices, farm density, farm size, and contact patterns may differ [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. In contrast to most developed regions where FMD has been eradicated, the disease is still endemic in most of Asia, Africa and parts of South America [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. In many of these endemic settings, there is no efficient control plan as FMD risk factors are poorly understood, and most of the parameters required for models are not well understood. These endemic areas constitute a real and permanent threat for FMD free countries through numerous transmission pathways. Considering the need to mitigate this potential event of FMDV entry from endemic to non-endemic FMD countries, the implementation of FMD risk assessment in endemic areas such as Africa is warranted. However, the most relevant question to be addressed is whether well-formulated and tailored FMD models exist for determining appropriate control policies in endemic countries.
</p>
