<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Multi-species interactions are critical to understand in order to accurately model viral dynamics in bat populations. To date, there is evidence for filovirus infection in a total of 17 bat species for (Marburgvirus, Zaire ebolavirus, Reston ebolavirus, and Lloviu virus), but no currently known bat hosts for Bundibugyo, Sudan, or Tai Forest ebolavirus (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="viruses-06-01759-t001">Table 1</xref>). Virus has only been detected via PCR and sequencing in 7 (41%) of these potential bat reservoir species, and some serological findings listed in 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="viruses-06-01759-t001">Table 1</xref> are sparse (e.g., only 2/679 Epomops franqueti seropositive for Marburg virus [
 <xref rid="B77-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. Multiple bat species could potentially act as reservoirs for Zaire ebolavirus, Reston ebolavirus, and Marburg virus, but only one host species is currently known for Lloviu virus (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="viruses-06-01759-t001">Table 1</xref>). Many of these species have overlapping geographic ranges, and have the potential (at a geographic, not necessarily ecological, scale) to interact and share pathogens (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-06-01759-f003">Figure 3</xref>). However, while either fragments of virus (PCR) or antibodies were detected in these hosts, their true role as reservoirs 
 <italic>versus</italic> incidental hosts and the relative contribution of each species to interspecific host dynamics is currently unknown. Multiple circulating pathogens can also change within-host and within-population dynamics and could confer cross-species immunity [
 <xref rid="B93-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. For example, multiple divergent Marburgvirus strains circulate within a single roost of R. aegyptiacus [
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. This poses interesting questions regarding how these pathogens interact, such as is there cross-immunity and do divergent viruses have the same infection dynamics? Though cross-reactivity is shown among ebolaviruses, it is unknown how this translates to immunity within the hosts [
 <xref rid="B116-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>]. Leroy 
 <italic>et al.</italic> demonstrated numerous bats infected (detected by PCR) with similar Zaire ebolavirus species PCR fragments some years apart, but within the species, these short genomic fragments differed between species and collection time [
 <xref rid="B1-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. In both cases, multiple hosts and circulating pathogens can complicate our understanding of virus-host interactions and should be considered during study design [
 <xref rid="B93-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>].
</p>
