<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The two major reductive systems in mammalian cells are the thioredoxin (Txn) and GSH pathways. The Txn system is completely dependent on selenium as the three thioredoxin reductases (TXNRD1–TXNRD3) are selenoproteins with the selenocysteine residue at the penultimate position of the C-terminal end of the protein [
 <xref rid="B26-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. TXNRD1 and TXNRD2 are ubiquitously present in the cytoplasm and mitochondria, respectively, while TXNRD3 expression is restricted to specific tissues. The primary substrates of TXNRD1 and TXNRD2 are Txn1 and Txn2, respectively, Txn2 being localized in the mitochondria. TXNRDs catalyze the NADPH-dependent reduction of oxidized thioredoxin (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="nutrients-11-02101-f002">Figure 2</xref>B). The Txns catalyze the reduction of protein disulfides such as in ribonucleotide reductase, peroxiredoxins (PRX), MSRB1, protein disulfide-isomerase (PDI), and are therefore critical for DNA synthesis, the defense against oxidative stress and disulfide formation within the endoplasmic reticulum [
 <xref rid="B20-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Peroxiredoxins are able to reduce H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>, organic hydroperoxides and peroxynitrite in order to protect cellular components from oxidative damage. However, the existence of multiple peroxide-removing enzymes such as catalase, GPX and PRX indicates that these peroxidases are not simply used in oxidant defense [
 <xref rid="B91-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. During inflammation, high levels of peroxides are produced by phagocytes to kill microorganisms. It has been well established that PRXs play cytoprotective antioxidant role in inflammation. Recently, it has been proposed that PRXs may play key roles in innate immunity and inflammation [
 <xref rid="B91-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. It becomes clear that, in addition to fighting oxidative stress, PRXs are important modulators of peroxide signaling. In addition to Txn, TXNRDs can reduce other small molecules containing sulfur, selenium, or oxidized semiquinone and therefore participate in many other cellular processes [
 <xref rid="B20-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B92-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>], 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="nutrients-11-02101-f002">Figure 2</xref>B.
</p>
