<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par12">The pathogenic effects of coronavirus entry using the ACE2 receptor in for instance lung epithelial cells appear to follow two paths: on the one hand, spike-receptor interaction causes downregulation and abolishment of the protective function of ACE2, resulting in local enhancement of angiotensin II production and unrestricted stimulation of the angiotensin receptor (AT
 <sub>1</sub>R) (Imai et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2008</xref>) (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). On the other hand, the binding of ACE2 to SARS-CoV spike glycoprotein induces so-called syncytia-formation and transformation into large multinucleated cells, as observed in clinical SARS infections (Imai et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2008</xref>) and also in post mortem samples taken from a 50-year old male patient from Wuhan (WHO 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2020</xref>). It was already suggested that severe lung damage, especially in the late phase of SARS, was largely ‘immunopathological in nature’ (Weiss and Leibowitz 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2011</xref>). In early phase fatal lung disease, histological examination showed hyaline membrane formation (indicative of ARDS) (World Health Organization 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2020</xref>) and loss of lung epithelial cells (or pneumocytes), resulting alveolar damage and mixed cellular infiltrates of lymphocytes (Weiss and Leibowitz 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2011</xref>). Often also multinucleated giant cells, carrying markers for both macrophages and pneumocytes were present (Weiss and Leibowitz 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2011</xref>), indicating the involvement of macrophage scavenging. Also in 2019-nCoV infections, these histological features were observed in post mortem specimen from lung (apart from the demonstration of lineage markers) (World Health Organization 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2020</xref>). In the late phase of SARS (phase III, 10–15 days after the onset of illness), also type II pneumocyte hyperplasia, squamous metaplasia and bronchiolitis obliterans were found in histological examination. These features are consistent with the late, irreversible obstruction of the bronchioles (Weiss and Leibowitz 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2011</xref>). The worsening of clinical progression, simultaneously with declining viral loads and markedly elevated cytokine levels, the so-called cytokine-storm (during SARS phase III, but also seen in COVID-19), corroborate the conclusion that these late pathological effects are the result of a fatal overreaction of the immune system (Weiss and Leibowitz 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2011</xref>) (see below).
</p>
