<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17">Dissemination of the COVID-19 is mediated by via cough or sneeze droplets or direct contact within human-to-human [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. The viral particles are thought to bind to the angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 receptor in humans thereby rendering the infected individual prone to the respiratory disorders [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. The coronavirus pneumonia develops within maximum 7 days with the early symptoms of fever, headache, cough, congestion, pharyngalgia, etc.[
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. The sequential secondary bacterial infections are not surprising during the viral infections. Suppression of the intricate innate antiviral responses induces the viral infection. The SARS-CoV-2 RNA encodes at least two proteases possessing the capacity of cleaving the cells of the innate immunity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. The viruses may replicate extensively in the cytoplasm by modifying the intracellular membranes to form specific replication organelles which protect the recognition of viral RNA by the innate immune sensors [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. The viral endoribonuclease (RNase) activity is another means of excaping the innate immunity. Besides, the viruses can modify their RNAs to keep protected the recognition by the foreign RNA sensors of the host immune cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Moreover, the receptor-binding domain (RBD) of viral spike can mediate the viral entry. Interestingly, a monoclonal antibody (MAb) can bind to the cell surface of the immunolglobulin G (IgG) Fc receptor which in turn mediates the viral entry into the host as also happens during the MERS-CoV infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Indeed, using the spike (S) protein, both the SARS-CoV-2 and SARS-CoV bind to the angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE 2) receptor of the host whereas MERS-CoV utilizes the host receptor Dipeptidyl peptidase 4 (DPP4); and it’s to be noted that SARS-CoV-2 possesses a longer spike protein than that of SARS-CoV; and moreover, the SARS-CoV-2 entry depends on the non-neutralizing antibodies while in case of SARS-CoV, the neutralizing antibodies block the viral entry whereas the MERS-CoV entry principally depends on the host natural killer (NK) cell inactivation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>].
</p>
