<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The levels of neutralizing antibodies against EBOV GP were detected by a single-round infectivity assay that we have developed in early studies (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Mohan et al., 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Briefly, EBOV GP-HIV pseudovirions were produced by transfecting 293T-cells with and HIV backbone plasmid (Env-defective) and together with a DNA plasmid expressing EBOV GP in pCAGGS using the transfection reagent Fugene HD (Roche). At 48 h post-transfection, pseudovirions in the medium from transfected cells were harvested, clarified, and filtered using a 0.45 micron filter, and then titrated in JC53BL cells (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Wei et al., 2003</xref>), which express β-galactosidase and luciferase under a 
 <italic>tat-</italic>activated promoter. Neutralization assays were then carried out as described in our previous studies (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Li W. et al., 2015</xref>). Briefly, pseudoviruses were fisrt incubated with serial dilutions of heat-inactivated serum samples for 1 h at 37°C, which were supplemented with heat-inactivated sera from naïve mouse (Innovative Research) to 5% of the total volume. The serum-pseudovirion mixtures were then added to JC53 cells that have been grown to 50% confluenvy in a 96-well plate and incubated at 37°C for 48 h. Afterward, the level of luciferase activity in each well were detected by a kit (Sigma), neutralization was calculated by measuring the percent decrease in luciferase activity in sample wells compared to virus-only control wells. The serum neutralizing activity is calculated with the formula: [(luciferase activity in control well – luciferase activity in sample well)/luciferase activity in control well × 100%], and is expressed as the percentage reduction of virus titers in sample wells compared to the titers in control wells. Statistical analysis of serum antibody responses between ID and IM vaccinated guinea pigs was performed by a Student’s 
 <italic>t</italic>-test.
</p>
