<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The review highlights some factors associated with arboviral seroprevalence. We noted an increase in seroprevalence among older people in 44% of DENV studies and 18.5% of CHIKV studies mainly conducted in endemic areas, whereas only one ZIKV study obtained this result. The epidemiological context of affected countries appears to be associated with the relationship between age and seroprevalence. For instance, in an emergence context, few studies reported this association, as the target population is naïve. However, some CHIKV studies not conducted in an endemic area reported this association, which may suggest that age is associated with level of exposure. We noted that 14 studies found an association between gender and seroprevalence. These findings suggest that there may be gender-related differences; however, these discrepancies require further exploration, as the health gender gap may stem from various patterns that affect exposure to mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006533.ref179" ref-type="bibr">179</xref>]. We also observed that, regarding DENV and CHIKV, this association varied between countries, and no study reported an association between gender and ZIKV seroprevalence. However, given the transmission issues associated with ZIKV, we can expect that in future studies, sexual transmission will correlate with higher seroprevalence among women. Although few studies revealed an association between ethnicity and seroprevalence, this finding can be related to background prevalence in the country of origin, in combination with increased early life exposure before migration or exposure during travel to their region of origin post migration. Moreover, these associations might also be partly explained by increased susceptibility related to the lower socioeconomic position of certain ethnic groups. The relationship between health and socio-economic status is well documented, and research has revealed a graded association in which people of lower socio-economic status have much worse health outcomes than those of higher socio-economic status [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006533.ref180" ref-type="bibr">180</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0006533.ref181" ref-type="bibr">181</xref>]. Finally, 20 studies also reported an association between environmental factors and seroprevalence, as certain environmental conditions, such as house structure or objects collected in the yard, are more hospitable to 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006533.ref182" ref-type="bibr">182</xref>].
</p>
