<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Influenza A virus presents as a permutation of 18 hemagglutinin (HA) and 11 neuraminidase (NA) possible subtypes, with a wide range of hosts (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Cauldwell et al., 2014</xref>). The latest two subtypes H17N10 and H18N11 are of bat origins (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Tong et al., 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Influenza B virus, including the Victoria and Yamagata lineages, is hosted by humans and seals (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Osterhaus et al., 2000</xref>). Although there is no direct evidence that influenza B is transmitted between humans and animals, it has been observed that influenza B can infect seal, swine, ferret, guinea pig, pheasant, dog and horse (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Osterhaus et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Pica et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Ran et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Pascua et al., 2016</xref>). Pandemic influenza is usually caused by influenza A virus, due to its rapid antigenic variation, strong replication capacity, and transmission ability associated with genetic reassortment (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Chan et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">White and Lowen, 2018</xref>). Influenza B virus, often neglected, has been circulating and, in some seasons, has predominated over influenza A, particularly among children (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Paul Glezen et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Tewawong et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Furuse et al., 2016</xref>). Vaccines against influenza A/H1N1 and A/H3N2 have been used effectively for more than 20 years for controlling and preventing potential pandemics. However, influenza vaccines against the B/Victoria and B/Yamagata lineages were used interchangeably. In the 2016–2018 seasons, the trivalent influenza vaccine did not include the B/Yamagata lineage.
</p>
