<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite a recent increase in the number of studies published about ZIKV, we still lack basic information about many aspects of its biology (
 <xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Messina et al., 2016</xref>). In addition to an outbreak of locally acquired cases of ZIKV in Florida in 2016, the contiguous United States is predicted to be suitable for further ZIKV expansion based on a variety of environmental factors (
 <xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Messina et al., 2016</xref>, “2016 case counts in the US,” 2017). We have little knowledge about what North American mosquitoes are capable of transmitting this virus, and although some 
 <italic>Anopheles</italic> and 
 <italic>Culex</italic> species have been shown to be inefficient vectors (
 <xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Dodson &amp; Rasgon, 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Kenney et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">Roundy et al., 2017</xref>) ZIKV has been isolated from these genera before (
 <xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">Pujhari &amp; Rasgon, 2016</xref>). Primary mosquito vectors for ZIKV have been demonstrated to be in the 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> genera, most notably 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> (
 <xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr">Wong et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Diallo et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">Grard et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Gendernalik et al., 2017</xref>). Recent environmental suitability maps suggest that 77% of counties in the United States are suitable for both of these 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> species, including the southeast, the south, southern portions of the northeast, and midwest, as well as coastal edges of the west (
 <xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">Johnson et al., 2017</xref>). ZIKV has been isolated from many other mosquito species and genera, but most of these have not been experimentally tested for their ability to serve as vectors (
 <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Faye et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">Waddell &amp; Greig, 2016</xref>). For this study, we selected several mosquito species that are abundant across large areas of the United (
 <italic>Anopheles freeborni</italic>, 
 <italic>An. quadrimaculatus</italic>, and 
 <italic>Culex. tarsalis</italic> (
 <xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Hayes et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Venkatesan &amp; Rasgon, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Manguin , 2013</xref>) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1</xref>), and evaluated their ability to become infected with and transmit ZIKV in the laboratory.
</p>
