<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d2 20140930//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Can J Infect Dis Med Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Can J Infect Dis Med Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PGI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Canadian Journal of Infectious Diseases &#x00026; Medical Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1712-9532</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1918-1493</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Pulsus Group Inc</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">idmm-26-e1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>AMMI Canada Guidelines</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Guidance for practitioners on the use of antiviral drugs to control influenza
outbreaks in long-term care facilities in Canada, 2014&#x02013;2015 season</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>Fred Y</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-idmm-26-e1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1-idmm-26-e1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>Upton D</given-names></name><degrees>MBBS</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-idmm-26-e1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stiver</surname><given-names>H Grant</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-idmm-26-e1"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Laverdi&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>Michel</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4-idmm-26-e1"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Skowronski</surname><given-names>Danuta</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af5-idmm-26-e1"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>Gerald A</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af6-idmm-26-e1"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-idmm-26-e1"><label>1</label>Professor of Medicine, Medical Microbiology and Pharmacology &#x00026; Therapeutics,
Faculty of Medicine, University of Manitoba, Winnipeg, Manitoba;</aff><aff id="af2-idmm-26-e1"><label>2</label>Professor, Department of Pediatrics &#x00026; Institute of Health Policy, Management
and Evaluation; Senior Associate Scientist, Research Institute; Chief, Division of Infectious
Diseases, Department of Pediatrics, Hospital for Sick Children, University of Toronto, Toronto,
Ontario;</aff><aff id="af3-idmm-26-e1"><label>3</label>Professor Emeritus of Medicine, Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of
Medicine, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, British Columbia;</aff><aff id="af4-idmm-26-e1"><label>4</label>Department of Microbiology-Infectious Disease, Hopital Maisonneuve-Rosemont,
Montreal, Quebec;</aff><aff id="af5-idmm-26-e1"><label>5</label>Epidemiology Lead, Influenza &#x00026; Emerging Respiratory Pathogens, BC Centre for
Disease Control, Vancouver, British Columbia;</aff><aff id="af6-idmm-26-e1"><label>6</label>Professor of Medicine, Biomedical &#x00026; Molecular Sciences and Pathology
&#x00026; Molecular Medicine; Chair, Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of Medicine,
Kingston General Hospital, Queen&#x02019;s University, Kingston, Ontario</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1-idmm-26-e1">Correspondence: Dr Fred Y Aoki, 510-745 Bannatyne Avenue, Winnipeg,
Manitoba R3E 0J9. E-mail <email>fred.aoki@umanitoba.ca</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Jan-Feb</season><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>26</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e1</fpage><lpage>e4</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright&#x000a9; 2015 Pulsus Group Inc. All rights
reserved</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license><license-p>This open-access article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution
Non-Commercial License (CC BY-NC) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits reuse, distribution and
reproduction of the article, provided that the original work is properly cited and the reuse is
restricted to noncommercial purposes. For commercial reuse, contact
<email>support@pulsus.com</email></license-p></license></permissions><abstract abstract-type="toc"><p>The AMMI Canada Guidelines document &#x02018;The use of antiviral drugs for influenza: A
foundation document for practitioners&#x02019;, published in the Autumn 2013 issue of the
<italic>Journal</italic>, outlines the recommendations for the use of antiviral drugs to treat
influenza. This article, which represents the first of two updates to these guidelines published in
the current issue of the <italic>Journal</italic>, aims to inform health care professionals of the
increased risk for influenza in long-term care facilities due to a documented mismatch between the
components chosen for this season&#x02019;s vaccine and currently circulating influenza strains.
Adjusted recommendations for the use of antiviral drugs for influenza in long-term care facilities
for this season are provided.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>The purpose of this guidance document is to inform physicians and other health care practitioners
of an increased risk of influenza outbreaks in long-term care facilities (LTCF) during the
2014&#x02013;2015 influenza season in Canada, and to provide recommendations for adjustment to LTCF
outbreak control measures on the basis of documented vaccine mismatch.</p><p>Influenza seasons dominated by A(H3N2) viruses are typically associated with greater morbidity
and mortality than other types/subtypes of influenza, especially in the elderly (<xref rid="b1-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="b3-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Significant genetic and antigenic differences have been identified so far in
2014&#x02013;2015 among circulating A(H3N2) viruses compared with the 2014&#x02013;2015 H3N2 vaccine
component chosen by the World Health Organization (WHO) for the northern hemisphere (<xref rid="b4-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="b5-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>).
These differences between circulating viruses and the vaccine strain (called &#x02018;antigenic
drift&#x02019; or &#x02018;vaccine mismatch&#x02019;) are anticipated to have important implications
for reduced vaccine protection this season. Consequently, adjunct protective measures, such as
antiviral medications, may require greater emphasis and expanded use in responding to LTCF outbreaks
this season.</p><sec><label>A.</label><title>PROCESS STATEMENT</title><p>The development of this updated guidance arose in November 2014 from information provided by the
Public Health Agency of Canada regarding early data indicating a mismatch of the influenza vaccine
H3N2 component to an emerging H3N2 seasonal strain. This created a need to update recommendations
for the use of antiviral drugs for this year&#x02019;s seasonal influenza. The concept was then
approved by Association of Medical Microbiology and Infectious Disease (AMMI) Canada. A first draft
was cowritten by all the authors (FYA, UDA, HGS, ML, DS and GAE). Subsequently, all the authors
reviewed, revised and approved the document before a further review from the AMMI Canada Guidelines
Committee and the Infectious Diseases and Immunization Committee of the Canadian Paediatric Society.
AMMI Canada approved the final document before submission to the <italic>Journal</italic> for
publication.</p></sec><sec><label>B.</label><title>OVERVIEW OF KEY MESSAGES</title><p>The current guidance document supplements recommendations in the AMMI Canada Guideline
&#x02018;The use of antiviral drugs for influenza: A foundation document for practitioners&#x02019;
(<xref rid="b6-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). The essential points in this special
supplement are: <list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p>Influenza A(H3N2) viruses are dominating (&#x0003e;90%) among influenza detections so far
in 2014&#x02013;2015, and have been associated with earlier and more LTCF outbreaks this season
compared with usual in several parts of Canada (<xref rid="b4-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>).
These viruses remain susceptible to the neuraminidase inhibitor (NI) drugs.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The majority of influenza A(H3N2) viruses (&#x0003e;95%) characterized thus far in Canada
this season show genetic and antigenic evidence of mismatch to the vaccine strain
(A/Texas/50/2012[H3N2]-like) that had been chosen in February 2014 by the WHO for
inclusion in the 2014&#x02013;2015 trivalent and quadrivalent vaccines for the northern hemisphere
(<xref rid="b4-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="b5-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><p>A substantial number of amino acid (AA) differences between circulating H3N2 viruses and the
vaccine component are found at key antigenic sites of the hemagglutinin (H) protein of the influenza
virus, and number and location of genetic differences are anticipated to substantially affect
vaccine effectiveness (VE) this season (<xref rid="b7-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="b12-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><p>VE estimates against H3N2 for the 2014&#x02013;2015 season will likely not be available until
later in the season (expected in February 2015), but in previous seasons of H3N2 vaccine mismatch,
VE estimates of 40% or lower have been found in association with a comparable or fewer
number of antigenic site AA differences between vaccine and H3N2 circulating viruses, even in young
adults (<xref rid="b13-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="b17-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><p>In the context of this significant vaccine mismatch, enhanced emphasis and expanded
recommendations for antiviral use during LTCF outbreak control are needed while influenza A(H3N2)
activity shows signs of spiking in several parts of Canada.</p></list-item><list-item><p>NI drugs, oseltamivir (Tamiflu<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>, Hoffmann-La Roche Ltd, Canada) and zanamivir
(Relenza<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>, GlaxoSmithKline Inc, Canada), are the antiviral medications to be
prescribed for both treatment and prevention of influenza, including H3N2 viruses. Amantadine is not
to be prescribed due to resistance of the H3N2 virus to its inhibitory action.</p></list-item><list-item><p>In view of vaccine mismatch for H3N2 viruses in 2014&#x02013;2015 and anticipated reduced VE for
that component, it is recommended that antiviral chemoprophylaxis be considered for all staff
working at the site of a declared influenza A(H3N2) LTCF outbreak regardless of whether they have
received this year&#x02019;s 2014&#x02013;2015 influenza vaccine.</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec><label>C.</label><title>VIROLOGICAL CONTEXT</title><sec><label>1.</label><title>Dominant influenza A(H3N2) activity early in the 2014&#x02013;2015 season</title><p>To date during the 2014&#x02013;2015 season in Canada (current as of week 50, ending December 13,
2014), 4283 (96%) influenza A viruses and 168 (4%) influenza B viruses have been
detected (<xref rid="b4-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). The number of influenza A detections
in week 50 nearly doubled from the prior week (week 49, ending December 6, 2014; n=2354), signifying
activity that is beginning to spike. This activity has been driven primarily by increased detection
of A(H3N2) viruses.</p><p>Of the 2011 influenza A viruses detected in Canada thus far with subtype information available to
December 13, 2014, 2005 (99.7%) are A(H3N2) and just six (0.3%) are A(H1N1)pdm09
(<xref rid="b4-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). This profile is very different from the prior
2013&#x02013;14 season when H3N2 viruses were sparse and A(H1N1)pdm09, descended from the 2009
pandemic virus, was instead the dominant influenza A epidemic strain (<xref rid="b4-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>).</p></sec><sec><label>2.</label><title>Evidence for antigenic drift/vaccine mismatch among H3N2 viruses detected in Canada</title><p>Of 61 influenza A(H3N2) viruses characterized so far this season by Canada&#x02019;s influenza
reference laboratory, the National Microbiology Laboratory (NML), 59 (97%) have shown
genetic and/or antigenic evidence of antigenic drift and mismatch to the 2014&#x02013;2015
A/Texas/50/2012(H3N2) vaccine strain (<xref rid="b4-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>).</p><p>Thirteen H3N2 viruses were characterized by standard hemagglutination inhibition (HI) assay and
of these, 12 (92%) met conventional thresholds for titre reduction that define antigenic
drift. An additional 58 viruses could not be characterized by HI and were instead assessed by
sequencing of the H3 gene. Of these, 57 of 58 (98%) clustered within a genetic group that
has been found by HI assay to be antigenically distinct from the A/Texas/50/2012(H3N2) vaccine
strain and, thus, also consistent with antigenic drift in these viruses (<xref rid="b4-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><label>3.</label><title>Emerging genetic subgroups of A(H3N2) bear multiple amino acid changes in key antigenic sites
with implications for reduced vaccine effectiveness (VE)</title><p>There are several genetic subgroups of H3N2 viruses currently circulating, with nomenclature as
described by the European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control (ECDC) in its periodic
surveillance reports (<xref rid="b18-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="b19-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Among 480 global H3 gene sequences collected worldwide between June
and November 2014 and publicly available for analysis in the GISAID EpiFlu Database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://platfrom.gisaid.org">http://platfrom.gisaid.org</ext-link>),
none from the northern or southern hemispheres were found to belong to the same genetic subgroup
3C.1 as the A/Texas/50/2012(H3N2) strain used in the 2014&#x02013;2015 northern hemisphere vaccine
(<xref rid="b5-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) (verbal communication, D Skowronski, BC Centre
for Disease Control).</p><p>Viruses belonging to phylogenetic subgroups 3C.3, 3C.3a and 3C.2a variously contributed during
the summer months (June to August), with lesser contribution of another subgroup that has not yet
received separate ECDC designation (provisionally labelled here as 3C.3x). In September 2014, the
WHO selected a virus within subgroup 3C.3a, represented by A/Switzerland/9715293/2013(H3N2), to be
the vaccine component for the southern hemisphere&#x02019;s upcoming 2015 season (<xref rid="b5-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). These emergent viruses are considered antigenically
distinct from the egg-propagated A/Texas/50/2012(H3N2)-like virus (subgroup 3C.1) used in the
2013&#x02013;2014 and 2014&#x02013;2015 vaccines for the northern hemisphere (<xref rid="b5-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="b18-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="b19-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>).</p><p>During the early fall (September to October), subgroup 3C.2a viruses have become more predominant
among GISAID sequences collected from the northern hemisphere, and this has been accompanied by
lesser contribution from subgroup 3C.3x. This subgroup distribution has also been observed among
H3N2 viruses collected and sequenced by investigators during the fall 2014 in British Columbia,
Canada (verbal communication, D. Skowronski, BC Centre for Disease Control). The emerging subgroups
3C.2a and 3C.3x H3N2 variants each bear multiple amino acid (AA) differences from the
A/Texas/50/2012(H3N2) vaccine strain and from the egg-adapted high-growth reassortant (HGR) provided
to manufacturers for vaccine production this season (called X-223A) (<xref rid="b5-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>).</p><p>Differences between these emerging H3N2 viruses and the 2014&#x02013;2015 vaccine strain are
found in key antigenic sites of the H3 protein known to influence antigenicity, immunogenicity and
vaccine effectiveness (<xref rid="b7-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="b12-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). In previous seasons, H3N2 viruses with comparable
or fewer AA substitutions at H3 antigenic sites relative to vaccine have been associated with VE of
approximately 40% or less in Canada and elsewhere (<xref rid="b13-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="b17-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). One of
the particular combinations of H3N2 mutations in subgroup 3C.3x viruses (an asparagine to aspartic
acid substitution at position 122 and a leucine to serine substitution at position 157) was
associated with VE of 30% or less in Spain with use of the same A/Texas/50/2012(H3N2)
vaccine component in 2013&#x02013;2014 that has been retained for 2014&#x02013;2015 (<xref rid="b20-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec><label>D.</label><title>LTCF OUTBREAK CONTROL MEASURES</title><p>LTCF include nursing homes and other institutions that provide health care to individuals,
including children, who are unable to manage independently in the community. Some facilities will
have multiple smaller units or wards with physical separation and shared- or unit-dedicated staff.
These factors will have to be considered in declaring whether a care facility influenza outbreak is
facility-wide or specific to a ward/unit.</p><p>When influenza virus is causing illness in the community, it may be introduced into the facility
by staff, including non-health care workers, newly admitted patients or visitors. Residents of LTCF
are at increased risk of severe and/or complicated illness because of frailty, comorbid medical
conditions and, in some residents, older age (<xref rid="b21-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>).
Annual influenza immunization is recommended for these individuals because of these high-risk
characteristics, and generally immunization rates are very high among residents. Among health care
workers and other staff, influenza immunizations rates are more variable but generally lower than in
residents.</p><p>Influenza outbreaks among residents are not uncommon in spite of their own high immunization
rates. This is probably due, in part, to an impaired immune response associated with aging and other
comorbidity. Controlling outbreaks of influenza in LTCF requires a multi-faceted approach including:
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Surveillance for influenza-like illness (ILI)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Laboratory testing to identify the cause of ILI</p></list-item><list-item><p>Promotion of, and adherence to, infection control guidelines and practices including respiratory
etiquette and routine practices, and the use of personal protective equipment</p></list-item><list-item><p>Timely communication</p></list-item><list-item><p>Influenza immunization for residents and staff</p></list-item><list-item><p>Exclusion of ill staff, visitor exclusion and new admission deferral</p></list-item><list-item><p>Antiviral drug therapy for ill residents and staff</p></list-item><list-item><p>Antiviral drug prophylaxis of non-ill residents and staff</p></list-item></list></p><p>Items 1 through 6 are outside the scope of this guidance and specific recommendations may vary by
province. Readers are referred to provincial guidelines and an interim guideline from the United
States Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (<xref rid="b22-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>).</p><p>For control of an outbreak of influenza among residents of a LTCF, surveillance for ILI is
critical for early identification and response. FluWatch defines ILI as acute onset of respiratory
illness with fever and cough and with one or more of sore throat, arthralgia, myalgia or prostration
but further underscores that in patients 65 years and older, fever may not be prominent (<xref rid="b4-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Where influenza is suspected, laboratory testing can
confirm the diagnosis. The preferred sample for individual influenza diagnosis is a nasopharyngeal
specimen obtained using a flocked swab. For surveillance purposes and outbreak diagnosis, nasal
specimens collected from several patients within a cluster affected by ILI may also be sufficient to
determine the cause of the outbreak. However, oropharyngeal secretions obtained with a throat swab
are suboptimal for influenza diagnosis. The preferred testing methods are, in order of declining
preference: RT-PCR, rapid influenza diagnostic tests and viral culture.</p><p>For surveillance purposes, FluWatch defines an influenza outbreak on the basis of two or more
cases of ILI within a seven-day period, including at least one laboratory-confirmed case of
influenza (<xref rid="b4-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). However, this is for surveillance
purposes and the declaration of an influenza outbreak and the enactment of control measures is at
the discretion of the local health authority/Medical Officer of Health in accordance with provincial
guidance. When an influenza outbreak is suspected in a LTCF, this should be reported within 24 h to
the local health authority/Medical Officer of Health to enable timely interventions. It is at the
discretion of the local health authority/Medical Officer of Health, in consultation with health care
and infection control practitioners, to declare an influenza outbreak in a LTCF and to recommend
specific interventions for its control according to provincial guidelines. It is similarly at the
discretion of the local health authority/Medical Officer of Health to declare an outbreak over and
to recommend when specific interventions may be halted. The end of a LTCF outbreak is generally
considered when no new cases of ILI have appeared for &#x02265;7 days (<xref rid="b22-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>) after the onset of the last case (an interval equal to an average
incubation period [three days] following the average period of communicability
[three to five days]) or roughly two incubation periods.</p></sec><sec><label>E.</label><title>ANTIVIRAL USE DURING LTCF INFLUENZA OUTBREAKS</title><p>It is generally accepted that antiviral drugs to treat and prevent influenza in residents,
together with other infection control measures, are important for the control of influenza outbreaks
in LTCF. Recommended practices with respect to antiviral use are as follows:</p><sec><label>1.</label><title>Antiviral drug therapy</title><sec><label>i.</label><title>Residents:</title><list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p>Oseltamivir or zanamivir treatment should be administered as soon as the clinical diagnosis of
influenza has been made because residents of LTCF are, by definition, at increased risk of
complications (<xref rid="b6-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><p>Nasal/nasopharyngeal secretions should be tested to confirm the diagnosis but treatment
initiation should not wait for the test result.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Antiviral therapy works best when initiated within the first 48 h after symptom onset. However,
these medications can still help even if begun more than 48 h after illness onset.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The dosage regimens for adults are oseltamivir 75 mg PO BID or zanamivir two inhalations BID. The
treatment dose for oral oseltamivir for infants (younger than one year) is 3 mg/kg twice a day.
Given that in Canada, oseltamivir is currently not approved for use in infants younger than one year
of age, the use of the drug for this age group should be done on case-by-case scenario basis. The
treatment dosages for children one year and older vary by the weight of the child: 30 mg twice a day
for children who weigh 15 kg or less, 45 mg twice a day for children who weigh more than 15 kg and
up to 23 kg, 60 mg twice a day for those who weigh more than 23 kg and up to 40 kg, and 75 mg twice
a day for those who weigh more than 40 kg. Clinicians are advised to consult an infectious diseases
clinician or pharmacist for dosing of premature infants in the extremely unlikely that they are
residents of a LCTF. Zanamivir is approved for children seven years of age and older (two
inhalations BID).</p></list-item><list-item><p>The recommended duration of therapy is five days.</p></list-item><list-item><p>There is no need to reduce doses in patients with mild to moderate reduced renal function and
drug-drug interactions are also not generally a concern (<xref rid="b6-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>).</p></list-item></list></sec><sec><label>ii.</label><title>Staff:</title><list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p>Staff with ILI during an outbreak should be offered antiviral treatment and sent home until their
symptoms have resolved.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Dose is per E1id, above.</p></list-item></list></sec></sec><sec><label>2.</label><title>Antiviral drug prophylaxis</title><sec><label>i.</label><title>Residents:</title><list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p>Upon diagnosis of an influenza outbreak, all residents becoming ill should be treated (vide
supra) while all non-ill residents regardless of whether they have received the current seasonal
vaccine should be started on chemoprophylaxis with either oseltamivir or zanamivir.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Generally, it is preferable to wait to initiate chemoprophylaxis until laboratory confirmation
has been received.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The prophylactic doses are oseltamivir 75 mg PO once daily or zanamivir two inhalations once
daily for adults. The prophylactic dose for oral oseltamivir for infants three months to younger
than one year of age is 3 mg/kg once daily. Prophylaxis is not recommended for infants younger than
three months of age. The dosages for children one year of age and older vary by the weight of the
child: 30 mg once a day for children who weigh 15 kg or less, 45 mg once a day for children who
weigh more than 15 kg and up to 23 kg, 60 mg once a day for those who weigh more than 23 kg and up
to 40 kg, and 75 mg once a day for those who weigh more than 40 kg. Zanamivir is approved for
children seven years of age and older (two inhalations once daily).</p></list-item><list-item><p>Prophylaxis should be continued for 14 days minimum or until the outbreak has been declared over
(see section D above).</p></list-item></list></sec><sec><label>ii.</label><title>Staff:</title><list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p>In the context of significant antigenic drift and/or vaccine mismatch for which suboptimal VE may
reasonably be anticipated, and in particular in relation to H3N2 viruses this season, it is
recommended that staff who provide resident care or conduct activities where they may have the
potential to acquire or transmit influenza (<xref rid="b21-idmm-26-e1" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>)
should also take prophylactic antiviral medication during the outbreak, regardless of whether they
have received the current season&#x02019;s influenza vaccine. This is because, despite some vaccine
protection anticipated, a substantial proportion of vaccinated individuals, including healthy
working-age adults, are anticipated to remain susceptible to drifted H3N2 viruses.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Antiviral prophylaxis recommendations should be reinstituted whenever an outbreak is declared
even for the same subtype and within the same setting and season. The maximum duration of continuous
prophylaxis should be eight weeks, but outbreaks managed with antivirals should generally be
terminated well within this period. In the unusual event that the outbreak is more prolonged,
control measures should be reassessed in consultation with the local Medical Officer of Health and
other experts.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Doses and durations should be as in section E2ic above.</p></list-item></list></sec></sec><sec><label>3.</label><title>Continued surveillance for ILI during an outbreak:</title><list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p>Residents or staff developing ILI while on prophylactic doses of an antiviral agent need to be
considered for treatment doses if influenza is diagnosed or considered likely.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Residents or staff receiving chemoprophylaxis who develop ILI should be assessed and tested to
determine the cause of their illness, which may be due to the current virus, another viral agent or
an oseltamivir- (or zanamavir)-resistant influenza virus.</p></list-item></list><p>Expert consultation is suggested to address: the cause, organize testing for NI resistance, and
to assess the possible need to possibly switch to another NI.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors wish to acknowledge the contribution of Suzana Sabaiduc and Catharine Chambers to the
summary of recent virus surveillance findings. The authors also acknowledge the critical review of
the present document by the Public Health Agency of Canada and the Infectious Diseases and
Immunization Committee of the Canadian Paediatric Society and its review and endorsement by the AMMI
Canada Guidelines Committee. AMMI Canada would like to acknowledge the Public Health Agency of
Canada who contributed by funding the translation of the guidelines. The authors also extend
appreciation to Ms Angela Nelson for her excellent secretarial assistance.</p></ack><fn-group><fn><p><bold>DISCLOSURES:</bold> Dr Fred Y Aoki: Honoraria: Merck; Research: Biocryst Inc. Dr Upton D
Allen: Research: Hoffmann La Roche Inc. Dr H Grant Stiver: Honoraria: Hoffman La Roche Inc; Advisory
Board: Hoffman La Roche Inc. Dr Gerald A Evans: Research: Biocryst Inc. Dr Michel Laverdiere and Dr
Danuta Skowronski: None.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="b1-idmm-26-e1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schanzer</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sevenhuysen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Winchester</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mersereau</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating influenza deaths in Canada,
1992&#x02013;2009</article-title><source>PLoS
ONE</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e80481</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24312225</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2-idmm-26-e1"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Shay</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Weintraub</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mortality associated with influenza and respiratory syncytial virus in
the United
States</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2003</year><volume>289</volume><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12517228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3-idmm-26-e1"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Shay</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Weintraub</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Influenza-associated hospitalizations in the United
States</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2004</year><volume>292</volume><fpage>1333</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15367555</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4-idmm-26-e1"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>Public Health Agency of
Canada</collab><article-title>FluWatch</article-title><comment>&#x0003c;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.phac-aspc.gc.ca/fluwatch/14-15/index-eng.php">www.phac-aspc.gc.ca/fluwatch/14-15/index-eng.php</ext-link>&#x0003e; (Accessed December 19,
2015).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5-idmm-26-e1"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>World Health Organization</collab><article-title>WHO
recommendations on the composition of influenza virus
vaccines</article-title><comment>&#x0003c;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.who.int/influenza/vaccines/virus/recommendations/en/index.html">www.who.int/influenza/vaccines/virus/recommendations/en/index.html</ext-link>&#x0003e; (Accessed
December 19, 2015).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6-idmm-26-e1"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>FY</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>UD</given-names></name><name><surname>Stiver</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Laverdi&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The use of antiviral drugs for influenza: A foundation document for
practitioners</article-title><source>Can J Infect Dis Med
Microbiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>24</volume><issue>Suppl
C</issue><fpage>1C</fpage><lpage>15C</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b7-idmm-26-e1"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bush</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Subbarao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitch</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predicting the evolution of human influenza
A</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1999</year><volume>286</volume><fpage>1921</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10583948</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b8-idmm-26-e1"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The molecular epidemiology of influenza
viruses</article-title><source>Semin
Virol</source><year>1995</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>70</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9-idmm-26-e1"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ndifon</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wingreen</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential neutralization efficiency of hemagglutinin epitopes,
antibody interference, and the design of influenza vaccines</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad
Sci USA</source><year>2009</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>8701</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19439657</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b10-idmm-26-e1"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Popova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Immunodominance of antigenic site B over site A of hemagglutinin of
recent H3N2 influenza viruses</article-title><source>PLoS
One</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e41895</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22848649</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b11-idmm-26-e1"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koel</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Bestebroer</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Substitutions near the receptor binding site determine major antigenic
change during influenza virus
evolution</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2013</year><volume>342</volume><fpage>976</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24264991</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b12-idmm-26-e1"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Two residues in the hemagglutinin of A/Fujian/411/02-like influenza
viruses are responsible for antigenic drift from
A/Panama/2007/99</article-title><source>Virology</source><year>2005</year><volume>336</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15866076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b13-idmm-26-e1"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skowronski</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Janjua</surname><given-names>NZ</given-names></name><name><surname>De Serres</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A sentinel platform to evaluate influenza vaccine effectiveness and
new variant circulation, Canada 2010&#x02013;11 season</article-title><source>Clin Infect
Dis</source><year>2012</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>332</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22539661</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b14-idmm-26-e1"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohmit</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrie</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Malosh</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Influenza vaccine effectiveness in the community and the
household</article-title><source>Clin Infect
Dis</source><year>2013</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>1363</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23413420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b15-idmm-26-e1"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skowronski</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Janjua</surname><given-names>NZ</given-names></name><name><surname>De Serres</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Low 2012&#x02013;13 influenza vaccine effectiveness associated with
mutation in the egg-adapted H3N2 vaccine strain not antigenic drift in circulating
viruses</article-title><source>PLoS
One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e92153</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24667168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b16-idmm-26-e1"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>McMenamin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Durnall</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness of trivalent seasonal influenza vaccine in preventing
laboratory-confirmed influenza in primary care in the United Kingdom: 2012/13 end of season
results</article-title><source>Euro
Surveillance</source><year>2014</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25033051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b17-idmm-26-e1"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>HQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundaram</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Influenza vaccine effectiveness in the United States during
2012&#x02013;13: Variable protection by age and virus type</article-title><source>J Infect
Dis</source><year>2014</year><month>11</month><day>18</day><comment>[Epub ahead of
print]</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b18-idmm-26-e1"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control
(ECDC)</collab><article-title>Surveillance report: Influenza virus
characterization</article-title><source>Summary
Europe</source><month>9</month><year>2014</year><comment>&#x0003c;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ecdc.europa.eu/en/publications/Publications/Influenza-ERLI-Net-report-Sept-2014.pdf">www.ecdc.europa.eu/en/publications/Publications/Influenza-ERLI-Net-report-Sept-2014.pdf</ext-link>&#x0003e;
(Accessed December 19, 2015).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b19-idmm-26-e1"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control
(ECDC)</collab><article-title>Surveillance report: Influenza virus
characterization</article-title><source>Summary
Europe</source><month>11</month><year>2014</year><comment>&#x0003c;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ecdc.europa.eu/en/publications/_layouts/forms/Publication_DispForm.aspx?List=4f55ad51-4aed-4d32-b960-af70113dbb90&#x00026;ID=1235">www.ecdc.europa.eu/en/publications/_layouts/forms/Publication_DispForm.aspx?List=4f55ad51-4aed-4d32-b960-af70113dbb90&#x00026;ID=1235</ext-link>&#x0003e;
(Accessed December 19, 2015).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b20-idmm-26-e1"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castilla</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez-Baz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Navascues</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Vaccine effectiveness in preventing laboratory-confirmed influenza in
Navarre, Spain: 2013/14 mid-season analysis</article-title><source>Euro
Surveill</source><year>2014</year><volume>19</volume><comment>pii:</comment><fpage>20700</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24556347</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b21-idmm-26-e1"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Advisory Committee Statement &#x02013; National Advisory
Committee on Immunization (NACI)</collab><article-title>Statement on seasonal influenza vaccine for
2014&#x02013;2015</article-title></element-citation></ref><ref id="b22-idmm-26-e1"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>United States Centers for Disease Control &#x00026;
Prevention</collab><article-title>Interim guidance for influenza outbreak management in long-term
care facilities</article-title><comment>(last updated December 19, 2011) &#x0003c;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.cdc.gov/flu/professionals/infectioncontrol/ltc-facility-guidance.htm">www.cdc.gov/flu/professionals/infectioncontrol/ltc-facility-guidance.htm</ext-link>&#x0003e;
(Accessed December 19, 2015).</comment></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>