<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">Recruitment was from 13th January 2015 until 14th February 2015. During this period, as patients arrived at the clinic, staff transferred their HIV clinic folder to the clinic reception, where SG would screen the folders of the first ten patients for eligibility, and all those eligible were invited to participate. Once those eligible had participated, the next available ten folders were screened, this system was continued until the sample size was reached. Eligibility criteria were aged 25 years and older, on ART for at least 6 months and not knowingly pregnant at the time of interview. All participants gave written informed consent and interviews were conducted in a private clinic room on the same day. During the interview, data on the patient’s age, sex, current and past smoking habit, self-reported previously diagnosed comorbidities: hypertension, diabetes, chronic respiratory disease (CRD), and epilepsy were collected through administration of a questionnaire. These NCDs were selected as a priority due to their high prevalence in this population. In addition, these conditions represent health system priorities for the Western Cape province, as evidenced by the fact that NCD weekly outpatient clinics and adherence clubs exist for these conditions, and that the Department of Health annual audit for NCDs focuses on these conditions as a part of primary care service provision [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. The diagnosis of these NCDs is in line with guidelines set out by the South African government for primary care [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Specifically hypertension was diagnosed based on two elevated (&gt; 140/90) blood pressure readings, diabetes diagnosed on the basis of a random blood glucose measurement &gt; 11 and fasting blood glucose &gt; 7, CRD was a clinical diagnosis based on symptoms and risk factors as set out in the primary care guidelines [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], and epilepsy diagnosed by a physician with specialist expertise based on the presence of two seizures with no other clear cause.
</p>
