<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">Because of the unusually high incidence of thrombotic complications despite prophylactic anticoagulation, some centers recommend a higher dose for prophylactic anticoagulation (e.g., enoxaparin 40 mg twice a day rather than the conventional dosing of 40 mg once a day) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Although there appears to be a consensus about treating all hospitalized patients with some form of anticoagulation, dosing strategies are not yet clear. The ISTH interim guidelines and some other expert opinions have proposed that routine therapeutic anticoagulation is not advised (even in patients who required mechanical ventilation); instead, prophylactic doses of LMWH should be considered in the absence of contraindications [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>. The dose recommended remains controversial, with some experts advocating intermediate doses (0.5 mg/kg/dose twice a day). However, this approach of either standard or intermediate dose prophylaxis has been questioned and systemic anticoagulation with unfractionated heparin infusion is routinely used for critically ill patients in some centers [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. This approach is recommended because CAC is considered to be an overwhelmingly thrombotic DIC with pulmonary embolism being difficult to diagnose in patients who require mechanical ventilation. Also, bleeding is noted to be rare even in sick patients, and hence the risk of therapeutic anticoagulation is not as great as other patients with sepsis-induced coagulopathy. Hyperfibrinogenemia with fibrin deposition in the air spaces and lung parenchyma due to a hypofibrinolytic state is well recognized in these patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Fibrin deposition can occur even before appearance of symptoms of infection as identified in lung biopsy specimens of two patients with lung cancer [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. There is limited experience in the use of fibrinolytic therapy with tissue plasminogen activator (TPA). It has been used in off-label fashion in three patients with a noted improvement in oxygenation [increase in partial pressure of oxygen (PaO
 <sub>2</sub>)/fraction of inspired oxygen (FiO
 <sub>2</sub>) (
 <italic>P</italic>/
 <italic>F</italic>) ratio] [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. Nebulized TPA may be effective with less risk of bleeding and this is currently being examined in a clinical trial (NCT04356833). A recent review has recommended standard prophylactic dose of anticoagulation in hospitalized but well patients, intermediate dose prophylaxis to those admitted in ICU and ARDS, and therapeutic anticoagulation to those with presumed or confirmed deep vein thrombosis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Currently, there are 19 trials registered with clinicaltrials.gov that are investigating anticoagulation in these patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>] (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). These are mainly adult trials with only one pediatric study. One registered study aims to look at antiplatelet agents to prevent cardiac complications. Outcomes from these trials (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) will be important for our understanding of the optimum anticoagulation strategy in this infection to prevent thrombosis-associated complications.
</p>
