<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Trop Med Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Trop Med Health</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Tropical Medicine and Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1348-8945</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1349-4147</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">240</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s41182-020-00240-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Letter to the Editor</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>COVID-19 pandemic in sub-Saharan Africa: preparedness, response, and hidden potentials</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5804-7990</contrib-id><name><surname>Osseni</surname><given-names>Issideen Ayinla</given-names></name><address><email>osseni.isdeen@yahoo.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.258164.c</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1790 3548</institution-id><institution>Department of Clinical Medicine, International School, </institution><institution>Jinan University, </institution></institution-wrap>510632 Guangzhou, People&#x02019;s Republic of China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412037.3</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0382 0205</institution-id><institution>Department of Medicine, </institution><institution>UAC Health Sciences Faculty, </institution></institution-wrap>Cotonou, Benin </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>17</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>48</volume><elocation-id>48</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">After the detection of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) first reported case in Nigeria, the virus has spread to all sub-Saharan Africa (SSA). Through different initiatives, SSA countries came together to create goal-driven taskforces to improve their responses against the virus. As COVID-19 raises major concerns over the scarcity of medical supplies, numbers of SSA countries adopted innovative solutions to fill in their shortage. This health crisis may come as an opportunity for SSA to demonstrate its pandemic readiness, responses, and reveal unknown potential.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>Pandemic</kwd><kwd>Sub-Saharan Africa</kwd><kwd>Preparedness</kwd><kwd>Response</kwd><kwd>Potential</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="Par11">To the editor,</p><p id="Par12">On 11 March 2020, COVID-19 caused by SARS-CoV-2 was declared a pandemic by the World Health Organization (WHO) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Nations across the globe respond swiftly and different mitigation measures were enforced such as travel and movement restriction, gathering prohibition, generalized or partial lockdown, handwashing, and good hygiene promotion. The first instance of COVID-19 in SSA was reported on 28 January 2020 in Nigeria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], and it has now spread to all SSA. With a vulnerable health care system, SSA countries are faced with multiple health challenges arisen from the COVID-19 pandemic. For instance, to avoid escalation in the numbers of cases and having hospitals submerged with patients, SSA governments put in place mitigation measures that limit population movement, therefore, breaking the chain of contamination. As a result, patients suffering from endemic diseases such as HIV, tuberculosis (TB), and malaria have limited access to health services hence prone to rationalized their medicines. Consequently, this situation will contribute to the appearance of drug-resistant pathogens, increase complications, and mortality from these endemic diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Another major concern was that the pandemic would prove difficult to be controlled in SSA because most countries have poor health systems and inadequate health infrastructures.</p><p id="Par13">A report from the World Bank showed that in 2017, SSA spent 5.17% of its total GDP on health. This number is far less than the 9.89% spent by the Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Consequently, there is less money spent on the development of its healthcare system. This resulted in under-maintained infrastructure, shortage of health workers while those available are inadequately trained, scarce supplies of personal protective equipment, ventilators, intensive care units (ICU) beds, and other medical necessities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p><sec id="Sec1"><title>Preparedness and response</title><p id="Par14">To avoid a potential health disaster, it was therefore important for SSA countries to take responsibility against the pandemic with the help of WHO, Non-Governmental Organizations (NGOs), and other healthcare run programs. Preventive measures such as the COVID-19 awareness campaign, debunking myths surrounding the disease, flight cancellations, gathering restrictions, handwashing, and good hygiene promotion were quickly enforced. Across SSA, governments have created presidential task forces for public health and pledged millions of dollars to be directed against the pandemic. On February 22, 2020, in response to the covenant reached by Africa Health Ministers during a meeting convened by the African Union Commission, the collaboration between Africa Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (Africa CDC) and the Southern Africa Center for Infectious Disease Surveillance (SACIDS) gave birth to Africa Taskforce on Coronavirus Preparedness and Response (AFTCOR) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. AFTCOR is a continent-wide strategy for COVID-19. It will build on existing monitoring systems and process the laboratory diagnosis and subtyping; surveillance, including screening at points of entry and cross-border activities; infection prevention and control in health care facilities; clinical treatment of people with severe COVID-19; risk communication; and supply chain management and stockpiles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. After the detection of their first few cases, some countries went on full lockdown while some decided to only contain affected areas. Meanwhile, many other SSA countries were having difficulties detecting COVID-19 cases because of inadequate testing capacities. On April 21, 2020, the Partnership to Accelerate COVID-19 Testing (PACT): Trace, Test &#x00026; Track (CDC-T3) was launched by the African Union Commission and the Africa CDC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. This new initiative aims to strengthen the capacity to test for COVID-19 across Africa, with emphasis on countries that are in dire need. As a result, at least 10 million Africans, who would have not been tested otherwise, will get tested in the next 6 months.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Detective work, adaptability, and innovative response</title><p id="Par15">Even with the best mitigation measures in place, viruses are more difficult to deal with than other microorganisms, so early detection is the best way to curb COVID-19 exponential spread. After the detection of their first cases, Health officials across SSA began an extensive detective work looking for people that were on the same plane as the patients (COVID-19 carrier) and people that have been in contact with them. To alleviate this exhaustive labor, some SSA countries such as Nigeria have come up with innovative technology like Mobile Location Data tracking. This lessens health official&#x02019;s efforts by either individualized or aggregated tracking the mobile phones of confirmed cases to trail the movement of suspected patients and their contacts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Similar initiatives were launched in Benin, Ethiopia, and South Africa as part of the COVID-19 management strategy.</p><p id="Par16">All over SSA, public-private partnerships are coming to life to channel scarce resources toward this pandemic. For instance, in Uganda, automotive manufacturer Kiira Motors Corporation has teamed up with the Makerere School of Public Health to develop inexpensive ventilators for critically ill coronavirus patients. These ventilators will still be valuable post-COVID-19 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Likewise in Nigeria, the federal government is in talks for a partnership with Innoson motors to manufacture low-cost ventilators. Countries like South Africa and Ghana are also looking into producing cost-effective ventilators. Meanwhile, researchers from the Pasteur Institute in Senegal have developed a cheap and quick diagnostic test for the virus. It cost one US dollar and gives results in 10&#x02009;min [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>].</p><p id="Par17">Despite economic meltdown, spiraling inflation, and political unrest over the past decade, universities in Zimbabwe are making medical supplies such as face masks, gloves, and hand sanitizers that meet standards amid generalized containment measures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Whereas in Kenya, a country that barely produces any surgical mask before grab attention when a clothes factory shifted its assembly line towards manufacturing 30,000 surgical masks a day. This transformation came in line to fill the shortage of surgical masks after the government made them compulsory to be worn in public [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Also in Kenya, a 3D company is making 3D face shields and has also printed prototype for a ventilator adaptor that could allow doctors to treat either two or four patients at the same time.</p><p id="Par18">To prevent COVID-19 spread, the government of South Africa has rolled out mobile testing units to avoid the movement of potentially infected people. These mobile laboratories are deployed nationwide for a large scale screening to trace and monitor the disease propagation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Meanwhile, in Benin, the government took an unprecedented step toward E-learning to limit the movement of students in overcrowded public universities. The ministry of education created a platform of E-learning where students could interact with teachers on video, using internet cost-free, via local network [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p><p id="Par19">Many more innovative and adaptive solutions came alive during this global crisis and to further support more flourishing efforts, Youth in Africa Initiative of the African Development Bank created the #AfricaVsVirus challenge. The goal of this approach was to develop tech and non-tech solutions to the most pressing challenges triggered by the coronavirus pandemic with the opportunity of winning up to 50,000 US dollars in in-kind prizes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Learning from experience</title><p id="Par20">Endemic diseases such as malaria, tuberculosis, and HIV are well known in SSA. Over the past decades, SSA has been subjected to emerging viral diseases such as Ebola and Lassa fever. Although being a health burden, these emerging viral diseases have provided several SSA countries vital health lessons, knowledge, and expertise [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. For instance, the establishment of Africa CDC which was modeled on the US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention was officially launched in January 2017 by the African Union after the 2014&#x02013;2016 Ebola epidemic, to prevent and improve the surveillance and emergency response to infectious diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. During the past Ebola outbreak, National Infection Prevention Control (IPC) plans were developed and published in each country, with IPC task forces established to coordinate infection control efforts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Learning from the past outbreak lead to the development and testing of evidence-based protocols to improve both patient management and the implementation of public health interventions. More importantly, SSA has learned the value of community engagement to help overcome cultural barriers to pass on educational messages for a successful implementation of all interventions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par21">The coronavirus pandemic poses major challenges all over the world. To improve and strengthen their responses against COVID-19, SSA countries came together under the control of Africa CDC to create different taskforces. The shortage of medical supplies and personal protective equipment is created by the pandemic lead numbers of SSA countries to adopt innovative counter-measure. Countries that have never produce surgical masks, gloves, sanitizers, or ventilators before have turned to domestic production. However, an important need remains to ensure the long-term sustainability of all the efforts underway. SSA needs investments and political will to continue its upward path to align public health resources, public-private partnerships, and scientific expertise to prevent, control, and manage future outbreaks before they become an epidemic. Also, this is an opportune occasion for SSA to further research on the potential of Traditional Medicine.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>SSA</term><def><p id="Par2">Sub-Saharan Africa</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>COVID-19</term><def><p id="Par3">Coronavirus disease 2019</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Africa CDC</term><def><p id="Par4">Africa Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WHO</term><def><p id="Par5">World Health Organization</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AFTCOR</term><def><p id="Par6">Africa Taskforce on Coronavirus Preparedness and Response</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PACT</term><def><p id="Par7">Partnership to Accelerate COVID-19 Testing</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SACIDS</term><def><p id="Par8">Southern Africa Center for Infectious Disease Surveillance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OECD</term><def><p id="Par9">Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IPC</term><def><p id="Par10">National Infection Prevention Control</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Not applicable</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author&#x02019;s contributions</title><p>I, alone, contributed to this paper. The author(s) read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>No funding was used to write this paper.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>All data used are publicly available, and sources are cited throughout.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par22">Not applicable</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par23">Not applicable</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par24">There are no conflicts of interest.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cucinotta</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>WHO declares COVID-19 a pandemic</article-title><source>Acta Biomed</source><year>2020</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.23750/abm.v91i1.9397</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32191675?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32191675</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Adepoju P. Nigeria responds to COVID-19; first case detected in sub-Saharan Africa. Nat. Med. 2020; <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/d41591-020-00004-2</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Amimo F, Lambert B, Magit A. What does the COVID-19 pandemic mean for HIV, tuberculosis, and malaria control?. Trop Med Health. 2020; <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s41182-020-00219-6</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">The world Bank. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SH.XPD.CHEX.GD.ZS?contextual=max&#x00026;end=2017&#x00026;locations=ZG-1W&#x00026;start=2000">https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SH.XPD.CHEX.GD.ZS?contextual=max&#x00026;end=2017&#x00026;locations=ZG-1W&#x00026;start=2000</ext-link>. Accessed 30 May 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nuwagira E, Muzoora C. Is Sub-Saharan Africa prepared for COVID- 19?. Trop Med Health. 2020; <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s41182-020-00206-x</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Africa Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://africacdc.org/news-item/africa-cdc-partners-with-sacids-on-covid-19-preparedness-and-response/">https://africacdc.org/news-item/africa-cdc-partners-with-sacids-on-covid-19-preparedness-and-response/</ext-link>. Accessed 12 May 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nkengasong JN, Mankoula W. Looming threat of COVID-19 infection in Africa: act collectively, and fast. Lancet. 2020; <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736</pub-id>(20)30464-5.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Africa Center for Disease Control and Prevention. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://africacdc.org/news-item/african-union-and-africa-centres-for-disease-control-and-prevention-launch-partnership-to-accelerate-covid-19-testing-trace-test-and-track/">https://africacdc.org/news-item/african-union-and-africa-centres-for-disease-control-and-prevention-launch-partnership-to-accelerate-covid-19-testing-trace-test-and-track/</ext-link>. Accessed 13 May 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ekong I, Chukwu E, Chukwu M. COVID-19 mobile positioning data contact tracing and patient privacy regulations: exploratory search of global response strategies and the use of digital tools in Nigeria. JMIR Mhealth Uhealth. 2020. 10.2196/19139.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wakabi M. Ugadan car maker in plans to make ventilators locally. The East African. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.theeastafrican.co.ke/scienceandhealth/Uganda-car-maker-in-plans-to-make-ventilators-locally/3073694-5528116-pw5eyk/index.html">https://www.theeastafrican.co.ke/scienceandhealth/Uganda-car-maker-in-plans-to-make-ventilators-locally/3073694-5528116-pw5eyk/index.html</ext-link>. Accessed 13 May 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Haque N. Senegal trials begin for $1 COVID-19 test kit. Al Jazeera," 28 April 2020. [Online]. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.aljazeera.com/news/2020/04/senegal-trials-1-covid-19-test-kit-200428132313740.html">https://www.aljazeera.com/news/2020/04/senegal-trials-1-covid-19-test-kit-200428132313740.html</ext-link>. Accessed 13 May 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Matiashe FS. Zimbabwe universities making face masks, gloves amid coronavirus. Microsoft Network. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.msn.com/en-au/news/world/zimbabwe-universities-making-face-masks-gloves-amid-coronavirus/ar-BB122wQ3">https://www.msn.com/en-au/news/world/zimbabwe-universities-making-face-masks-gloves-amid-coronavirus/ar-BB122wQ3</ext-link>. Accessed 13 May 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bearak M. The Kenyan factory that transformed into a surgical mask assembly line overnight. The Washington Post. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/africa/the-kenyan-factory-that-transformed-into-a-surgical-mask-assembly-line-overnight/2020/04/08/fac04912-783e-11ea-a311-adb1344719a9_story.html">https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/africa/the-kenyan-factory-that-transformed-into-a-surgical-mask-assembly-line-overnight/2020/04/08/fac04912-783e-11ea-a311-adb1344719a9_story.html</ext-link>. Accessed 13 May 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">South African Government News Agency. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.sanews.gov.za/south-africa/sa-rolls-out-mobile-covid-19-testing-units">https://www.sanews.gov.za/south-africa/sa-rolls-out-mobile-covid-19-testing-units</ext-link>. Accessed 13 May 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gouvernement de la Republique du Benin. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.gouv.bj/actualite/669/le-gouvernement-lance-plate-forme-learning-cours-ligne-dans-universites-publiques-benin/">https://www.gouv.bj/actualite/669/le-gouvernement-lance-plate-forme-learning-cours-ligne-dans-universites-publiques-benin/</ext-link>. Accessed 13 May 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Africa Vs Virus Challenge. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://africavsvirus.com">https://africavsvirus.com</ext-link>. Accessed 13 May 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kapata N, Ihekweazu C, Ntoumi F, Raji T, Chanda-Kapata P et al. Is Africa prepared for tackling the COVID-19 (SARS-CoV-2) epidemic. Lessons from past outbreaks, ongoing pan-African public health efforts, and implications for the future. Int J Infect Dis. 2020; <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2020.02.049</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Coltart CEM, Lindsey B, Ghinai I, Johnson AM, Heymann DL. The Ebola outbreak, 2013&#x02013;2016: old lessons for new epidemics. Phil. Trans. R. Soc. B. 2020; <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2016.0297</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>