<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Among the viral agents, specific therapy is recommended in encephalitis due to the herpes group of viruses. Acyclovir in a dose of 10 mg/kg administered as an intravenous infusion over 1 hour every 8 hours for 14 days (21 days in immuno-compromised cases) is indicated in HSVE 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>
 </sup>. The success of antiviral therapy depends on early institution of therapy. In many centers in the West, in the absence of an epidemic, acyclovir is started as soon as VE is suspected clinically, regardless of whether any evidence of localization is present. In the Indian context, no hard criteria can be laid down since the relative importance of HSVE in different regions of the country is not really known. It seems reasonable to start acyclovir in non-seasonal cases, especially if focal features are present or neuroimaging studies reveal temporal lobe involvement. The toxicity and side effects of acyclovir include bone marrow suppression, vomiting and hypotension after intravenous administration, and (occasionally) non-oliguric renal failure in dehydrated patients 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>
 </sup>. Confusion, hallucinations, seizures, and coma are rare. Blood counts and relevant biochemical parameters should be closely monitored. Caution should be exercised in the presence of renal impairment as 80% of the drug is excreted unchanged in the urine 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>
 </sup>. Relapses may occur in as high as 5% of cases 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>
 </sup>. Resistance to acyclovir is rare (about 0.5% in immunocompetent patients) 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>
 </sup>. Foscarnet is used for acyclovir-resistant HSE 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>
 </sup>. Acyclovir is also recommended for varicella zoster encephalitis, and ganciclovir is an alternative drug. A combination of ganciclovir and foscarnet is recommended for cytomegaloviral encephalitis 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>
 </sup>. Pleconaril is an investigational agent for enteroviral infections, which acts by inhibiting viral attachment and uncoating 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>
 </sup>. Oseltamivir can be considered for influenza (H1N1) encephalitis/encephalopathy 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>
 </sup>. Trials with interferon alpha and nasogastric ribavirin in JE in children have revealed no benefit 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>, 
  <xref rid="ref-62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>
 </sup>. The tetracycline drug minocycline is a known neuroprotective agent with antiviral properties and excellent penetration into CSF. A trial of nasogastric minocycline in AES in Lucknow revealed modest benefit in terms of both cumulative mortality at 3 months from onset and neurologic sequelae 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>
 </sup>. Intravenous azithromycin or oral minocycline/doxycycline is currently recommended for rickettsial meningoencephalitis 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>
 </sup>.Treatment of AIE is immunosuppression through high-dose methylprednisolone pulse therapy, intravenous immunoglobulin, plasmapheresis, rituximab, and azathioprine 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
