<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0075">Some aspects of prevention require resourcefulness or resources outside the reach of the individual or the community. But even when the requirements are known and accessible, prevention may not be achievable. Puerperal and postpartum sepsis still causes considerable morbidity and mortality worldwide despite the discovery of preventative measures more than a century ago. Tuberculosis remains a significant issue for underdeveloped countries and for deprived populations in rich countries. Vector borne infections such as malaria remain endemic in many parts of the world. The Zika virus, also transmitted through insect bites, has resulted in significant outbreaks. Wound infections, including tetanus affecting the umbilical cord in new-born babies, remain an important challenge in developing countries. Other infections that could be sexually transmitted such as HIV, syphilis, chlamydia, gonorrhoea and hepatitis B are largely preventable and influenced by individual behaviour. Blood borne infections such as hepatitis C, hepatitis B and HIV are influenced by individual behaviour and the quality of medical facilities. Many diseases such as tuberculosis, measles and meningitis, as well as those causing pandemics such as SARS, pandemic influenza and the recent Covid-19 corona virus infection are transmitted through droplets. Vertical transmission from mother to baby can occur during pregnancy or labour and is influenced by maternal behaviour and by the quality of medical care. All of this raises ethical questions that span a woman’s responsibility to herself or to the unborn baby, the responsibility of health services in relation to those who are at risk because of factors within or outside their control, and the degree of acceptable risk to health care personnel themselves. There are wider questions concerned with the role of health care personnel and how they can balance their role in relation to individual good, societal interests and wider determinants of health. Sociodemographic determinants can influence susceptibility to infections and the ability of individual women to seek help. The relevance of these questions emphasises the challenges to depictions of health care professionals as narrowly confined to delivering benefit whilst observing confidentiality, autonomy and justice. An important question relates to the role of doctors in jurisdictions that require some diseases to be notified to authorities or where there is a risk of transmission to partners or contacts.</p>
