<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the CNS, the TLR7-mediated apoptosis pathway leads to cell death under either physiological (eg. neurodegeneration) or pathological (eg. neurotropic virus infection) conditions [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008142.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008142.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008142.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. To investigate the role of TLR7 in EV71-related neurological damage, we therefore detected multiple markers of apoptosis including activated Caspase-3, DNA damage, and apoptosis-associated gene expression in the cerebral cortex of WT and TLR7
 <sup>-/-</sup> mice. Our observations revealed that the induction of apoptosis upon EV71-infection was significantly reduced in TLR7
 <sup>-/-</sup> mice. The coordinated neuroinflammatory response may be an important factor in neural injury [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008142.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In TLR7-mediated neural apoptosis upon EV71-infection, the level of IL-6 was predominantly induced in the cerebral cortex on days 3 and 5 after EV71 infection, and was also specifically modulated by TLR7. Subsequently, we assessed the role of IL-6 in TLR7-mediated neuropathogenesis upon EV71 infection. In an intracranial injection model, IL-6 blockade effectively protected EV71-infected mice from neurological lesion-related symptoms. Correspondingly, IL-6 blockade significantly reduced the induction of apoptosis in the cerebral cortex of EV71-infected mice, while IL-6 blockade mediated such protection is independent of the virus load. Similar with findings regarding that IL-6 blockade protects mice from EV71-induced immunopathogenesis in the intraperitoneal infection model [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008142.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Besides the TLR/TNFα/apoptosis/necroptosis pathway as a driver of neurodegeneration in Alzheimer’s disease [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008142.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1008142.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], we identified a distinct TLR7/IL-6/apoptosis axis in viral neural pathogenesis mediated by TLR7 upon EV71 infection 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>.
</p>
