<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par52">Very recently, Pilotto 
 <italic>and colleagues</italic> described the case of a SARS-CoV-2-positive 60-year-old Italian patient with a transient akinetic mutism due to encephalitis. The analysis of CSF, negative for several neurotropic viruses such as herpes (HSV-1 and 2, HHV-6, HHV-8, EBV, VZV), adenovirus, enterovirus, and Sars-CoV-2, revealed the high presence of pro-inflammatory cytokines, such as IL-6, TNF-α, IL-8, and pleocytosis, suggesting a possible cytokine-mediated hyperinflammation response to SARS-COV2 infection (Pilotto et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">2020</xref>). Interestingly, additional cases have been supported by positive virus detection in CSF. Morigughi 
 <italic>and colleagues</italic> described the occurrence of meningoencephalitis (diagnosis of aseptic encephalitis) in a 24-year-old male patient with SARS-CoV2 RNA positive detection in CSF samples, but not in nasopharyngeal swab. This man was found unconsciousness and with a stiff neck 9 days after symptom onset (headache, fever, and generalized fatigue at day 1, treated with antiviral and antipyretics under a first diagnosis of influenza; additional symptoms were worsening headache and sore throat at day 5) and experienced a transient generalized seizure during emergency transport to the hospital, and multiple epileptic seizures during emergency hospitalization. He had high CSF pressure (320mmH
 <sub>2</sub>O) and no evidence of brain edema. Further brain MRI revealed right lateral ventriculitis and encephalitis mainly on right mesial lobe and hippocampus and pan-paranasal sinusitis. Authors claimed that the symptoms of encephalitis and cerebropathia should be considered as first indication, as the respiratory ones, for the diagnosis of hidden COVID-19 patients, and suggest the importance to pay attention to nasal and paranasal condition in the diagnosis and treatment for SARS-CoV-2 (Moriguchi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2020</xref>).
</p>
