<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mechanical ventilation is generally used to assist or replace spontaneous breathing, involving two types, invasive ventilation and non-invasive ventilation. The former refers to mechanical ventilation that involves any instrument entering the trachea through the oral cavity, like trachea intubation and ECMO. Non-invasive ventilation, such as face or nasal masks, are generally appropriate for mild illnesses. Ventilator-associated pneumonia (VAP) frequently occurs in patients requiring mechanical ventilation, leading to high mortality, with an incidence from 5% to 67% depending on the population studied and the diagnostic criteria used (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Barbier et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B119" ref-type="bibr">Torres et al., 2017</xref>). In the process of orotracheal intubation, bacteria can rapidly migrate from the oral cavity and upper respiratory tract into the lungs (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">de Carvalho Baptista et al., 2018</xref>). Another risk factor is that ICU mechanical ventilation patients find it difficult to clear oral secretions via swallowing or coughing (
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">Paju and Scannapieco, 2007</xref>). Many studies have reported that the main pathophysiologic mechanism for VAP development is oropharyngeal colonization (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Doré et al., 1996</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Bahrani-Mougeot et al., 2007</xref>). Several members of the oral microbiota (e.g., 
 <italic>Streptococcus oralis, Prevotella salivae</italic>, and 
 <italic>Mycoplasma salivarium</italic>) have previously been detected by 16S rRNA gene analysis in the BALF samples of VAP patients (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Bahrani-Mougeot et al., 2007</xref>). Respiratory distress and hypoxemia are the main clinical symptoms in severe COVID-19 patients due to serous exudation and hyaline membrane formation of their alveolar spaces. Oxygen saturation, as measured in their fingers, of less than 93% or as low as 50% have been observed (
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">National Health Commission of the People’s Republic of China, 2020</xref>). Therefore, they require high-flow nasal cannula or higher-level oxygen support measures to correct this hypoxemia. The lung hypoxia created in these patients is a suitable environment for the growth of anaerobic bacteria including those from the oral microbiota. Therefore, more attention should be paid to potential infections arising from oral microbiota before, and during, mechanical ventilation.
</p>
