<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0170">The levels of PEDV-specific sIgA antibody in the colostrum/milk of dams are key to determine the extent of passive immunity of their piglets against PEDV infection (
 <xref rid="bib0375" ref-type="bibr">Langel et al., 2019a</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0380" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0370" ref-type="bibr">Langel et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0385" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0575" ref-type="bibr">Saif et al., 2012</xref>). The sIgA antibody is resistant to proteolytic enzymes and is highly efficient at neutralizing PEDV in the intestinal mucosa (
 <xref rid="bib0370" ref-type="bibr">Langel et al., 2016</xref>). In the mammary glands of female swine, however, there is an absence of lymphoid follicles for antigen processing and IgA or IgG antibody production (
 <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> A and B). The PEDV-specific sIgA antibodies in the colostrum and milk are produced by effector B cells or plasmablasts that migrate from the GALT of the PEDV-infected intestine to the mammary gland (
 <xref rid="bib0370" ref-type="bibr">Langel et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0385" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0575" ref-type="bibr">Saif et al., 2012</xref>). This is defined as the gut-mammary-sIgA axis, that was first described by Saif and Bohl in studies of immunity to TGEV [reviewed in (
 <xref rid="bib0575" ref-type="bibr">Saif et al., 2012</xref>)]. The details were reviewed previously (
 <xref rid="bib0370" ref-type="bibr">Langel et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0385" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0575" ref-type="bibr">Saif et al., 2012</xref>). The endothelium in the mammary glands contains specialized endothelial venules that attract and bind to the specific integrins on the surface of the IgA-plasmablasts, such as α4β7 and chemokine receptor 9 (CCR9) (
 <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">Bourges et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0280" ref-type="bibr">Jiang et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0580" ref-type="bibr">Salmon, 2000</xref>). Mucosal addressin cellular adhesion molecule 1 (MAdCAM-1) and chemokine ligand 25 expressed in the specialized venules (
 <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>D and E) interact with α4β7 and CCR9, respectively. Extravasated sIgA antibody-secreting cells reside in the alveoli-supporting fibrous stroma of the mammary glands (
 <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>A–C). The number of PEDV-specific sIgA antibody-secreting cells may positively correlate with the amount and density of these endothelial surface molecules in the mammary glands (
 <xref rid="bib0580" ref-type="bibr">Salmon, 2000</xref>), although the specific role of each surface molecule in the gut-mammary-sIgA axis needs to be better characterized.
</p>
