<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Within this context, influenza epidemiological and virological surveillance plays an essential role and it is carried out, at global level, by World Health Organization Global Influenza Surveillance and Response System (GISRS) (
 <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) and at European level, by the European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control (ECDC) (
 <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). The national influenza surveillance systems, together with the analysis of epidemiological features, have the specific goal to monitor the circulation of IVs, analyse antigenic, genetic and biological characteristics, also including the susceptibility to available antiviral drugs. Moreover, they work to recognize any new viral variants in order to implement the appropriate containment and prevention strategies in a timely manner (
 <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). In Italy, these activities are carried out by influenza surveillance system, named InfluNet, coordinated by the National Influenza Centre at the Istituto Superiore di Sanità (NIC/ISS). Influnet is based on the collaboration of sentinel practitioners who, starting from the 46th week of each year until the 17th of the following year, perform respiratory samples from patients with a clinical presentation of influenza-like illness (ILI) (
 <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>-
 <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). The regional influenza Laboratories perform isolations and antigenic characterizations of IVs during the epidemic season, to constantly monitor the different types/subtypes circulation and to evaluate the match between epidemic and vaccine strains. This is fundamental to formulate the vaccine composition of the following season, because the degree of match between circulating and vaccine strains is one of the factor, togheter with the characteristics of the person being vaccinated (such as their age and health), that contribute to the vaccine effectiveness (
 <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>-
 <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>).
</p>
