<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>RWV is the most commonly used platform for suspension culture, providing cells with the spatial freedom to display their natural affinities to co-localize and self-assemble, and this model is particularly useful for studying the innate immune response to microbial infections [
 <xref rid="B117-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>]. As an example, McConkey et al. recently described how that the trophoblast JEG-3 choriocarcinoma cell line recapitulates the morphological and secretory phenotypes associated with primary syncytiotrophoblasts when co-cultured in 3D with microvascular endothelial cells [
 <xref rid="B118-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>]. Additionally, 3D organoid models can be developed from stem cells to mimic in vivo tissues, and Turco et al. generated human trophoblast organoids that can be used to study development and dysfunction at the placenta, in addition to being viable for long-term culture [
 <xref rid="B119-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]. Nanotechnology has also enabled organs to be constructed on a microdevice, known as the organ-on-a-chip. An organ-on-a-chip can be broadly defined as a microfabricated cell culture device designed to model the functional units of human organs in vitro [
 <xref rid="B120-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>]. Several groups have reported the development of placenta-on-a-chip microdevices for the study of complex placenta responses. The placental barrier can be simulated in vivo to create a 3D microenvironment and flow system in both trophoblast and endothelial cells, resembling the dynamic environment in maternal and fetal circulations in the body [
 <xref rid="B8-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B119-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>,
 <xref rid="B120-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>,
 <xref rid="B121-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>,
 <xref rid="B122-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>]. Yin et al. modeled the placenta barrier using the organ-on-a-chip technology to investigate transfer at the maternal–fetal interface by co-culturing placental cells to mimic the placenta in vivo [
 <xref rid="B122-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>].
</p>
