<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig3">
 <label>Figure 3</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Identification of SMARCA2-regulated MxA cofactors. (
   <bold>a</bold>) A549-MxA were transfected with an siRNA targeting SMARCA2 (Dharmacon D-017253-01) or a non-targeting control siRNA (siNT). 72 h post siRNA transfection cells were infected with H5N1 strain A/Thailand/1(KAN-1)/2004 at an MOI of 1 and harvested using DNA/RNA shield (Zymo Research). RNA extraction, rRNA depletion and analysis of the respective transcriptome was performed by Zymo Research as part of the EpiQuest TM service. (
   <bold>b</bold>) Gene ontology term enrichment analysis of host mRNAs differentially regulated by depletion of SMARCA2 in infected A549-MxA cells. (
   <bold>c</bold>) Host cell factors whose mRNA abundance was strongly decreased after SMARCA2 knockdown were silenced in A549-MxA cells using siRNA pools. 66 h after siRNA transfection A549-MxA cells were either treated, or not, with IFN-α (25 U/mL) and infected 6 h later with H7N7-RL reporter virus (MOI = 0.3). After 24 h virus reporter activity was measured using Renilla-Glo (Promega) substrate (3 technical replicates). The heatmap indicates increased (green) or decreased (red) viral replication as compared to the non-targeting siRNA control (white). (
   <bold>d</bold>) Knockdown and infection was performed as in (
   <bold>c</bold>) but experiments were extended to A549-shMxA cells and only siRNAs resulting in strong increase of viral reporter activity were used for knockdown (see (
   <bold>c</bold>)) (6 technical replicates). (
   <bold>e</bold>) To assess MxA-dependent effects, the ratios of reporter virus activities (from (
   <bold>d</bold>)) between A549-MxA cells and A549-shMxA cells were calculated and are presented as a heat map (High ratios in green and low ratios in red). Log2FC = Log2 Fold Change.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_20458_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e938" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
