<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>These two approaches to drug discovery that we can call the “normal” and “reverse” approaches are, unfortunately, at the moment exclusive. The main reason for this is not only scientific but economic and political, and that is why this aspect should shortly be discussed here. We live in a segregated world with on the one side the “rich” Western countries with their own unsustainable complex economic system (capitalism) and, on the other side, the “poorer” non-Western countries with their more sustainable simpler economic systems. In Western countries, scientific research should lead to the creation of financial profits in the short term in order to sustain their complex economic system. In practice, this means that funding for research into (new) medicines will be made available only if research will lead to the development of a new drug that can be sold for a profit in order to create or sustain a company and keep people employed. In short, to keep the economy growing, profits need to be made. As such, there is nothing wrong with this approach, but it does however focus on the creation of wealth and employment on the short term, and not on the health of people. One advantage of this economic system on a scientific level is that these countries have extremely well-equipped laboratories to perform in-depth scientific research into new medicines, but as long as potential profits take centre stage. Because of this, research into medicinal plants has basically been stopped for the simple reason that a medicinal plant cannot be produced and sold in order to create wealth—it is just too inexpensive and will therefore not be able to financially sustain anyone or any company. Identifying a new lead compound from a medicinal plant will be supported to some degree, but only if the possibility of patenting and eventual profits exist. The harsh reality is that if a medicinal plant works or not (the science behind it) does not really matter at all—it just does not fit into the economic model. In non-Western countries, the focus is still primarily on the health of people and not on short-term direct profits. Here, medicinal plants have always played a role and will continue to do so as long as the main objective is the health of their citizens and not direct short-term profits. That people sell medicinal plants for a profit in these countries does of course take place, but this is not on a comparable scale to the cost of drugs in Western countries.</p>
