<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Progress in genome sequencing technologies has resulted in an exceptionally high number of SARS-CoV-2 genomes sequenced during the 2019–2020 COVID-19 pandemic. In fact, the COVID-19 pandemic is the second one in history, after the 2009 H1N1 influenza pandemic [
 <xref rid="B117-ijms-21-04546" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>,
 <xref rid="B118-ijms-21-04546" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>], for which genomic data have been generated almost in a real-time fashion, allowing a detailed reconstruction of transmission trees. Genome sequences have been made publicly accessible through several repositories, including a data sharing service hosted by the Global Initiative on Sharing All Influenza Data (GISAID) (
 <uri xlink:href="https://www.gisaid.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.gisaid.org/</uri>) [
 <xref rid="B119-ijms-21-04546" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>,
 <xref rid="B120-ijms-21-04546" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>]. In addition to public genome repositories, open-source platforms for real-time data visualization and analysis of genomic data are also available, including NextStrain (
 <uri xlink:href="https://nextstrain.org" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://nextstrain.org</uri>) and CoV-GLUE (
 <uri xlink:href="http://cov-glue.cvr.gla.ac.uk" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://cov-glue.cvr.gla.ac.uk</uri>). NextStrain is fed with sequences from the GISAID repository and uses the Augur bioinformatics toolkit (
 <uri xlink:href="https://github.com/nextstrain/augur" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://github.com/nextstrain/augur</uri>) for tracking molecular evolution and the Auspice software (
 <uri xlink:href="https://nextstrain.github.io/auspice/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://nextstrain.github.io/auspice/</uri>) for interactive visualization of phylogenomic data. Conversely, CoV-GLUE is a web application based on an integrated software environment called GLUE (Genes Linked by Underlying Evolution), designed to create bioinformatic resources based on viral genome sequences [
 <xref rid="B121-ijms-21-04546" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>]. CoV-GLUE is also based on GISAID data and contains a database of replacements and indels that have been found in previously sampled SARS-CoV-2 sequences. New SARS-CoV-2 genome sequences can be loaded into the platform to identify novel or known mutations, assign them to potential lineages and visualize them in a phylogenetic context.
</p>
