<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>CHIKF was first extensively described in children during outbreaks in India and South Asia during the mid-1960s (
 <xref rid="viruses-11-00294-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-11-00294" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-viruses-11-00294" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-11-00294" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-11-00294" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-11-00294" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. In Thailand, CHIKF was described as a dengue-like illness with fever, rash, arthralgia, and myalgia, with occasional hemorrhagic manifestations [
 <xref rid="B5-viruses-11-00294" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-11-00294" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-11-00294" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-11-00294" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-11-00294" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-11-00294" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In a cohort of 148 CHIKV-exposed children, Vu Qui et al. [
 <xref rid="B18-viruses-11-00294" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] described multiple dengue-like illnesses in the Saigon region that were difficult to diagnose during the acute period due to similar disease symptoms with dengue and that viral neutralization tests were necessary for a definitive diagnosis. During the 1964 CHIKV outbreak in Madras, India, Jadhav et al. [
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-11-00294" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] describe pediatric CHIKV infection in great detail. For 33 infants with a dengue-like illness, 11 were admitted to the hospital. All 11 infants had fevers with five having temperatures greater than 104 °F [
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-11-00294" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Ten of the 11 infants developed a macular erythematous rash [
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-11-00294" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Diarrhea was seen in four infants and severe arthralgia in one infant [
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-11-00294" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Two infants experienced febrile seizures [
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-11-00294" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Later studies explained that the outbreaks in Thailand and Vietnam were caused by CHIKV of the Asian lineage [
 <xref rid="B25-viruses-11-00294" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].
</p>
