<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recent concerns of malaria spreading worldwide have focused interest on prevention with transmission-blocking vaccines, which protect mosquitoes. These vaccines are designed to generate neutralizing antibodies against the antigens of the sexual-phase gametocytes or ookynetes that infect mosquitoes. TBV vaccines do not protect the vaccinated individual but, if used at high coverage, interrupt the transmission of Malaria in endemic areas (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). TBV vaccines include assays with the P25 and P28 ookynete surface proteins (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). In contrast to the PEV and BSV vaccines, which have already been assayed in completed Phase III trials, the assays of the Pfs25 antigen are in early development and so far, have only completed Phase I trial assays, though with success. In one of them, the Pfs25 protein was engineered as a VLP, manufactured in 
 <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> plants, and was formulated with Alhydrogel (
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>). In a second Phase I trial, Pfs25 was conjugated to the recombinant, detoxified ExoProtein A from 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> (
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>). The efficacy of TBV vaccines has been tested using membrane assays. In these experiments, mosquitoes are fed on chicken embryo membranes that cover small receptacles containing human blood infected with 
 <italic>Plasmodium</italic>. The addition of plasma of humans vaccinated with Pfs25 to the infected blood caused a reduction of the oocytes and sporozoites found inside the guts of the insects (
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>). Currently, a phase II trial is evaluating the efficacy of P25-based vaccine in Malian adults (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). In comparison to PBV and BSV, there are fewer concerns about genetic diversity regarding the P-25-based vaccines (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>).
</p>
