<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Using the model that provides the best prediction for the season total cases in the three provinces (i.e., a 2-strain model with BL incidence for Macca and the 2-strain model with SAT incidence for both Madina and Riyadh), we predicted the total number of cases in the following year. Using the parameter estimates in the last prediction point (i.e. 48
 <sup>th</sup> week) of the current season, we draw 1000 samples. Based on these parameter samples, we determined 1000 estimates of the season total cases in the next year[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. We then defined a large outbreak in the forthcoming season in a particular region, as those events when cases exceeded the total number of cases in the previous season by more than one standard deviation (see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0008065.g005">Fig 5</xref>). Thus, the probability of a large outbreak (P
 <sub>l</sub>) in those provinces isdetermined as the ratio of samples that exceed the total number of cases in a season divided by the total number of samples. We also considered the case when two strains of MERS-CoV may be co-circulating in the human population in Saudi Arabia. We also simulated the situation when one strain is assumed to be more active with a higher transmission rate, whilst the other is much less transmissible among individuals in the different provinces of Saudi-Arabia[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].Although we have considered two strains circulating in the community setting, we do not distinguish among strains in hospital premises. This is due to the lack of strain specific data in hospital settings. However, we are able to distinguish the contribution of infection from Community and Hospital setting by estimating the Community reproduction number (R
 <sub>C</sub>) and the Hospital reproduction number (R
 <sub>H</sub>). However, to account for this effect, we propose three different forces of infection (BL, NM and SAT) to model the MERS transmission in the three provinces. Saturated (SAT) functions describe “Crowding effects” in disease transmission, whereas Non-monotone (NM) functions are used to incorporate”psychological effects”. As the CFR in MERS-CoV is about 40%, it is easily expected that awareness in front of a MERS-CoV situation may play an important role during an epidemic[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Thus a model with such a crowding effect might seem a priori more realistic in comparison to the bilinear (BL) transmission (see also 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0008065.g002">Fig 2</xref>). The crowding effect in disease transmission[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] can also be interpreted as the behavioral change of susceptible individuals when the number of infected individuals increases (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0008065.g002">Fig 2</xref>). This fact causes a lower number of new infections when a large number of infected individuals are already present in the community. This behavioral change in the susceptible population may occur due to, for instance, public health awareness campaigns and alerts raised by local or international authorities. The psychological effect is somewhat similar to the crowding effect, but with the effect of fear being added to the awareness. The psychological effect is stronger as the transmission rate decreases more rapidly with an increasing number of infected individuals (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0008065.g002">Fig 2</xref>) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Recently, Kucharski et al.[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] suggested that MERS-CoV transmission is over dispersed and hence outbreaks can include super-spreading events. In a similar study, Nishiura et al.[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] concluded that super-spreaders who visited multiple healthcare facilities drove up the epidemic by generating larger number of secondary cases. Therefore, we also consider the role of potential super-spreaders in the context of a 2-strain model with BL incidence function.
</p>
