<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0020">Clinical manifestations of RSV infection in young children include nasal congestion, difficulty breathing potentially resulting in respiratory distress, bronchiolitis and pneumonia with or without fever, as well as apnea in young infants. While RSV associated illness is common in children less than 5 years of age, moderate to severe disease is seen primarily in infants. RSV disease in infants under 6 months of age accounts for about half of documented RSV cases in many studies. The vast majority of RSV-related hospitalizations occur in young children during the first two years of life. In one prospective cohort study in Arizona, US, almost 30% of infants with a medically attended illness in the first year of life was due to RSV, which was usually diagnosed as bronchiolitis or pneumonia 
 <xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref> and similar rates have been observed in developing countries 
 <xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. At least 2% of all US infants are hospitalized with RSV disease, with the peak occurrence in the second month of life. Hospitalization rates are higher in risk groups including premature infants and those with underlying cardiac or pulmonary diseases. Infants in aboriginal populations such as Native Americans or Alaska Natives may have hospitalization rates 3–5 times higher than that of the general US population 
 <xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. To date, RSV treatment is mainly supportive and consists of respiratory support and fluid management. Support to treat apnea associated with RSV infection in preterm and very young infants may also be required. Despite the relatively minimal care typically administered to RSV-infected children in industrialized countries, RSV-related mortality is substantially higher in low and middle income countries 
 <xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>.
</p>
