<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In order to investigate the temporal signal, we regressed root-to-tip genetic distances from this ML tree against sample collection dates using TempEst v 1.5.1 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk</ext-link>) [
 <xref rid="CIT0010">10</xref>]. The ML phylogeny was used as a starting tree for Bayesian time-scaled phylogenetic analysis using BEAST 1.10.4 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://beast.community/index.html" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://beast.community/index.html</ext-link>) [
 <xref rid="CIT0011">11</xref>]. We employed a stringent model selection analysis using both path-sampling (PS) and stepping stone (SS) procedures to estimate the most appropriate molecular clock model for the Bayesian phylogenetic analysis [
 <xref rid="CIT0012">12</xref>]. We tested a) the strict molecular clock model, which assumes a single rate across all phylogeny branches, and b) the more flexible uncorrelated relaxed molecular clock model with a lognormal rate distribution (UCLN) [
 <xref rid="CIT0013">13</xref>]. Both SS and PS estimators indicated the uncorrelated relaxed molecular clock (Bayes Factor = 4.3) as the best fitted model to the dataset under analysis. Besides, we have used the he HKY+G4 codon partitioned (CP)1 + 2,3 substitution model and the Bayesian Skyline coalescent model of population size and growth [
 <xref rid="CIT0014">14</xref>]. We computed MCMC (Markov chain Monte Carlo) duplicate runs of 100 million states each, sampling every 10,000 steps. Convergence of MCMC chains was checked using Tracer v.1.7.1 [
 <xref rid="CIT0014">14</xref>]. Proper mixing of the MCMC was checked for ESS values &gt;200 for each estimated parameter using Tracer 1.7. Systematic Biology. 2018;67(5):901–4). A Maximum Clade Credibility (MCC) trees was obtained from the tree posterior distribution using TreeAnnotator (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://beast.community/index.html" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://beast.community/index.html</ext-link>) after 10% burn-in.
</p>
