<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We reanalyzed a published dataset that tested both symptomatic and asymptomatic individuals during norovirus outbreaks at food catering settings in Japan from November 10, 2005 to December 9, 2006 (
 <italic>n</italic> = 55 outbreaks).
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>
 </sup> In that study, a total of 2,229 involved individuals, including food-handlers, other workers, and potentially exposed customers, were examined for the presence of symptoms (ie defined as either non-bloody diarrhea or vomiting) and also virus shedding from their feces, conducting a survey shortly after each outbreak (within 1 week). Asymptomatic individuals were defined as persons without diarrhea and vomiting, and the asymptomatic ratio was defined as the proportion of asymptomatically infected individuals among the total of infected individuals. Through stool specimen tests using highly sensitive real-time reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR), which has the highest detection limit among all existing genome testing methods
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>
 </sup> the virus and its genogroup/genotype were identified. Due to its highly sensitive nature, the real-time RT-PCR was shown to detect positive norovirus specimens if &gt;10 copies were included in a well.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>
 </sup> Since asymptomatic healthy individuals as well as symptomatic cases were tested, the results in each outbreak are classified into four categories, ie, (i) symptomatic and virus positive, (ii) symptomatic but virus negative, (iii) asymptomatic and virus positive, and (iv) asymptomatic and virus negative. In addition to the number of people in each category for each outbreak, genotyping results were obtained. Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">1</xref> summarizes the survey results, and the coded data are given in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sm01">eTable 1</xref>. It should be noted that the number of asymptomatic and virus-negative individuals includes both uninfected individuals and infected cases without virus shedding. The abovementioned study
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>
 </sup> has been very rigorous, in that all individuals involved in each food-borne outbreak were fully surveyed, which has been extremely rare and not routinely attainable. In addition, such a study must employ the highly sensitive real-time RT-PCR, a condition that was also satisfied by the 2005–2006 study.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>
 </sup> Moreover, all events were observed in the same year in Japan within food handling facilities of comparable sizes.
</p>
