<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2">Coxsackievirus A16 (CA16), which belongs to the human enterovirus A species of the Picornaviridae family, is one of the major causative agents of hand, foot, and mouth disease (HFMD), which is a common infectious disease mostly seen in children under 5 years old
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>
 </sup>. In most instances, HFMD is a benign, self-limiting disease that is often characterized by fever, pharyngitis, and vesicular eruptions on the hands and feet, as well as in the mouth
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>
 </sup>. However, in some epidemic outbreaks, severe progressive HFMD with fatalities has been observed
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>
 </sup>. The occurrence of high mortality is usually concomitant with central nervous system (CNS) complications, such as acute flaccid paralysis, aseptic meningitis, brainstem encephalitis, and pulmonary edema
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup>. Currently, three companies in mainland China, namely, Beijing Vigoo Biological Co., Ltd. (Vigoo), Sinovac Biotech Co., Ltd. (Sinovac), and the Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences (CAMS) have successfully developed inactivated EV71 vaccines. All three vaccines have been reported to have high safety and efficacy for preventing EV71 infections, but they have no cross-protective effects on other enterovirus infections, including CA16
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>
 </sup>. Previous studies have indicated that most CA16 infections present only mild symptoms. However, accumulating evidence in recent years has demonstrated that CA16 might actually be more virulent in children and has induced severe cases of CNS complications and fatal outcomes, which were similar to those of EV71 infections
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup>. Furthermore, some severe and fatal HFMD cases with CA6 and CA10 infections have shown a clear increasing trend in recent years
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup>. Taken together, these findings demonstrate that it is important to explore the underlying molecular basis of HFMD pathogenesis and progression induced by CA16 infections, which might provide novel approaches for the development of vaccines that cover multiple species of enterovirus.
</p>
