<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="brief-report"><?OLF?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?covid-19-tdm?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">World J Pediatr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">World J Pediatr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>World Journal of Pediatrics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1708-8569</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1867-0687</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Singapore</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Singapore</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7297931</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">375</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12519-020-00375-z</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Personal Viewpoint</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Pediatric COVID-19: what disease is this?</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6682-5529</contrib-id><name><surname>Hon</surname><given-names>Kam Lun Ellis</given-names></name><address><email>ehon@hotmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6689-7194</contrib-id><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>Karen Ka Yan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1">Department of Paediatrics and Adolescent Medicine, The Hong Kong Children&#x02019;s Hospital, Hong Kong SAR, China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>1</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Children's Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine 2020</copyright-statement><license><license-p>This article is made available via the PMC Open Access Subset for unrestricted research re-use and secondary analysis in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for the duration of the World Health Organization (WHO) declaration of COVID-19 as a global pandemic.</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p id="Par2">The coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic spares no nations or cities causing escalating incidence and mortality. Royalty, prime ministers, celebrities and high government officials alike have been affected by the disease. For peculiar reasons, children and infants have generally been spared in Hong Kong, China until recently, when returning students from affected cities with the virus who largely presented with mild symptoms. In fact, several countries have reported on pediatric COVID-19.</p><p id="Par3">According to the data gathered by the Centre for Health Protection, as of May 22, there have been 111 confirmed pediatric cases of COVID-19 in Hong Kong, China consisting of 62 males and 49 females, aged between 0 and 18&#x000a0;years old. All cases have been reported to be either mild or asymptomatic, with no pediatric intensive care unit (PICU) admissions and fortunately no deaths [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Most of the pediatric cases were imported cases (90%), and the remaining were mostly epidemiologically linked with local/possible local cases (7.2%), followed by those epidemiologically linked with imported cases (1.8%) and local cases (1%). The mean age for the imported cases is much higher than that of the non-imported cases (15.1 versus 6.5&#x000a0;years, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). When comparing the local proportion of COVID-19 infections in the 0&#x02013;19&#x000a0;years age group in Hong Kong, China with other countries (most of these countries use 19-years as their upper age limit), the percentage (14.3%) is very high (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). This can be explained by the aforementioned group of overseas students that have been imported to our city. Most of the local imported cases were travelers returning from the UK and the USA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. With over 1064 confirmed cases and four deaths, 10.4% of the infected patients were children (&#x02264;&#x02009;18&#x000a0;years old). The infection is generally very mild in children, and 39.6% were asymptomatic. This phenomenon is consistent with our experience with SARS 17&#x000a0;years ago, when most of the infected children also had mild clinical manifestations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. The Chinese mainland also has reported mortality and morbidity of pediatric COVID-19 cases and has concluded that the disease was generally mild [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Mortality is very low in children, and most of the known cases were teenagers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Similarly, low mortality and morbidity among children infected with severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) or middle east respiratory syndrome coronavirus or SARS-CoV had been observed in the literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Hence, it is reassuring that children are less likely to be adversely affected by COVID-19. In contrast, mortality appears to be higher in the local adult population at approximately 0.4% and even higher (3.7%) in the US [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of COVID-19 cases in the 0&#x02013;19&#x000a0;years old of different cities/countries<sup>a</sup></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Variables</th><th align="left">Hong Kong, China [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]</th><th align="left">Mainland China [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]</th><th align="left">Singapore<break/>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]</th><th align="left">Korea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]</th><th align="left">USA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]</th><th align="left">Italy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]</th><th align="left">United Kingdom<break/>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]</th><th align="left">Spain<break/>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Total COVID-19 cases in the study population</td><td align="left">1064</td><td align="left">72,314<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">802</td><td align="left">9037</td><td align="left">671,485</td><td align="left">20,686</td><td align="left">145,808</td><td align="left">198,863</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Infection in the 0&#x02013;19 y,&#x000a0;<italic>n </italic>(%)&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">153 (14.3)</td><td align="left">965 (1.3)<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">38 (4.7)</td><td align="left">573 (6.3)</td><td align="left">12,791 (1.9)<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left">268 (1.3)</td><td align="left">2365 (1.6)</td><td align="left">950 (0.5)<sup>d</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9">Demographics and case characteristics</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Age (y), median (IQR)</td><td align="left">18 (15&#x02013;19)</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">18 (5.8&#x02013;19)</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">No data</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Male:female</td><td align="left">1:0.76</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">1:1.38</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">No data</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Asymptomatic, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td align="left">53 (34.6)</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">No data</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Imported, <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td align="left">141 (92.2)</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">27 (71.1)</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">No data</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Symptoms onset to diagnosis (d), median (IQR)</td><td align="left">2 (0&#x02013;5)</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">No data</td><td align="left">No data</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Mortality</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">2<sup>&#x000a7;</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>COVID-19</italic> coronavirus disease 2019, <italic>IQR</italic> interquartile range. <sup>a</sup>Patients up to 19&#x000a0;years old were included as most cities/countries report data with this age range; <sup>b</sup>Include suspected COVID-19 cases; <sup>c</sup>Include patients&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;18&#x000a0;years old only; <sup>d</sup>Include patients&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;15&#x000a0;years old only</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par4">Reports of children with confirmed COVID-19 in mainland China have described mild cold-like&#x02009; with/without &#x02009;gastrointestinal symptoms and suggest that severe complications (e.g., acute respiratory distress syndrome, septic shock) appear to be uncommon. However, as with other respiratory illnesses, certain populations of children with underlying health conditions may be at increased risk of severe infection. One report stated that the detection of human-CoV alone or in co-infection with rhinovirus-C was independently associated with pediatric intensive care unit admission in young children hospitalized for lower respiratory infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>].</p><p id="Par5">The virus does not pass from pregnant women to fetuses during pregnancy. It appears that transmission does not include vertical routes, such as amniotic fluid, cord blood, or breast&#x000a0;milk [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Approved or clinically proven antiviral drugs recommended for COVID-19 in children do not exist. Clinical management includes prompt implementation of recommended infection prevention and control measures in healthcare settings and supportive management of complications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Children should engage in the usual preventive actions to avoid infection, including cleaning hands often using soap and water or alcohol-based hand sanitizer, avoiding contact with others who are sick, and staying up to date on vaccinations, including influenza vaccine.</p><p id="Par6">It is still unclear why coronavirus disease is milder in the pediatric population, similar to other respiratory viral illnesses. Mortality and morbidity of coronavirus disease are postulated to be due to the exaggerated cytokine storm that results in self-destruction of the lung parenchyma and other organ systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Similar to other respiratory viral diseases, such as the seasonal influenza, two demographic groups seem to have a higher propensity to die from the disease, namely frail elderly people with chronic disease and seemingly healthy adults with exacerbated autoinflammatory responses with cytokine storm syndromes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. In contrast, two groups of patients seem to survive epidemics of coronavirus infections with very mild symptoms, namely the children and infants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Our pediatric experience concurs with global data and allows us to reassure anxious parents of the benign nature of coronavirus among children and young people. Nevertheless, from a public health perspective, our current imperative is to contain these imported cases and to prevent onward transmissions, especially from children and young people to the elderly and vulnerable patients with co-morbidities. Coronavirus in mild or asymptomatic adolescent returners, like soldiers in the Trojan Horse, have to be contained. Universal masking, vigilant contact tracing, surveillance programs for testing suspected cases and social distancing are proven effective non-pharmaceutical interventions that are indispensable for containing the epidemic. The global battle against the coronavirus continues.</p><p id="Par7">The latest engima associated with pediatric COVID-19 is a novel multisystem inflammatory syndrome (MIS) of hyperinflammation resembling toxic shock syndrome, atypical Kawasaki disease (KD) or the Kawasaki disease shock syndrome (KDSS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Another novel acronym, PIM-TS is coined which stands for pediatric multisystem inflammatory syndrome temporally associated with SARS-CoV-2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Although controversial, common respiratory viruses including adenovirus, enterovirus, rhinovirus, coronavirus and respiratory syncytial viral have long been reported to be associated with KD. We postulate that SARS-CoV-2 may behave like any respiratory virus that can occasionally cause MIS, KDSS or the multi-organ dysfunction syndrome so familiar to the intensivists. Perhaps, we do not need another acronym.</p></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Both authors contributed to the drafting and opinions in this viewpoint article, and approved the final version of the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>None.</p></notes><notes notes-type="ethics"><title>Compliance with ethical standards</title><notes id="FPar2"><title>Ethical approval</title><p id="Par9">None for this viewpoint article.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par8">No conflict of interest.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Centre for Health Protection. Latest situation of cases of COVID-19. 2020. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.chp.gov.hk/files/pdf/local_situation_covid19_en.pdf">https://www.chp.gov.hk/files/pdf/local_situation_covid19_en.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 23 May 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>McGoogan</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characteristics of and important lessons from the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) outbreak in China: summary of a report of 72314 cases from the Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.2648</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32515813?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32515813</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ministry of Health Singapore. Official update of COVID-19 situation in Singapore. 2020. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://experience.arcgis.com/experience/7e30edc490a5441a874f9efe67bd8b89">https://experience.arcgis.com/experience/7e30edc490a5441a874f9efe67bd8b89</ext-link>. Accessed 29 Mar 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Korean Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. The updates on COVID-19 in Korea as of 24 March. 2020. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.go.kr/board/board.es?mid=a30402000000&#x00026;bid=0030&#x00026;act=view&#x00026;list_no=366633">https://www.cdc.go.kr/board/board.es?mid=a30402000000&#x00026;bid=0030&#x00026;act=view&#x00026;list_no=366633</ext-link>. Accessed 29 Mar 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Cases of coronavirus disease (COVID-19) in the U.S. 2020. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/cases-updates/cases-in-us.html">https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/cases-updates/cases-in-us.html</ext-link>. Accessed 27 Apr 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, National Center for Health Statistics. Provisional death counts for coronavirus disease (COVID-19). 2020. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nvss/vsrr/covid19/index.htm">https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nvss/vsrr/covid19/index.htm</ext-link>. Accessed 27 Apr 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">National Institute of Health. Epidemia COVID-19. 2020. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.epicentro.iss.it/coronavirus/bollettino/BollettinosorveglianzaintegrataCOVID-19_19-marzo2020.pdf">https://www.epicentro.iss.it/coronavirus/bollettino/BollettinosorveglianzaintegrataCOVID-19_19-marzo2020.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 28 Mar 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Public Health England. The weekly surveillance report in England. 2020. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/886696/COVID19_Weekly_Report_20_May.pdf">https://assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/886696/COVID19_Weekly_Report_20_May.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 23 May 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ministry of Health. Report on COVID-19 in Spain. 2020. https://www.isciii.es/QueHacemos/Servicios/VigilanciaSaludPublicaRENAVE/EnfermedadesTransmisibles/Documents/INFORMES/InformesCOVID-19/Informen26.Situaci&#x000f3;ndeCOVID-19enEspa&#x000f1;aa27deabrilde2020.pdf. Accessed 28 Apr 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Novel Coronavirus Pneumonia Emergency Response Epidemiology Team</collab></person-group><article-title>The epidemiological characteristics of an outbreak of 2019 novel coronavirus diseases (COVID-19) in China</article-title><source>Zhonghua Liu Xing Bing Xue Za Zhi</source><year>2020</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>151</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32064853</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hon</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>KKY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Severe acute respiratory symptoms and suspected SARS again 2020</article-title><source>Hong Kong Med J</source><year>2020</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12809/hkmj208375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32077866</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Diagnosis, treatment, and prevention of 2019 novel coronavirus infection in children: experts&#x02019; consensus statement</article-title><source>World J Pediatr</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12519-020-00343-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32333248?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32333248</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>XX</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SARS-CoV-2 infection in children</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>382</volume><fpage>1663</fpage><lpage>1665</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMc2005073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32187458</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of COVID-19 among children in China</article-title><source>Pediatrics</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2020-0702</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32179660?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32179660</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gaubert J. Coronavirus in France: healthy 16 year-old dies of COVID-19. 2020. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.euronews.com/2020/03/27/coronavirus-in-france-healthy-16-year-old-dies-of-covid-19">https://www.euronews.com/2020/03/27/coronavirus-in-france-healthy-16-year-old-dies-of-covid-19</ext-link>. Accessed 28 Mar 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Brown L. Teen football player Jaquan Anderson dead from coronavirus in New Orleans. 2020. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://nypost.com/2020/03/27/teen-football-player-jaquan-anderson-dead-from-coronavirus-in-new-orleans/">https://nypost.com/2020/03/27/teen-football-player-jaquan-anderson-dead-from-coronavirus-in-new-orleans/</ext-link>. Accessed 28 Mar 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hon</surname><given-names>KLE</given-names></name><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>WTF</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>PKS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>WCW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwan</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical presentations and outcome of severe acute respiratory syndrome in children</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2003</year><volume>361</volume><fpage>1701</fpage><lpage>1703</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(03)13364-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12767737</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsuno</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gagliardi</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Paula</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name><surname>Luna</surname><given-names>LKS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jesus</surname><given-names>BLS</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Human coronavirus alone or in co-infection with rhinovirus C is a risk factor for severe respiratory disease and admission to the pediatric intensive care unit: a one-year study in Southeast Brazil</article-title><source>PLoS One.</source><year>2019</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>e0217744</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0217744</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31158256</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Working Group for the Prevention and Control of Neonatal 2019-nCoV</collab></person-group><article-title>Infection in the Perinatal Period of the Editorial Committee of Chinese Journal of Contemporary Pediatrics Perinatal and neonatal management plan for prevention and control of 2019 novel coronavirus infection</article-title><source>Zhongguo Dang Dai Er Ke Za Zhi.</source><year>2020</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32051071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>FWT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>EKO</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hon</surname><given-names>EKL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>RWK</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis Lo</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical, virologic and immunologic profiles of a young infant with severe acute respiratory syndrome</article-title><source>Pediatr Infect Dis J</source><year>2005</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>567</fpage><lpage>568</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.inf.0000164703.61282.3b</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15933575</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>CWK</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>FWT</given-names></name><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inflammatory cytokine profile in children with severe acute respiratory syndrome</article-title><source>Pediatrics</source><year>2004</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>e7</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.113.1.e7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14702488</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>McAuley</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tattersall</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Manson</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>COVID-19: consider cytokine storm syndromes and immunosuppression</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2020</year><volume>395</volume><fpage>1033</fpage><lpage>1034</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30628-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32192578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Licciardi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pruccoli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Denina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Parodi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Taglietto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosati</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SARS-CoV-2-induced Kawasaki-like hyperinflammatory syndrome: a novel COVID phenotype in children</article-title><source>Pediatrics.</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2020-1711</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32439816?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32439816</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alunno</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Carubbi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Carrio</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Storm, typhoon, cyclone or hurricane in patients with COVID-19? Beware of the same storm that has a different origin</article-title><source>RMD Open.</source><year>2020</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e001295</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/rmdopen-2020-001295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32423970</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shulman</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pediatric coronavirus disease-2019&#x02013;associated multisystem inflammatory syndrome</article-title><source>J Pediatric Infect Dis Soc.</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jpids/piaa062</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32441751?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32441751</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deza Leon</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Redzepi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>McGrath</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Haq</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Shawaqfeh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sethuraman</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>COVID-19&#x02013;associated pediatric multisystem inflammatory syndrome</article-title><source>J Pediatric Infect Dis Soc.</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jpids/piaa061</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32441749?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32441749</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hon</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>KKY</given-names></name><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>AKC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sridhar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Overview: The history and pediatric perspectives of severe acute respiratory syndromes: Novel or just like SARS</article-title><source>Pediatr Pulmonol.</source><year>2020</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>1584</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ppul.24810</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32483934</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>