<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0025">As of 4 June 2020, 54 countries are affected in Africa with 150 610 cumulative confirmed cases and 4281 reported deaths [
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The five most affected African countries are South Africa with 37 525 cases and 792 deaths, Nigeria with 11 166 cases and 315 deaths, Algeria with 9733 cases and 673 deaths, Ghana with 8548 cases and 38 deaths, and Cameroon with 6789 cases and 203 deaths, on June 4, 2020. The first confirmed African cases of SARS-CoV-2 were reported on 14 February 2020 in Egypt for north Africa [
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and on 27 February 2020 in Nigeria for Sub-Saharan Africa [
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Gilbert et al. estimated the risk of importation of cases of COVID-19 to Africa according to air travel flows from infected provinces of China to Africa and taking into account the African countries' capacity to detect COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The countries at highest importation risk from China were Egypt, Algeria, South Africa, Nigeria and Ethiopia. Three of these countries (South Africa, Algeria and Nigeria) are the three most affected countries and Egypt has recorded 28 615 cases and 1088 deaths. Another study predicted a high risk of exposure in countries of small size like Mauritius (1 097 013 estimated cases for 1 265 303 inhabitants; 335 confirmed cases on 4 June 2020) or Equatorial Guinea (819 289 estimated cases for 1 308 974 inhabitants; 1306 confirmed cases on 4 June 2020) [
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Using a branching process model, Pearson et al. estimated the number of cases of COVID-19 in each African country, and more especially the timing of reporting 10 000 cases for all African countries [
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. For instance, the timing of reporting 10 000 cases was between 11 and 18 April (3836 cases on 4 June 2020) in Senegal, 17 and 23 April (6585 cases on 4 June 2020) in Cameroon, 7 to 21 May (86 cases on 4 June 2020) in Angola and 23 April and 3 May (1486 cases on 4 June 2020) in Ethiopia. The data declared to WHO indicated the spread of COVID-19 in Africa but with lower confirmed cases than expected. We discuss several hypotheses that could explain the later emergence and spread of the COVID-19 pandemic in African countries.
</p>
