<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In 
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>
 </xref>b–g, we sketch common scenarios in which airborne and surface-mediated virus transmission can take place during daily life activities. When leaving an apartment building or entering indoor workplaces, elevator buttons and door handles (
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>
 </xref>b) offer surfaces of reduced area that are likely touched by many individuals and, thus, facilitate virus transmission. In addition, airborne viruses exhaled from infected individuals can be dispersed and effectively transmitted to healthy people in confined spaces such as elevators (
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>
 </xref>b), office pantries, and shared toilets (
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>
 </xref>f). The latter can additionally be contaminated by transfers of microorganisms to the air during flushing.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref51">51</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref52">52</xref>
 </sup> Buses and other means of public transportation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref53">53</xref>
 </sup> (
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>
 </xref>c) also involve many individuals sharing confined air in small spaces as well as frequent hand contact with small area surfaces such as handrails. Although often involving larger volumes, the work environment in shared offices (
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>
 </xref>d) and workshops can foster virus transmission as well because people spend long working hours inside of them. Similarly, public indoor spaces such as shops, restaurants, and cafeterias (
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>
 </xref>g) involve a high turnover of customers and, thus, represent another likely scenario for efficient virus transmission.
</p>
