<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0095">Cytokine storm refers to an aberrant or uncontrolled release of proinflammatory cytokines that lead to acute inflammation and pyrexia, which begins at a local site and spreads throughout the body via the systemic circulation. The previous out breaks of SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV have witnessed acute lung injury (ALI), ARDS and death which is accompanied by rapid virus replication that led to excessive inflammatory cell infiltration and cytokine storm [
 <xref rid="bb0270" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Similarly, now in COVID-19 outbreak, elevated cytokine levels are observed in critically ill patients. A case report by Chen et al., has observed a markedly higher levels of TNF-α, IL-10, IL-2R, and IL-6, with remarkable reduction in CD4+ and CD8+ T lymphocytes, nearly in all 11 severe cases tested as compared to 10 moderate cases. The reduction in T lymphocyte number may further reduce the production of IFN-γ [
 <xref rid="bb0275" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. These findings are in line with Pederson et al. and Diao et al. which demonstrated that the depletion of T cells and dysfunction in COVID-19, which can be implicated with the cytokine storm through the activation of highly inflammatory macrophages that produce the inflammatory cytokines and may dampen adaptive immunity against SARS-CoV-2 infection. Also, an increase in the inflammatory indicators such as D-dimer and procalcitonin were found [
 <xref rid="bb0280" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0285" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Based on the clinical data by Hui Li many critically ill COVID-19 patients developed typical sepsis symptoms such as cold extremities, shock weak peripheral pulses and severe metabolic acidosis and hypothesized that the viral sepsis could be one of the critical clinical manifestations in cytokine storm. However, very little is known about the involvement of Toll like receptors (TLR) [
 <xref rid="bb0290" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. In another case study, the COVID-19 patients plasma samples were analyzed for cytokines by multiplex assay, where IL-1β, IL-7, IL-10, IL-8, IL-9, basic FGF, IL1-RA, GM-CSF, G-CSF, IP-10, MIP-1A, MIP-1B, MCP-1, PDGF, TNF-α, VEGF, and IFN-γ were found to be elevated in both (Intensive care unit) ICU and non-ICU patients, while no apparent changes were found in the levels of IL-15, IL12p70, IL-5, Eotaxin, and RANTES when compared to healthy adults. On the other side, the higher plasma levels of IL-7, IL-2, IL-10, GSCF, TNF-α, MCP-1, MIP-1A, and IP-10 were observed in ICU patients in comparison with non-ICU patients. This data suggest that the disease severity might be through the involvement of cytokine storm with SARS-CoV-2 infected critically ill patients [
 <xref rid="bb0265" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Another case series was on 138 hospitalized patients, where the symptoms are consistent with the previously mentioned case report, all of the 138 patients showed bilateral involvement, critical illness was seen in older patients with co-morbidities. Apart from these symptoms, prolonged prothrombin and elevated lactate dehydrogenase levels were observed in 80 and 55 patients, respectively. Another observation was a gradual increase in blood urea, creatinine levels, neutrophils and lymphocytes counts before death. The other major complications during hospitalization are shock, arrhythmia, ARDS, and acute kidney injury [
 <xref rid="bb0295" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Chen and colleagues based on a retrospective, single-center study on 99 cases [
 <xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], subsequently, Qian and colleagues reported that in 67.03% infected patients had multilobe infiltration in 53.85% patient population and an elevated levels of C-reactive protein (CRP) was seen, further in 15.39% patients elevated levels of procalcitonin was detected. Interestingly, in one case report COVID-19 had been detected from the rectal swab, who suffered from abdominal symptoms but tested twice negative by throat swab [
 <xref rid="bb0300" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Therefore, along with the antiviral therapy it may be crucial to use anti- inflammatory agents in treating COVID-19 patients. Theoretically, corticosteroids may suppress lung inflammation, and they have been prescribed in 72.2% of ICU patients [
 <xref rid="bb0305" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>] but its efficacy in treating the cytokine storm in COVID-19 patients is still controversial as the concerns centered around their short-and long-term adverse effects as well as promotion of viral rebound and ARDS [
 <xref rid="bb0310" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>].Therefore, it is important to identify the cytokine storm in response to SARS-CoV-2 infection and the mechanism behind the cytokine storm. It would also be important to elucidate the role of anti-inflammatory agents against SARS-CoV-2 induced inflammation.
</p>
