<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0100">EBOV infection in survivors generated a higher anti-GP-binding antibody titer compared with ChAd3-MVA prime boost-vaccination. The observed differences in neutralization between EVD survivor samples with low (#28 &amp; #43) and high (#79 &amp; #92) titer suggest that EVD survivors may generate a variable immune response following EBOV infection. The difference in neutralization antibody titers and/or potency may correlate with antibody affinity and specificity for higher frequency of antibody binding to the fusion peptides and base of the stalk in samples #79 and #92 compared with #28 and #43, as observed with MAbs from survivors (
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Bornholdt et al., 2016</xref>). Real-time antibody kinetics of post-vaccination antibodies by SPR revealed limited antibody class switching and modest antibody affinity even after prime-boost vaccination compared with post-infection antibodies in EBOV survivors even with a similar timescale following vaccination/infection. The ChAd3-MVA (replication-defective) vaccination-induced antibody class switching and affinity was similar to that generated by rVSV-EBOV-GP (a replication competent virus) vaccination in our previous study (
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Khurana et al., 2016</xref>). Importantly, the GP-binding antibodies induced by EBOV infection were long-lasting responses, lasting up to 6 months post-infection, in contrast to the rVSV-EBOV GP prime-boost vaccination study that demonstrated a short-lived antibody response, which declined to pre-vaccination levels by 6 months post-vaccination (
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Khurana et al., 2016</xref>). Moreover, the presence of GP-bound IgG4 in most survivor plasma suggests a persistent infection or long-term exposure to antigen following EBOV infection. Since IgG2 response is mostly driven by polysaccharide antigens, an IgG2 response of 8.3% GP-binding antibodies in sample #92 obtained from six EVD survivors in Sierra Leone (who did not receive any experimental treatment) is speculated to be due to a possible polysaccharide antigen-induced class switching to IgG2 by highly glycosylated GP following infection.
</p>
