<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although the HA stalk based strategies have shown promising broad protection in animal models, potential safety issues have been raised (Crowe, 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Khurana, 
 <xref rid="B119" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). It is suggested that the stalk antibodies are responsible for antibody-dependent enhancement of viral infectivity in a swine model. In a study, pigs vaccinated with inactivated H1N2 vaccine developed more severe respiratory diseases upon heterologous H1N1 challenge as compared to the non-vaccinated control, which was ascribed to infectivity-enhancing effects of stalk antibodies (Khurana et al., 
 <xref rid="B120" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Similarly, the HA subunit vaccine resulted in vaccine-associated enhanced respiratory disease (VAERD) in pigs after heterologous challenge (Gauger et al., 
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Rajao et al., 
 <xref rid="B199" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). This effect cannot be generalized as the enhancement was noticed only in the adjuvanted antigen in a swine model, but not seen in similar studies with non-adjuvanted vaccines in a ferret model (Krammer et al., 
 <xref rid="B134" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). In addition, it has been recently shown that head-reactive, non-neutralizing monoclonal antibodies increase the stalk flexibility and membrane fusion kinetics, resulting in enhanced respiratory disease in a mouse model (Winarski et al., 
 <xref rid="B247" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). These results indicate that head-reactive antibodies may also induce antibody-dependent enhancement. However, similar observations in humans are debatable. For instance, humans immunized with 2008–2009 inactivated TIV exhibited an increase in illness following infection with 2009 H1N1 pandemic virus (Janjua et al., 
 <xref rid="B107" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Skowronski et al., 
 <xref rid="B211" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>) due to the presence of cross-reactive antibodies (Monsalvo et al., 
 <xref rid="B169" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Similar fatal cases were observed during 1957 H2N2 pandemic, although the relation of HA stalk antibodies to these observations is not known. It is noteworthy that NAI antibodies could reduce VAERD caused by mismatched heterologous HA, suggesting that vaccines which target HA protein alone may be prone to VAERD and cross-protective NAI antibodies may counteract VAERD (Rajao et al., 
 <xref rid="B198" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Although there is no report on VAERD associated with the headless or chimeric HA vaccines, careful monitoring is advised as these approaches rely heavily on stalk antibodies. The inclusion of NA antigens into HA stalk-based vaccine merits further evaluation. Another issue raised by a recent study is the auto-reactivity of stalk antibodies to human proteins, which is significantly higher than the head antibodies, as confirmed by multiple 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> assays (Bajic et al., 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2019b</xref>). Although biological implications of this observation have not been studied 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>, it was speculated that vaccine strategies focused exclusively on the stalk, or any single conserved epitope may fail to induce adequate antibody titers due to negative selection of the auto-reactive B cell clones (Bajic et al., 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2019b</xref>). However, clinical observations showed that, despite under potential negative selection, preexisting stalk antibodies conferred protection against the 2009 pandemic A/H1N1 infection in humans (Ng et al., 
 <xref rid="B178" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>).
</p>
