<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par13">Since 2007, this mosquito has been responsible in Europe for local CHIKV cases
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup> and DENV cases
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>
 </sup> stressing that the species is a competent vector to both arboviruses. The vector competence assessing the ability of a mosquito to transmit a pathogen is a measure which can be modulated by genetic, epigenetic and also environmental factors
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup>. Firstly, the outcome of infection depends on the specific combination between vector and pathogen genotypes described under genotype-by-genotype (G x G) interactions
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>
 </sup>. Notably, different mosquito generations in insectaries were used in this study; their vector competence for viruses could be affected due to adaptation to laboratory conditions. However, we initiated the mosquito population from a large size of field-collected mosquitoes to avoid inbreeding. This allowed to keep the population genetic diversity, and limit changes in mosquito fitness performance for 13 generations
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup>. Thus, the results of mosquito vector competence for arboviruses were expected to be reliable. Using experimental viral challenges, it has been shown that 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> from Southeast France was highly efficient to transmit CHIKV with virus detected in mosquito saliva from day 3 post-infection
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>, as was also 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> from Italy
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup>. Interestingly, CHIKV strains belonged exclusively to the ECSA genotype
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup>. Nine years after the emergence of CHIKV in the Indian Ocean region, CHIKV was detected in October 2013 in Saint-Martin Island in the Caribbean
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup> which against all expectations, belonged to the Asian genotype
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup>. Despite several hundreds of CHIKV cases imported to continental Europe from the Americas, no autochthonous transmission of the Asian CHIKV was reported. A previous study showed that low temperatures limit the transmission of the Asian genotype
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup> and not of the ECSA genotype providing further evidence that environmental factors such as the temperature can intervene in modulating the G x G interactions through genotype-by-genotype-by-environment (G x G x E) interactions
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
