<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Beyond the antiviral antibody response, the virus-host interactions that determine the magnitude and duration of vertebrate viremia following an arbovirus infection are poorly understood. In some cases, alphavirus particles interact directly with glycosaminoglycans (GAGs), such as heparan sulfate (
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Bernard et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Byrnes and Griffin, 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Gardner et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Heil et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Klimstra et al., 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">Smit et al., 2002</xref>), that are ubiquitously found on the surface of mammalian cells. Following serial passage in cell culture, alphaviruses frequently acquire adaptive mutations that enhance interactions between viral particles and GAGs. (
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Bernard et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Byrnes and Griffin, 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Heil et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Klimstra et al., 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">Silva et al., 2014</xref>). Alphaviruses that have acquired enhanced in vitro GAG binding are rapidly cleared from the circulation of mice (
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Bernard et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Byrnes and Griffin, 2000</xref>), suggesting that virion-GAG interactions are one mechanism that can determine the magnitude and duration of arboviral viremia. However, the extent to which specific GAGs contribute to clearance of circulating alphavirus particles has not been defined in vivo. Beyond GAGs, previous work demonstrated that opsonization of DENV particles by mannose binding lectin (MBL), which can neutralize particles via a C3-dependent mechanism, accelerated their clearance from the circulation of mice (
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Fuchs et al., 2010</xref>). However, we found that the innate clearance of circulating CHIKV and RRV was maintained in mice lacking C3 and in mice lacking antibodies, suggesting that the clearance of these circulating alphavirus particles occurs through a non-opsonic mechanism.
</p>
