<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22">All the recruited patients were required to be admitted in hospital for close monitoring despite no severe signs appearing at the time of admission. Non-structural (NS)-1 antigen test (Bio-Rad Laboratories Inc., Marnes-la-Coquette, France) positive patients were further confirmed by reverse transcription (RT) PCR and in-house IgM antibody capture enzyme linked immuno-sorbent assay (MAC-ELISA) or anti-dengue IgM/IgG ELISA as described previously (Additional file 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Primary and secondary dengue infections were determined using IgM/IgG ratios in acute and convalescent sera by capture ELISAs (Pasteur Institute, Vietnam). Secondary infection was defined when the IgM/IgG ratio was &lt; 1.8 or had a positive IgG result in acute phase with subsequent ≥ 4- fold rise in convalescent sera [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Likewise, DENV IgM positive case was considered to be primary infection when the ratio of IgM/IgG was ≥ 1.8 or had a negative IgG result in acute phase [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. NS1 positive patients (except 2 NS1 negative but RT-PCR positive patients) were recruited to ensure active (current) DENV infection (Additional file 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1). Also, anti-DENV IgG detection (Pasteur Institute) remained helpful to rule out past infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Therefore, we considered all the included patients had active DENV infection. With thorough clinical examinations and DENV specific assays (antigen, antibody and viral RNA) in a dengue endemic setting, it was less likely to have infections other than DENV.
</p>
