<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">Varicella epidemics in adults are not yet well studied. Previous studies have confirmed middle-aged and old adults with simultaneous occurrence of varicella and herpes zoster [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]; however, these rare cases with varicella and herpes zoster have seldom been reported. Here, we also described a rare case of varicella and herpes zoster in late adulthood. For this case, we excluded the possibility of contact with varicella or herpes zoster patients because his family members were healthy and he did not have a recent history of travel at home and abroad. The vesicles on the neck, trunk and back without dermatomal distribution were indistinguishable from the varicella in childhood; however, the vesicles in the left ear had dermatomal distribution and PHN, so we diagnosed this patient as a rare case. A total of 110 young university students were diagnosed with varicella during February 2016–January 2017 in India [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. A total of 22 adult foreigners from 8 countries experienced varicella during January 2012–December 2016 in central Tokyo, Japan [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. A 54-year-old Japanese woman also suffered from varicella caused by VZV [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]; however, this woman had secondary VZV infection because she had a high titre of VZV IgG. One of the important limitations in this study is not detecting the titre of VZV IgG because an ELISA kit was not available. The titre of HSV-2 IgM was detected, but the result was negative. Hence, we could not determine whether this patient had a secondary infection or reactivation of VZV. This rare simultaneous infection of varicella and herpes zoster in this patient was confirmed to be caused by VZV infection; however, if further differentiating between disseminated VZV infection and varicella, understanding the pathogenesis of varicella and herpes zoster occurring at the same time will provide more useful information for the treatment of VZV infection. Patients with varicella zoster disease of the central nervous system (CNS) may present without accompanying zoster rash [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], so our understanding of the molecular triggers for latent VZV remains largely unknown.
</p>
