<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since there are many types of HAdV, mAbs employed in diagnostic reagents for HAdV detection should ideally target highly conserved epitope types in order to minimize the risk of failure in detecting new emergent types, as recombination is an accepted feature of HAdV evolution. In this study, Fabs 2A6 and 4E2 with specific reactivity to HAdV were developed using phage antibody library technology and evaluated for their applicability in developing IFA for HAdV detection. Both Fabs were expressed in 
 <italic>E</italic>. 
 <italic>coli</italic> at a relatively high level, and purified Fabs could be obtained in only 3 days. Compared with other expression systems, the 
 <italic>E</italic>. 
 <italic>coli</italic> expression system is more economical and straightforward for protein production. Based on the design of the vector pComb3XSS, the fusion tags 6×His and HA allow for purification and detection of Fab. In addition to these tags, both Fabs also can be purified and detected by Protein L. We investigated the cross-reactivity of both Fabs to different types of HAdV using CLEIA and IFA, and the results demonstrated that both Fabs strongly reacted with HAdV-B3, B7, B11, B14, B55, and E4. The results of CLEIA and IFA differed between both Fabs, indicating that the HAdV-binding capacity of Fab 2A6 was stronger than that of Fab 4E2. The specificity was examined by CLEIA using other respiratory viruses, such as influenza virus (IFV) and RSV. We found no cross-reactivity between either Fab and IFV or RSV. The specificity and cross-reactivity of both Fabs to HAdVs indicated that the generated Fabs could be applied in the development of diagnostic tests for HAdV. When the generated Fabs are used to detect antigens in nasopharyngeal swab samples, they are specific to HAdV and will not recognize other viruses, ensuring that the results are reliable. Some mAbs with specificity to HAdV have been reported, but they recognize only one or several types within a single species[
 <xref rid="pone.0219091.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0219091.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0219091.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. In this study, the generated Fabs recognized several types within species B and HAdV-E4. So far, no mAbs have been reported that recognize all known types of HAdV. The number of HAdV types that are recognized by a diagnostic reagent can be increased using a pool of two or more noncompeting antibodies. The number of mAbs used in the development of a diagnostic reagent for HAdV detection can be decreased using the generated Fabs, as both Fabs recognized at least six types of HAdV.
</p>
