<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Methodologically, the identification of clusters of cases linked by transmission (i.e. cases belonging to the same transmission tree or stemming from a single introduction, here referred to as 'outbreak clusters’) is strongly related to other fields which have received considerable attention from statisticians and modellers over the last decades. First, it is closely linked to outbreak detection methods, which generally aim to identify excesses of cases compared to a reference ‘baseline’ in incidence time series [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006554.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006554.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], and are for instance routinely used to detect the beginning of seasonal influenza epidemics from surveillance data [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006554.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006554.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Some extensions to spatiotemporal data [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006554.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006554.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] have shown geographic information can be a useful complement to temporal data [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006554.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006554.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], but little efforts have been devoted to generalising these approaches to other types of data such as pathogen whole genome sequences (WGS). Second, the identification of outbreak clusters is also closely related to outbreak reconstruction methods, which infer transmission chains using complex outbreak models integrating multiple sources of data such as time, space, and WGS [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006554.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006554.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Lastly, population genetics has had a long-standing tradition of developing clustering methods [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006554.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006554.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], some of which have proved useful for studying pathogen populations [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006554.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006554.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Unfortunately, despite these connections to well-developed methodological fields, the integration of multiple data sources (e.g. epidemiological and genomic data) to identify outbreak clusters remains in its infancy [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006554.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].
</p>
