<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par32">Besides being able to infect hNPCs, HIV may also affect their maturation and the fate of neural stem cells. That HIV or gp120 can inhibit adult neurogenesis (Okamoto et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR376">2007</xref>; Lee et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR272">2013</xref>; Putatunda et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR410">2018</xref>) has been the topic of past reviews (Schwartz and Major 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR457">2006</xref>; Venkatesan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR524">2007</xref>; Peng et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR387">2008</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR388">2011</xref>; Ferrell and Giunta 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR154">2014</xref>; Hauser and Knapp 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR201">2014</xref>; Putatunda et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR411">2019</xref>). How HIV inhibits the self-renewal, tripotential differentiation, and survival of neural progenitors/stem cells or the genesis of adult neurons in the subgranular zone (SGZ) of the dentate gyrus is uncertain. HIV and gp120 [via actions at the same chemokine receptor(s) (Tran and Miller 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR510">2005</xref>; Li and Ransohoff 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR281">2008</xref>)] are proposed to modulate the adult neurogenesis via Notch (Fan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR150">2016</xref>), by obstructing a cell cycle checkpoint via the activation MAPK-activated protein kinase 2 and Cdc25B/C (Okamoto et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR376">2007</xref>), or through signaling by platelet-derived growth factor BB (Chao et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">2014</xref>) or BDNF (Lee et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR272">2013</xref>). The extent that HIV regulates the genesis of neural progenitors within the subventricular zone of the developing CNS through similar mechanisms as in the adult SGZ of the dentate gyrus is uncertain—even though HIV disrupts the generation of neurons and glia during maturation or in adults. For example, MAPK/ERK1/2 enhances p53- and p21-dependent downregulation of cyclin D1 hindering progression through the G
 <sub>1</sub> phase of the cell cycle in hNPCs (Mishra et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR342">2010</xref>; Malik et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR305">2014</xref>). Importantly, opioids too can affect the genesis of neurons and glia during maturation or in the adult directly via convergent pathways (Hauser and Knapp 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR202">2018</xref>; Kibaly et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR235">2018</xref>) suggesting yet another site of opioid and HIV interactions in dysregulating the creation and fate of new neurons and glia.
</p>
