<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Influenza virus continues to be a major public health concern, causing both annual epidemics and occasional pandemics (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). In a pandemic, a new influenza virus emerges and infects the human population which has little or no pre-existing immunity (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Vaccines remain the main method of infection control, however their timely implementation and poor immunogenicity in certain vulnerable patient groups remain a considerable problem (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Although antiviral drugs such as Oseltamivir are available to control the spread of the virus their effectiveness is limited in treating patients with influenza (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). There is clearly an urgent need for additional approaches and antibodies present new opportunities for both therapeutic and prophylactic intervention. Passive transfer of serum antibodies from convalescent patients has been used in the past (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>), however, this approach is of limited use in a global pandemic emergency. A much more promising strategy is to use recombinant monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) against influenza and several are currently in clinical development (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>–
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). These rare mAbs bind to functionally conserved epitopes such as those in the hemagglutinin (HA) stem, thereby providing strain independent protection. However, for passive immunotherapy to provide sufficient long-term protection, frequent repeated injections are required which would be prohibitively expensive in low resource areas. A more practical and cost-effective strategy would be to use antibody gene therapy which would provide long term sustainable protection through antibody production within the patient.
</p>
