<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Structural analysis of several of the earliest human mAbs against the influenza HA stem revealed the unusual feature that they employ only their heavy chains for antigen recognition (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). This implies that the light chains were not required for binding to these difficult to access epitopes. In addition, some of the most potent cross-neutralizing human mAbs described have very low levels of somatic hypermutation and are often constrained to particular germline genes (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). This suggests that they may be products of an immediate and sub-optimal immune response to influenza (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). This prompted our interest in naturally occurring “heavy-chain only” antibodies from camelids and our isolation of high affinity broadly neutralizing single domain antibodies (nanobodies) against influenza A and B (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). This antibody format is unique to camelid species (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) and can be isolated from immunized alpacas as highly optimized single domain binding units that have gone through extensive somatic hypermutation possibly due to the alpaca’s limited immune history of exposure to influenza (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). Nanobodies have several well-described advantages over conventional mAbs which make them ideal for applications in infectious disease (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>–
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). One interesting feature is that they have a preference for binding to clefts and grooves through unusually long CDR loops (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). In addition, their simple modular structure and single gene format enables easy engineering for different delivery and therapeutic applications (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>–
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). This next generation of antibodies has reached a significant milestone with the approval in September 2018 of the first nanobody, Caplicizumab
 <sup>TM</sup>, for the treatment of a blood clotting disorder (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>).
</p>
