<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is often necessary to transport specimens required for diagnosis across international borders, and this raises issues related to biological security for both animals and man. Legislation may require that sera are treated to inactivate any pathogens that are present in specimens. Several techniques can be employed, including chemical sterilization or heat treatment, but these might have deleterious effects on samples, compromising test sensitivity and specificity. As noted above, gamma irradiation represents an effective method for virus inactivation, but tests may require adjustment, as irradiation can in some circumstances affect their diagnostic sensitivity and specificity. Sera from cattle infected with 
 <italic>T. congolense</italic>, 
 <italic>T. vivax</italic>, and 
 <italic>T. brucei</italic> were irradiated with 30,000 Gy and then used in enzyme-linked immunosorbent assays (ELISAs) for detection of invariant trypanosomal antigens (Rebeski et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR152">1998</xref>). In samples where there were unequivocal positive or negative ELISA results, irradiation had no effect on the diagnostic sensitivity of the assays—all samples shown to be positive before irradiation remained positive and those shown to be negative remained negative. However, a statistically significant reduction in signal in each of the ELISAs was observed using the irradiated sera. Serum samples where the values for optical density before irradiation were close to the diagnostic cut-off showed a negative bias after irradiation. Without correction, these samples gave more false-negative test results upon irradiation. It was therefore necessary to adjust the diagnostic negative/positive threshold of the ELISAs using defined irradiated serum samples; otherwise, the frequency of false-negative results was increased. When irradiated sera were used in indirect ELISA tests for detection of antibodies to 
 <italic>T. congolense</italic> and 
 <italic>T. vivax</italic> (Rebeski et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR153">2001</xref>), optical density values were higher for most gamma-irradiated antibody positive and negative test samples than in the unirradiated samples. The intraplate precision and agreement between tested and expected values of measurements, however, were not altered. Although there was a bias of higher measurement values after gamma irradiation, this could be compensated after readjustment of the cut-off points to obtain best separation of antibody-positive and negative samples. Irradiation is also useful in inactivating samples that contain pathogens harmful to laboratory personnel. 
 <italic>B. anthracis</italic> samples exposed to 25,000 Gy could still be detected by real-time PCR and in fact detection of DNA targets was enhanced; in ELISA tests, the direct ELISA was affected negatively by irradiation, but a sandwich ELISA was unaffected (Dauphin et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2008</xref>). Irradiated antigens have also been used in the diagnosis of Rift Valley fever (RVF), where classical detection methods pose significant health risks and require as long as 7 days to produce results. A sandwich ELISA to detect IgM and IgG antibodies to RVF virus in domesticated livestock had high diagnostic sensitivity (Paweska et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR141">2003b</xref>), while an indirect ELISA had similar high diagnostic sensitivity and specificity in livestock and in a number of different wildlife species (Paweska et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR140">2003a</xref>). Irradiation of rinderpest virus with doses of 10,000–60,000 Gy led to a dose-dependent reduction in activity as measured by virus neutralization, ELISA, and IFAT. In a competitive ELISA, bluetongue virus (BTV) antigen irradiated at 10,000–60,000 Gy also showed a loss in immunoreactivity at the higher dose levels (Afshar et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">1991</xref>). A gamma-irradiated inactivated cell culture derived African horse sickness viral antigen has been used in a blocking ELISA (B-ELISA) for detecting antibody to a subgroup-reactive epitope of African horse sickness virus (House et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">1996</xref>). Foot and mouth disease virus irradiated from 10,000 to 45,000 Gy appeared to have unaltered antigenicity in blocking ELISA tests (Motamedi-Sedeh et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR126">2009</xref>).
</p>
