<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="brief-report"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">NPJ Vaccines</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">NPJ Vaccines</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>NPJ Vaccines</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2059-0105</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7338534</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">209</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41541-020-0209-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Comment</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Plasma-based COVID-19 treatments in low- and middle-income nations pose a high risk of an HIV epidemic</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2491-9866</contrib-id><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>Leonardo M. R.</given-names></name><address><email>leonardo.ferreira@ucsf.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1634-7514</contrib-id><name><surname>Mostajo-Radji</surname><given-names>Mohammed A.</given-names></name><address><email>mmostajo@rree.gob.bo</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Clubes de Ciencia Bolivia Foundation, Santa Cruz de la Sierra, Bolivia </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.266102.1</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2297 6811</institution-id><institution>Department of Surgery, </institution><institution>University of California San Francisco, </institution></institution-wrap>San Francisco, CA 94143 USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.266102.1</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2297 6811</institution-id><institution>Diabetes Center, </institution><institution>University of California San Francisco, </institution></institution-wrap>San Francisco, CA 94143 USA </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Ajax Biomedical Foundation, Newton, MA 02458 USA </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.266102.1</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2297 6811</institution-id><institution>The Eli and Edythe Broad Center of Regeneration Medicine and Stem Cell Research, </institution><institution>University of California San Francisco, </institution></institution-wrap>San Francisco, CA 94143 USA </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label>Embassy of Science, Technology and Innovation, Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Bolivia, La Paz, Bolivia </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.452939.0</institution-id><institution>Permanent Mission of Bolivia to the United Nations, </institution></institution-wrap>New York, NY 10017 USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>6</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>58</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1" abstract-type="Standfirst"><p id="Par1">Convalescent plasma therapy holds promise as a transient treatment for COVID-19. Yet, blood products are important sources of HIV infection in low- and middle-income nations. Great care must be taken to prevent plasma therapy from fueling HIV epidemics in the developing world.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Infectious diseases</kwd><kwd>Vaccines</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="Par2">The COVID-19 pandemic has inspired rapid research towards medications and vaccines to prevent the spread of the disease. Many drugs have been promoted as potential treatments for the disease, including hydroxychloroquine, azithromycin, Remdesivir, Avifavir, ivermectin, chlorine dioxide, among others<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. Their effectiveness has been based on small studies and massively inflated by the media, only to later show limited to no benefit in larger studies and, sometimes, even cause severe side effects. The reality is that, to date, there is no proven drug to treat COVID-19. A potential vaccine will take at least 1 year to be developed and tested. Yet, a promising strategy to hold down the fort has arisen: convalescent plasma therapy. Trials to treat COVID-19 using this method are being initiated in many countries, including low- and middle-income nations in Africa, Southeast Asia, and Latin America.</p><p id="Par3">Convalescent plasma therapy is based on the concept of passive immunity. Individuals who recover from SARS-CoV-2 infection have, in principle, developed neutralizing antibodies against the virus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Collecting plasma, the liquid component of blood, from someone who has recently recovered from COVID-19 and infusing it into someone with an ongoing infection would confer the plasma recipient with antibodies to combat the virus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Of note, this is an immediate transient treatment and does not replace the long-lasting immune memory generated by a vaccine. Indeed, high-affinity IgG antibodies have a half-life of up to three weeks in blood<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Nevertheless, the hope is that the infusion of convalescent plasma enriched in antibodies will substantially boost the recipient&#x02019;s immediate immune response to clear the virus.</p><p id="Par4">The infrastructure for collecting and administering plasma exists. The risks are known and rather low when the healthcare infrastructure is optimal. More than 16,000 patients at hundreds of US hospitals have received convalescent plasma therapy for COVID-19. A study in New York City found that convalescent plasma recipients had improved survival and less-supplemental oxygen requirements than control patients<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Yet, convalescent plasma therapy is not without its perils, especially in low- and middle-income nations with suboptimal healthcare infrastructures and less strict regulations. Blood transfusions can transmit blood-borne pathogens<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup> and lead to conditions such as transfusion-related acute lung injury and transfusion-associated circulatory overload<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. In fact, blood transfusions have been shown to represent an important source of HIV infection in many low- and middle-income countries, being associated with positive HIV status<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. It is unlikely that most low- and middle-income countries will be able to secure the blood supply by universal HIV testing<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Even when funding is provided, access to medical materials and supplies in the international market remains difficult for the developing world<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">For years, the United Nations Development Programme (UNDP) and the World Health Organization (WHO) have subsidized molecular testing in the developing world. One such program, the introduction of &#x0201c;all-in-one cartridge&#x0201d; systems for RNA sample isolation and PCR-based testing, has been used for HIV and tuberculosis diagnosis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. This technology has recently been approved for COVID-19 testing, although with significant delays in the delivery of reagents and supplies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Importantly, this platform has a higher cost and lower throughput than other PCR-based approaches. It allows the processing of only up to four samples per run, severely limiting its utility for COVID-19 and HIV PCR-based testing in larger communities. Moreover, governmental laboratories with RNA testing capabilities are currently saturated in many low- and middle-income countries<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>, leaving administrators to decide between testing for COVID-19 or HIV.</p><p id="Par6">Regulations worldwide have forbidden paid organ and tissue donations for decades. Yet, these measures remain far from effective, particularly, in the developing world<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. The reality of plasma donations is similar. In Bolivia, for instance, although law 1716 forbids any kind of payment for tissue donation, advertisements requesting paid plasma donations are common, even in prime time TV and national newspapers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Such strategy is likely to be successful, as media coverage has been shown to positively impact organ and tissue donation rates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. Some regions have circulating lists of infected individuals. Plasma donations are compensated with thousands of dollars, several times the local average monthly salary, and can be performed once a week. Patients who recover following convalescent plasma infusion are then encouraged to donate their plasma. In addition to resembling a pyramid-type scheme, such practice does not have a solid scientific rationale, as these patients are highly unlikely to have developed any neutralizing antibodies against SARS-CoV-2. In fact, even among individuals who recover from SARS-CoV-2 on their own, one-third have low or undetectable neutralizing antibody titers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Such a plasma black market is reminiscent of events in the 1990s in China, where an HIV epidemic began with local pay-for-plasma schemes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par7">Rapid and affordable antibody-based HIV and COVID-19 testing capacity must be escalated in the developing world. One possible strategy is to share plasmids with biomedical facilities in low- and middle-income countries, which could then locally produce the reagents for antibody-based testing, circumventing the high costs and waiting times associated with importing such tests from abroad<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Centers with a proven track record of testing for endemic contagious diseases in the developing world exist, some of them resulting from multinational collaborations with developed nations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Furthermore, antibody-based tests generated in-house may be more accurate and cost-effective than commercial ones<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>, so sharing parts and reagents (e.g., plasmids, purified antibodies) may be more desirable than already assembled testing kits. Importantly, conventional antibody-based HIV testing may miss early infection<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Hence, methods to detect viral nucleic acids directly remain desirable. Recently developed CRISPR-based methods to detect specific viral RNA sequences amenable to lyophilization, long-term storage, and reconstitution on paper represent a promising approach to detect the presence of SARS-CoV-2 and HIV, both RNA viruses, in locations with little to no healthcare infrastructures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. More bilateral and multilateral scientific collaborations between high- and low- and middle-income countries should be encouraged to gradually foster productive scientific collaboration and build local biomedical infrastructure<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par8">In summary, convalescent plasma therapy holds promise as an emergency transient treatment for critical COVID-19 patients. Nevertheless, it is of utmost importance to emphasize that, unlike chemicals, such as hydroxychloroquine, which can only harm the individual taking them, plasma therapy can endanger entire communities. In scenarios of scarce blood-borne pathogen testing capacities, few enforced regulations, and widespread misinformation and disease stigma, unregulated convalescent plasma therapy may well become a recipe for a new HIV epidemic in the developing world.</p></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Both authors wrote this manuscript.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par9">L.M.R.F. holds patents on cell-based gene therapy methods for HIV treatment. M.A.M.-R. is the Bolivian Science, Technology and Innovation Ambassador and leads the Bolivian COVID-19 response team. The authors declare no other conflict of interest.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An update on current therapeutic drugs treating COVID-19</article-title><source>Curr. Pharmacol. Rep.</source><year>2020</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40495-020-00216-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wu, F. et al. Neutralizing antibody responses to SARS-CoV-2 in a COVID-19 recovered patient cohort and their implications. <italic>medRxiv.</italic>10.1101/2020.03.30.2004736 (2020).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Liu, S. T. H. et al. Convalescent plasma treatment of severe COVID-19: a matched control study. <italic>medRxiv.</italic>10.1101/2020.03.30.20047365 (2020).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayton</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kinetics of FcRn-mediated recycling of IgG and albumin in human: pathophysiology and therapeutic implications using a simplified mechanism-based model</article-title><source>Clin. Immunol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>146</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clim.2006.09.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17046328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bihl</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Castelli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Marincola</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dodd</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name><name><surname>Brander</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transfusion-transmitted infections</article-title><source>J. Transl. Med.</source><year>2007</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>25</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1479-5876-5-25</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17553144</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Semple</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Rebetz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapur</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transfusion-associated circulatory overload and transfusion-related acute lung injury</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2019</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>1840</fpage><lpage>1853</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2018-10-860809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30808638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lepage</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Van de Perre</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nosocomial transmission of HIV in Africa: what tribute is paid to contaminated blood transfusions and medical injections?</article-title><source>Infect. Control Hosp. Epidemiol.</source><year>1988</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>200</fpage><lpage>203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/30146444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3372990</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nkengasong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Let Africa into the market for COVID-19 diagnostics</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2020</year><volume>580</volume><fpage>565</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/d41586-020-01265-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32346145</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ndlovu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multidisease testing for HIV and TB using the GeneXpert platform: a feasibility study in rural Zimbabwe</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>e0193577</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0193577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29499042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mehtar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Limiting the spread of COVID-19 in Africa: one size mitigation strategies do not fit all countries</article-title><source>Lancet Glob. Health</source><year>2020</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e881</fpage><lpage>e883</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2214-109X(20)30212-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32530422</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pe&#x000f1;aranda, R. &#x00026; Tancara, C. Cenetrop ha colapsado, tiene m&#x000e1;s de 2.000 muestras acumuladas. In <italic>Brujula Digital</italic> (La Paz, Bolivia, 2020).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Budiani-Saberi</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Delmonico</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Organ trafficking and transplant tourism: a commentary on the global realities</article-title><source>Am. J. Transpl.</source><year>2008</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>925</fpage><lpage>929</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-6143.2008.02200.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cuevas, A. Convocan a recuperados del COVID-19 de entre 18 y 60 a&#x000f1;os para donar su plasma. In <italic>L</italic><italic>a Razon</italic> (La Paz, Bolivia, 2020).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quick</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Examining the association between media coverage of organ donation and organ transplantation rates</article-title><source>Clin. Transplant.</source><year>2007</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1399-0012.2006.00628.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17425748</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">McLaughlin, K. China&#x02019;s history with AIDS explains a puzzling aspect of the &#x02018;CRISPR babies&#x02019; story. In <italic>STAT</italic> (New York, USA, 2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pirard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The validity of serologic tests for Trypanosoma cruzi and the effectiveness of transfusional screening strategies in a hyperendemic region</article-title><source>Transfusion</source><year>2005</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>554</fpage><lpage>561</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0041-1132.2005.04214.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15819677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leal</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Cortes</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cedillo-Rivera</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibody-based detection tests for the diagnosis of Helicobacter pylori infection in children: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2008</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>e3751</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0003751</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19015732</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hashida</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Shortening of the window period in diagnosis of HIV-1 infection by simultaneous detection of p24 antigen and antibody IgG to p17 and reverse transcriptase in serum with ultrasensitive enzyme immunoassay</article-title><source>J. Virol. Methods</source><year>1996</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0166-0934(96)02087-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8910647</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gootenberg</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nucleic acid detection with CRISPR-Cas13a/C2c2</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2017</year><volume>356</volume><fpage>438</fpage><lpage>442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aam9321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28408723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gronowski</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Who or what is SHERLOCK?</article-title><source>EJIFCC</source><year>2018</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><?supplied-pmid 30479604?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30479604</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carosso</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>LMR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mostajo-Radji</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scientists as non-state actors of public diplomacy</article-title><source>Nat. Hum. Behav.</source><year>2019</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1129</fpage><lpage>1130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41562-019-0716-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31427786</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>