<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par31">The basis of viral phylogenetic analysis with phyloscanner are subgraphs, sets of tips and internal nodes of a phylogeny that are attributed to one individual with a parsimony-based algorithm
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>. A single individual can have multiple subgraphs in one tree. The following statistics were calculated to characterize the phylogenetic relationship between two individuals 
 <italic>i</italic> and 
 <italic>j</italic> in one phylogeny:
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par32">Subgraph distance between 
    <italic>i</italic> and 
    <italic>j</italic> (Δ
    <sub>
     <italic>ij</italic>
    </sub>): The distance between any two subgraphs 
    <italic>u</italic>, 
    <italic>v</italic> is the shortest patristic distance between any nodes or tips of 
    <italic>u</italic> and 
    <italic>v</italic> and Δ
    <sub>
     <italic>ij</italic>
    </sub> is the minimum patristic distance between subgraphs 
    <italic>u</italic> from 
    <italic>i</italic> and 
    <italic>v</italic> from 
    <italic>j</italic>. Deep-sequence phylogenies from different parts of the genome had markedly different branch lengths, reflecting evolutionary rate variation across the genome. Prior to calculating subgraph distances, we standardized phylogenies by multiplying branch lengths with the ratio of expected branch lengths in the genomic window from which the tree was reconstructed, divided by the expected branch lengths in the 
    <italic>gag</italic> and 
    <italic>polymerase</italic> genes (Supplementary Table 
    <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par33">Adjacency of 
    <italic>i</italic> and 
    <italic>j</italic> (
    <italic>A</italic>
    <sub>
     <italic>ij</italic>
    </sub>): True if the shortest path between at least one subgraph 
    <italic>u</italic> from 
    <italic>i</italic> and 
    <italic>v</italic> from 
    <italic>j</italic> is not attributed to any sampled individual other than 
    <italic>i</italic> and 
    <italic>j</italic>, and false otherwise.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par34">Paths from 
    <italic>i</italic> to (
    <italic>P</italic>
    <sub>
     <italic>ij</italic>
    </sub>): number of subgraphs from 
    <italic>j</italic> which have as ancestor a subgraph from 
    <italic>i</italic>.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
