<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig2">
 <label>Fig. 2</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Pathogenesis and outcomes of COVID-19.</title>
  <p>
   <bold>a</bold> | Following infection of the lungs, (severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) induces the death of epithelial cells, in particular, type II pneumocytes, as part of the viral replication cycle. Macrophages and neutrophils elicit a specific innate immune response to eradicate the pathogen and kill virus-infected cells. The increase in pro-inflammatory cytokines within the lung leads to the recruitment of leukocytes, further propagating the local inflammatory response. Among these cytokines, interleukin-2 (IL-2), IL-6, granulocyte-colony-stimulating factor (GCSF), interferon-γ (IFNγ), IFNγ inducible protein 10 (IP-10), monocyte chemoattractant protein 1 and 3 (MCP1 and 3), macrophage inflammatory protein 1α (MIP-1α) and tumour necrosis factor (TNF) stimulate the adaptive immune response. At this stage, infiltration of lymphocytes (CD4
   <sup>+</sup> and CD8
   <sup>+</sup> T cells) and natural killer (NK) cells is required to ensure an optimal defence response against SARS-CoV-2. CD4
   <sup>+</sup> T cells mediate antibody production by B cells and also enhance effector CD8
   <sup>+</sup> T cell and NK responses during viral infections. This orchestrated immune response leads to viral eradication and resolution of the disease. In these patients, coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) seems to manifest as a mild disease with symptoms similar to the common flu that resolve spontaneously. 
   <bold>b</bold> | For unknown reasons, but possibly individual predisposition or differences in viral loads during primary SARS-CoV-2 infection, some patients experience more severe disease. A maladaptive immune response, characterized by lymphopenia and suppression of CD4
   <sup>+</sup> T cells, is likely accountable for the poor prognosis of these patients. In the absence of robust CD4
   <sup>+</sup> T cell activation, B cells generate a polyclonal antibody response that may be ineffective in neutralizing SARS-CoV-2. Increased numbers of exhausted T cells that express high levels of programmed cell death protein 1 (PD1), suggest decreased proliferation and activity of CD8
   <sup>+</sup> T cells. Similarly, NK cells exhibit increased levels of the inhibitory CD94–NK group 2 member A (NKG2A). Impaired cytotoxic activity results in persistent viral shedding that amplifies macrophage and neutrophil activation, leading to the massive production of cytokines (a process referred to as hypercytokinaemia). In these patients, COVID-19 manifests as a severe disease, consisting of advanced pneumonia and acute respiratory distress syndrome. The generation of excess cytokines and persistent viral infection leads to systemic vascular damage, disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC) and the failure of vital organs, including the kidney and the heart.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="41581_2020_357_Fig2_HTML" id="d30e571" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
