<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig4">
 <label>Fig. 4</label>
 <caption>
  <title>The effects of COVID-19 on the kidney.</title>
  <p>The kidney expresses high levels of angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) and transmembrane protease serine 2 (TMPRSS2) and has been identified as a target organ for severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) infection by several studies. 
   <bold>a</bold> | Within the glomerulus, podocytes and endothelial cells have been identified as specific sites for viral infection. SARS-CoV-2-induced podocyte dysfunction is likely to induce impairment of glomerular filtration, leading to proteinuria and haematuria, which are often observed in patients with coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19). Infection of endothelial cells alters glomerular capillary haemostasis and induces the formation of fibrin thrombi. 
   <bold>b</bold> | SARS-CoV-2 has also been found in proximal tubular cells, which exhibit high levels of ACE2 in the apical brush border. SARS-CoV-2 infection leads to loss of the brush border and vacuolar degeneration in tubular epithelial cells, with luminal debris composed of necrotic epithelium with evidence of complement activation and membrane attack complex (MAC) (C5b–9) deposition on tubular cells and massive macrophage infiltration in the kidney interstitium. 
   <bold>c</bold> | In addition, a non-viral-dependent mechanism might also be accountable for kidney dysfunction in the context of COVID-19, including a possible contribution of the 
   <italic>APOL1</italic> ‘risk’ genotype in inducing focal segmental glomerulosclerosis following SARS-CoV-2 infection, as well as the role of haemodynamic factors, cardiac dysfunction, high levels of mechanical ventilation, hypovolaemia, nephrotoxic drug treatments and nosocomial sepsis resulting in COVID-19-associated acute kidney injury (AKI).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="41581_2020_357_Fig4_HTML" id="d30e1427" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
