<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par30">Determining the safety and biocompatibility of MSNs is crucial owing to its variable characteristics. The data generated from literature suggest that careful control of particle size and shape is the determinant factor in the biodistribution and toxicity of MSNs. In addition, the safety and toxicity of MSNs also depend on the administered MSNs dosage. Surface MSNs properties also have a great impact on their biodistribution and biocompatibility (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>). The major toxicity pathway associated with silica is due to its surface chemistry (silanol groups) which can interact with the membrane components leading to the cells lysis and cellular components leaking (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>). Mesoporous silica exhibited lower hemolytic effect compared to non-porous silica (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>). This could be attributed to the lower density of silanol groups on the surface of mesoporous structures (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>). Authors (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>) made an attempt to study the single and repeated dose MSNs toxicity following intravenous administration in mice. LD50 of MSNs was found to be higher than 1000 mg kg
 <sup>-1</sup>. In single dose toxicity studies, mice were injected with MSNs at a low dose and high dose. At the higher dose of 1280 mg kg
 <sup>-1</sup>, mice did not survive. In contrast, the groups treated with low MSNs dose did not show any behavioral changes nor any hematology or pathological changes. To carry out the detailed repeated dose toxicity studies, intravenous administration of hollow MSNs (HMSNs) were given to mice continuously for 14 days and observed for a month. During the one-month observation period, no mortality was observed. Moreover, no remarkable changes in pathology or blood parameters were observed. In order to assess the MSNs fate after different administration routes, Fu 
 <italic>et al</italic> . (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>) tested MSNs with a particle size of 110 nm in ICR mice. Following administration via hypodermic, intramuscular and intravenous injection as well as oral administration, the 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> distribution of fluorescent-tagged MSNs was tracked. It was observed that of all the exposure routes, the oral route was found to be well tolerated even when the dose was increased to 5000 mg kg
 <sup>-1</sup> and intravenous route seemed to have the least threshold. MSNs administered via intravenous route were found to preferentially accumulate in the liver and spleen at the end of 24 h and 7 days whereas those administered by other routes did not show any fluorescence in these organs. It was observed that a portion of the MSNs administered via intramuscular and hypodermic routes could cross different biological barriers with a slow absorption rate. The major excretion routes of MSNs were found to be via urine and feces with the highest values after oral administration as compared to other routes. No histopathological changes were observed in liver, spleen, kidney and lung at the end of 24 h and 7 days by different exposure routes. The results suggested that MSNs were found to be safe and well tolerated when administered by oral and intravenous routes (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>).
</p>
