<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several mutations or groups of mutations in reverse transcriptase enzyme can promote resistance by selectively impairing the ability of reverse transcriptase to incorporate an analogue into DNA. They essentially include the M184V mutation, the Q151M complex of mutations, and the K65R mutation (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab12" ref-type="table">28.12</xref>). The M184V mutation involves the replacement of methionine by valine at position 184 of the reverse transcriptase and is the main mutation that confers resistance to lamivudine (Boucher et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">1993</xref>). Methionine 184 is located at the heart of the catalytic site of reverse transcriptase, and its replacement by a valine, which has a different side chain, interferes with the proper positioning of lamivudine triphosphate within the catalytic site (Sarafianos et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR155">1999</xref>). The M184V mutation induces very high levels of resistance to lamivudine. When lamivudine is used as a single agent, resistant strains overtake wild-type virus in a few weeks (Schuurman et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR158">1995</xref>), and when lamivudine is used as part of a failing regimen of HAART, the M184V mutation is almost always the first mutation to emerge (Havlir et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2000</xref>). The group of mutations referred to as the Q151M complex (Iversen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">1996</xref>) (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab12" ref-type="table">28.12</xref>) is most often selected for in the course of the failure of regimens containing stavudine and didanosine. This pathway always starts with the Q151M substitution, a residue located in the immediate vicinity of the nucleotide-binding site of reverse transcriptase, and is followed by the gradual accumulation of secondary mutations that enhance resistance and increase the activity of the enzyme (Kosalaraksa et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">1999</xref>). The Q151M complex is relatively rare in HIV-1 (fewer than 5 % of all HIV strains with resistance to nucleoside analogues) but can confer high-level resistance to most but not all (e.g., lamivudine and tenofovir) analogues (Iversen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">1996</xref>). Interestingly, the Q151M complex is markedly more frequent in HIV-2 than in HIV-1. The K65R mutation is seen with increasing frequency in patients in whom therapy with nucleoside or nucleotide analogues fails, especially when the regimen includes tenofovir or abacavir. This mutation appears to confer resistance to most analogues, with the exception of zidovudine.
</p>
