<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract abstract-type="summary">
 <title>Author summary</title>
 <sec id="sec004">
  <title>Why was this study done?</title>
  <list list-type="bullet">
   <list-item>
    <p>Changes in local climate conditions (i.e., rainfall, temperature) can affect the risk of outbreaks of diseases transmitted by mosquitoes, such as dengue fever, chikungunya, and Zika.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Climate information can be used to develop forecasts of disease outbreaks.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec005">
  <title>What did the researchers do and find?</title>
  <list list-type="bullet">
   <list-item>
    <p>In this study, we devised a statistical model to test whether dengue outbreaks in the Caribbean island of Barbados could be predicted using weather station data for temperature and a precipitation index—used to monitor drought and extreme rainfall—as model inputs from June 1999 to May 2016.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>The model was able to successfully predict months with dengue outbreaks versus nonoutbreaks in most years.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>The risk of dengue outbreaks increased with increasing minimum temperature (Tmin; up to 25°C). Disease outbreaks were more likely to occur 4 to 5 months after periods of drought and 1 month after periods of excess rainfall.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>The modelling results suggest that a drought period followed by intense rainfall 4 to 5 months later could provide optimum conditions for an imminent dengue outbreak.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec006">
  <title>What do these findings mean?</title>
  <list list-type="bullet">
   <list-item>
    <p>In practice, the Regional Climate Centre (RCC) could use this dengue model to generate disease forecasts using their seasonal climate forecast products.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Public health decision-makers can use the dengue forecasts as an early warning tool to plan interventions to reduce the risk of dengue and other mosquito-borne diseases.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>The ability of the model to predict dengue outbreaks is complicated by the emergence of new diseases with similar symptoms that are transmitted by the same mosquito vector, including chikungunya and Zika.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
</abstract>
