<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fn-group>
 <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
  <p>Support statement: A. Zumla is a co-Principal Investigator of the Pan-African Network on Emerging and Re-Emerging Infections (PANDORA-IDNET) funded by the European and Developing Countries Clinical Trials Partnership the EU Horizon 2020 Framework Programme for Research and Innovation; and is also in receipt of a National Institutes of Health Research senior investigator award. C.W.M. Ong is funded by Singapore National Medical Research Council (NMRC/TA/0042/2015, CSAINV17nov014); National University Health System, Singapore (NUHS/RO/2017/092/SU/01, CFGFY18P11, NUHS/RO/2020/042/RO5
   <sup>+</sup>5/ad-hoc/1); National Centre for Infectious Diseases, Singapore (STPRG-FY19-003); and is recipient of the Young Investigator Award, Institut Merieux, Lyon, France. A-G. Märtson was funded by Marie Skłodowska-Curie Actions, grant agreement number 713660–PRONKJEWAIL–H2020-MSCA-COFUND-2015. The article is part of the activities of the Global Tuberculosis Network (GTN) and of the WHO Collaborating Centre for Tuberculosis and Lung Diseases, Tradate (ITA-80, 2017-2020-GBM/RC/LDA). Part of the work was supported by the Italian Ministry of Health, Ricerca Corrente (Linea 1 and Linea 4). Funding information for this article has been deposited with the 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.crossref.org/services/funder-registry/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Crossref Funder Registry</ext-link>.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: G.B. Migliori has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: M. Raviglione has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: G. MacGregor-Skinner has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: G. Sotgiu has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: J-W. Alffenaar has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: S. Tiberi has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: C. Adlhoch has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: T. Alonzi has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: S. Archuleta has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: S. Brusin has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: E. Cambau has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: M.R. Capobianchi has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: C. Castilletti has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: R. Centis has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: D.M. Cirillo has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: L. D'Ambrosio has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: G. Delogu has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: S.M.R. Esposito has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: J. Figueroa has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: J.S. Friedland has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: B.C.H. Ho has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: G. Ippolito has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: M. Jankovic has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: H.Y. Kim has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: S. Rosales Klintz has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: C. Ködmön has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: E. Lalle has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: Y.S. Leo has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: C-C. Leung has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: A-G. Märtson has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: M.G. Melazzini has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: S. Najafi Fard has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: P. Penttinen has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: L. Petrone has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: E. Petruccioli has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: E. Pontali has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: L. Saderi has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: M. Santin has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: A. Spanevello has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: R. van Crevel has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: M.J. van der Werf has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: D. Visca has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: M. Viveiros has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: J-P. Zellweger has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: A. Zumla has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: D. Goletti has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Conflict of interest: C.W.M. Ong has nothing to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
</fn-group>
