<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Many resistance mutations impair viral replication. Because these mutations modify key viral proteins, they have deleterious effects of variable extent on protein function. Although some of these deficits can be partially corrected by compensatory mutations (Nijhuis et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125">1999</xref>), viruses forced to develop higher levels of resistance under intense and continuous pressure by antiretroviral drugs often have a substantial impairment in their replicative capacity (Barbour et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2002</xref>). The degree of replicative impairment conferred by resistance mutations is highly variable. The most crippling mutations appear to be those associated with resistance to protease inhibitors (Zennou et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR188">1998</xref>), but significant replicative defects can be related to mutations in reverse transcriptase that confer resistance to nucleoside analogues or nonnucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors (Back et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">1996</xref>; Bleiber et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2001</xref>) as well as envelope mutations associated with resistance to enfuvirtide. The clinical effect of resistance-associated loss of viral replicative capacity is the subject of intense investigation. Several observations suggest that resistant viruses have lost some of their virulence. When antiretroviral treatment is interrupted in patients infected with HIV that is resistant to multiple drugs, the resistant strain is more or less rapidly replaced by wild-type virus. This change is accompanied by a drop in CD4 T-cell counts, suggesting that wild-type virus has a greater replicative and pathogenic potential (Deeks et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2001</xref>). In a significant proportion of patients in whom HAART is failing, the CD4 T-cell counts remain significantly above pretreatment levels, despite the poor control of replication (Kaufmann et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">1998</xref>). Whether this apparent immunologic benefit of HAART in spite of patent virologic failure is the direct consequence of reduced viral pathogenicity, a sign of persistent residual activity of some drugs in the regimen, or both, remains to be elucidated. Consequently, therapeutic strategies that take advantage of resistance-associated loss of HIV replicative capacity have yet to be identified.
</p>
