<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Dangerous animal viruses are those that require zero or only a few mutations in order to begin replicating themselves in human cells. They are dangerous because these mutational combinations might arise in the animal reservoir or in an intermediate host species, creating alive-on-arrival viral variants that can begin replicating upon encountering a human host. It is critical to note that these mutational combinations must arise without the advantage of being selected for within the human body, because selection can only occur after replication in humans has begun. Further, all necessary mutations for replication in humans would need to appear together in the same viral variant arising in nature. With these criteria in mind, it is easy to see why animal viruses are highly unlikely to randomly acquire compatibility with humans when there are many different host blocks to overcome. This is, in fact, the basis of successful treatment of HIV infections with multidrug cocktails; while HIV can easily mutate to escape one drug, no single viral genome acquires the multiple drug escape mutations required for viral replication in a multiple-drug–treated host. Alarmingly, some of the H5N1 influenza viruses that are currently circulating in the avian reservoir already harbor PB2 mutations that would make them compatible with the human ANP32A [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Likewise, it is known that bat coronaviruses require mutations in their surface glycoprotein (spike) in order to use the human ortholog of their receptor, ACE2 (
 <bold>
  <xref rid="pbio.3000217.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>
 </bold>). But when coronoviruses are sampled from wild bats, a small number of them already encode spike variants compatible with human ACE2 [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. The critical question is, how many additional obstacles (if any) do these viruses need to overcome to replicate themselves in human cells?
</p>
