<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>However, in every host genome, some genes get trapped into a different mode of evolution in which they are selected for continual sequence change at the protein level. This occurs in genes that are engaged with ever-changing forces in the external world, with classic examples being genes that help us to discriminate new food sources, evade new predators, or resist new pathogens [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. These types of dynamic external forces can place intense selective pressure on certain classes of host genes, such as odorant receptors and innate immunity genes, to encode proteins with ever-new interaction specificities. Viral restriction factors and innate immune sensors are often evolving under this type of “positive” natural selection [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>–
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref084" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. Our lab and others have shown that rapidly evolving host proteins can be potent blocks to virus host switching, and this is due to nonequivalency in virus interaction surfaces from one species to the next. Further, these proteins can usually be identified bioinformatically by a special evolutionary signature contained in their gene sequence (dN/dS &gt; 1, indicating that natural selection is acting in favor of nonsynonymous substitutions, dN, relative to the baseline rate of synonymous substitutions, dS). Identifying this dN/dS &gt; 1 signature in mammalian genes, in particular those important for virus biology, has proven itself to be a powerful shortcut in identifying host proteins that interact differently with viruses in one possible animal host versus another [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref082" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref085" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>–
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref097" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. Predictions based off of the identification of host genes with dN/dS &gt; 1 must still be tested in the lab, but this combined bioinformatic and experimental approach can ultimately allow us to identify dangerous animal viruses for which human blocks are few rather than many. Most of the human proteins known to block the replication of animal viruses (partial list in 
 <bold>
  <xref rid="pbio.3000217.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>
 </bold>) are evolving under positive selection [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref093" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref095" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref096" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref098" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>] or exhibit other types of significant sequence divergence between the reservoir animal and human orthologs. (For instance, most avian versions of ANP32A have 33-amino–acid insertion compared to mammalian versions [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]). The beauty of this, therefore, is that candidate human proteins that are protecting us from animal viruses can be identified bioinformatically, usually by a signature of dN/dS &gt; 1 in their gene sequence.
</p>
