<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Molecular virology has achieved significant successes in recent decades: Many infectious diseases can be prevented through the use of modern vaccines or have been completely eradicated (10.1007/978-3-642-20718-1_10). This ultimately made possible the global elimination of infectious agents such as smallpox virus. Poliovirus, which causes poliomyelitis, is no longer found on some continents, and is currently confined to fewer than ten countries worldwide. In cases in which no preventive vaccination is possible today, e.g., against HIV and some herpesviruses such as cytomegalovirus and herpes simplex virus, a large number of antiviral drugs are available. Although these drugs do not provide a cure, they substantially allow the control of symptoms. These successes might tempt one to assume that virus research has become unnecessary. The assessment of the epidemiological situation by the WHO and the many sensationalistic headlines in newspapers and the media with which we are repeatedly confronted imply the opposite. Because of their frequent and high rates of mutation, viruses are subject to continuous change and development: viruses are permanently compelled to cope with the infected organism and its immune defence systems, always trying to undermine and circumvent them. In particular, viruses that persist in the organism are capable of evading the host immune defence systems by very skilful strategies. The worldwide increase in travel leads not only to contact with new human pathogens, but also to their rapid dissemination. This is demonstrated, for example, by SARS virus infections (10.1007/978-3-642-20718-1_14), the pandemic with the new influenza A virus variant (Mexican flu, “swine flu”) and the threatening potential with regard to humans of new highly pathogenic influenza viruses (10.1007/978-3-642-20718-1_16). New and novel viral diseases which have their origin in the animal kingdom (zoonoses) are also expected owing to increased environmental changes and their serious consequences. Outbreaks of infection with Ebola virus, Nipah virus and Hendra virus are examples. Deforestation of rainforests has led to a change in living conditions for bats, which then infect horses and pigs and, via these intermediate hosts, also humans. Birds carried West Nile virus from Africa to North America, and avian flu virus H5N1 was transported from Asia to Europe by migratory birds. The AIDS pandemic that was induced by human immunodeficiency viruses was originally the result of a zoonotic transmission from monkeys to humans, followed by efficient further dissemination within the human population.</p>
