<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="ppat.1007892.g010" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1007892.g010</object-id>
 <label>Fig 10</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Inhibition of M2 ion channel results in loss of activation of LC3B.</title>
  <p>A549 cells were inoculated at an MOI of 5 PFU/cell with PR8 viruses encoding avian or human-derived M segments and incubated in the presence or absence of 200 μM amantadine from 1 hpi. Cells were lysed at 8 hpi. 
   <bold>(A)</bold> Representative Western immunoblot. Vinculin expression was measured to allow normalization of viral protein levels. NP expression was measured to assess viral replication. Levels of M1 and M2 protein were assessed using an antibody (Mab E10) to a common epitope of M1 and M2 proteins, allowing relative expression to be assessed. Levels of LC3B I and II were assessed using an antibody that detects both the precursor and activated forms of LC3B protein. 
   <bold>(B)</bold> M1 protein and 
   <bold>(C)</bold> M2 protein were normalized to vinculin and displayed as a percentage of total M gene-expressed protein. 
   <bold>(D)</bold> The ratio of M1:M2 protein expression. 
   <bold>(E)</bold> LC3B I and 
   <bold>(F)</bold> LC3B II were normalized to vinculin and displayed as a percentage of total LC3B protein. 
   <bold>(G)</bold> As a control to ensure the specificity of amantadine, we incubated chloroquine-treated A549 cells in the presence or absence of 200 μM amantadine for 8 h. 
   <bold>(H)</bold> LC3B I and 
   <bold>(I)</bold> LC3B II were normalized to vinculin and displayed as a percentage of total LC3B protein. Graphs in 
   <bold>B-F, H-I</bold> show the means with SD from three independent experiments. For each experiment, two replicate Western immunoblots were performed and quantitated. Statistical significance was assessed using ordinary one-way ANOVA.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1007892.g010" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
