<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14">Animal models of MERS-CoV are restricted by the availability of the receptor DPP4 that contains distinct amino acid sequence motif. Besides the reservoir host dromedary camels and bats, NHPs, rabbits, and other livestock animals, such as goat, cow, sheep, and pig, have been shown to express DPP4 that can bind to MERS-CoV [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128">128</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR130">130</xref>]. However, DPP4 of frequently used small animal models like mouse, hamster, and ferret did not bind to MERS-CoV [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128">128</xref>]. In NHPs, MERS-CoV infection showed similar clinical signs as in humans, ranging from mild to severe, depending on the species of NHPs. Although DPP4 expressions were similar between rhesus macaques and common marmosets, the disease severity was from mild to moderate and from moderate to severe, respectively [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR131">131</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132">132</xref>]. Lack of replication of MERS-CoV in small animal models poses problems of cost and space, especially since experiments using MERS-CoV must be carried out in an animal biosafety level 3 facility [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR133">133</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR135">135</xref>]. Mouse engineering technology has been deployed in diverse ways to generate mice expressing human type DPP4 (hDPP4) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR136">136</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR140">140</xref>]. MERS-CoV infection in mice having hDPP4 exhibited only moderate signs of respiratory pathology, most likely due to the low level expression of hDPP4 in the mouse lung [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR135">135</xref>], but MERS-CoV could be adapted in these mice to a more pathogenic virus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR139">139</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR141">141</xref>]. In addition to NHP and hDPP4-mouse models, rabbits might be a good candidate for MERS-CoV transmission experiments due to its camel-like receptor distribution in the upper respiratory tract (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR142">142</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR150">150</xref>]. However, while dromedary camels and New World camelids could transmit MERS-CoV upon contact, rabbits could hardly transmit the virus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR130">130</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR143">143</xref>]. MERS-CoV has been shown to use α-2,3 SA as a receptor assistant, which dromedary camels but not rabbits express in the nasal epithelium [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR130">130</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR151">151</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR152">152</xref>]. Humans do not express the primary receptor DPP4 in the upper respiratory tract but transmits MERS-CoV well [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR153">153</xref>]. Despite the controversies, humans have been reported to express α-2,3 SA in the upper respiratory tract [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. Contribution of the ‘pre-attachment’ receptor α-2,3 SA or any other ‘assistant’ receptors to MERS-CoV transmission might be worth further investigation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR151">151</xref>]. As far as the Animal Efficacy Rule of FDA is concerned, there appears no other choices but hDPP4-mouse and NHP models in the case of MERS-CoV studies. Human-like symptoms of MERS-CoV infection have not been reproduced in other animals than hDPP4-mice and NHPs. 
</p>
