<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One IAV replication cycle is orderly composed of virus binding, internalization, RNA replication and viral protein synthesis, assembly, budding and release from infected cells [
 <xref rid="B38-viruses-12-00225" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Through the time course inhibition experiments, we found that OA-10 inhibited IAV replication in the co- and post-treatment modes (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-12-00225-f003">Figure 3</xref>), but was unable to block IAV binding to A549 cells (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-viruses-12-00225">Figure S3</xref>). To identify the exact stage(s) of IAV replication cycle affected by OA-10, we investigated the time course inhibition within one IAV lifecycle and found that OA-10 exerted its effect during the early stages of IAV infection (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-12-00225-f004">Figure 4</xref>). During this stage, IAV attachment to target cells is mediated by HA1 via sialic acid-receptor binding, and subsequent virus-endosome membrane fusion is mediated by rearrangement of HA2 at low pH. Our results showed that OA-10 did not block IAV binding to cells at 4 °C (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-viruses-12-00225">Figure S3</xref>). In addition, OA-10 did not inhibit IAV adsorption to chicken RBCs at concentrations of 10 and 20 µM, in spite of the fact that non-classical hemagglutination inhibitions of OA-10 at 40 and 80 µM were observed. These results suggest that the HA1 receptor binding domain is likely not a main target. Given that OA-10 exhibited antiviral activity during early stage(s) of IAV infection cycle, we speculated that OA-10 might target the membrane fusion step mediated by the more conserved hemagglutinin transmembrane subunit HA2. This hypothesis was confirmed by the activity of blocking hemolysis of OA-10 in a low pH environment in a dose-dependent manner (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-12-00225-f005">Figure 5</xref>C), as hemolysis is mediated by HA2 rather than HA1 [
 <xref rid="B39-viruses-12-00225" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>].
</p>
