<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18">This study had some limitations: First, the identified transmission chains are likely to suffer from missing links due to low sampling density. A low sampling density generally results in reduced clustering of HIV-1 sequences
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>
 </sup>. Because majority of the studies in the coastal Kenya setting have mostly focused on recruiting MSM participants, FSW and HET in our analysis had low sampling densities and inevitably, several transmission chains may have been missed. Furthermore, it is important to acknowledge that the IDU sequences were from one study, using samples from one setting (Mombasa), and collected over a period of less than one year (2010). It is therefore likely that our findings are not representative of the entire IDU epidemic in coastal Kenya. Larger studies of HIV-1 transmission in the IDU population in coastal Kenya are therefore warranted; still we found clear branching patterns indicative of long-standing HIV-1 transmission associated with intravenous drug use. Second, skewed sampling between risk groups may result in overrepresentation of some types of risk group-specific and mixed clusters. Third, given that annotating sequences from sub-Saharan Africa with information about transmission risk factor has become common only in recent years, some published sequences used in this analysis lacked risk data and were assigned HET (by far the most dominant route of HIV-1 transmission in coastal Kenya). However, the risk group for nodes within a cluster that had inadequate annotation can often be deduced from association with nodes with a known risk group
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup>. Since none of the presumed heterosexual sequences in this study was found in mixed clusters, it is unlikely that this potential caveat had any effect on our conclusions. Finally, few HIV-1 
 <italic>pol</italic> sequences were available after the year 2010 for all risk groups. This limited our analysis to the representation of some risk groups by the year and area of sampling, further restraining characterisation of recent clusters and ongoing transmission chains.
</p>
