<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par7">Currently, the world is facing severe coronavirus disease of 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic, which is caused by a genetically proficient virus, severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2). Although the origin of the COVID-19 virus and its pathogenicity and immunogenicity is not known entirely, it is speculated to have been developed by genetic re-assortment between the coronavirus of bat and pangolin [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Apparently, this outbreak has no any relation with Avian Influenza as there is no resilient evidence of genetic recombination between Coronavirus and Influenza virus. However, Qinghong Zeng et al. speculated that some human coronaviruses could have acquired the hemagglutin in-esterase gene of the influenza C virus through a recombinant process as a result of mixed infections in human [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Additionally, Luytjes et al. opined a supportive view stating that recombination events as a result of the co-infection of corona virus with the influenza C virus might give rise to a new corona virus OC43 with acquired haemagglutinating properties [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. The previous experiences with human influenza pandemics have demonstrated the vital role of the avian influenza virus in the origin of pandemic influenza viruses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The viruses that caused the pandemics of 1918, 1957, and 1968 all had genes of avian influenza origin, which fomented the pandemic spread of such viruses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Recently, Wu et al. reported the first case of co-infection with SARS-CoV-2 and influenza A virus in Wuhan, China [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Similar co-infections between AIV and SARS-CoV-2 in humans and animals might favor the emergence of novel viral strains.
</p>
