<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Niclosamide has traditionally been used to treat tapeworm infections for many years, and it is inexpensive and well tolerated 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> with an extremely high acute oral LD
 <sub>50</sub> value of &gt;5000 mg/kg in rats (niclosamide ethanolamine salt).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>
 </sup> In human medicines, single oral doses of 0.5, 1, and 2 g of niclosamide are recommended for children under 2 years, children between 2 and 6 years, and children older than 6 years and adults, respectively, to treat infections with 
 <italic>Taenia solium</italic>, 
 <italic>T. saginata</italic>, and 
 <italic>Diphyllobothrium latum</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>
 </sup> Human infections with rat tapeworm 
 <italic>Hymenolepis diminuta</italic> were eliminated by 5–7 daily doses of 2 g of niclosamide each, while the treatment of 
 <italic>Hymenolepis nana</italic> infection requires one or several 5–7 day courses of niclosamide treatment. One 7 day course regimen for adults is 2 g of niclosamide on day 1 followed by 1 g daily for 6 days.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref55">55</xref>
 </sup> When treating human volunteers each with a single oral dose of 2000 mg of niclosamide, the maximum serum concentration of niclosamide was equivalent to 0.25–6.0 μg/mL (0.76–18.3 μM). The wide concentration range was caused by the intraindividual absorption differences. Niclosamide is only partially absorbed from the intestinal tract, and the absorbed part is rapidly eliminated by the kidneys with no cumulative toxic effects in human.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>
 </sup> Through a series of drug repurposing screening campaigns, niclosamide was found to be effective against a variety of human conditions such as cancer and viral infections. Currently, there are four ongoing human clinical trials of niclosamide in ulcerative colitis, prostate carcinoma, and colorectal cancer in the ClinicalTrails.gov clinical trials registry.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref56">56</xref>
 </sup> Of note, niclosamide has several weaknesses such as unneglectable cytotoxicity and limited aqueous solubility as well as relatively low absorption and oral bioavailability (
 <italic>F</italic> = 10%), which may hamper its extensive clinical development as an antiviral agent.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref57">57</xref>
 </sup> Our group has made substantial efforts in medicinal chemistry based on niclosamide as a lead compound and discovered a series of 
 <italic>O</italic>-alkylamino-tethered derivatives as potent and orally bioavailable anticancer agents with improved aqueous solubility
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>
 </sup> and diversified salicylamide derivatives as potent anti-HAdV inhibitors with increased potency (submicromolar IC
 <sub>50</sub>s) and significantly decreased cytotoxicity likely by targeting different steps in the HAdV life cycle.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref58">58</xref>
 </sup> The ester derivative prodrug of niclosamide was also reported to increase its systemic drug exposure and extend the duration of exposure.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref59">59</xref>
 </sup> The development of nanobased formulations is another useful strategy for improving the pharmacological and pharmacokinetic properties of niclosamide and maximizing its therapeutic potential for clinical applications.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref60">60</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref62">62</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
