<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The need to carry drinking water for long ocean voyages allowed the unintentional transport and introduction of several mosquito species, including members of the 
 <italic>Culex pipiens</italic> complex that included the Northern and Southern House Mosquitoes, aptly named for their close association with humans. This complex apparently arose within the Ethiopian region [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70-viruses-05-02079">70</xref>], but now is distributed circumglobally [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71-viruses-05-02079">71</xref>], being able to survive cold northern winters as well as exploit warm southern latitudes, with hybrids found at intervening latitudes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72-viruses-05-02079">72</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73-viruses-05-02079">73</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74-viruses-05-02079">74</xref>]. A third member of the complex, 
 <italic>Cx. pipiens</italic> form molestus seems to have evolved from above ground 
 <italic>Cx. pipiens</italic> populations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75-viruses-05-02079">75</xref>] to exploit underground collections of water in temperate [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36-viruses-05-02079">36</xref>], but not tropical latitudes, where these underground habitats are exploited by 
 <italic>Cx. quinquefasciatus</italic>. Females in this complex typically blood feed on birds, but southern and admixed populations also feed on humans and dogs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64-viruses-05-02079">64</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67-viruses-05-02079">67</xref>]. Other rural 
 <italic>Culex</italic> such as 
 <italic>Culex nigripalpus</italic> in the southeast and 
 <italic>Culex tarsalis</italic> in the west have exploited irrigated agricultural landscapes, managed wetlands and some urban habitats. Both species feed on both avian and mammalian hosts, but shift to more frequent mammal feeding during late summer, thereby functioning effectively as both enzootic and bridge vectors [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67-viruses-05-02079">67</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76-viruses-05-02079">76</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B77-viruses-05-02079">77</xref>].
</p>
