<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Furthermore, it acts as a critical factor for tissue tropism and the determination of host range (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). Notably, S protein is one of the vital immunodominant proteins of CoVs capable of inducing host immune responses (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). The ectodomains in all CoVs S proteins have similar domain organizations, divided into two subunits, S1 and S2 (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). The first one, S1, helps in host receptor binding, while the second one, S2, accounts for fusion. The former (S1) is further divided into two subdomains, namely, the N-terminal domain (NTD) and C-terminal domain (CTD). Both of these subdomains act as receptor-binding domains, interacting efficiently with various host receptors (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). The S1 CTD contains the receptor-binding motif (RBM). In each coronavirus spike protein, the trimeric S1 locates itself on top of the trimeric S2 stalk (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). Recently, structural analyses of the S proteins of COVID-19 have revealed 27 amino acid substitutions within a 1,273-amino-acid stretch (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Six substitutions are located in the RBD (amino acids 357 to 528), while four substitutions are in the RBM at the CTD of the S1 domain (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Of note, no amino acid change is seen in the RBM, which binds directly to the angiotensin-converting enzyme-2 (ACE2) receptor in SARS-CoV (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). At present, the main emphasis is knowing how many differences would be required to change the host tropism. Sequence comparison revealed 17 nonsynonymous changes between the early sequence of SARS-CoV-2 and the later isolates of SARS-CoV. The changes were found scattered over the genome of the virus, with nine substitutions in ORF1ab, ORF8 (4 substitutions), the spike gene (3 substitutions), and ORF7a (single substitution) (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Notably, the same nonsynonymous changes were found in a familial cluster, indicating that the viral evolution happened during person-to-person transmission (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). Such adaptive evolution events are frequent and constitute a constantly ongoing process once the virus spreads among new hosts (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). Even though no functional changes occur in the virus associated with this adaptive evolution, close monitoring of the viral mutations that occur during subsequent human-to-human transmission is warranted.
</p>
