<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Economists are often criticized for producing bad records in predictions. Acknowledging the fact, Beck (
 <xref rid="pa2157-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>), has recommended several ideas to interpret the effect of COVID‐19 on the financial markets. To him, the effect of the coronavirus on financial markets will depend upon three significant conditions. First, to what extent the virus will further spread and its effect on economic activities worldwide. Second, the effective implementations of fiscal and monetary policy to the crisis. Third, the central's banks and regulators reactions to the possible bank fragility. Applying these three conditions, we examine the impact of COVID‐19 on the Indian financial system. The effect of the coronavirus and the lockdown it triggered is visible on the financial markets in India. The banking sector in India was already going through a crucial time even before the emergence of the crisis. The collapse of Yes bank created some hue and cry in the banking sector. Amidst the anomalies in the economic activities and deteriorations in the quality of the assets, the rating Agency Moody, has revised the prospectus of the Indian banking system to negative from stable.
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="pa2157-note-0008">8</xref> The outbreak of the virus will affect the profitability of banks adversely as there has been an increase in loan‐loss provisions and a decline in revenues. The deterioration in the assets quality across micro, small and medium enterprises (MSMEs), corporate and retail segments will induce a huge pressure on banks capitalization. Capital infusions to the public sector banks (PSBs) as done by the governments over the past few years can mitigate the pressures on bank capitalization. Given the current situation, where the private sector banks are facing default, the growing risk aversion faced by the old private sector banks will put funding and liquidity pressures on small private sector banks. The outbreak has also hit investor confidence in the financial market. Investor sentiment has been so low that despite relatively lower cases reported in India, the Indian stock market has fared worst among global peers. Indian stock market has lost 26% in dollar terms between February 1 and April 9, compared with a decline of 20 and 14% in European and United States markets.
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="pa2157-note-0009">9</xref>
</p>
