<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Another important reason for the rapid spread is related to the large number of patients with no or mild symptoms with SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="B4-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. The asymptomatic proportion was estimated to be 17.9% according to data from people who underwent a two-week quarantine on the Diamond Princess cruise ship [
 <xref rid="B24-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Unlike SARS-CoV, the detected viral load is similar in the asymptomatic and symptomatic patients with COVID-19, which suggests potential transmission of the virus from asymptomatic or mild symptomatic patients to other people [
 <xref rid="B25-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Fever is the most common symptom (88.7%) but it can be present in only 43.8% on admission [
 <xref rid="B27-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Since absence of fever in COVID-19 is more frequent than in SARS-CoV (1%) and in MERS-CoV (2%) infection, afebrile patients may be missed if the surveillance case definition only focuses on fever detection [
 <xref rid="B22-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The second most common symptom is cough (67.8%), while nausea or vomiting (5.0%) and diarrhea (3.8%) are uncommon. The median incubation period has been estimated to be four to five days, similar to SARS-CoV [
 <xref rid="B27-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. According to the retrospective study from China including 191 patients with COVID-19, the median time from illness onset to dyspnea, sepsis, and ARDS were seven days, nine days, and twelve days, respectively [
 <xref rid="B7-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. In nonsurvivors, the median time from illness to death was 21 days. Very recently, a cross-sectional survey including 59 patients was reported from Italy, noting that 34% of the patients had olfactory or taste disorders [
 <xref rid="B29-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. This may play a role as a clinical screening tool to orientate testing of paucisymptomatic individuals, but larger studies are warranted to confirm this finding.
</p>
