<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The study used dengue surveillance data that were collected by the NDCP program over a 20-year period between 1994–2013, and published annually by the Ministry of Health in annual record booklets [
 <xref rid="pone.0224353.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. The NDCP program was set up in 1999 to coordinate dengue surveillance and control. Detection and reporting of dengue followed the Ministry of Health Guidelines 1999 [
 <xref rid="pone.0224353.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. A case definition recommended by the World Health Organization for provisional diagnosis was used to detect clinical cases. The case definition comprised acute febrile illness of ≥38°C lasting 2–7 days with at least two of the main symptoms including severe headache, retro-orbital pain, nausea, vomiting, myalgia, arthralgia, haemorrhagic manifestations, and leukopenia [
 <xref rid="pone.0224353.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>][
 <xref rid="pone.0224353.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Before 2002, a few cases were confirmed using serological tests, but from 2002 onwards, the surveillance system collated cases confirmed using anti-dengue virus IgM Elisa test [
 <xref rid="pone.0224353.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Cases detected in the clinics and laboratories had to be reported to the province/city Preventive Medicine department within 24 hours and reports on the trends observed were issued at monthly intervals. A dengue outbreak was officially declared when a locality (a group/street/hamlet/sub-hamlet, inhabitant group or equivalent) reported clinical cases fitting the case definition given above, or when a laboratory confirmed case, together with finding the presence of mosquito vector/or mosquito vector larvae within 200m radius around a patient’s house. The study only accessed records aggregated at the province level–these data therefore had no personal information. Estimates of human population by province-month were derived via a reverse calculation described by Lee [
 <xref rid="pone.0224353.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] and used as the denominator for estimating incidence. The reverse estimation procedure used published dengue cases and dengue incidence in 100,000.
</p>
