<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Cells conditioned with cmCTR and cmMTB supernatants (approximately 1.5 million cells) were treated with TRIzol Reagent (Invitrogen) and stored at −80°C. Total RNA was extracted from the TRIzol samples using the RNeasy mini kit (Qiagen). RNA amount and purity (absorbance at 260/280 nm) was measured with the Nanodrop ND-1000 apparatus (Thermo Scientific). According to the manufacturer's protocol, complementary DNA was then reverse transcribed from 1 µg total RNA with Moloney murine leukemia virus reverse transcriptase (Invitrogen), using random hexamer oligonucleotides for priming. The microarray analysis was performed using the Agilent Human GE 4 × 44 v2 (single color), as previously described (
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Lugo-Villarino et al., 2018</xref>). Briefly, we performed hybridization with 2 μg Cy3-cDNA and the hybridization kit (Roche NimbleGen). The samples were then incubated for 5 min at 65°C, and 5 min at 42°C before loading for 17 hr at 42°C, according to manufacturer's protocol. After washing, the microarrays were scanned with MS200 microarray scanner (Roche NimbleGen), and using Feature Extraction software, the Agilent raw files were extracted and then processed through Bioconductor (version 3.1) in the R statistical environment (version 3.6.0). Using the limma package, raw expression values were background corrected in a ‘normexp’ fashion and then quantile normalized and log
 <sub>2</sub> transformed (
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Ritchie et al., 2015</xref>). Density plots, boxplots, principal component analyses, and hierarchical clustering assessed the quality of the hybridizations. Differentially expressed genes between macrophages exposed to cmCTR or cmMTB supernatants were extracted based on the p-value corrected using the Benjamini-Hochberg procedure. The log
 <sub>2</sub> normalized expression values were used to perform Gene Set Enrichment Analyses (GSEA). The GSEA method allows to statistically test whether a set of genes of interest (referred to as a geneset) is distributed randomly or not in the list of genes that were pre-ranked according to their differential expression ratio between macrophages exposed to cmCTR or cmMTB supernatants. The output of GSEA is a GeneSet enrichment plot. The vertical black lines represent the projection onto the ranked GeneList of the individual genes of the GeneSet. The top curve in green corresponds to the calculation of the enrichment score (ES). The more the ES curve is shifted to the upper left of the graph, the more the GeneSet is enriched in the red cell population. Conversely, the more the ES curve is shifted to the lower right of the graph, the more the GeneSet is enriched in the blue cell population.
</p>
