<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>HIV-1 migration was inferred using a MCMC structured coalescent approach with MultiTypeTree [
 <xref rid="pone.0237560.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] as implemented in BEAST2 v2.4.5 [
 <xref rid="pone.0237560.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] under a GTR substitution model (4 gamma categories), a strict molecular clock model set to a rate of 1.52 x 10
 <sup>−3</sup> substitutions/site/year with a lognormal distribution, and chain lengths &gt;5 x 10
 <sup>8</sup> sampled to generate 10,000 trees. The strict molecular clock rate represents the posterior from effective population size estimates described above. HIV-1 migration is measured in terms of the number of ancestral migrations events from city 
 <italic>x</italic> to city 
 <italic>y</italic>. Restrictions were set on population size (log
 <sub>10</sub>) for each city based on mapping exercises carried out in Pakistan [
 <xref rid="pone.0237560.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Convergence of each run was assessed using Tracer 1.7.1 to ensure that ESS &gt;200 were obtained for all statistics and that acceptable mixing was achieved [
 <xref rid="pone.0237560.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Structured coalescent analysis was limited to HIV-1 subtype A1 sequences from our study given the computational limitations for reliable ancestral migration estimates [
 <xref rid="pone.0237560.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Older database sequences (e.g. from Karachi and Sargodha) were omitted from this analysis to provide a contemporary snapshot of HIV-1 migration. PWID in Pakistan are a highly mobile population [
 <xref rid="pone.0237560.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] therefore, including older database sequences may not be representative of the most current HIV-1 migration patterns. HIV-1 subtype A1 sequences were chosen according to the subtyping approach described above. Any potential recombinant HIV-1 subtype A1 sequences were identified with RDP v4.97 [
 <xref rid="pone.0237560.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] and omitted from the structured coalescent analysis (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0237560.s011">S10 Table</xref>). All XML files are available upon request.
</p>
