<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par44">
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par45">As per WHO, 209,839 people are affected by COVID-19 until March 20, 2020.
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par46">COVID-19 is accountable for 8778 death and is present in 168 countries worldwide.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par47">Several studies are going on for exploring efficient medication and vaccine for COVID-19.
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par48">S-glycoprotein-based and mRNA-based vaccines show prominent response.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par49">SARS-CoV-2 shows similarity to SARS-CoV and bat-CoV.
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par50">The similarity in genome structure especially in S protein can be utilized for vaccine development and alternate medications which are effective on SARS-CoV.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par51">Precaution is only cure is true in the case of COVID-19.
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par52">Maintenance of social distancing, hygiene, and isolation.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par53">Social awareness by government, media, NGOs, and responsible citizens.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par54">Isolation of infected, suspected, and possible asymptomatic carriers.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par55">Total lock down in highly affected places.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par56">Proper maintenance of clean and sanitized environment.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par57">COVID-19 is a novel virus, and proper precautions is the only cure.
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par58">Support to government and responsible agencies by following advisory and guidelines.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par59">Follow all the instructions and guidelines released by the WHO.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
