<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0035">Evidence suggests that the gut microbiota can remotely boost the host’s response to respiratory viral infections. Paradoxically, dysbiosis of the microbiota can also worsen the outcome of the disease. The gut microbiota’s role in hCoV infections has yet to be defined. In the setting of influenza infections, the results of experiments with antibiotic treatment (to deplete the residual microbiota) have demonstrated that the gut microbiota is critical for controlling viral replication (
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Ichinohe et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Abt et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Steed et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bradley et al., 2019</xref>). Bacterial cell wall components and bacterial metabolites (such as desaminotyrosine) favor the production of type I interferons and inflammasome-dependent cytokines by pulmonary cells. The gut microbiota also boosts CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cell effector function, a process that contributes to viral clearance (
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Ichinohe et al., 2011</xref>). Whereas altering the gut microbiota with antibiotics increases the severity of the infection, stimulating the microbiome with a high-fiber diet has the opposite effect (
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Trompette et al., 2018</xref>). The stimulatory mechanisms involve short-chain fatty acids (SCFAs, the end products of dietary fiber fermentation by commensal bacteria) that are absorbed by and act on immune cells to reduce the inflammatory component of infection. SCFAs also enhance the effector activity of CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells by stimulating cellular metabolism (
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Trompette et al., 2018</xref>). Similar protective effects have been observed with the respiratory syncytial virus (
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Antunes et al., 2019</xref>). It remains to be seen whether the gut microbiota also participates in early control (through innate immunity) and late control (through adaptive immunity) of coronavirus replication, and this topic warrants investigation (
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). It would also be useful to investigate the effect of SCFA-promoting high-fiber diets and/or probiotics on the outcome of SARS-CoV-2 infection.
</p>
