<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The model of rabies transmission used in this study makes several assumptions that should be considered. First, individuals do not change their behaviour once infected. It is well known that rabies can manifest as either encephalitic (furious) or paralytic (dumb) and evidence suggests that, unless vaccinated, the furious form is more likely to develop in dogs [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007565.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. However, it is not clear what determines the type of rabies an individual develops or if the different forms result in considerable deviations from the individuals’ typical behaviour. Such deviations could result in changes to the contact network with either new connections being formed, the loss of connections or changes in the strength of connections. A second assumption is that when individuals were removed due to death, the network structure did not change. Removing these assumptions would require a rewiring of the network and this process should be biologically informed. Reynolds et al [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007565.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] attempted to account for dumb and furious behaviours by assuming different frequencies of each and either changing the transmission probability (higher for furious and lower for dumb) or by altering the individual’s contact behaviour (removing half their connections for dumb or doubling them for furious). They found that both methods produced similar results and the speed of transmission increased when there was a higher frequency of furious individuals and decreased with a higher frequency of dumb individuals. Although this effort to model behavioural change can be insightful, the methods of rewiring are not biologically informed and so should be interpreted carefully as they cover a limited number of possible scenarios in which the network could change. Solutions to such network dynamics are challenging as there is a lack of experimental data on the processes of network rewiring and, without this guidance, the number of potential modes of change is too computationally demanding to include in models. For diseases such as rabies it is unlikely that such data will ever exist given the ethical implications of such experimentation. However, understanding how a network rewires as individual states or community membership change could better allow network models to include such dynamics that are thought to be a major obstacle for controlling rabies [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007565.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].
</p>
