<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Adenovirus (AdV) infections are now regarded as a significant source of human or animal morbidity and mortality. Human adenovirus (hAdV) infections are readily transmittable, infecting all age groups, especially infants and the elderly, as well as those with immunodeficiency and organ transplantation.
 <xref rid="jmv25674-bib-0059" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>59</sup>
 </xref> HAdV has a non‐enveloped spherical structure with a diameter of 70 to 100 nm. The external shell consists of 252 capsomeres, including 240 hexons and 12 pentons, which are composed of an icosahedral viral capsid. The capsomeres are arranged on 20 triangular surfaces, making the shell form 30 edges and 12 vertices. The genome of hAdV exists in the capsid in the form of linear double‐stranded DNA with sizes ranging from 34 to more than 37 kb. The genome contains the early expressed E1~E4 genes associated with replication of hAdV, intermediate gene of Ⅸ and Ⅳa2, and late region genes L1~L5 associated with the production of mature virions.
 <xref rid="jmv25674-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>60</sup>
 </xref> HAdV belongs to the 
 <italic>Adenoviridae</italic> family, and it has been classified into seven species (A to G) with over 50 serotypes based on hexon and fiber protein characteristics, relative nucleic homology, immunochemical responses, biological properties, and phylogenetic relationships.
 <xref rid="jmv25674-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>35</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jmv25674-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>61</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jmv25674-bib-0062" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>62</sup>
 </xref> This subdivision has some clinical relevance, essentially because different hAdVs differ in tissue orientation and disease type. HAdV can cause multiple diseases, such as respiratory disease (hAdV‐B, ‐C, and ‐E), gastroenteritis (hAdV‐F and ‐G), keratoconjunctivitis (hAdV‐B and ‐D), and meningoencephalitis (hAdV‐A, ‐B, and ‐D).
 <xref rid="jmv25674-bib-0059" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>59</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jmv25674-bib-0063" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>63</sup>
 </xref> Therefore, effective and rapid diagnosis of hAdV ahead of its progression will provide for effective monitoring of hAdV infection and guarantee timely and effective treatment of hAdV‐associated diseases.
</p>
