<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Huang et al. first reported a prevalence of acute myocardial injury of 12% as a major complication among 41 hospitalized patients infected with SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="B5-jcm-09-01683" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. In another study from Wang et al. conducted on 138 hospitalized patients with Covid-19, cardiac injury was found in 7.2% of patients overall and in 22.2% of patients who were treated in the intensive care unit (ICU) [
 <xref rid="B1-jcm-09-01683" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. These findings could suggest that acute myocardial injury may have a relevant role in worsening clinical outcomes in Covid-19 patients, even without clear evidence of myocardial ischemia. Indeed, Zhou et al., in a retrospective report of 191 patients admitted with SARS-Cov-2 pneumonia, diagnosed acute myocardial injury in 33 out of 191 (17%) patients in their cohort [
 <xref rid="B66-jcm-09-01683" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Interestingly, they found that non-survivors were more likely to develop acute myocardial injury than survivors (
 <italic>n</italic> = 32, 59% vs. 
 <italic>n</italic> = 1, 1%; 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001). Notably, the first autopsy in this cohort was performed on a 53-year-old woman with chronic renal failure, and findings were consistent with AMI (data resulting from personal communication between a pathologist and the Chinese Academy of Science, not available in a published manuscript). In a single-center retrospective study by Shi et al., conducted on a cohort of 416 consecutive Covid-19 patients in Wuhan, China, cardiac injury was found in 19.7% patients (
 <italic>n</italic> = 82) [
 <xref rid="B6-jcm-09-01683" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Those patients were older, had more CV comorbidities (hypertension, diabetes, cerebrovascular disease, and heart failure), and presented with more severe acute illness than patients without cardiac injury. This study demonstrated that myocardial injury was independently associated with an increased risk of mortality in patients with Covid-19. It should be underlined that among those 82 patients with cardiac injury, only 22 (26.8%) underwent an electrocardiogram (ECG) after admission, and only 14 out of 22 ECGs (63.6%) were performed at the same time as the elevation of cardiac biomarkers. All ECGs were described as abnormal, with findings compatible with myocardial ischemia, such as T-wave depression and inversion, ST-segment depression, and Q waves. The above findings may suggest that 14 out of 416 patients in this cohort (3.36%) may have developed myocardial ischemia, with features consistent with NSTEMI. No evidence of STEMI in this cohort was provided, even if limited availability of ECGs may have led to underestimation of AMI cases. In addition, the National Health Commission of China reported that among people who died from Covid-19, 11.8% of patients without underlying CV diseases had substantial heart damage, showing elevated levels of cTnI or cardiac arrest during hospitalization [
 <xref rid="B67-jcm-09-01683" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. In a meta-analysis by Lippi et al. that included a total number of 341 patients (123 with severe disease, 36%), it appeared that cTnI values were significantly increased in patients with severe SARS-CoV-2 infection compared to those with milder forms of disease [
 <xref rid="B68-jcm-09-01683" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>].
</p>
