<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par39">In practice the definition of encephalitis depends on the presence of clinical signs due to the involvement of the brain tissue itself manifesting as encephalopathy for a period of at least 24 hours and/or specific neurological features with evidence of inflammation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. The indicators of inflammation are fever, cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) pleocytosis, and electroencephalogram (EEG) and neuroimaging findings consistent with encephalitis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. One of the most useful ways to think of infection is “fever for infection”. The clinical signs of encephalitis are usually non specific but not subtle. However, in immune suppressed patients they may be subtle and often also chronic. The encephalopathy is not due to other metabolic causes, toxins, other neurological disorders or systemic infections [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. It can be caused by a wide variety of etiological factors including viruses, bacteria, parasites, atypical bacteria or immune-mediated processes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], but the specific etiology is only confirmed in 60% of cases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. The disease course can be acute, sub-acute or chronic, and it is determined by the immune status of the patient [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Viruses responsible for sub-acute or chronic presentations in immunocompromised patients are measles virus causing inclusion body encephalitis, VZV causing multifocal leukoencephalopathy, CMV, herpes simplex virus (HSV) type 2, human herpes virus (HHV) type 6, enteroviruses, John Cunningham virus and BK virus causing progressive multi-focal leukoencephalopathy and human immunodeficiency virus (HIV). In immune competent patients John Cunningham virus and BK virus can also cause progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy, whereas measles virus causes SSPE [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].
</p>
