<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015">In the United States, there has been controversy over discussions about injecting disinfectants into patients with SARS-CoV-2 infection or treating them with ultraviolet rays [
 <xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Disinfectants are poisonous when mishandled, but when these concepts are circulated to populations with low health literacy, people may poison themselves from self-administration. Of note, there had been a 20% increase in calls to U.S. poison centers related to disinfectants and cleaning products compared to last year [
 <xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. While some of these calls are related to accidental pediatric exposures, others involve inadvertent misuse of the product [
 <xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. There were notable increases in inhalational exposures, as well as exposures to bleach products and alcohol-based sanitizers [
 <xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Even though chloroquine derivates are not approved treatments for COVID-19, there has been a great deal of media attention surrounding the potential therapeutic benefit of the drugs. Due to the media attention surrounding chloroquine, an Arizona man died after ingesting chloroquine phosphate (an additive to household products meant to treat fish parasites) in an effort to prevent himself from getting infected with coronavirus. [
 <xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In Madagascar, there were claims of an herbal coronavirus “cure” produced from the artemisia plant, yet the WHO stated that the tonic is not evidence-based and is potentially toxic [
 <xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Promoting unproven COVID-19 treatments will only worsen the current healthcare crisis, as people will certainly experiment with these remedies. As a result, health care systems will become overwhelmed with many critically ill patients, from both COVID-19 and those with toxicity from nonevidence-based treatments.
</p>
