<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The impact of the distinct mechanisms of interference may be modulated by factors that were not included in our simple model. First, heterogeneity may exist in the transmission rates across individuals and over time within the same partnership: in particular, per-contact transmission risk may decrease from the first exposures to subsequent contacts within a serodiscordant partnership (independent of the effect of acute infection) [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Such an effect can arise if the individuals highly susceptible to the virus of their partners tend to be rapidly infected, and the couples that remain serodiscordant become enriched in cases of low transmissibility over time (as reviewed in [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]). Similar effects are expected also if the partners of infected individuals can develop partially protective immunity to HIV in the exposures that do not result in transmission [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Irrespective of the mechanism, if time dependent variation in transmissibility is strain specific, then the invader virus has the advantage of being engaged in “first contact” with higher probability than the resident strain, which would decrease the first comer advantage of the latter. Second, if superinfection can generate a new “acute” temporary peak in viremia (and transmissibility) at least in some of the cases [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], then this mechanism of interference may also be weaker, which could reduce the first comer advantage (particularly in high-prevalence epidemics, according to our results). On the other hand, a detailed analysis of transmission risk in serodiscordant couples in Africa [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], and a recent phylodynamic analysis of a North American epidemic [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] have both estimated about 20-fold higher transmissibility during acute compared with chronic HIV infection. Using a 9-fold consensus estimate [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] we may thus have underestimated the interference effect if repeated “acute” peaks of transmissibility do not (or only rarely) occur after superinfection. Third, the observed partial inhibition of superinfection may not take effect until several months from the first infection [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], e.g., if partially protective immune responses and/or a limiting depletion of target cells take a longer time to develop [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. This would allow unhindered superinfection in the first few months after seroconversion, which would reduce the first comer advantage, especially if the second strain arrives while the first epidemic is still in its growth phase. Fourth, there is considerable debate on the strength of the (partial) protection from superinfection. Several studies have found zero or very low rates of superinfection [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] (which would implicate strong protection against superinfection), while at the other extreme some studies have found rates of superinfection comparable to those of initial infection [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] (which would indicate little or no protection). The differences in the estimates may reflect genuine variation between the study populations, but also differences in study design, inclusion criteria and sensitivity of detection [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Importantly, deep sequencing methods allow the detection of superinfecting strains that grow only to low levels in the superinfected individuals (e.g., [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]), and may often be lost after a transient episode of superinfection [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Such low-level superinfection is likely to result in onward transmission of the minority variant with much lower probability compared with the baseline rate of transmission. In the context of population level spread and competition, superinfection is likely to be relevant only when the superinfecting strain grows to dominate the virus pool of the individual, which we approximated by allowing only strain replacement (and no co-existence) in the default scenario of our simulations. Relaxing this assumption and allowing for unhindered superinfection abrogated most of the first comer advantage in our results: we therefore conclude that the strong founder effects observed in the global phylogeography of HIV are more parsimoniously explained if superinfection is partially inhibited and the transmission of more than one strain from the same individual is rare.
</p>
