<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Alternative or additional mechanisms may also contribute to the preservation of founder effects. If viral adaptation occurs to host traits that vary between human populations, then a locally adapted virus strain will enjoy a selection advantage against strains adapted to other host populations (as has been observed in some model systems of host-parasite interactions [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]). For example, the distribution of Human Leukocyte Antigen (HLA) alleles may differ between human populations, and local transmission may fix escape mutations against the locally frequent alleles that initially had a protective effect [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], particularly in populations with lower HLA diversity [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]; although this seems to be occurring slowly and to a limited extent where HLA diversity is high [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Location or population specific differences may exist in other host traits affecting HIV acquisition or transmission (e.g., in restriction factors [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] or in other components of innate immunity [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]). Each locally adapted virus strain may therefore have a competitive advantage within its established host population, and a disadvantage in other populations—which would also slow down the global mixing of variants or could even result in the long term survival of several virus strains in different populations. We note, however, that long-term co-existence of several virus strains in the same epidemic (connected transmission group) is possible only if specific conditions are fulfilled, e.g., strain-specific immunity or therapy creates frequency-dependent selection that favours the rare type. Without such specific conditions, the strain with the highest transmission potential in a given host population drives all other strains extinct in the long run: this principle of competitive exclusion holds true from simple abstract mathematical models [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004093.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>] to complex simulations, including ours.
</p>
