<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The research requirements to support eradication have been reviewed extensively elsewhere [
 <xref rid="B6-viruses-12-00313" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Moving forward the necessary research to be commissioned will be indicated by a gap analysis and must be both pragmatic and cost-effective. This may include research on: socio-economic analysis; epidemiological studies, e.g., on disease transmission chains; identification of small ruminant populations acting as reservoirs and modelling of this; identifying the genetic determinants of virulence; diagnostic and surveillance methodology; molecular epidemiology; filter paper sampling for serology; rapid field tests; and, optionally, novel vaccines (marked and recombinant, e.g., vaccines able to distinguish infected from naturally infected [DIVA] animals). Socio-economic studies and epidemiology may assist for advocacy. Other studies in epidemiology will help informing vaccination strategies. Few of these researches will assist for early diagnosis at the field or transport of specimens in the absence of cold chain facilities. The research for diagnostic tests for understanding their suitability to be used for PPR investigation in non-typical animal hosts, and if needed, development of new tests that are fit for purpose. Filter paper can be used as a good support for transportation of dried fluid to the laboratory for serology, molecular detection and genotyping. Research can also assist for differential diagnostics for post-vaccination monitoring/reassurance. The existing vaccines have already been developed in a thermostable forms and production has started (such as in Ethiopia). Other areas of research worth highlighting include an apparent variation in disease severity, which has been observed between different species of goats. Detailed research is required to define this susceptibility and to examine whether the variation extends to specific features such as the duration of viral shedding in infected animals, factors which will contribute to the dynamics of PPR transmission [
 <xref rid="B7-viruses-12-00313" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-viruses-12-00313" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Another example would be developing a deeper understanding of how small ruminants are bred, raised, moved, traded and slaughtered in PPR endemic countries. This will enable a broader appreciation of the lifestyle of the livestock keepers who own and depend on these animals. This knowledge will certainly assist to design effective intervention strategies for vaccination campaigns, and ensure effective advice is given to local veterinary services about appropriate control measures.
</p>
