<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In mouse models, CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cell numbers in the joints increased during acute CHIKV infection. However, they do not protect against CHIKV-associated pathologies as mice deficient in CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells still developed joint inflammation (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). This observation is in contrast to other findings whereby CD8 T cells play an active role in mediating viral clearance and disease resolution in mouse models of Ross River virus (RRV) (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>) and Venezuela Equine Encephalomyelitis virus (VEEV) (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). CHIKV RNA could be detected in the footpad of mice at up to 16 weeks post-challenge, suggesting that chronic CHIKV infection could persist in the footpad (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). Persistent infection indicates that CHIKV epitopes could be continuously presented by antigen-presenting cells (APCs) to CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells, leading to sustained activation of T cell receptor. This will eventually cause CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cell exhaustion and render them incapable of eliminating infected cells (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>), resulting in perpetual CHIKV infection. Indeed, the lower levels of CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells and their decreased expression of activated marker CD69 suggest an exhausted phenotype in chronic CHIKV patients (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). In chronic viral (e.g., LCMV and HIV) and parasitic (e.g., malaria) diseases, persistent infection causes prolonged activation of CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells, which eventually drives them to exhaustion and become unresponsive. This condition happens through, mostly but not limited to, the programmed death-1 signaling axis (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>–
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). The shutdown of exhausted CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cell function allows pathogens to remain established, cascading into a vicious cycle of a further immune shutdown and more persistent infection. Given that CHIKV infection is shown to persist in infected mice and individuals (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>), the CHIKV-specific CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells may become exhausted and become incapable of controlling the infection. Targeting this pathway to reverse the exhaustion in CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells has been demonstrated to eliminate chronic malaria infection in a mouse model (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>), thus indicating that this is another potential avenue to treat chronic CHIKV infection.
</p>
