<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The research on the virucidal properties of SAAs, also targets non-sexually transmitted viruses that are related to significant mortality rates in vulnerable groups. For instance, the Ebola virus (EBV) is a serious life threat, causing re-emerging epidemics as there is no specific medication available yet. In the early 2000s, following the African epidemic of the late 1990s, the findings of a study proposed that the nano-emulsion ATB could decrease the Ebola virus strain Zaire concentration by over 4.0 logs in a cell culture medium and surfaces in 20 min. Such a significant decrease in the viral population could potentially lead to its complete eradication [
 <xref rid="B121-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>]. Another serious seasonal epidemic is influenza infections. The efficacy of current anti-viral agents against influenza is doubted, underlining the urgent need for more effective preventive and treatment strategies [
 <xref rid="B122-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>]. Surface sanitization is a crucial factor in limiting influenza spread. Household cleaning disinfectants, branded anti-viral wipes and surfactant-coated silica nanoparticles (SNPs) reportedly limited influenza virus strain H1N1 viability [
 <xref rid="B123-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>]. In particular, SNPs coated with didodecyl dimethyl ammonium bromide (DDAB; a quaternary ammonium cationic surfactant) were effective against the H1N1 influenza strain, in suspension or when immobilized into surfaces, indicating its potential role as an attractive coating factor for large surfaces and prosthetics [
 <xref rid="B124-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>]. Lastly, two nano-emulsions made from soybean oil, tributyl phosphate and Triton X-100, namely 8N8 and 20N10, exhibited prophylactic properties against influenza infection, in both in vitro and in vivo models.Specifically, CD-1 mice that received these mixtures prior to the viral exposure exhibited significantly elevated survival rates compared to mock-treated animals [
 <xref rid="B125-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>]. The emergence of the severe acute respiratory syndrome-coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2) almost six months ago in Wuhan, China, and the consequent coronavirus disease of 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic, has fast-tracked many studies on preventative and therapeutic means. Despite the global efforts, currently, there are no specific drugs and/or vaccines available. Therefore, the public relies on disinfection and sanitization methods to limit the viral spread. Very recent studies showed that SARS-CoV-2 can remain infectious on inanimate objects from 2 h to 9 days, depending on temperature, humidity and the type of material. Ethanol, 2- and 1- propanolare rigorous disinfectants of surfaces and skin, and limit the virus infectivity as much as 5 logs, in just 30 s [
 <xref rid="B126-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>]. Additionally, chlorine-based solutions, that are mainly used for surface and wastewater treatments, have exhibited concentration-depended anti-SARS-CoV-2 effects. Indeed, 1:50 and 1:100 dilutions have been proved to limit the viral load by 3 logs [
 <xref rid="B127-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>].
</p>
