<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although many host proteases are deemed essential for late-stage processing of proteins translated from viral RNA, viral 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> (also called M
 <sup>pro</sup>) and PLP have emerged as popular targets for COVID-19. HIV protease inhibitors lopinavir and ritonavir, included in the SOLIDARITY trial despite mixed reviews in the clinic, have been predicted to bind SARS-CoV-1 and CoV-2 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> (96% sequence identity) based on computational studies.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>
 </sup> While HIV proteases are aspartic proteases, coronavirus proteases are members of the cysteine protease family. Given that approximately a quarter of human proteases are predicted to belong to this class, design of specific viral inhibitors remains a challenge. Fortunately, to aid in the rational design of inhibitors, a crystal structure of SARS-CoV-2 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> was reported recently.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>
 </sup> As part of this work, peptidomimetic compounds (α-keto amides), previously designed against β- and α-coronaviruses, were modified for stability. The most promising mimetic (
 <bold>4</bold>) inhibited SARS-CoV-2 replication in human lung cells at micromolar concentrations and therefore requires further improvement. Carboxamide and acetamide scaffold structures have been shown to inhibit 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> of SARS-CoV-1, along with other inhibitors that have been reviewed elsewhere.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>
 </sup> Another viable viral target, PLP, shows lower sequence conservation between SARS-CoV-1 and CoV-2 (76% homology). Notably, PLP possesses additional activities beyond polypeptide processing, such as deubiquitination and cleavage of the ubiquitin-like modifier, ISG15. These PLP-dependent activities contribute to viral immune evasion in the host. Inhibitors of PLP-mediated ISG15 cleavage activity, such as compound 
 <bold>5</bold>, have EC
 <sub>50</sub> values of ∼10 uM against SARS-CoV-1 infection in cell culture with no associated cytotoxicity.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>
 </sup> Structural information and the noted unique features of SARS-CoV cysteine proteases can be exploited for selective inhibition, but existing scaffolds still require optimization to disable SARS-CoV-2 infections in the host.
</p>
