<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As mentioned above, ERVs are viral footprints that are found in the host genomes. Over the time of evolution, integrated ERVs can be either lost or fixed (when the frequency of inserted ERV becomes 100% in the population), if the elements are beneficial for the host, as a result of natural selection and random mutations [
 <xref rid="B8-viruses-12-00852" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Owing to their ability to integrate into the host genome, ERV sequences have important implication in host phenotypic effects that can have consequences in the context of physiological functions and diseases [
 <xref rid="B31-viruses-12-00852" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. For example, the syncytins in humans, namely syncytin-1 encoded by a HERV-W provirus 
 <italic>env</italic> and syncytin-2 encoded by a HERV-FRD provirus 
 <italic>env</italic>, are thought to have been acquired by the primates many millions ago (~25 million years ago for syncytin-1 and &gt;40 million years ago for syncytin-2) [
 <xref rid="B32-viruses-12-00852" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-viruses-12-00852" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] and are essential for placental morphogenesis. It has also been proposed that the syncytins can have immunomodulatory functions, including immunosuppression [
 <xref rid="B34-viruses-12-00852" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] and the inhibition of Th1 cytokine production [
 <xref rid="B35-viruses-12-00852" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], possibly through the putative immunosuppressive domain in their transmembrane subunit. The overall effect is thought to contribute to the physiological maternal tolerance for the fetus during pregnancy [
 <xref rid="B34-viruses-12-00852" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-viruses-12-00852" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-viruses-12-00852" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Owing to their critical physiological roles in the placenta, this domestication and appropriation of the HERV Envs exerts a positive selection for gene fixation or retention along the primate evolution, observing high degree of conservation and very limited human polymorphisms [
 <xref rid="B36-viruses-12-00852" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-viruses-12-00852" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].
</p>
