<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In several CHIKD cases, inflammation causing joints pain might persist for several months or years, resulting in symptoms similar to rheumatoid arthritis, and is termed as the chronic phase of CHIKD (
 <xref rid="B176" ref-type="bibr">176</xref>–
 <xref rid="B178" ref-type="bibr">178</xref>). Typically, the chronic phase is characterized by joint swelling, joint stiffness, arthralgia, and tendonitis/tenosynovitis (
 <xref rid="B119" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>). Serologically, it marks a significant reduction of the virus as well as of viral RNA, reduced osteoprotegerin, and increased IL-6 and RANKL (receptor activator of NF-κB) ferritin, CRP (C-reactive protein), CXCL9, CXCL1, CHIKV-specific IgG titer IL-12 GM-CSF, IL-17, IL-27, IL-29, IL-8, MCP-1, MIP, CD95/CD95L, CXCL-9, and CXCL-10 (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B162" ref-type="bibr">162</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B179" ref-type="bibr">179</xref>–
 <xref rid="B182" ref-type="bibr">182</xref>). At this stage, CHIKV virus particles/viral RNA is cleared from the blood; however, studies have reported the persistence of CHIKV RNA in the macrophages (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) and fibroblast during chronic phase (
 <xref rid="B183" ref-type="bibr">183</xref>). Further, the viral dsRNA (intermediate stage during replication) found in the monocytes/macrophages of joints has been reported to trigger an arthritogenic response by activating NF-κB, both in 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> studies (
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>), as well as in ankles and wrists of mice Rag
 <sup>−/−</sup> (
 <xref rid="B119" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>). Apart from RNA intermediates, studies have reported the persistence of CHIKV specific proteins in host cells over an extended period of time. CHIKV-nsP3 was found to be present as granules along the cell membrane in cells in persistent infection (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>), while in another study, CHIKV-capsid proteins were evident in CHIKV infected mice as late as 60 days post-infection, suggesting the active translation of viral proteins during the chronic phase of CHIKD (
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>).
</p>
