<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Priming with DNA and boosting with viral vectors is an approach focused on the induction of cellular immune responses. Viral vectors usually include adenovirus, vaccinia, fowlpox, and vesicular stomatitis virus (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). It has been proposed that strategies that involve primary vaccinations with DNA followed by boosting with a recombinant poxvirus vector encoding the same immunogen, could elicit a protective CD8+ T cell response in animal models against various diseases such as HIV, malaria, and even cancer (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). In the specific case of malaria control the studies conducted by Li and coworkers were the pioneers demonstrating that the immunization of mice with a recombinant vaccinia virus, after priming with an influenza virus expressing the same CS protein of the parasite, enhances the effectiveness of the anti-parasite immunity, apparently by expanding the antigen-induced CD8+ T cells. The sequence in which these vectors were used for immunization was crucial, because when the reverse immunization was evaluated the results were completely different (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). Although a partial protective immunity against this parasite can be induced by a single immunization with a vaccinia virus presenting the CS protein a second dose with the same antigen failed to enhance the immune response, probably because the primary immune response neutralized the second dose of the virus. Similar results were observed by Rodríguez and colleagues when evaluated the effectiveness of several recombinant influenza and vaccinia viruses to induce a malaria-specific immune response (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). Their results support the concept that live viral vectors expressing the appropriate proteins and/or epitopes can be used as vaccine candidates in prime-boost strategies. Other studies indicate that complementary prime-boost immunization strategies that use recombinant vaccinia virus and bacterial plasmids could be useful for the control of flavivirus diseases (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>).
</p>
