<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0180">Lethal mutagenesis is another antiviral approach that takes advantage of the high rate of RNA virus mutation by intentionally further increasing it so that the virus becomes unable to replicate its genome with enough fidelity to maintain its infectiousness [
 <xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. Clouser et al. studied the synergistic effect of resveratrol in combination with decitabine (5-aza-2′-deoxycytidine, 5-aza-dC), a deoxyribonucleoside analogue able to lethally mutagenize HIV-1 in a cell culture system [
 <xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. In a previous study, the same research group demonstrated the synergistic effect between a nucleoside analogue and a ribonucleotide reductase inhibitor (RNRI) in increasing the HIV mutation rate, resulting in HIV infectivity decrease [
 <xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. Indeed, resveratrol has been reported to inhibit HIV-1 replication by interacting with SIRT1 [
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] and to be an inhibitor of ribonucleotide reductase, the enzyme involved in the reduction of ribonucleotides into the corresponding deoxyribonucleotides [
 <xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. Therefore, Clouser et al. synthesized fifteen resveratrol derivatives and screened them on HIV-1-infected 293T-cells alone and in combination with decitabine. Piceatannol and 
 <bold>23a</bold> showed an improved activity against HIV-1 infection, maintaining a low cytotoxicity (
 <xref rid="fig15" ref-type="fig">Fig. 15</xref> , 
 <xref rid="tbl5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref> ). Replacing the double bond with a heterocycle (
 <bold>20</bold>–
 <bold>22</bold>, 
 <bold>23e</bold>-
 <bold>23f</bold>) or with an α, β-unsaturated ketone (
 <bold>19</bold>) did not improve the potency of resveratrol. The 2-hydroxy-naphthalene (
 <bold>23c</bold>) and the isoquinoline (
 <bold>23d</bold>) moieties were also ineffective in improving the potency. Conversely, hydroxy groups seemed to play a key role in the antiviral activity since piceatannol, bearing four hydroxy functions, was one of the most active compound, whereas compound 
 <bold>7</bold>, differing from the most active compound 
 <bold>23a</bold> only in the pyridine ring in place of a 4-hydroxy phenyl ring, completely lost potency. The benzofuran and benzothiophene derivatives (
 <bold>10a</bold>, 
 <bold>b</bold>-
 <bold>11a</bold>, 
 <bold>b</bold>), bearing three hydroxyl groups, demonstrated a better activity than resveratrol, having however a low SI. Overall, the distance between the aromatic rings bearing at least three hydroxy group and the resulting conformation of the compounds seemed to influence the antiviral effects. On the other hand, only resveratrol demonstrated a synergism with decitabine, increasing HIV-1 mutant frequency [
 <xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. However, in 2016 the same authors studied combinations of resveratrol and 5-azacytidine (5-aza-C), the decitabine riboside analogue, and they found that the synergistic activity at low concentration of resveratrol as RNRI is mainly due to decreased accumulation of RT products rather than to increased viral mutagenesis [
 <xref rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>].
</p>
