<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Non-canyon binders attach to the virus surface elsewhere outside the canyon, tethering the virus to the cell surface eventually signaling for virus internalization. Importantly, they are diverse in molecular characteristics. These receptors include (i) the LDL-receptor used by HRV-C (Verdaguer et al., 
 <xref rid="B133" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>); (ii) the decay-accelerating factor (DAF), receptor of many echoviruses and CVBs (Bergelson et al., 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>; Pettigrew et al., 
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Plevka et al., 
 <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Pan et al., 
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Yoder et al., 
 <xref rid="B151" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>); (iii) P-selectin glycoprotein ligand-1 (PSGL-1) used by EV71 (Nishimura et al., 
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>); and (iv) scavenger receptor B2 (ScaRB2), a receptor of EV71 (Yamayoshi et al., 
 <xref rid="B147" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Zhou et al., 
 <xref rid="B159" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). This group possibly includes heparan sulfate used by several enteroviruses (Escribano-Romero, 
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Zautner et al., 
 <xref rid="B153" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; McLeish et al., 
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Tan et al., 
 <xref rid="B126" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Nishimura et al., 
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) and cadherin-related family member 3 (CDHR3) used by HRV-C (Watters and Palmenberg, 
 <xref rid="B137" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Non-canyon binders rarely induce substantial conformational changes due to their interaction, and some may not be essential for infection since few mutations allow or limit their usage (Pan et al., 
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; McLeish et al., 
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Lee et al., 
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). This alternative receptor usage can modify the infection mechanism, as seen in the case of CVB3 binding to DAF which signals the trafficking of the attached virus to tight junctions where the virus can meet CAR (Coyne and Bergelson, 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>).
</p>
