<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The spatiotemporal mapping of HFRS incidence distribution was performed using the BME method [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007091.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] by simultaneously assimilating the core or general knowledge base (
 <italic>G</italic>-KB) and the site-specific or specificatory knowledge base (
 <italic>S</italic>-KB) of HFRS in Heilongjiang Province. Specifically, the mean and covariance functions were treated as 
 <italic>G</italic>-KB and the log-transformed HFRS data 
 <italic>Y</italic>(
 <bold>
  <italic>p</italic>
 </bold>) was regarded as 
 <italic>S</italic>-KB. The implementation of the BME method (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0007091.s004">S4 Text</xref>) to separately analyze data classes defined in terms of percentiles (
 <xref rid="pntd.0007091.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) will be termed class-dependent BME (cd-BME). The cd-BME mapping results will be subsequently superimposed and back-transformed to obtain the final HFRS incidence space-time maps, which provide information about the actual form of the spatiotemporal HFRS spread. For comparison purposes, the standard BME implementation and the mainstream inverse distance weighting (IDW) method were also employed to analyze the original data set without class-decomposition. To evaluate the performance of the different approaches, a ten-fold cross validation analysis was conducted that involved three distinct accuracy indicators: the root mean square error (RMSE), the mean absolute error (MAE), the determination coefficient of the corresponding linear regression (
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sup>2</sup>). Space-time computational data analysis (BME) used the software library Spatiotemporal Epistemic Knowledge Synthesis-Graphical User Interface (SEKS-GUI, [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007091.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]), while the IDW was implemented using R software [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007091.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. An outline of the proposed methodological framework is presented in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0007091.g002">Fig 2</xref>.
</p>
