<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>After binding to SA receptors, IAV is internalized by receptor-mediated endocytosis. Rust et al. previously demonstrated that most IAV particles enter cells through clathrin-mediated endocytosis (CME) (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Besides, IAV is also internalized through caveola-mediated endocytosis, clathrin- and caveola-independent endocytosis, and macropinocytosis (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Many cellular factors have been implicated in IAV entry because HA binding to SA receptors alone is insufficient for successful viral endocytosis into host cells. For example, EPN1 is recruited to the binding sites of IAV, where it initiates the formation of clathrin-coated pits, ultimately resulting in the internalization of the virus (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Loss of terminal N-linked glycosylation due to a mutation in the 
 <italic>GNT1</italic> gene arrests IAV internalization at the plasma membrane before the virus is endocytosed (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Plasma membrane lipid raft clustering, caused by IAV attachment, activates epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>), leading to the activation of downstream signaling molecules, such as phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase (PI3K) and phospholipase C γ1 (PLC-γ1) (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), which enhances IAV uptake. CD81 promotes the trafficking of IAV to fusion-competent endosomes and further organizes the endosomal membrane to assist viral fusion (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Upon IAV infection, Itch is phosphorylated and recruited to endosomes, where it ubiquitinates the viral M1 protein and mediates the release of viral ribonucleoprotein (vRNP) complexes from the endosomal compartments (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Although these cellular factors have been implicated in IAV endocytosis, the biological details underlying the IAV entry process remain poorly understood, and the roles of other host factors have yet to be revealed.
</p>
