<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The natively paired antibody genes were cloned from single cells, as previously described [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007716.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Briefly, reverse transcription was carried out to synthesize the cDNA from each single cell using a one-step cDNA synthesis kit (Bio-Rad) according to the manufacturer’s protocol. Antibody variable regions were amplified by a two-step nested PCR with 3.5 μl of the template cDNA. All PCR reactions were performed in 96-well plates in a volume of 25 μl per well with our validated primers [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007716.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The purified gene fragments were inserted into the vector with the human IgG1 constant region. The human-macaque chimeric antibodies were expressed in HEK293-F cell lines (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biocompare.com/12832-HEK-293-Cell-Lines/68091-GIBCO-FreeStyle-293F-Cells/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Thermo Fisher Scientific</ext-link>). IgG sequences were analyzed for their CDR3 length, germline IgH, Igκ, and Igλ V-gene family distribution using IgBLAST with IMGT V domain delineation (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/igblast/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/igblast/</ext-link>). The method of antibody expression in mammalian cells and purification by Protein A has been described previously [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007716.ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1007716.ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. Briefly, 0.5 μg aliquots of heavy chain plasmid and light chain plasmids (total of 1 μg plasmids/1 ml of the transfected cell) were co-transfected into HEK293-F cell lines for transient expression with TrueFect reagent (United BioSystems). The supernatants were harvested 7 days after transfection. Antibodies were purified with Protein A resin (Repligen) according to the manufacturer’s instructions.
</p>
