<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack>
 <title>Authors’ contributions</title>
 <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: MLC, AE, LM, CR. Performed the experiments: LM, MLC, CR. Analyzed the data: AC, MLC. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MLC, LM, CG. Wrote the paper: AC, MLC, FB, AE, CD, CR, CG, LM, PF, DMS, JG, GP, OR. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
 <sec id="FPar1">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p>We thank all the patients who are participating in the ANRS PRIMO cohort and the ANRS PRIMO Cohort scientific committee: V Avettand-Fenoël, F Barin, C Bourgeois, ML Chaix, A Cheret, S Couffin-Cadiergues, JF Delfraissy, A Essat, H Fischer, C Goujard, C Lascoux-Combe, C Lecuroux, L Marchand, L Meyer, C Rouzioux, A Saez-Cirion, R Seng. We also thank all physicians participating to the ANRS Primo Cohort study cohort; the full list can be found at 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://u822.kb.inserm.fr/COHAD/participantsPRIMO.htm" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://u822.kb.inserm.fr/COHAD/participantsPRIMO.htm</ext-link>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar2">
  <title>Competing interests</title>
  <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar3">
  <title>Availability of data and material</title>
  <p>The datasets during and/or analysed during the current study available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar4">
  <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
  <p>The study protocol was approved by the Paris Cochin Ethics Committee, and all patients gave their written informed consent.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar5">
  <title>Funding</title>
  <p>This study was supported by the ANRS (Agence Nationale de Recherches sur le SIDA et les Hépatites virales), Paris, France; the Department of Veterans Affairs and Grants from the National Institutes of Health AI093163, AI036214, AI027763, AI120009, MH101012, TR000098-04AI100665, MH097520, DA034978, DA041007, AI068636, MH081482, AmFAR Grant 108537, the James B. Pendleton Charitable Trust and the Bettencourt-Schueller Foundation. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p>
 </sec>
</ack>
