<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0065">Coumarin can act as an inhibitor for HIV proteases [
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Temitope 
 <italic>et al.</italic>, synthesized a series of novel N-benzylated coumarin-AZT conjugates that have inhibitory activity against both HIV-protease and Reverse transcriptase [
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Membrane fusion by binding of viral envelop protein and CD4 of T cells/Macrophages is the crucial step in HIV infection [
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Tricyclic coumarin GUT70, a natural compound isolated from 
 <italic>Callophyllum brasiliense</italic> demonstrated strong inhibitory activity on HIV-1 replication by the suppression of NF-kB activation in both acutely and chronically virus-infected cells [
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. GUT70 has the ability to reduce the membrane fluidity that affects viral entry. Matsuda 
 <italic>et al.</italic>, found that GUT-70 reduced membrane fluidity, inhibited membrane fusion and thus inhibited HIV infection [
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Further, expression of the HIV-1 receptor (CD4) and co-receptors (CXCR4 and CCR5) was downregulated which may also contribute to blocking the HIV entry [
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. 4-phenylcoumarin derivatives called neoflavanoids were synthesized and their anti-HIV effects were assessed on MT-2 infected cells 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. It suggested that the acyl group was essential for the inhibition of both the Tat and NF-kB pathway [
 <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. The HIV-replication inhibitory activity of a 4-phenyl coumarins mesouol (extracted from 
 <italic>Marila pluricostata</italic>) has been studied in Jurkat T cells. Mesuol attenuated TNF- α induced HIV-1-LTR (Long terminal repeat) activity via phosphorylation of p65 (NF-kB). Mesuol suppressed NF-kB p65 subunit phosphorylation and its transcriptional activity in TNF-α induced T cells but displayed neutral response on integration and reverse transcription [
 <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>].
</p>
