<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">The reason that coronavirus can cause human pandemic is closely related to its special structure [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. The sequencing results of SARS-CoV-2 genome sequence showed that its genome contains about 29 kb bases and 11 protein-coding regions (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), including 1ab, 1a, S, 3a, 4, M, 6, 7a, 7b, 8, N, 10 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The entry of SARS-CoV-2 into host cells was mediated mainly by the use of spike protein (S) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Therefore, we performed phylogenetic analysis of S protein of the human pathogenic coronavirus (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). S protein is a prominent trimer structure on the surface of the virus, containing two functional subunits S1 and S2, where S1 is responsible for binding to host cell surface receptors, and S2 is responsible for membrane fusion between the virus and the cell. There is a furan cleavage site at the boundary between S1 and S2 subunits, which is mutated during virus invasion, thus distinguishing SARS-CoV-2 from SARS-CoV [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Veesler et al. showed that SARS-CoV-2 entered cells using S protein by utilizing the angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) receptor on the surface of host cells, which is widely present in human respiratory and intestinal mucosal epithelial cells, enabling SARS-CoV-2 to infect humans and cause transmission in humans, which is similar to the transmission mechanism of SARS-CoV [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. In addition, studies have shown that the expression level of ACE2 gene in the lungs of smokers is significantly higher than that of non-smokers, and smokers are more likely to be infected with SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. These findings provide an important theoretical basis for drug development and epidemic prevention and control. In addition, an analysis of the SARS-CoV-2 genomic phylogenetic network revealed three types of variation, which the researchers tentatively named A/B/C, where A is the ancestor type, A and C mainly exist in Europe and the United States, while B mainly exists in east Asia, providing a new idea for the origin of SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. 
</p>
