<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Respiratory infections caused by influenza viruses usually are associated with mild-to-moderate disease symptoms but are linked with high morbidity and mortality in susceptible populations like the elderly, young children, patients with co-morbidities and immunocompromised patients. Influenza virus causes seasonal epidemics, with typically 3 to 5 million cases of severe illness worldwide, according to WHO reports [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008036.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], and influenza type A viruses (IAV) cause the more severe disease form. Vaccines against influenza are based on the induction of adaptive immunity that targets the projected yearly epidemics. While most vaccines are based on inactivated IAV formulations inducing anti-IAV IgG responses, live attenuated influenza vaccines (LAIV) are also used as formulations for i.n. administration. This is based on the assumption that the induction of local immunity may provide superior immune protection [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008036.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1008036.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. However, it remains unclear whether this protection depends on local IgA responses, on cytotoxic T cell responses, or on their combined antiviral activity. Of note, functional T cell responses were shown to substantially contribute to antiviral IAV immunity [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008036.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1008036.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In particular, cytotoxic influenza-specific CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T lymphocytes (CTLs) promote viral clearance indirectly by secretion of pro-inflammatory cytokines such as IFNγ [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008036.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] and directly by perforin/Fas-mediated killing of infected epithelial cells in the bronchoalveolar space [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008036.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. However, it remained unclear if T cell responses alone may control IAV, or if Ig responses were the crucial contributor to LAIV-mediated immune protection. We considered that this question could be addressed by developing a vaccine formulation that optimizes T cell responses against IAV while excluding the humoral ones.
</p>
