<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20">Antimicrobial peptides (AMPs) are considered as a suitable drug candidate to treat MDR bacteria, but they are unstable in vivo and have a short half-life with low penetration into mammalian cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. HPA3P
 <sup>His</sup>, as an antimicrobial peptide, loaded onto a gold nanoparticle conjugated with 
 <italic>Vibrio vulnificus</italic> specific DNA aptamer. The resulted composite promoted bacterial degradation by destroying the integrity of the 
 <italic>V. vulnificus</italic> membrane, thus, caused bacterial cell death. In this study, following intravenous injection, AuNP-Apt
 <sup>His</sup>-HPA3P
 <sup>His</sup> induced 0% mortality in infected mice, compared to the HPA3P
 <sup>His</sup> alone (100% mortality). AuNP-Apt
 <sup>His</sup> exhibited bactericidal activity in concentrations more than 5 nM. AuNP-Apt
 <sup>His</sup>-HPA3P
 <sup>His</sup> had several advantages; 1) The AuNP-AptHis enabled the efficient intracellular delivery of HPA3P
 <sup>His</sup> to the host; 2) It increased the stability of HPA3P
 <sup>His</sup> by protecting it from proteolysis; 3) It helped avoiding short-term reiterative administrations and reducing overall cost of therapy; 4) This system was simple and did not show any evident host toxicity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. On similar note, Yeom, J.-H et al. reported a C-terminally hexa-histidine-tagged A3-APO (A3-APO
 <sup>His</sup>) AMP, which were loaded onto AuNPs conjugated with His-tag DNA aptamer (AuNP-Apt
 <sup>His</sup>) in order to successfully and effectively deliver the antimicrobial peptide into 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic>-infected HeLa cells. Anti- His-tag aptamer improved the attachment of His-tag-AMP to NPs. The system was designed to improve AMP stability and its intracellular delivery and had potential impact in the elimination of intracellular 
 <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic> infection by disrupting the bacterial cell. In vivo evaluation of this system in mice also indicated promising results [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>].
</p>
