<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Med Hypotheses</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Med. Hypotheses</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Medical Hypotheses</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0306-9877</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-2777</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier Ltd.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7215164</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S0306-9877(20)30932-4</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mehy.2020.109831</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">109831</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Do pets protect their owners in the COVID-19 era?</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au005"><name><surname>Jurgiel</surname><given-names>Jan</given-names></name><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="af010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au010"><name><surname>Filipiak</surname><given-names>Krzysztof J.</given-names></name><email>krzysztof.filipiak@wum.edu.pl</email><xref rid="af015" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au015"><name><surname>Szarpak</surname><given-names>&#x00141;ukasz</given-names></name><xref rid="af020" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au020"><name><surname>Jaguszewski</surname><given-names>Mi&#x00142;osz</given-names></name><xref rid="af025" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au025"><name><surname>Smerka</surname><given-names>Jacek</given-names></name><xref rid="af030" ref-type="aff">f</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au030"><name><surname>Dzieci&#x00105;tkowski</surname><given-names>Tomasz</given-names></name><xref rid="af035" ref-type="aff">g</xref></contrib><aff id="af005"><label>a</label>Wroclaw Medical University, Poland</aff><aff id="af010"><label>b</label>Erasmus+ Exchange Student at Nova Medical University, Lisbon, Portugal</aff><aff id="af015"><label>c</label>First Chair and Department of Cardiology, Medical University of Warsaw, Poland</aff><aff id="af020"><label>d</label>Lazarski Univeristy, Warsaw, Poland, Polish Society of Disaster Medicine, Warsaw, Poland</aff><aff id="af025"><label>e</label>First Department of Cardiology, Medical University of Gdansk, Gdansk, Poland</aff><aff id="af030"><label>f</label>Department of Emergency Medical Service, Wroclaw Medical University, Wroclaw, Poland</aff><aff id="af035"><label>g</label>Chair and Department of Medical Microbiology, Medical University of Warsaw, Poland</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author. <email>krzysztof.filipiak@wum.edu.pl</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>12</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>142</volume><fpage>109831</fpage><lpage>109831</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Elsevier Ltd</copyright-holder><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s0005"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0005">The outbreak of COVID-19 &#x02013; the global spread of the disease caused by SARS-CoV2 &#x02013; took place at the end of 2019 in Wuhan, China <xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. After the infection of more than 120.000 people and the death of almost 5.000, the World Health Organization announced it as a <italic>global controllable pandemic</italic>
<xref rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. In April of 2020, the number of cases exceeded 2 million and the infection was spread over more than 180 countries <xref rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. Human coronaviruses (HCoVs) were on the origin of not only the current pandemic, but also of the SARS and MERS epidemics, which infected and took the lives of thousands of people <xref rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. Virologic and genetical studies confirmed that bats have been transmission hosts for both of the viruses, which were further spread by civets and dromedaries <xref rid="b0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. Recent studies suggest that specific types of animals can be the source of different coronaviruses: bats for alpha- and beta-CoVs, avian for gamma- and delta-CoVs, and rodents for the ancestor of the beta-CoVs lineage A <xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>.</p><p id="p0010">The infection is not exclusive to wild animals and there are many known strains that affect livestock and pets <xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. Symptoms caused by coronaviruses depend on the type of strain; they may include gastrointestinal ailments (diarrhoea, vomiting, anorexia), respiratory ailments (dyspnoea, coughing, wheezing) and others. The animal origin of the novel coronavirus led to a discussion about the possible transmission of the disease by contact with pets. A common fear that raised even more after the confirmation of the SARS-CoV2 in a tiger in the Bronx zoological garden <xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. The World Health Organization faced those concerns stating the lack of evidence on the spreading of the novel coronavirus from pet animals to people <xref rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>.</p><p id="p0015">The empirical observations show that the presence of pets may have a positive impact on the course of COVID-19. Anecdotal evidence try to persuade that veterinary doctors are rarely affected with COVID-19. Doctor Sabina Olex-Condor, a Spanish physician in Madrid, suggested in an interview that the mild course is more frequent in patients owning pets (available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.vetnolimits.com" id="ir005">www.vetnolimits.com</ext-link>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.psy.pl" id="ir010">www.psy.pl</ext-link>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plus.gloswielkopolski.pl" id="ir015">www.plus.gloswielkopolski.pl</ext-link>). The correlation between pet-ownership and the presence of a mild course of COVID-19 has not been found yet. In our study, we conducted a review of the literature, trying to establish a possible explanation to this observation. We suggest that the re-emerging contact with animal coronaviruses may lead to the stimulation of the immunological system, thus creating an effective response to SARS-CoV-2 infection.</p></sec><sec id="s0010"><title>The occurrence of the animal coronavirus in pets</title><p id="p0020">The possible positive effect of pet-ownership can be considered if the presence of the animal coronaviruses is high across the pet population. Therefore, we studied the papers presenting the occurrence of the animal coronaviruses. In our analysis, we focus on dogs, due to two reasons: 1) they are the most common species taken as home pets <xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, 2) canine coronaviruses can be transmitted easily to humans via droplets. Feline coronaviruses are also detected in cats, but their symptoms are mainly related to the gastrointestinal tract or are causative agent of uncommon and usually fatal, aberrant immune response to viral infection, but transmission animal-to-human is highly limited <xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>.</p><p id="p0025">
<xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>
shows the detection rate in dogs. According to studies, the detection of canine respiratory coronavirus (CrCoV) is settled from 7.5% to 54.7%. Studies with the most prominent sample (Priestnal et al. 2006 and More et al. 2020) showed detection: 54.7% for North America, 36.0% for the United Kingdom, and 53.0% for New Zealand.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of studies detecting coronaviruses rate in dogs.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Author</th><th>Number of samples (n)</th><th>Detection rate</th><th>Method</th><th>Region</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Priestnal et al. (2006) <xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref></td><td>1000<break/>824</td><td>54.7%<break/>36.0%</td><td>Serology testing</td><td>North America<break/>UK</td></tr><tr><td>More et al. (2020) <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref></td><td>1015</td><td>53.0%</td><td>Serology testing</td><td>New Zealand</td></tr><tr><td>Priestnal et al. (2007) <xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref></td><td>490</td><td>23.3%</td><td>Serology testing</td><td>Italy</td></tr><tr><td>An et al. (2010) <xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td><td>483</td><td>12.8%</td><td>Serology testing</td><td>Korea</td></tr><tr><td>Hielb et al. (2019) <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref></td><td>264</td><td>7.5%</td><td>Serology testing</td><td>Austria</td></tr><tr><td>Knesl et al. (2009) <xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref></td><td>251</td><td>29.0%</td><td>Serology testing</td><td>New Zealand</td></tr><tr><td>Mitchell et al. (2017) <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref></td><td>247</td><td>47.0%<break/>7.7%</td><td>Serology testing<break/>molecular testing</td><td>Europe</td></tr><tr><td>Decarao et al. (2007) <xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref></td><td>215</td><td>32.0%</td><td>Serology testing</td><td>Italy</td></tr><tr><td>Schulz et al. (2014) <xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref></td><td>151</td><td>9.8%</td><td>Molecular testing</td><td>Germany</td></tr><tr><td>Erles et al. (2003) <xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref></td><td>119</td><td>37.0%</td><td>Molecular testing</td><td>UK</td></tr><tr><td>Erles et Brownlie <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>(2005)</td><td>113</td><td>38.9%</td><td>Serology testing</td><td>UK</td></tr><tr><td>Sowman et al. (2018) <xref rid="b0145" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref></td><td>93</td><td>50.5%</td><td>Serology testing</td><td>New Zealand</td></tr><tr><td>Wille et al. (2020) <xref rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref></td><td>88</td><td>14.7%</td><td>Molecular testing</td><td>Sweden</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0030">Data show that the occurrence of CrCoV is high in dogs, which might suggest that humans who possess a pet can have more frequent contact with different types of canine coronaviruses. Since the infected pets may not have symptoms, the contact of owners with pathogens can be unnoticed <xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s0015"><title>Cross-reactivity and immune system mobilization</title><p id="p0035">The human immunological system fights different viral infections by three pathways: 1) interferon-mediated, 2) cytotoxic cells-mediated, and 3) antibody-mediated <xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. On the first, interferons provide an effective immunological reaction by the activation of NK-cells and macrophages, repression of viral proteins production, and regulation of antigen presentation to T-cells. On the second path, cytotoxic cells can directly kill the host cells infected by the virus using specific receptors and enzymes, thus stopping further infection <xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>.</p><p id="p0040">The antibody-mediated ceasing of infection can be executed through different mechanisms: agglutination, phagocytosis or complement system degradation, but all of these are stimulated by the antibody opsonisation <xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. The effectiveness of this process is related to the specificity of the antibody &#x02013; the capability of the antibody to discriminate between similar and dissimilar antigens. However, due to <italic>cross-reactivity</italic>, antibodies can respond to other antigen due to the resemblance of its structures <xref rid="b0170" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. Response to a similar antigen can lead to effective immunological protection as it was executed against the primary target. The cross-reactivity is related to the degree of the resemblance of the primary antigen to the other, for example: neutralizing antibodies against &#x0201c;old&#x0201d; SARS-CoV have moderate binding force to novel coronavirus SARS-CoV-2.</p><p id="p0045">The coronaviruses genome encodes for four structural and sixteen non-structural proteins, approximately <xref rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>, <xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. The spike proteins (S-protein) are the structural proteins that recognize and attach to ACE2 located on the cell membrane of the airways epithelia and lung parenchyma. In their study, Tilocca and colleagues sequenced the SARS-CoV-2 aminoacidic sequence and compared it to the sequences derived from the other animal coronaviruses <xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. The analysis showed that the resemblance of the whole sequence between SARS-CoV-2 and Canine Respiratory Coronavirus (CrCoV) is 36.39% (comparing the protein GI QHR63290 to QAY30030). However, further investigation of the epitope sequence shows the high homology: 57.14%, 80.00%, 83.33%, and 100.00% in CrCoV epitopes: 789&#x02013;799, 754&#x02013;764, 424&#x02013;437, and 1139&#x02013;1152, respectively. Based on the data, we suggest that recurrent contact with animal coronaviruses may lead to immunization. This effect was confirmed by the experimental studies. The investigation conducted by Lu and colleagues, showed that the nucleocapsid protein derived from CrCoV and expressed in <italic>E. coli</italic> displayed antigenic cross-reactivity with antisera against human coronaviruses <xref rid="b0190" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>.</p><p id="p0050">Furthermore, Zhao and colleagues propose one more explanation to the protective effect of the contact with zoonotic coronaviruses <xref rid="b0195" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. Cross-reactivity with T-cells can induce the immunological response. CD4+ memory T-cells on the epithelium of the airways can effectively produce interferon-gamma, which leads to activation of other cells and effective reaction.</p><p id="p0055">Thus, patients owning pets could have a mild course of the SARS-CoV-2 infection, which was observed in Spain. The recurrent contact with pathogens may work as immune-mobilization against SARS-CoV-2 in many different paths.</p></sec><sec id="s0020"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="p0060">
<list list-type="simple" id="l0005"><list-item id="o0005"><label>1.</label><p id="p0065">Canine respiratory coronaviruses occur often among dogs.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0010"><label>2.</label><p id="p0070">Ownership of a pet can lead to the contact with dogs&#x02019; coronaviruses.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0015"><label>3.</label><p id="p0075">Re-occurring contact with dogs&#x02019; coronaviruses might stimulate the human immunological system, and provide an effective response to SARS-COV-2.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0020"><label>4.</label><p id="p0080">There is a need for further investigation on the correlation between pet ownership and the course of COVID-19. Such data, even obtain retrospectively, are worth to analyse.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec><sec id="s0025"><title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title><p id="p0085">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bi005"><title>References</title><ref id="b0005"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y.-C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.-S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>Y.-J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The outbreak of COVID-19: an overview</article-title><source>J Chin Med Assoc</source><volume>83</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>220</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32134861</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0010"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0010">WHO Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) Situation Report &#x02013; 52.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0015"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0015">COVID-19 Dashboard by the Center for Systems Science and Engineering (CSSE) at Johns Hopkins University (JHU).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0020"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mallapaty</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What the cruise-ship outbreaks reveal about COVID-19</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>580</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>18</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0025"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sorensen</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS): development of diagnostics and antivirals</article-title><source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source><volume>1067</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>500</fpage><lpage>505</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16804033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0030"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0030"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.emro.who.int/health-topics/mers-cov/mers-outbreaks.html" id="ir020">http://www.emro.who.int/health-topics/mers-cov/mers-outbreaks.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0035"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wunderink</surname><given-names>R.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MERS, SARS and other coronaviruses as causes of pneumonia: MERS, SARS and coronaviruses</article-title><source>Respirology</source><volume>23</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29052924</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0040"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bats are natural reservoirs of SARS-like coronaviruses</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>310</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>676</fpage><lpage>679</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16195424</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0045"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ithete</surname><given-names>N.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Close relative of human middle east respiratory syndrome coronavirus in bat, South Africa</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><volume>19</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>1697</fpage><lpage>1699</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24050621</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0050"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>P.C.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Discovery of seven novel mammalian and avian coronaviruses in the genus deltacoronavirus supports bat coronaviruses as the gene source of alphacoronavirus and betacoronavirus and avian coronaviruses as the gene source of gammacoronavirus and deltacoronavirus</article-title><source>J Virol</source><volume>86</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>3995</fpage><lpage>4008</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22278237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0055"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>P.C.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular diversity of coronaviruses in bats</article-title><source>Virology</source><volume>351</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>180</fpage><lpage>187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16647731</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0060"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0060"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>S.K.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Discovery of a novel coronavirus, china rattus coronavirus HKU24, from Norway rats supports the murine origin of betacoronavirus 1 and has implications for the ancestor of betacoronavirus lineage A</article-title><source>J Virol</source><volume>89</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>3076</fpage><lpage>3092</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25552712</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0065"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0065"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vlasova</surname><given-names>A.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenney</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saif</surname><given-names>L.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emerging and re-emerging coronaviruses in pigs</article-title><source>Curr Opin Virol</source><volume>34</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30654269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0070"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0070"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-52177586" id="ir025">https://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-52177586</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0075"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0075">WHO Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) advice for the public: Myth busters.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0080"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0080"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Applebaum</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peek</surname><given-names>C.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zsembik</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Examining U.S. pet ownership using the General Social Survey</article-title><source>Soc Sci J</source><volume>1&#x02013;10</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03623319.2020.1728507</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0085"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0085"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaimes</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Whittaker</surname><given-names>G.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Feline coronavirus: insights into viral pathogenesis based on the spike protein structure and function</article-title><source>Virology</source><volume>517</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>108</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29329682</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0090"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0090"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Priestnall</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brownlie</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubovi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Erles</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serological prevalence of canine respiratory coronavirus</article-title><source>Vet Microbiol</source><volume>115</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16551493</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0095"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0095"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>More</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunowska</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Acke</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cave</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A serological survey of canine respiratory coronavirus in New Zealand</article-title><source>New Zealand Vet J</source><volume>68</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31513753</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0100"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Priestnall</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pratelli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brownlie</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Erles</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serological prevalence of canine respiratory coronavirus in southern italy and epidemiological relationship with canine enteric coronavirus</article-title><source>J VET Diagn Invest</source><volume>19</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>176</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17402612</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0105"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>D.-J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A serological survey of canine respiratory coronavirus and canine influenza virus in Korean dogs</article-title><source>J Vet Med Sci</source><volume>72</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>1217</fpage><lpage>1219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20410676</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0110"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hiebl</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of selected viral pathogens in dogs with canine infectious respiratory disease in Austria</article-title><source>J Small Anim Pract</source><volume>60</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>594</fpage><lpage>600</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31301071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0115"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0115"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knesl</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Allan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shields</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The seroprevalence of canine respiratory coronavirus and canine influenza virus in dogs in New Zealand</article-title><source>New Zealand Vet J</source><volume>57</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>295</fpage><lpage>298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19802044</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0120"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0120"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>European surveillance of emerging pathogens associated with canine infectious respiratory disease</article-title><source>Vet Microbiol</source><volume>212</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29173585</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0125"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0125"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Decaro</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serological and molecular evidence that canine respiratory coronavirus is circulating in Italy</article-title><source>Vet Microbiol</source><volume>121</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17215093</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0130"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0130"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>B.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balzer</surname><given-names>H.-J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of respiratory viruses and Bordetella bronchiseptica in dogs with acute respiratory tract infections</article-title><source>Vet J</source><volume>201</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>369</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24980809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0135"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0135"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erles</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toomey</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>H.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brownlie</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of a group 2 coronavirus in dogs with canine infectious respiratory disease</article-title><source>Virology</source><volume>310</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12781709</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0140"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0140"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erles</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brownlie</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigation into the causes of canine infectious respiratory disease: antibody responses to canine respiratory coronavirus and canine herpesvirus in two kennelled dog populations</article-title><source>Arch Virol</source><volume>150</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>1493</fpage><lpage>1504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15841339</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0145"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0145"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sowman</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cave</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunowska</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A survey of canine respiratory pathogens in New Zealand dogs</article-title><source>New Zealand Vet J</source><volume>66</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>236</fpage><lpage>242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29924957</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0150"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0150"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wille</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolutionary genetics of canine respiratory coronavirus and recent introduction into Swedish dogs</article-title><source>Infect Genet Evol</source><volume>82</volume><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">104290</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0155"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0155"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buonavoglia</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Canine coronavirus highly pathogenic for dogs</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><volume>12</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>492</fpage><lpage>494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16704791</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0160"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0160"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.immunology.org/public-information/bitesized-immunology/pathogens-and-disease/immune-responses-bacteria" id="ir030">https://www.immunology.org/public-information/bitesized-immunology/pathogens-and-disease/immune-responses-bacteria</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0165"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0165"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosendahl Huber</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Beek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Jonge</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luytjes</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Baarle</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>T cell responses to viral infections &#x02013; opportunities for peptide vaccination</article-title><source>Front. Immunol.</source><volume>5</volume><year>2014</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0170"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="h0170"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Immunology and evolution of infectious disease</chapter-title><year>2002</year><publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0175"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0175"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emerging coronaviruses: genome structure, replication, and pathogenesis</article-title><source>J Med Virol</source><volume>92</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>418</fpage><lpage>423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31967327</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0180"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0180"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiological and genetic analysis of severe acute respiratory syndrome</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><volume>4</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>672</fpage><lpage>683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15522679</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0185"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0185"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tilocca</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular basis of COVID-19 relationships in different species: a one health perspective</article-title><source>Microbes Infect</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micinf.2020.03.002</pub-id><comment>S1286457920300484</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0190"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0190"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic and antigenic characterization of recombinant nucleocapsid proteins derived from canine coronavirus and canine respiratory coronavirus in China</article-title><source>Sci China Life Sci</source><volume>59</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>615</fpage><lpage>621</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27084706</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0195"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0195"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Airway memory CD4 + T cells mediate protective immunity against emerging respiratory coronaviruses</article-title><source>Immunity</source><volume>44</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>1379</fpage><lpage>1391</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27287409</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>