<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par12">
 <italic>Amycolatopsis rifamycinica</italic> is the first soil bacteria that provided the rifamycins in 1957. For a while, it was considered the only bacterial source of rifamycins till their discovery in 
 <italic>Salinispora</italic> group. Although there are several rifamycins isolated from bacteria, the most widely used derivative of rifampicin (rifampin) is a semisynthetic rifamycin. Rifamycins are preferable as they can cross mammalian tissue and cell membrane easily (Bhattacharjee 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2016</xref>). As a result, rifamycin-SV and its derivatives are deemed first line in the treatment of intracellular pathogens and demonstrated inhibitory action in various biological systems. Among the antibacterial agents of these derivatives, some act by inhibiting the bacterial DNA-dependent RNA polymerase. Furthermore, rifampin inhibits poxvirus replication in vitro via a mechanism other than inhibiting DNA-dependent RNA polymerase. In vitro screening for selective inhibition of RNA-dependent DNA polymerase (reverse transcriptase) on a number of derivatives revealed that certain derivatives prevented focus formation by RNA tumour viruses (Szabo et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">1976</xref>). Rifamycin derivatives were also found to act against type II DNA topoisomerases. Besides, phylogenetic studies showed that viral type II DNA topoisomerase and their bacterial counterparts have similarities indicating that the antibacterial topoisomerase inhibitors can act against African swine fever (ASFV) replication. In fact, fluoroquinolones, a class of synthetic antibacterial drugs, were shown to inhibit the ASFV replication by interacting with type II topoisomerase (Zakaryan and Revilla 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119">2016</xref>). Rifampicin, rifapentine and rifabutin (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">22.5</xref>) are semisynthetic and water-soluble derivatives of 3-formylrifamycin SV, used in therapies against different Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacterial strains including methicillin-resistant 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA), mycobacteria (
 <italic>Mycobacterium bovis</italic> or 
 <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>) and leprosy, legionella. They are also able to prevent viral infections (e.g. influenza) (Czerwonka et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2016</xref>).
</p>
