<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The effectiveness of both vaccination and internal travel restrictions on mitigating an infectious disease have been studied in various settings, e.g. [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Germann et al. [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] study the spread of a hypothetical pandemic influenza, with a basic reproductive number in the range 1.6-2.4, in the United States, and find that (domestic) travel restrictions do not have an effect on the final size of the epidemic, but might be able to slightly delay the time course. They also find that vaccination drastically reduces the final number of cases and delays the spread. Ferguson et al. [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] find that reducing long distance travel within the United States (domestic air travel) only slightly delays the influenza epidemic, for a hypothetical pandemic influenza strain with varying transmissibility. They consider vaccination in both the United Kingdom and the United States, and find that vaccination significantly reduces the final size of the epidemic. In accordance with these studies, the US Department of Health and Human Services also claims that vaccination is the most effective way of preventing the public health impact of (pandemic) influenza [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. In a review study, Mateus et al. [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] find that domestic travel restrictions can delay the influenza epidemics by one week, and that extensive travel restrictions can reduce the final size of the epidemic. Both seasonal and pandemic influenza strains are considered. They also find that travel restrictions have minimal impact in urban centers with dense population and high mobility. Brownstein et al. [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] consider the influenza epidemic following the travel ban after 9/11. They claim that the decrease in air traffic in the United States caused a delayed and prolonged influenza season (however, note also the rebuttal in [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]). For a hypothetical influenza strain in Korea, it was found that 50% internal travel restrictions delayed the peak timing and had a slight reduction effect on the peak [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Some work has also been done on mathematical explanations and expressions for delay in epidemic spreading due to travel restrictions, for border control on international travel [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], and for more general mobility networks [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].
</p>
