<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>During the 2009 influenza pandemic, uniform vaccination guidelines were given (i.e. pro rata), for instance in Norway [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], Ireland [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] and the United States [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], and the default vaccination strategies are usually uniform [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. However, the effectiveness of the different vaccination strategies and which strategy is best in terms of minimising attack rate, possibly depend on the population clustering of the underlying country. We thus simulate the epidemic with three different vaccination strategies—uniform vaccination, prioritising urban locations and prioritising rural locations. This allows us to compare the three vaccination strategies as a function of population clustering and provides us with a better understanding and possibilities for refined vaccination strategies. There are numerous examples of spatially targeted vaccination and antiviral strategies in the literature [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Some of these are based on dynamic optimisation strategies [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], while others are based on prioritising locations with high prevalence (i.e. geographically targeting hotspots) [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. In [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], pro rata vaccination strategies are compared to vaccination strategies prioritising locations sequentially by population size (among other vaccination strategies). This is similar to the vaccination strategy we investigate, targeting urban and/or rural locations.
</p>
