<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0185">Remdesivir is an anti-viral that was seen to both prevent and treat infection caused by MERS-COV in monkeys (
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>). Although current clinical studies exclude pregnant women, Remdesivir may be administered in critically ill pregnant patients (NCT0428070500) (
 <xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>). To date, no information is available concerning the effects of Remdesivir in pregnancy. Due to the increased release of cytokines and subsequent inflammatory damage during COVID-19, Tocilizumab, a monoclonal antibody that binds the receptor interleukin-6, has been used in China, with at least one clinical trial that is ongoing (NCT04310228) (
 <xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>). A major concern for pregnant patients is that IgG isotype antibodies cross the placenta at an increasing rate in accordance with gestational age (
 <xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>). However, the effect of each medication on fetal development is unknown. Furthermore, in the rheumatology literature it is recommended that Tocilizumab be avoided during pregnancy given the lack of data on adverse fetal effects (
 <xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>). Other anti-viral medications that have been used that have clear evidence of teratogenicity, either in humans or animal models, include Favipiravir and Ribavirin (
 <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>). Notably, the aforementioned medications are experimental, thus it is imperative to have a risk-benefit discussion with patients given the medication side-effect profiles, potential effects in pregnancy, and unknown benefits. Until randomized trials with adequate controls are completed, it is difficult to draw definitive conclusions concerning the efficacy of any of these treatments (
 <xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>).
</p>
