<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="bullet">
 <list-item>
  <p>Preliminary assessment of raw reads</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Read quality enhancement by filtering ribosomal RNA and mapping to human reference genome.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Transcript abundance estimation and differential expression analysis</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>The whole transcriptome data analysis process involved checking the read quality, mapping the reads to reference sequence and differential gene expression analysis.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Quality analysis of RNA reads was done through FastQC tool. Quality analysis of RNA reads across read positions and overall data quality across the samples was analyzed. High quality reads (Q&gt;20) were 50–69% across the samples tested, which corresponds 99% inferred base call accuracy. Reads were initially mapped to ribosomal RNA sequences (5, 5.8, 12, 16, 18 and 28s) using Bowtie-0.12.8 with default settings. Reads that mapped to ribosomal sequences were excluded from further analysis (
   <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0228068.s003">S1 Table</xref>). Remaining reads were mapped to human reference genome hg19, ENSEMBL release GRCh37.68 using Tophat-2.0.5. Quality control metrics such as read summary, coverage and transcript associated reads were computed using RNASeQC. 
   <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0228068.s003">S1</xref> and 
   <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0228068.s004">S2</xref> Tables show mapping summary to the hg19 genome and exonic rates respectively.13-86 million (14.6–49.3% of total) reads mapped to human genome (hg19), of which 77–88% were uniquely mapped. All the samples exhibited high exonic rate (61–88% of uniquely mapped reads were mapped to exonic regions). ~ 15,000–22,000 genes were detected with &gt;5 unique reads across samples. On an average, 32 million reads were available for expression analysis. Principal component analysis (PCA) and correlation plots were obtained on log10 FPKM values and a coefficient value close to 1.0 was obtained indicating highly linear relation between the samples.
  </p>
 </list-item>
</list>
