<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F3" position="float">
 <label>FIGURE 3</label>
 <caption>
  <p>The structure of influenza virus HA protein in the native and fusion-intermediate states, which serve as the target of the protein- and peptide-based influenza virus inactivators. 
   <bold>(A)</bold> Schematic representation of HA composition, including surface subunit HA1 and transmembrane subunit HA2. 
   <bold>(B)</bold> Attachment of HA protein to the cellular receptor(s) and fusion of viral envelope with endosomal membrane. To initiate the entry process, the RBS on HA attaches the virus to cell surface receptors that contain terminal sialic-acid residues, followed by entry of the virion into an endosome of the host cell via endocytosis. The acidic environment in the endosome induces conformational change of HA, enabling the exposure of the fusion peptide on the N-terminus of HA2. Subsequently, the fusion peptide inserts into the endosomal membrane with the C-terminal transmembrane domain (TMD) anchoring HA2 in the viral envelope, creating a pre-hairpin conformation (extended intermediate). Afterward, the HA2 trimers fold back on themselves forming a hairpin conformation, which then further collapses into a six-helix bundle, bringing the viral envelope and endosomal membrane together for fusion. The pre-fusion trimer is highlighted in a green box, which is shown in more detail in 
   <bold>(C)</bold>. 
   <bold>(C)</bold> Side view of the pre-fusion, trimeric conformation of HA protein present on the virion surface (modified from PDB ID: 4FNK). The heads of HA1 subunits are colored with dark tints, showing the receptor-binding pockets (RBPs). Names of inactivators are listed in the three boxes, and the arrows depict their target sites, including the conserved stem and RBP. Notably, potential inactivators remaining to be tested are listed in the box with dashed lines and arrow.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="fmicb-11-01063-g003" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
