<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Considering the outbreaks of Africa and Asia, experts were surprised that CHIKV had not initiated autochthonous transmission in the Americas, given that the 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> in the Americas were suitable vectors for urban transmission. In 2013, however, a CHIKV isolate belonging to the Asian lineage was identified in the Caribbean. The virus quickly spread to neighboring islands and into South America. Brazil noted its first case in 2014. More than one million cases have been reported to PAHO since [
 <xref rid="B192-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">192</xref>]. Around 2015, another introduction of an ECSA lineage virus was noted in Brazil with sustained autochthonous transmission, proving that ECSA stains were capable of urban transmission outside of Africa and introduction of new strains continues to be a threat [
 <xref rid="B220-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">220</xref>,
 <xref rid="B221-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">221</xref>]. The states in the northeast have been the hardest hit [
 <xref rid="B222-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">222</xref>,
 <xref rid="B223-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">223</xref>]. In 2016 and 2017, the number of confirmed CHIKF cases totaled 261,000 and 171,000, respectively [
 <xref rid="B223-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">223</xref>]. After this initial introduction, CHIKV spread across the South and Central America spreading as far north as Mexico. The majority of cases in the United States were travel related though some might have been locally acquired [
 <xref rid="B224-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">224</xref>,
 <xref rid="B225-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">225</xref>]. Interestingly, CHIKV has not initiated an enzootic cycle in the Americas and is an active area of investigation since the mosquito and nonhuman primate species capable of harboring infection are present in the Amazon [
 <xref rid="B226-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">226</xref>,
 <xref rid="B227-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">227</xref>].
</p>
