<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Measles is a highly contagious illness produced by the negative-sense RNA measles virus (MV) of the family 
 <italic>Paramyxoviridae</italic>, and is transmitted through respiration or aerosol [
 <xref rid="B90-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. Prior to the licensure of a vaccine in 1963, measles epidemics occurred every two to three years and caused 2.6 million deaths annually [
 <xref rid="B91-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. MV was first isolated in tissue culture by Enders and Peebles in 1954 using samples from an infected child named David Edmonston [
 <xref rid="B34-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. The virus was propagated on primary human kidney and amnion cells and attenuated through passages in chick embryos and chick embryo fibroblasts. This process gave rise to Edmonston A and B strains [
 <xref rid="B34-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B90-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. While Edmonston A was too reactogenic for vaccination use, Edmonston B was licensed as an LAV in 1963, with further attenuation through five additional passages on chick embryo fibroblasts at 36–37 °C [
 <xref rid="B9-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The reactogenicity of measles LAV (MV-LAV) led to the creation of further attenuated strains, such as AIK-C from the original Edmonston strain [
 <xref rid="B92-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>], Schwarz from Edmonston A [
 <xref rid="B93-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>], and Edmonston Zagreb [
 <xref rid="B94-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>] and Moraten [
 <xref rid="B95-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>] from the Edmonston B strain. Approaches to developing these strains involved further passage in chick cell culture [
 <xref rid="B93-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>], passage in chick cell culture at elevated [
 <xref rid="B95-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>] or lowered temperatures [
 <xref rid="B92-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>], and passage in human diploid fibroblasts [
 <xref rid="B94-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. Independent measles strains such as CAM 70 [
 <xref rid="B96-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>], Leningrad 4 [
 <xref rid="B97-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>], Changchun 47 and Shanghai 191 [
 <xref rid="B98-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>] were also produced. All MV-LAV cause fevers and a rash to some extent, but most side effects are mild and short-lived [
 <xref rid="B9-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Safe, effective, and affordable MV-LAVs have had a profound effect on the disease: between 2000 and 2017, the incidence of measles decreased by 83%, and deaths due to measles fell by 80% [
 <xref rid="B99-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>]. 
</p>
