<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Vaccination is the mainstay of influenza infection control, however, high-risk patient groups such as the elderly and immune-compromised, do not respond well to vaccines (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>). As such, there is a need for additional prophylactic and therapeutic approaches that are independent of the patient’s immune system and the prior availability of the matching influenza strain (
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>). One approach, which is of considerable interest, is passive immunotherapy or prophylaxis with broadly neutralizing monoclonal antibodies which bind to conserved epitopes on influenza HA (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>–
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>). We have previously described R1a-B6 which has an epitope overlapping the fusion peptide, suggesting a post-viral attachment mechanism of action through the inhibition of viral membrane fusion (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). In this study, we have evaluated the prophylactic efficacy of R1a-B6 using intramuscular AAV delivery. We have chosen to explore intramuscular delivery instead of intranasal delivery as others have chosen (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>) as this has been reported to produce higher and more durable expression levels in systemic circulation (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). For example in macaques, AAV expression in the nasal cavity was shown to decrease after 3–4 months which was likely due to the turnover of nasal epithelial cells and loss of transgene expression (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). In contrast, the low turnover rate of muscle cells should, in principle, mean that the AAV transgenes can be maintained for much longer (
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). This delivery method is also simpler to implement in resource poor settings alongside other immunizations.
</p>
