<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Anti-CHIKV IgM antibodies appear as early as three days after infection, but their presence is usually detected only after three to four months [
 <xref rid="B18-viruses-11-00407" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-11-00407" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. In contrast, anti-CHIKV IgG antibodies remain detectable in convalescent individuals for many years; thus, anti-CHIKV IgG are able to provide insights into the seroepidemiology of CHIKV [
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-11-00407" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-11-00407" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. However, it is often difficult to differentiate acute from convalescent cases based on the detection of specific IgG alone in highly endemic areas. Despite this difficulty, a recent multi-country quality assurance study showed that the IgG detection of CHIKV infection may be more useful than IgM detection [
 <xref rid="B25-viruses-11-00407" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Therefore, we sought to develop an improved diagnostic tool to detect CHIKV-specific IgM and IgG based on a recombinant subunit protein that may be important in improving the sensitivity of serodiagnosis for clinical management and epidemiological surveillance. We have recently reported a recombinant CHIKV E2 protein in mammalian cells [
 <xref rid="B26-viruses-11-00407" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Based on this, we sought to detect and quantify anti-CHIKV E2 IgM and IgG E2 in human sera from CHIKV acute infections or convalescent patients. In order to validate our in-house ELISA, we have used a cohort of sera from infected patients tested by a reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) along with the sera from healthy volunteers, and then compared these to a commercial ELISA assay. Results showed that our in-house E2 based IgM and IgG ELISA assays could detect anti-CHIKV IgM and IgG antibodies with similar or higher sensitivity than the commercial kit. The data presented here also provide valuable serological information regarding the current seroprevalence of CHIKV in the city of Lázaro Cárdenas, state of Michoacán, in México.
</p>
