<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Sequences in the coding regions acting as bundling signals to bring together the different genomic vRNPs are believed to function via direct RNA-RNA interactions
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref> or via indirect interactions mediated by a yet unknown viral or cellular protein
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>. Until now, no putative interacting motifs could be identified using 
 <italic>in silico</italic> analyses, most probably because 1) viral RNA coils around the NP proteins in a complex way in the vRNPs, 2) packaging signals could potentially be discontinuous, and 3) RNA-RNA interactions might involve non Watson-Crick base-pairing
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>. Direct RNA-RNA interactions have been demonstrated 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">37</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">38</xref> and the networks of interaction between the eight vRNAs that were obtained for different subtypes of influenza A viruses highlighted the complexity of the bundling process and how difficult it might be to identify the specific nucleotides involved. Single, synonymous mutations at extremely conserved positions within the coding region were nonetheless shown to be sufficient to impair the incorporation of the specific segment into viral particles
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">39</xref>. Our approach based on serial passaging of the chimeric viruses was successful in identifying specific residues in the NA coding regions that could be important for interactions with other segments. Mutations A1355G in 
 <bold>PB2</bold>-NA-
 <bold>PB2</bold> and U1308C in 
 <bold>PA</bold>-NA-
 <bold>PA</bold> appeared near the 5′NC region and were shown to restore segment 6 incorporation and virus fitness. Since both the PB2 and PA 5′NC regions were longer than the original 5′NC region of segment 6, our results suggest that these mutations restored the necessary links between segment 6 and another segment to allow its efficient packaging. Introduction of these mutations into wild-type 
 <bold>NA</bold>-NA-
 <bold>NA</bold> had different consequences. Mutation A1355G (found in the passaged 
 <bold>PB2</bold>-NA-
 <bold>PB2)</bold> impaired to some extent virus fitness (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3c</xref>) and segment 6 incorporation (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3d</xref>) in MDCK cells. The effect was more pronounced in A549 cells (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. S3d</xref>). This suggests a putative, additional role of the amino-acid change resulting of the A1355G mutation, although this deleterious effect was not obviously seen for the 
 <bold>PB2</bold>-NA
 <sup>A1355G</sup>-
 <bold>PB2</bold> virus infection in A549 cells (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. S3d</xref>). In addition, the effect on virus fitness and segment 6 incorporation in infected MDCK was shown to be base dependent in 
 <bold>PB2</bold>-NA-
 <bold>PB2</bold> (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. S3b and c</xref>). As for mutation U1308C (found in the passaged 
 <bold>PA</bold>-NA-
 <bold>PA)</bold>, its introduction in 
 <bold>NA</bold>-NA-
 <bold>NA</bold> had no effect (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3g</xref>). We therefore hypothesized that the specific distance of the mutated nucleotide from one of the ends might be the key determinant. However, our various attempts at clarifying this mechanism by introducing different substitutions in both 
 <bold>NA</bold>-NA-
 <bold>NA</bold> and 
 <bold>PA</bold>-NA-
 <bold>PA</bold> did not lead to any conclusive results (data not shown), and therefore how mutation U1308C affects segment 6 incorporation remains to be determined.
</p>
