<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Evidence suggests that many pathogens are transmitted between their animal reservoirs and humans but fail to be transmitted from human to human or do so at rates that do not allow pathogen establishment within the human population. For example, sequence data from HIV-1 and HIV-2 suggest that as many as 10 prior transmission events into human populations occurred over the last century before this virus emerged globally (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">
  <italic>23</italic>
 </xref>). Recent data from our own field sites suggest that simian foamy viruses infect bushmeat hunters regularly, so far without evidence of human-to-human transmission (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">
  <italic>26</italic>
 </xref>). Other pathogens, such as avian influenza and Hendra viruses, which do not appear to be transmitted through bushmeat consumption, have also led to several small epidemics with little or no evidence of human-to-human transmission. We have termed this "viral chatter," a seemingly common phenomenon of repeated transmission of nonhuman viruses to humans, most of which results in no human-to-human transmission (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">
  <italic>28</italic>
 </xref>). We hypothesize that this mechanism is common in viral emergence. High rates of viral chatter will increase the diversity of viruses and sequence variants moving into humans, increase the probability of transmission of a pathogen that can successfully replicate, and ultimately increase the ability of a human-adapted virus to emerge in a more widespread manner. In some cases this process may result in the evolution of a new viral strain (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">
  <italic>29</italic>
 </xref>) and may be a very common mechanism for viral emergence into the human population (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">
  <italic>23</italic>
 </xref>
 <italic>,</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">
  <italic>28</italic>
 </xref>).
</p>
