<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Confirmatory testing using an alternative serological or antigen/virus detection assay is recommended for ELISA-positive serum, especially for endemic areas, and/or poorly preserved samples (
 <xref rid="B164" ref-type="bibr">164</xref>). The IFAT is an established confirmatory test utilizing African green monkey kidney cells (Vero cells) infected with culture-adapted viral (e.g., BA71V) and a fluorophore-conjugated secondary antibody capable of detecting swine immunoglobulins (Ig). It provides a high level of specificity by allowing direct visualization of antibody reactivity with intracellular ASFV antigens in virus factories of infected cells, facilitating discernment from background noise (
 <xref rid="B164" ref-type="bibr">164</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B189" ref-type="bibr">189</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B195" ref-type="bibr">195</xref>). The ASFV IPT is conceptually similar to IFAT and has comparable sensitivity and specificity but instead uses a peroxidase-tagged secondary anti-swine Ig detection antibody, thereby avoiding the requirement for a fluorescent microscope and facilitating larger scale testing (
 <xref rid="B164" ref-type="bibr">164</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B186" ref-type="bibr">186</xref>). The IPT has been shown to possess greater sensitivity in detecting early ASFV-specific antibody responses than the OIE-recommended indirect ELISA and multiple commercial ELISAs (
 <xref rid="B167" ref-type="bibr">167</xref>). Both the IFAT and IPT are OIE-recommended confirmatory serological tests recommended for ELISA-positive samples from areas free of ASFV and for inconclusive ELISA samples from endemic areas; the IPT is considered preferable over the IFAT (
 <xref rid="B164" ref-type="bibr">164</xref>). Immunoblots (IBs) or Western blots (WBs) use soluble cytoplasmic ASFV proteins as antigens, and can be used as an alternative to the IFAT and the IPT. They are highly specific and not too difficult to interpret since the immunoreactive proteins of ASFV detected by antibodies in the IB/WB test have been well-described (
 <xref rid="B164" ref-type="bibr">164</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B187" ref-type="bibr">187</xref>). Antibodies from positive animals maintain reactivity on IBs for longer than with the OIE-recommended indirect ELISA when the test serum is stored at room temperature or 37°C; the IB can be advantageous for poorly-preserved sera samples or where reliable refrigeration is not available (
 <xref rid="B196" ref-type="bibr">196</xref>). IBs using recombinant p54, a highly immunogenic ASFV protein expressed in 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> or baculovirus systems, have been described, and are easier to interpret than ASFV-infected cell-based IBs, and avoid the need for ASFV antigens produced in cells (
 <xref rid="B182" ref-type="bibr">182</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B191" ref-type="bibr">191</xref>). 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>-expressed p30 has also been demonstrated to be a highly sensitive and specific antigen for IBs, capable of detecting serological responses as early as 6–8 days post-infection (
 <xref rid="B197" ref-type="bibr">197</xref>). IBs/WBs based on individual ASFV proteins do not offer the multiple ASFV antigen array present in ASFV-infected cell lysate. Therefore, future IB/WB approaches for ASF serological diagnosis should include multiple recombinant ASFV antigens in order to increase specificity and sensitivity.
</p>
