<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Ideally, all health care facilities should have dedicated infection control professional (ICP) whose primary responsibility is the prevention of infection. The ICP is responsible for having the knowledge of which infectious diseases must be reported by state legislation or regulation to the local or state health department. In the absence of an ICP, the designated manager is responsible for the reporting. The general categories of conditions reported are communicable diseases, sexually transmitted diseases, TB, and vaccine preventable disease. Notifiable diseases vary somewhat by state although all states require reporting of diseases subject to quarantine (cholera, plague, and yellow fever) according to the World Health Organization’s International Health Regulations. The responsibility for reporting diseases to the local health authority depends upon the requirements set forth by that authority. A report to the local health authority in whose jurisdiction the reporter is located is required by any person having knowledge of a known or suspected case or carrier of communicable disease or a death caused by a communicable disease determined notifiable by the local health authority. Among those required to report include: physicians, nurses, nurse aides, dentists, laboratory personnel, school personnel, long-term care personnel, day care personnel, and college/university personnel. Health care providers may disclose individually identifiable health information for use in public health to public health authorities without individual consent without violating HIPAA regulation. The specific data required for reporting includes patient information (name, address, date of birth, gender, race, ethnicity) and testing information (name of test and test result). The Centers for Disease and Control website should be consulted for the latest listing of notifiable diseases in the USA which is revised periodically depending upon the emergence of new pathogens or a decline or elimination of an existing pathogen (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab4_7" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Even under the best of circumstances, it may take 2–3 weeks to confirm a patient’s illness was part of an outbreak because of the time to contact the health system, the timing of the collection of the specimen, clinical laboratory identification of the agent, shipping time of the specimen to the public health lab, and confirmation by the public lab. Thus, cases enumerated by signs and symptoms while an outbreak of a disease is occurring should be considered preliminary until confirmed by laboratory findings. 
</p>
