<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In Ayurveda, there is thinking of epidemics under the term of 
 <italic>Janapadodhwamsa</italic> where it is mentioned that due to either of deranged 
 <italic>Vayu</italic> (air), 
 <italic>Jala</italic> (water), 
 <italic>Desha</italic> (habitat) and 
 <italic>Kala</italic> (seasons), certain diseases arise which kill mass of people. These diseases can be considered as either airborne or waterborne infectious diseases or diseases occurring due to soil contamination or conditions arising due to weather or seasonal hazards. Further, under the heading of 
 <italic>Adidaivika</italic>
 <italic>Bala</italic>
 <italic>Pravritta</italic>
 <italic>Vyadhi</italic> (diseases arising due to such causes that cannot be controlled by human intelligence), terms such as 
 <italic>Sansargaja</italic> and 
 <italic>Upsragaja</italic> are mentioned which indicate that there are certain diseases which can be transmitted directly from infected persons to healthy persons such as contagious diseases or certain diseases can be transmitted by respiration/air borne. As per the hints available in Ayurveda, the management of these infectious diseases can be either preventive or curative. For example, now the changes in weather or seasons can be predicted and thus, before starting of epidemics which are most likely to occur in that weather, adequate arrangements and planning can be done so as minimize the morbidity. This is termed as anticipation that is the first stage of response and which enables to focus on the most likely threats, forecasting of the most likely diseases to emerge and the quick identification of the vectors that will worsen the impact or facilitate the spread of infections. However, in newly emerging viral diseases where there is little scientific knowledge, a vigilant observation can help prepare plan and management in future outbreaks. Further, early detection may help for rapid implementation of effective measures, which are the key to reduce the risk of distratous spread. In Ayurveda, it is mentioned that collection of potent medicines should be done and if required, 
 <italic>Shodhana</italic> (bio-purification) and 
 <italic>Rasayana</italic> (immunomodulatory changes) can be planned in the persons in the risk areas, so as to improve the immunity and thus making the risk of infection low. It is noted that certain viral infections occur in a specific period of year when either the weather is favorable for viral potency or there are potent vectors to carry the infection or when immunity of the human body is low. For example, looking at the history of outbursts of chikungunya or dengue infections in India, it can be stated that these viral epidemics are more common just after the monsoon when breeding of mosquitoes is increased, and as per the Ayurveda, this is the time of 
 <italic>Pitta</italic>
 <italic>vitiation</italic> and chances of 
 <italic>Jvara</italic> are more. Hence, for the management of these type of viral fevers, prevention can be started from the monsoon season by adopting steps such as taking 
 <italic>Neema</italic> (
 <italic>Azadirachta</italic>
 <italic>indica</italic> A. Juss) leaves juice or taking 
 <italic>Neema</italic> (
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>indica</italic> A. Juss) bark powder or 
 <italic>Sudrashana</italic> powder or 
 <italic>Guduchi</italic> powder, along with this proper fumigation of the areas shall be done with dry 
 <italic>Neema</italic> (
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>indica</italic> A. Juss) leaves, 
 <italic>Kapura</italic>, 
 <italic>Vacha</italic> (
 <italic>Acorus</italic>
 <italic>calamus</italic> Linn.). Many of viral diseases such as chikungunya infections are rarely fatal and symptoms are generally self-limiting and last for 2–3 days. However, in the long term, it can cause secondary conditions such as post-chikungunya arthritis resulting in long-term disabilities which may cause medical and economic burden in affected areas. In such cases analgesics and/or nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs may provide relief, but resistance to or dependence on corticosteroids beyond the 3
 <sup>rd</sup> month after disease onset may be evocative of post-chikungunya chronic inflammatory rheumatism. This finding indicates that early treatment to control the inflammatory process may, prevent bone erosions and reduce to chance of side effects of prolonged cortico-therapy which is required in such cases of post-chikungunya chronic inflammatory rheumatism.
</p>
