<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Stochastic SIR models typically require the same assumptions as a deterministic SIR model (Section 
 <xref rid="insr12402-sec-0008" ref-type="sec">2.3</xref>). To reflect the stochastic nature of disease transmission and recovery, stochastic processes such as a Poisson process are used to model the accumulation of cases. Following the earlier definitions of 
 <italic>β</italic> and 
 <italic>γ</italic>, the number of effective contacts in the population is a Poisson process with rate 
 <italic>βN</italic>. Of these contacts, only those between the contagious and susceptible will lead to new infections. Hence, the counting process defined by the number of exposed (i.e. 
 <italic>I</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>)+
 <italic>R</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>), or equivalently 
 <italic>N</italic>−
 <italic>S</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>)) follows a Poisson process with rate 
 <italic>βS</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>)
 <italic>I</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>)/
 <italic>N</italic>. Hence, the number of newly exposed in an instantaneous duration of 
 <italic>dt</italic> follows a Poisson distribution with mean 
 <math id="nlm-math-29">
  <mfrac>
   <mrow>
    <mi>β</mi>
    <mi>S</mi>
    <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
    <mi>I</mi>
    <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
   </mrow>
   <mrow>
    <mi>N</mi>
   </mrow>
  </mfrac>
  <mi>d</mi>
  <mi>t</mi>
 </math>. On the other hand, the duration of time individuals staying infectious is assumed to be independent and identically distributed according to an exponential distribution with rate 
 <italic>γ</italic>, and hence, the mean infectious duration is 1/
 <italic>γ</italic>. When we jointly consider all 
 <italic>I</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>) infectious subjects at time 
 <italic>t</italic>, exit events occur independently with a rate 
 <italic>γI</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>), and the gap times between two adjacent exits are exponentially distributed with mean 1/{
 <italic>γI</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>)}. In summary, the number of removed individuals is a counting process following a Poisson process with rate 
 <italic>γI</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>). Such stochastic formulation is commonly used, for example, in Bailey (
 <xref rid="insr12402-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">1975</xref>) and Andersson and Britton (
 <xref rid="insr12402-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>). Through the earlier definitions, 
 <italic>S</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>),
 <italic>I</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>) and 
 <italic>R</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>) are now random variables that can be directly sampled. In fact, it suffices to assume only two of the three counting processes in order to define a stochastic SIR model due to the constant sample size constraint.
</p>
