<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>sgRNA sequences targeting exons of the human 
 <italic>STT3A</italic>, 
 <italic>STT3B</italic>, 
 <italic>MAGT1</italic>, or 
 <italic>TUSC3</italic> genes were designed by using the GeneArt CRISPR search and design tool (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://apps.thermofisher.com/apps/crispr/index.html" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://apps.thermofisher.com/apps/crispr/index.html</ext-link>). Predesigned sequences with the fewest predicted off-target cleavage sites were selected. For 
 <italic>STT3A</italic> and 
 <italic>STT3B</italic>, two target sequences were selected for each gene (
 <italic>STT3A</italic>-target-1, TATATCTCCCGATCTGTGGC; 
 <italic>STT3A</italic>-target-2, ACAGACATTCCGAATGTCGA; 
 <italic>STT3B</italic>-target-1, GACGACTTGTGCTTGCTCTC; STT3B-target-2, CGTGGATGATGCTTTCGAAG). For 
 <italic>MAGT1</italic> and 
 <italic>TUSC3</italic>, one target sequence was selected (
 <italic>MAGT1</italic>-target-1, ATAACGGAGTAATTTCTCGG; 
 <italic>TUSC3</italic>-target-1, CGCTCAATCTTCCGAATGAA). A pair of partially cDNA oligonucleotides encoding each sgRNA sequence was synthesized and ligated into a pSpCas9(BB)-2A-Puro plasmid (PX459; Addgene, catalog no. 62988), which bears both the Cas9 gene, and the sgRNA scaffold backbone containing an oligonucleotide cloning site. Construction of the plasmids was performed according to a standard target sequence cloning protocol involving an annealing step and a ligation reaction (
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>). Briefly, the DNA oligonucleotide pairs encoding the 20-nucleotide sgRNA were 5′ phosphorylated by T4 polynucleotide kinase (NEB) and annealed in a thermocycler with the following parameters: 37°C for 30 min, 95°C for 5 min, and cooling to 25°C at 5°C min
 <sup>−1</sup>. The DNA oligonucleotides were then ligated into the linearized pSpCas9(BB)-2A-Puro vector using Quick ligase (NEB) at room temperature for 10 min. Finally, the ligated plasmids were transformed into a competent 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> strain, plated on an LB plate containing 100 μg/ml ampicillin, and incubated overnight at 37°C. The colonies were checked by Sanger sequencing for correct sgRNA insertion. Plasmids encoding Cas9 and each sgRNA were isolated and transfected into HEK293T cells using Lipofectamine 2000 transfection reagent (Invitrogen) to direct genome editing. The transfected cells were selected by incubating with 2 μg/ml puromycin for 72 h, and then isogenic cell lines were isolated by serial dilutions and allowed to expand for 2 to 3 weeks. Genomic DNA from the isogenic cell lines was extracted by using a TIANamp genomic DNA kit (DP304; Tiangen Biotech). PCR amplification of the modified regions was defined by Sanger sequencing using specific genomic cleavage detection primers, and cell lines exhibiting frameshift mutations at the corresponding sites were selected and further confirmed by Western blotting. 
 <italic>MAGT1</italic> and 
 <italic>TUSC3</italic> double-knockout cells (
 <italic>MAGT1</italic>
 <sup>–</sup>
 <italic>TUSC3</italic>
 <sup>–</sup>) were constructed by transfecting the 
 <italic>TUSC3</italic>-sgRNA plasmid into 
 <italic>MAGT1</italic>
 <sup>–</sup> cells to direct a second editing event. Isogenic cell lines bearing the desired editing outcomes were sequenced and selected in the same way.
</p>
