<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20">Recombinant airborne transmissible A/H5N1 A/Indonesia/05/2005 virus (A/H5N1
 <sub>AT</sub>) was initially described in ref. 
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>. The A/H5N1
 <sub>AT</sub> virus carries 9 amino acid substitutions as compared to the A/H5N1 virus (A/H5N1): PB2-E627K, PB1-H99Y, PB1-I368V, NP-R99K, NP-S345N, HA-H103Y, HA-T156A, HA-Q222L, and HA-G224S. The var A/H5N1
 <sub>AT</sub> virus carries one silent nucleotide substitution in the PB2 gene (A339G), which was introduced into the reverse genetics plasmids using QuikChange (Agilent) site directed mutagenesis, according to the manufacturer’s instructions. Recombinant A/H5N1 viruses carrying subsets of airborne substitutions were initially described in ref. 
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>. Airborne substitutions were introduced into the reverse genetics plasmids using QuikChange (Agilent) site directed mutagenesis, according to the manufacturer’s instructions. A/H5N1 viruses used for virus histochemistry were recombinant viruses with seven gene segments of A/Puerto-Rico/8/1934 and the wild-type or mutant HA segment (A/H5N1
 <sub>HA-Q222L/G224S</sub>) of A/Indonesia/5/2005 from which the multibasic cleavage site was removed. Recombinant A/H5 influenza viruses were rescued in 293T cells by using reverse genetics using a modified version of pHW2000
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>
 </sup>. Cells were plated the day before transfection in gelatinized 100 mm diameter culture dishes to obtain 50% confluent monolayers. 293T cells were then transfected using calcium phosphate with 40 μg of total DNA. After overnight transfection, the transfection medium was replaced with fresh medium supplemented with 2% FCS for virus production. Cells were incubated for 72 h, after which supernatants were harvested. Virus-containing supernatants were cleared by centrifugation for 10 min at 300 × 
 <italic>g</italic> and used to infect MDCK to generate virus stocks and stock titers were determined by endpoint tirations in MDCK cells. The A/H3N2 A/Netherlands/213/2003 and A/H1N1 A/Netherlands/602/2009 viruses used for virus histochemistry were human isolates propagated in MDCK cells.
</p>
