<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="f3" position="float">
 <label>Figure 3</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Key events in pathogen transmission from mosquito to vertebrate host and implications to effector selection. The transmission of mosquito-borne pathogens can be suppressed by blocking one or more of the steps required for pathogen infection and/or dissemination in mosquitoes. For 
   <italic>Plasmodium</italic> parasites (I) and arboviruses (II) effectors can be built to block one or more essential points in the pathogen replication cycle: 
   <bold>(A)</bold>—initial infection of a midgut epithelial cell; 
   <bold>(B)</bold>—spread of infection among midgut epithelial cells; 
   <bold>(C)</bold>—midgut escape of infecting agents from midgut epithelial cells into hemolymph; 
   <bold>(D)</bold>—salivary gland infection, and 
   <bold>(E)</bold>—salivary gland escape where the pathogens spread to salivary glands and are expectorated in a subsequent blood meal of the female mosquito, respectively. If any one or more of these events is completely blocked, then transmission cannot occur. At each of these potential intervention points, there is a bottleneck that constricts pathogen population size and diversity. By selecting effectors with timing and specificity that can exploit these natural bottlenecks, it may slow the rate that pathogen resistance to the effector is developed. For example, as 
   <italic>Plasmodium</italic> parasites (I) move through the gametocyte, gamete, zygote 
   <bold>(A)</bold>, ookinete 
   <bold>(B)</bold>, and oocyst 
   <bold>(B-C)</bold> stages, their population size and diversity progressively decreases with a substantial genetic bottleneck at each stage. However, the population size increases dramatically when the oocysts release sporozoites 
   <bold>(C-E)</bold>. Most current anti-
   <italic>Plasmodium</italic> effectors developed to date target the ookinete stage when the parasite population is relatively small, but if pathogen resistance to anti-ookinete effectors does occur then targeting the oocyst stage, where the parasite population size is the lowest and least diverse, may slow resistance. Similar to a combinatorial drug approach, targeting multiple parasite development stages concurrently is also a strategy that researchers are taking to circumvent resistance. Arbovirus populations (II) go through a series of population expansions and reductions that correspond with the essential points in their replication cycle 
   <bold>(A-E)</bold>. In the vertebrate, purifying selection reduces the genetic diversity of viruses acquired during blood feeding (1), but with the high mutation rate the genetic composition of the virus genome drifts as it disseminations through the mosquito. Effectors that target the virus in the early stages of infection 
   <bold>(A</bold> and early 
   <bold>B)</bold> prior to expansion and diversification of the virus in the midgut would potentially decrease the likelihood of the virus circumventing an antiviral effector. Most current antiviral effector designs target these early stages.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="fgene-10-01072-g003" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
