<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The mean incubation period for SARS‐CoV‐2 is estimated to be between 2 and 14 days, with an average of 5 days.
 <xref rid="ppul24810-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>35</sup>
 </xref> There is evidence of human‐to‐human transmission through droplets or direct contact; and precautions should be practiced in the healthcare settings to prevent airborne transmission, which may be underestimated, among many uncertainties about this novel virus.
 <xref rid="ppul24810-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>36</sup>
 </xref> There have been confirmed cases in healthcare workers, and the reported cases were 3.8% and 20% of the total confirmed cases in China and Italy, respectively.
 <xref rid="ppul24810-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>31</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppul24810-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>37</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppul24810-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>38</sup>
 </xref> With the ascertainment of asymptomatic carriage, the risk of transmission within the community is very high.
 <xref rid="ppul24810-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>39</sup>
 </xref> The most common symptoms include fever, cough, dyspnea, myalgia, or fatigue.
 <xref rid="ppul24810-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>30</sup>
 </xref> In a series of 41 cases, only a few patient had prominent upper respiratory tract signs even though abnormalities in chest computed tomography (CT) images were detected among all patients.
 <xref rid="ppul24810-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>30</sup>
 </xref> CT chest scans have a higher sensitivity for diagnosis of COVID‐19 as compared with PCR swab samples; and the findings include bilateral, subpleural, ground‐glass opacities with air bronchograms, ill‐defined margins, and a slight predominance in the right lower lobe.
 <xref rid="ppul24810-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>40</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppul24810-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>41</sup>
 </xref> Indeed, CT chest abnormalities are now diagnostic criteria in the latest “Novel coronavirus diagnosis and treatment plan” published by the National Health Commission of the People's Republic of China.
 <xref rid="ppul24810-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>42</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
