<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A few hundred years ago, dengue was primarily a sylvatic disease. The sylvatic cycle is ecologically and evolutionarily-distinct from the human transmission cycle, causing sporadic outbreaks in humans [
 <xref rid="B33-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. A sylvatic cycle that serves as an enzootic cycle involving canopy-dwelling 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> mosquitoes and lower primates for dengue transmission has been well-documented in the rainforests of western Africa and Southeast Asia, including Peninsular Malaysia and eastern Senegal [
 <xref rid="B6-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. 
 <italic>Aedes luteocephalus</italic>, 
 <italic>A. furcifer</italic>, and 
 <italic>A. taylori</italic> were the principal transmission vectors in Africa [
 <xref rid="B35-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], and the primatophilic canopy-dwelling mosquitoes of the 
 <italic>A. niveus s.l</italic>. complex—a group that includes 
 <italic>Aedes pseudoniveus</italic>, 
 <italic>Aedes subniveus</italic>, 
 <italic>Aedes vanus</italic>, 
 <italic>Aedes albolateralis</italic>, 
 <italic>Aedes niveoidesan</italic>, and 
 <italic>Aedes novoniveus</italic>—were the principal vectors in Asia (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="microorganisms-07-00296-f001">Figure 1</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B40-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. In other locations in tropical Africa and Asia, probable rates of sylvatic DENV transmission to humans are unknown, but appeared to be minimal [
 <xref rid="B41-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. In North America, several species of new-world non-human primates were found to be resistant to DENV infection, and no cases of sylvatic DENV transmission were recorded. Similarly, no evidence of enzootic circulation through lower primates have been found in Panama [
 <xref rid="B43-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. However, seroconversions among indigenous Ayoreo Indians living in an isolated forested region of Bolivia, where 
 <italic>A. aegypti</italic> is absent, recommend that sylvatic DENV transmission may happen in the region [
 <xref rid="B44-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Cross-species transmission of DENV in rural areas of Africa and Asia from non-human primates to humans tends to occur when great numbers of the enzootic vector(s) are present [
 <xref rid="B45-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. The sylvan environments in rural areas of Africa and Asia can be a source of an abundant amount of primary vector 
 <italic>A. albopictus</italic>, which is responsible for the transfer of the virus into human habitats [
 <xref rid="B46-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Endemic/epidemic cycles involved the human host, and viruses are transmitted mainly by 
 <italic>A. aegypti</italic>, 
 <italic>A. albopictus</italic>, and other mosquitos that serve as secondary vectors, such as 
 <italic>A. mediovittatus</italic>, 
 <italic>Aedes polynesiensis</italic> and other members of 
 <italic>Aedes scutellarin</italic> [
 <xref rid="B47-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>].
</p>
