<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F0002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 2.</label>
 <caption>
  <p>RA exerts its antiviral effects by directly targeting virus-host receptor interaction. (A) Centrifugal filtration assay. The data are expressed as the mean ± SD from three independent experiments and analysed by Student’s 
   <italic>t</italic>-tests (***
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). (B) Effect of RA on the binding of EV-A71 to SCARB2 and PSGL1. EV-A71 was pretreated with DMSO or RA (280 μM) at 4°C for 1 h and then incubated with protein G Mag Sepharose conjugated to extracellular fragments of PSGL1 (upper panels) and SCARB2 (lower panels). Lane 1 contains 0.2 µg virus samples as an input control. The results are representative of at least three independent experiments. (C) Attachment assay using L-PSGL1 cells and Jurkat cells. Viruses were incubated with DMSO or RA (280 μM) at 4°C for 1 h and then infected into cells at 4°C for another 1 h. The amount of the attached virus was estimated by real-time RT-PCR. The data are expressed as the mean ± SD from three independent experiments and analysed by Student's 
   <italic>t</italic>-test (***
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). (D) Effect of RA (28 or 280 μM) on binding of EV-A71 to heparan sulfate beads. The 2231/1998 virus was pre-treated with RA before binding to the heparan sulfate beads, and the precipitated viruses were evaluated through western blotting. The results are representative of at least three independent experiments. (E) Effect of the combination of RA and DBPR103 on anti-EV-A71. (Left) Chemical structure of DBPR103. (Right) The CI values for drug combination. CI &gt; 1, CI = 1, and CI &lt; 1 indicated antagonistic, additive, and synergistic effects, respectively.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <alternatives>
  <graphic specific-use="web-only" content-type="black-white" xlink:href="TEMI_A_1767512_F0002_OB" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  <graphic specific-use="print-only" content-type="black-white" xlink:href="TEMI_A_1767512_F0002_PB" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </alternatives>
</fig>
