<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Results of studies assessing local rates of malaria misdiagnosis are trickling out of SSA. In Nigeria, 83% of children under 5 years old received ACT even after testing negative for malaria 
 <italic>via</italic> microscopy [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Clinical and home-based presumptive treatment of malaria remains common and has probably masked actual malaria transmission reduction in some countries [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>], particularly in urban areas. Malaria over-diagnosis in SSA also suffers from high clinical workloads, variable health worker training and lab techniques, and low laboratory capacity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Because many fevers are still treated at home (using both modern and traditional medicines), clinical data greatly underestimates the enormity of AFI in SSA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. In hyper- and holoendemic regions, naturally acquired immunity provides protection against malaria, as infected adults routinely maintain a level of parasite prevalence that would otherwise kill a malaria-naïve visitor, but without experiencing overt disease themselves [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. This further complicates the proper diagnosis of AFI, as febrile patients presumed to have malaria may test positive on a highly-sensitive malaria rapid diagnostic test (RDT) due to a low parasite load that their immune system keeps in check, yet actually be suffering from another infection. We need to rethink the concept of misdiagnosis by systematically establishing the baseline epidemiology for all major sources of fever while also confronting the many non-biomedical perceptions of fever among local communities [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. The burden of communicable diseases in SSA remains heterogeneous and enigmatic [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>], and recent findings raise important questions about the interaction between demography, malaria control, and other neglected tropical diseases. We can look to Ghana as an important case study.
</p>
