<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The two ZIKV lineages, Asian and African, display differences in their associated pathology and, especially infections with the Asian lineage, may result in severe malformations and developmental defects [
 <xref rid="B43-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. However, after in utero inoculation of ZIKV in a fetal pig model, the trans-fetal ZIKV transmission and the viral loads in the placenta, as well as cerebrum and cerebellum of the fetuses, were higher for African than for Asian strains [
 <xref rid="B53-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. This emphasizes that further studies on the epidemiology and the heterogeneity of ZIKV strains are required [
 <xref rid="B53-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Genomic epidemiology contributes to our understanding of how changes within the viral genome could contribute to changes in viral pathology. One amino acid substitution within the precursor membrane protein of ZIKV was sufficient to result in more microcephaly in a mouse embryonic microcephaly model and in a higher rate of infectivity and cell death induction on mouse and human neural progenitor cells (NPCs) as compared to the parental virus [
 <xref rid="B54-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Furthermore, among ZIKV strains, differences in the capacity to induce an antiviral innate immune response and sensitivity to IFN were detected [
 <xref rid="B55-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. The innate immune evasion strategy, especially displayed by the emerging Brazilian strains, could contribute to viral pathogenesis during congenital infection [
 <xref rid="B55-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. In contrast to HCMV and ZIKV, RV displays only a low level of variation within its low-passaged clinical isolates. While differences in the adaptation of cellular metabolism and the requirement for glutamine were detected [
 <xref rid="B56-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>], a comparable level of innate immune activation was identified [
 <xref rid="B22-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Moreover, the number of circulating RV strains has decreased in the last decade. The most recent WHO RV nomenclature update in 2013 proposed one provisional (1a) and 12 recognized (1B–1J and 2A–2C) genotypes belonging to two clades (1 and 2), [
 <xref rid="B57-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. In 2018, strains belonging to only two genotypes (1E and 2B) were reported to the global Rubella Nucleotide Surveillance (RubeNS) database (
 <uri xlink:href="www.who-rubella.org/files/wer8832.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.who-rubella.org/files/wer8832.pdf</uri>), [
 <xref rid="B58-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. In many countries, genotype replacements were noted (e.g., [
 <xref rid="B59-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]) and lately involve, most often, genotype 2B as the new dominant genotype. While the reasons for the observed dominance are unknown, the question has been raised whether 2B strains have higher transmission ability [
 <xref rid="B62-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. This epidemiological change towards one dominating genotype, in addition to the presence of just one serotype for RV, can be considered advantageous for its use as an archetypic congenital virus model. Genetic variants present within RV genotypes are less likely to influence congenital pathogenicity. Thus, only the currently dominating genotype 2B appears to be sufficient for the assessment of RV on cell culture models for human embryonal development.
</p>
