<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Bioinformatics and data management proved to be a bottleneck in our pipeline and are a primary target for optimisation. The lab-on-an-SSD method (ARTIC network) simplified the installation of bioinformatic software and available pipelines, but as this is a developing resource, we did encounter issues that stalled analysis. This was largely due to limited experience and lack of access to a dedicated bioinformatician to troubleshoot problems. In general there is a critical need for bioinformatics training in LMICs, which has been recognised as a priority area for development, e.g. the 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://h3abionet.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Pan African Bioinformatics Network</ext-link> for the Human Heredity and Health in Africa consortium and NIH-funded Application of Genomics and Modelling to the Control of Virus Pathogens (GeMVi). Future work will focus on support for bioinformatic pipeline development, including optimising barcoding assignment and consensus building thresholds for RABV samples. This may involve the integration of Read Assignment, Mapping, and Phylogenetic Analysis in Real Time ( 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/artic-network/rampart" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">RAMPART</ext-link>), a promising new tool to assess genome coverage and reference matching for each barcode concurrently as sequencing proceeds. We sequenced completely offline to avoid problems with internet connection (normally necessary to initialise MinION sequencing) and limit reliance on data transfer to servers for data storage. Sequence data was stored locally on either internal or external hard drives, with subsequent transfer to university servers in the UK at a later date. However, data transfer was problematic with the large number of files produced (in one instance corrupting a hard drive) and using one laptop for all sequencing and subsequent analysis was slow. Identifying local or cloud-based data solutions is advised to ensure data backup and take advantage of high-performance computing resources when available, but will come at additional cost.
</p>
