<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The main limitation of an amplicon-based approach is the requirement for prior knowledge of the pathogen for targeted sequencing. This can be an issue if little is known about circulating RABV diversity in an area e.g. following an emergence event, an incursion of a new variant or where multiple divergent lineages co-circulate. We have found that primer design can accommodate a reasonable level of RABV diversity, but its application is still limited. Recent discoveries of novel lyssaviruses ( 
 <xref rid="ref-63" ref-type="bibr">Shipley 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2019
 </xref>), cross-species transmission events ( 
 <xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr">Kuzmin 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr">Mollentze 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014a
 </xref>) and the emergence of new variants ( 
 <xref rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr">Kotait 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2019
 </xref>) indicate that when an amplicon-based approach is insufficient, a less targeted method would be useful to monitor threats as dog-mediated rabies is eliminated. Metagenomic sequencing is considered the gold standard for viral pathogen sequencing, offering an unbiased, untargeted approach but suffers from sensitivity issues when working with low viral titres. Success with RABV metagenomic sequencing varies according to sample quality and viral titre, with often &lt;1% of reads mapping to a RABV reference sequence ( 
 <xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">Brunker 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015
 </xref>). Therefore, a high sequencing throughput per sample is required. The MinION is not considered a high-throughput platform but recent and ongoing improvements to flowcell chemistry and data output from the MinION (10–20Gb in 48hours) have advanced the feasibility of conducting whole genome viral metagenomic sequencing directly from clinical samples, even with low viral titre samples ( 
 <xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Kafetzopoulou 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018
 </xref>).
</p>
