<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0205">The registered vaccine in Argentina is composed of 4 vaccine strains, including C3 Indaial, as well as the vaccine authorized in USA and Canada for emergency situation 
 <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. Although there were no reports of serotype C in the world since 2004, the authorized vaccine in Argentina requires the inclusion of serotype C since 2006 
 <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. Regarding potency, the vaccines manufactured in Argentina are formulated to meet a minimum of 75% of EPP (or minimum of 3 PD50). However, most of the batches released to the market showed &gt;85% of EPP in the potency test in cattle conducted by SENASA 
 <xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. Additionally, a commercial vaccine similar to the one used in our study has shown early immunity in cattle 
 <xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. Unlike previous studies in cattle in which high-potency vaccines were used 
 <xref rid="b0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, this study used a polyvalent vaccine that is regularly administered in systematic vaccination campaigns in Argentina. This has the added advantage that in case of an epidemic outbreak is faced, the vaccine would be rapidly available in large quantities. In this sense, rolling stocks of ready-to-use polyvalent vaccines have been considered as a feasible vaccine reserve to respond rapidly to outbreaks 
 <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. Mostly, FMD free countries have Antigen Banks through contracts with vaccine manufacturing companies. In the case of disseminated outbreaks in high density areas, the number of doses from Antigen Banks may be insufficient, and therefore the use of ready-to-use vaccines from countries that apply such vaccines in their vaccination programs has been proposed 
 <xref rid="b0145" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. In agreement with the results presented in this controlled study, field evidence on the effects of vaccination reducing within herd transmission was reported by Brito et al. 
 <xref rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref> in which the protective effect of the vaccine was evidenced by the association between vaccination and low rate of within herd transmission.
</p>
