<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="ppat.1008611.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1008611.g005</object-id>
 <label>Fig 5</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Facilitation of MAVS degradation by H7N9 PB1-F2 in immune-stimulated cells.</title>
  <p>(
   <bold>A and B</bold>) Impact of H7N9 PB1-F2 on MAVS protein level. THP-1 cells were infected with H7-2 WT and H7-2ΔF viruses at MOI = 1. At 6, 12, and 24 hpi, infected cells were harvested for total protein extraction, SDS-PAGE and Western blot analysis with anti-MAVS and anti-H7N9 PB1-F2 (A). PA and GAPDH served as normalization controls for viral infection and loading. Harvested cells were also subjected to RT-qPCR analysis of MAVS mRNA level relative to that of GAPDH mRNA using comparative Ct method (B). (
   <bold>C and D</bold>) Impact of WSN PB1-F2 on MAVS protein level. THP-1 cells were infected with WSN WT and WSN ΔF viruses at MOI = 1. MAVS protein and mRNA were analyzed as above. (
   <bold>E</bold>) HEK293T cells in 6-well plates were co-transfected with 1 μg pEF-Bos-Flag-MAVS and 0.2 μg PB1-F2 expression constructs. After 24 hours, 100 μg/mL cycloheximide (CHX) was added. Cells were harvested for total protein extraction at 0, 6, 12 and 24 hours after drug treatment for SDS-PAGE followed by Western blot analysis with anti-Flag. Relative band intensity of MAVS over GAPDH was plotted in the lower panel. (
   <bold>F</bold>) HEK293T cells were transfected with 0.5 μg pEF-Bos-Flag-MAVS together with increasing dosage of expression construct for PB1-F2-Flag of WSN and H7N9 (0, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 1.5 and 2 μg). After 48 hours, cells were harvested for total protein extraction followed by SDS-PAGE and Western blot analysis with anti-Flag for detection of both MAVS (70 kDa) and PB1-F2 (15–20 kDa) normalized to GAPDH. (
   <bold>G and H</bold>) HEK293T cells in 6-well plates were transfected with 1.5 μg PB1-F2 expression constructs. After 24 hours, cells were either mock-transfected or transfected with 1 μg/mL poly (I:C) for 18 hours before harvested for total protein extraction followed by SDS-PAGE and Western blot analysis with anti-MAVS and anti-Flag (G) or for RT-qPCR analysis of MAVS mRNA (H). (
   <bold>I and J</bold>) HEK293T cells in 6-well plates were transfected with 1.5 μg PB1-F2 expression constructs. After 24 hours, cells were either mock-infected or infected with Sendai virus (100 hemagglutinating units/ml) for 18 hours before harvested for total protein extraction followed by SDS-PAGE and Western blot analysis with anti-MAVS and anti-Flag (I) or for RT-qPCR analysis of MAVS mRNA relative to HPRT mRNA by comparative Ct method (J). Bars represent means ± SD of triplicate experiments.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1008611.g005" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
