<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our results underscore the need to resolve substantial uncertainties about within-host DENV dynamics, in particular with respect to viremia and infectiousness of asymptomatic, pre-symptomatic, and post-2° infections. An improved understanding of differences in viremia profiles between 1° and 2° infections, and the mechanisms underlying those processes requires more detailed immunological and viremia titer data, including quantifications of infectious particles, particularly from earlier stages of the infection [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006965.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1006965.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Similarly, a greater understanding of the factors underlying differences in viral trajectories [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006965.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1006965.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1006965.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], infectiousness [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006965.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1006965.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], and disease rates [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006965.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] between serotypes is needed to gain better, more context-specific estimates of the contributions of silent transmission to DENV transmission. Further, uncertainty about the net infectiousness of post-2° infections limits understanding of dengue dynamics overall [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006965.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] and the contribution of silent transmission in particular. Acquiring this kind of empirical data is complicated by the difficulty of identifying people in these classes when they are viremic and the absence of diagnostic tools that reliably distinguish 2° from post-2° infections [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006965.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Moreover, people with symptomatic infections may experience impaired mobility [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006965.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] or otherwise modified interactions with mosquitoes, the impacts of which on net transmission are presently not well understood. Resolving these uncertainties and identifying effective strategies for mitigating the contributions of all infections, apparent or not, to DENV transmission will require comprehensive studies that combine field work and modeling to address the coupled nature of multiple transmission heterogeneities [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006965.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] (see 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1006965.s001">S1 Text</xref> for a comprehensive discussion of additional limitations and research needs).
</p>
