<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">Understanding the genetic processes associated with species introduction and establishment in new environments is fundamental to infer the evolutionary mechanisms underlying the dynamics and history of invasive processes. But, when an invasive species is a threat to human health, such as a disease vector, knowledge of population dynamics and demography is useful to interpret the causes and predict the risks of disease outbreaks. 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> (Skuse 1894), the Asian tiger mosquito, is an emblematic example of an arbovirus vector that has rapidly and successfully invaded much of the globe supported by its life history traits and high propagule pressure driven by human activities. This mosquito took four decades to invade the world, while its counterpart 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> did so in four centuries
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>
 </sup>. From its home range in tropical Southeast Asia, where it was originally a zoophilic forest species
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>
 </sup>, 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> spread first to the islands in the Indian and Pacific Oceans
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>
 </sup> and, during the 1980s, rapidly extended its range across temperate regions in Europe, the Americas and Africa
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup>. This mosquito is able to tolerate climate/environment interactions that differ from its home range
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup>. Its ability to diapause during unfavourable seasons and to lay desiccation-resistant eggs has facilitated its expansion in temperate regions
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup>. It is listed among the top hundred most dangerous invasive species identified
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup>. Its spread has created public health concerns as experimental infections have shown the species’ competence for at least 20 arboviruses and it is considered the main vector for chikungunya (CHIKV), and to a lesser degree for dengue (DENV) and Zika (ZIKV) viruses
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>. Anthropogenic activities, by creating new breeding and trophic niches of adaptation close to human habitations
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup>, strengthened the association of 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> with humans, with important public health implications. Indeed, beyond its original range, it has been increasingly involved in local autochthonous transmission of chikungunya in many places where it has become established, including La Réunion, continental Europe, Africa, the Americas and Japan, determining major CHIKV epidemics of severe, persistent, debilitating arthralgia
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>
 </sup>. Chikungunya virus (CHIKV, genus Alphavirus in the family Togaviridae), first discovered in 1952 in Tanzania
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup> and generally transmitted by 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> mosquitoes, comprises three genetic lineages: Asian, West African and East/Central/South African (ECSA) which apparently evolved independently in different geographic areas
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>
 </sup>. The fact that 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> is becoming the major vector of CHIKV is due to a series of adaptive mutations in the CHIKV ECSA lineage, the most known being an alanine to valine substitution at position 226 of the E1 glycoprotein (ECSA E1-A226V). This adaptive mutation, established in the Indian Ocean region in 2004–2005, dramatically increased the vector competence of 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> for CHIKV, with respect to the previously more typical vector, 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic>. In association with the high invasive potential of 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>, the ECSA E1-226V variant rapidly spread even in temperate areas such as Europe, causing CHIKV outbreaks.
</p>
