<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <title>Abstract</title>
 <sec id="s0100">
  <title>Background</title>
  <p>The World Health Organization (WHO) estimates 127 million new cases of 
   <italic>Chlamydia trachomatis</italic> (CT), 87 million new cases of 
   <italic>Neisseria gonorrhea</italic> (NG), and 156 million new cases of 
   <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> (TV) each year, which corresponds to 355 (219–606), 303 (216–468), and 243 (97.6–425) thousand disability-adjusted life-years. In low-resource settings, however, sexually transmitted infections (STIs) are treated syndromically and many individuals with asymptomatic infection may be missed, especially adolescents and young adults with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s0101">
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>We enrolled patients aged 15–24 with HIV (N = 300) attending a family-centered HIV clinic in Mbabane, Eswatini. Participants completed a sexual history questionnaire and provided urine as well as oropharyngeal and/or vaginal swabs, if sexually active, for testing with Xpert CT/NG and TV tests. Analysis included bivariate and multivariate odds ratios and test sensitivity and specificity.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s0102">
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>Sexually transmitted infection rates were highest (25.0%; 95% confidence interval [CI], 15.2–37.3) in females ages 20–24 who were ever sexually active. In patients with confirmed STIs, NG (15 of 32, 47%) was more common than CT (9 of 32, 28%) and TV (8 of 32, 25%). Syndromic screening alone had a sensitivity of 32.0% (95% CI, 14.9–53.3) and specificity of 86.0% (95% CI, 79.0–91.4) but varied by gender. The presence of an STI was associated with reporting new sexual partner(s) (OR = 2.6; 95% CI, 1.1–6.4), sometimes to never using condoms (OR = 4.2; 95% CI, 1.7–10.2), most recent sexual partner &gt;25 years old (OR = 3.2; 95% CI, 1.3–7.9), and HIV diagnosis at age ≥15 years (OR = 3.4; 95% CI, 1.4–8.2).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s0103">
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p>Syndromic screening alone performed poorly. Routine diagnostic testing significantly increases STI detection and should be considered in high-risk populations, such as adolescents and young adults with HIV.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
