<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="abs0010">
 <sec>
  <title>Objectives</title>
  <p>Virus infection is underevaluated in older adults with severe acute respiratory infections (SARIs). We aimed to evaluate the clinical impact of combining point-of-care molecular viral test and serum procalcitonin (PCT) level for antibiotic stewardship in the emergency department (ED).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Design</title>
  <p>A prospective twin-center cohort study was conducted between January 2017 and March 2018.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Setting and Participants</title>
  <p>Older adult patients who presented to the ED with SARIs received a rapid molecular test for 17 respiratory viruses and a PCT test.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Measures</title>
  <p>To evaluate the clinical impact, we compared the outcomes of SARI patients between the experimental cohort and a propensity score–matched historical cohort. The primary outcome was the proportion of antibiotics discontinuation or de-escalation in the ED. The secondary outcomes included duration of intravenous antibiotics, length of hospital stay, and mortality.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>A total of 676 patients were included, of which 169 patients were in the experimental group and 507 patients were in the control group. More than one-fourth (27.9%) of the patients in the experimental group tested positive for virus. Compared with controls, the experimental group had a significantly higher proportion of antibiotics discontinuation or de-escalation in the ED (26.0% vs 16.1%, 
   <italic>P</italic> = .007), neuraminidase inhibitor uses (8.9% vs 0.6%, 
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001), and shorter duration of intravenous antibiotics (10.0 vs 14.5 days, 
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusions and Implications</title>
  <p>Combining rapid viral surveillance and PCT test is a useful strategy for early detection of potential viral epidemics and antibiotic stewardship. Clustered viral respiratory infections in a nursing home is common. Patients transferred from nursing homes to ED may benefit from this approach.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
