<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>
  <bold>
   <italic>Introduction:</italic>
  </bold> Two species of 
  <italic>Aedes (Ae.)</italic> mosquitoes (
  <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> and 
  <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>) are primary vectors for emerging arboviruses that are a significant threat to public health and economic burden worldwide. Distribution of these vectors and the associated arboviruses, such as dengue virus, chikungunya virus, yellow fever virus, and Zika virus, was for a long time restricted by geographical, ecological, and biological factors. Presently, arbovirus emergence and dispersion are more rapid and geographically widespread, largely due to expansion of the range for these two mosquitoes that have exploited the global transportation network, land perturbation, and failure to contain the mosquito population coupled with enhanced vector competence. 
  <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> and 
  <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> may also sustain transmission between humans without having to depend on their natural reservoir forest cycles due to arthropod adaptation to urbanization. Currently, there is no single strategy that is adequate to control these vectors, especially when managing arbovirus outbreaks.
 </p>
 <p>
  <bold>
   <italic>Objective:</italic>
  </bold> This review aimed at presenting the characteristics and abilities of 
  <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> and 
  <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>, which can drive a global public health risk, and suggests strategies for prevention and control.
 </p>
 <p>
  <bold>
   <italic>Methods:</italic>
  </bold> This review presents the geographic range, reproduction and ecology, vector competence, genetic evolution, and biological and chemical control of these two mosquito species and how they have changed and developed over time combined with factors that may drive pandemics and mitigation measures.
 </p>
 <p>
  <bold>
   <italic>Conclusion:</italic>
  </bold> We suggest that more efforts should be geared toward the development of a concerted multidisciplinary approach.
 </p>
</abstract>
