<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Previous studies using conventional HIS mice have demonstrated the importance of the myeloid compartment in HIS mice for accurately investigating anti-LAV immunity. More recently, we reported NRGF-HIS mice (see Section ‘Cytokine Environment and Niche Space’ for model description) and NRGF-HIS mice expressing transgenic HLA-A*0201 (NFA2-HIS) as a new HIS mouse model for investigating YFV-17D-induced immunity [
 <xref rid="B17-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. In this model, the adenovirus-mediated expressing of hFLT3L promotes the selective expansion of human dendritic cells, myeloid cells and granulocytes, unlike in conventional NRG, NSG or BRG mice, where hFLT3L expression/injection leads to the expansion of both the human and murine myeloid compartment. Although this might not be an issue for all LAVs, the mouse interferon response has been shown to strongly restrict YFV-17D infection in mouse models of infection [
 <xref rid="B148-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>,
 <xref rid="B328-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">328</xref>,
 <xref rid="B329-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">329</xref>], in contrast to humans, where YFV-17D can overcome such a response. Therefore, hFLT3L-mediated expansion of the myeloid compartment in conventional HIS mouse strains can lead to important immune interference between the mouse and human hematopoietic compartment. Unlike conventional NRG-HIS mice (in which the human myeloid compartment is not expanded), we found that NFA2-HIS mice can mount a peripheral transcriptomic response upon YFV-17D that shared key similarities with the response observed in human vaccinees [
 <xref rid="B17-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. NFA2-HIS mice were consistently able to mount a YFV-17D-specific CD8+ T cell response as well as an YFV-17D-IgG response, which led to the clearance of viral RNA in the peripheral blood, unlike in conventional NRG-HIS mice where infection persist over time in periphery. This work demonstrates the strong potential of second-generation HIS mice and emerging models to uncover fundamental immunological processes regulating adaptive immune priming in vivo and in a human context, and therefore sheds light on the elusive mechanisms governing LAV-induced protective immunity.
</p>
