<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>SIVcpz–HIV-1 group M and SIVgor–HIV-1 group O divergence dates were estimated using a Bayesian relaxed clock analysis implemented in BEAST 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Drummond1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. For SIVcpz–HIV-1 group M, we analyzed the partial 
 <italic>pol</italic> gene sequences (nucleotide 3887 to 4775 according to the HXB2 numbering) recently obtained from chimpanzees 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Keele1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, three additional SIVcpz lineages (X52154, AY169968 and AF382828), and HIV-1 group M sequences previously analyzed by Lemey et al. (2005) 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lemey3" ref-type="bibr">[136]</xref>. For SIVgor–HIV-1 group O, we analyzed partial 
 <italic>pol</italic> gene sequences (nucleotide 4230 to 4775 according to the HXB2 numbering) from three SIVgor 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-VanHeuverswyn1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, two SIVcpz (U42720 and X52154), and HIV-1 group O sequences previously analyzed by Lemey et al. (2004) 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lemey2" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. We applied a general time reversible model with gamma-distributed rate variation among sites combined with an uncorrelated lognormal relaxed clock model and a piecewise constant population size model 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Drummond1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. These conserved gene regions in the HIV genome are less subject to substitution saturation, but contain poor temporal signal 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lemey2" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. Therefore, we used a normal prior distribution on the TMRCA for both HIV-1 group M (1931±8 years) and HIV-1 group O (1915±17 years), based on published dates and their uncertainty 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Korber1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lemey2" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, to calibrate the molecular clock. Posterior distributions were obtained using Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) analysys and MCMC runs were investigated using Tracer (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/tracer/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/tracer/</ext-link> ).
</p>
