<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The ZIKV infections was first reported in Bangladesh at 2013 by a seroprevalence study and ZIKV neutralizing antibodies were detected onward from 2013 [
 <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. In 2014, another ZIKV infection was reported in Chittagong district of Bangladesh, and has been confirmed by RT-PCR in serum samples followed by partial
 <italic> E</italic> gene sequencing and phylogenetic tree analysis [
 <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The only clinical signs of the patient were fever for 5 days and maculopapular rash on body having no overseas travel history within last 2 weeks of symptoms appeared. However, this Bangladeshi ZIKV was closely related with Brazilian and South American strains [
 <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. As far we know, until that there is no other report of ZIKV infectious in Bangladesh, Does it mean really there is no ZIKV infection in Bangladesh? ZIKV has been circulating among almost all the neighboring countries of Bangladesh, namely, India, Myanmar, Malaysia, Nepal, and Singapore [
 <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>–
 <xref rid="ref66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Bangladeshi people living in Singapore have been also affected by ZIKV [
 <xref rid="ref67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Peoples are also frequently visiting these neighboring countries, enabling easy entry of the ZIKV to Bangladesh. Moreover, many Burmese (Rohingya) recently entered Bangladesh could also be the potential source for ZIKV in Bangladesh as local transmission reported by the travelers [
 <xref rid="ref68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Bangladesh is a densely populated country with rapid urbanization which might be also a risk factor for ZIKV [
 <xref rid="ref69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>–
 <xref rid="ref71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Very recently, the endemic Chikungunya virus infection occurred throughout the countries followed by massive Dengue infection. Currently, there is no effective surveillance on ZIKV infections in Bangladesh. Either Zika is circulating and remained to be undiagnosed or it might be next endemic infection in Bangladesh next to the Chikungunya and Dengue virus infections [
 <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>].
</p>
