<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">Coronaviruses (CoV) are single-stranded RNA viruses, so named after the crown-like appearance given by glycoprotein spikes around the viral envelope, which can be observed by electron microscope. Coronaviridae family includes several genera (from 
 <italic>α</italic> to 
 <italic>δ</italic>) that are capable to affect human and other vertebrates: the α-CoV and β-CoV can affect human and various mammals by infecting respiratory, gastrointestinal, and central nervous system, while γ-CoV and δ-CoV mainly affect birds [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Since the outbreak of severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS)-CoV in the south of China in 2002, coronaviruses have been recognized as the cause of several epidemics throughout the world. Recently, a new viral strain appeared in the middle of the same country, in Wuhan [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], starting a pandemic that is currently involving over two million people around the world, more than 100,000 deaths and whose numbers are still increasing each day [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Italy is one of the most severely involved countries with up to 160,000 assessed cases and more than 20,000 deaths [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. This new viral strain belongs to the β-CoV genus and has been named SARS-CoV-2. According to the current knowledge, the clinical manifestations of SARS-CoV-2 are commonly characterized by fever, cough, nasal congestion, asthenia, anosmia, ageusia and dyspnea. The infection may further evolve with the onset of systemic symptoms characterized by cardiovascular coagulation and liver impairment and an atypical pneumonia, that might require hospitalization [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. The relatively high frequency of these life-threatening complications, together with the high transmissibility and swift global diffusion, forced serious responses from world authorities leading to severe restrictions in the attempt to control the pandemic of the coronavirus disease (COVID-19) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. With the aim to contain the disease, researchers activated globally to clarify viral transmission routes and to validate diagnostic tests to quickly identify infected subjects. There is evidence of the SARS-CoV-2 RNA presence in various biological matrices such as stool samples, blood and urine: in stool in particular there seems to be a relatively high detection rate, with longer clearance time than nasopharyngeal swabs from respiratory secretions; blood and urine, instead, seem to have a very low frequency of viral RNA detection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Nonetheless, this suggests that infection routes other than respiratory droplets are theoretically possible. The presence of SARS-CoV-2 in seminal fluid could have sexual and reproductive implications [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] and reflect in COVID-19 infection and transmission, but this matter has been under-investigated so far. Sperm cryopreservation is routinely used to preserve male fertility and to manage couple infertility in several clinical settings [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Cytotoxic agents used in cancer or some surgical intervention can impair spermatogenesis and alter ejaculation. In addition, surgical sperm extraction in azoospermic patients represents another specific indication for sperm freezing [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. While conventional or microsurgical sperm extraction in patients with obstructive or non-obstructive azoospermia can be easily delayed because of the pandemic, semen cryopreservation cannot be delayed in cancer patients who need to start chemotherapy. In the latter situation, sperm cryobanks represent the only chance of patient’s fertility preservation.
</p>
