<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para2030">Similar to Pakistan, HAV and HEV are common causes of mortality due to acute hepatitis in Bangladesh. Hepatitis A and E accounted for 2·8% and 31·1% of all deaths due to acute hepatitis in Bangladesh in 2015 (
 <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>).
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref> Historically, hepatitis A infection was thought to be hyperendemic in Bangladesh; a study from 2000 showed that 100% of children up to 6 years of age had been exposed and were immune to HAV.
 <xref rid="bib149" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>149</sup>
 </xref> A 2009 seroepidemiological study showed a clear trend in anti-HAV seroconversion with age, where seropositivity progressively increased from 40·4% in children aged 1–5 years to more than 98·0% in adults older than 30 years, and very low anti-HAV seroprevalence of about 30% in children younger than 10 years in high-income settings.
 <xref rid="bib150" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>150</sup>
 </xref> The prevalence of anti-HAV in people aged 20–40 years in Bangladesh has declined rapidly during the past three decades because of a general increase in socioeconomic status and hygiene standards.
 <xref rid="bib151" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>151</sup>
 </xref> As a result, this age group has a high risk for HAV infection, and clinically overt hepatitis A is increasing in adolescents and adults.
 <xref rid="bib152" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>152</sup>
 </xref> Although the endemicity of HAV seems to be decreasing, adolescents and adults with high socioeconomic status remain at particularly high risk of symptomatic and severe illness, because individuals of high socioeconomic status have a low chance of HAV infection as children.
 <xref rid="bib152" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>152</sup>
 </xref> The clinical manifestations of hepatitis A depend on the age of the host: less than 30% of infected young children showed symptomatic hepatitis, whereas about 80% of infected adults had symptoms of severe acute hepatitis.
 <xref rid="bib151" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>151</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
