<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>West Nile virus (WNV) belongs to the flavivirus genus in the family of Flaviviridae with other globally important viral pathogens. Flaviviruses enter host cells through clathrin-mediated endocytosis, which requires help from a variety of host factors, and release their genome from the endosome into the cytoplasm after acidification-induced membrane fusion [
 <xref rid="B1-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. WNV has an approximately 11 kb long, single-stranded, positive sensed RNA genome, which encodes a single open reading frame with terminal 5′ and 3′ UTRs that have a 5′ cap and no poly-A tail, respectively. Using the host cellular machinery, the viral RNA genome trafficks through the cytosol to the endoplasmic reticulum (ER), where the viral RNA is translated as a polyprotein that is then cleaved into ten functional proteins by both cellular and viral proteases. There are three structural proteins (capsid [C], pre-membrane [PrM/M], and envelope [E]), and seven non-structural proteins (NS1, NS2A, NS2B, NS3, NS4A, NS4B, and NS5) [
 <xref rid="B4-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. However, studies suggest that additional proteins may also be produced through ribosomal frameshifting [
 <xref rid="B6-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. While non-structural proteins play essential roles in the replication of viral genomic RNA, the structural proteins assemble the virion and mediate host receptor binding and viral entry. With the help of viral and cellular proteins, the positive-sense viral genomic RNA is transcribed into negative-sense RNA serving as a template for the replication of progeny viral genome RNA. The structural proteins assemble the nucleocapsid on membranes in the ER, and bud into the cytoplasm via the Golgi network. The progeny virus travels to the cell surface in an exocytic vesicle and matures as cellular enzymes cleave the prM, resulting in the release of mature virion [
 <xref rid="B8-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].
</p>
