<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0001">At the end of 2019, several patients were diagnosed with pneumonia of unknown cause, epidemiologically associated with the same seafood market. Alongside the Spring Festival exodus, an outbreak seemed unavoidable. This condition attracted the attention of the Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), who immediately launched an emergency response. The World Health Organization (WHO) also responded promptly and declared the outbreak a public health emergency of international concern (PHEIC). The causative agent of the unidentified pneumonia has been confirmed as a novel coronavirus by sequencing and aetiological investigations by several independent laboratories in China. Following the isolation of the new coronavirus, it was found to be distinct both from Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV) and severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV) 
 <xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr">[1</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr">2]</xref>. Coronaviruses are single-stranded RNA viruses belonging to the family Coronaviridae that can cause various diseases with enteric, respiratory, hepatic and neurological symptoms 
 <xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. The new coronavirus, originally denoted 2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) and officially renamed severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) by the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses, and the disease it causes, namely coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), has quickly become of tremendous concern worldwide. There have been significant outbreaks in many regions of China as well as global expansion including to Asia, Europe, North America, South America, Africa and Oceania. The disease is potentially zoonotic, with an estimated mortality rate of 2–5%. Person-to-person transmission may occur through contact and respiratory transmission or possibly by the faecal–oral route. Currently, the number of confirmed infections has been increasing daily but there is no definite treatment for COVID-19 pneumonia, although some potential drugs are under investigation. For the last two decades, outbreaks of coronaviruses and intermittent worldwide public health emergences remind us that coronaviruses are still a severe global health threat that cannot be ignored. According to the latest research, useful information for control of the disease is urgently required and is highly essential.
</p>
