<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>WT or MARCO
 <sup>-/-</sup> C57BL/6 mice were treated i.v. with 100 μl/10 g body weight of PLL or CLL 42 hr prior to i.v. inoculation with 2.5 × 10
 <sup>9</sup> genomes of CHIKV AF15561 diluted in 100 μl of diluent. At 45 min post-inoculation, mice were sacrificed, perfused with 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA), and liver lobes were collected and fixed in 4% PFA for 24 hr. Tissues were paraffin-embedded and sectioned. RNA in situ hybridization was performed using the RNAscope 2.5 HD Assay-Brown (Advanced Cell Diagnostics (ACD) Cat. No. 322300) according to the manufacturer’s protocol. In brief, paraffin-embedded tissue sections were incubated at 60
 <bold>°</bold>C for 1 hr followed by deparaffinization. Endogenous peroxidase activity was quenched by pretreatment with hydrogen peroxide for 10 min at room temperature (RT), and slides were boiled in RNAscope Target Retrieval Solution for 15 min. Slides were then treated with Protease III at 40
 <bold>°</bold>C for 30 min in the ACD Ez II Hybridization Oven (ACD Cat. No. 321710), followed by hybridization of V-CHIKV-sp-01 probe (ACD Cat. No. 481891) for 2 hr at 40
 <bold>°</bold>C in the EZ II Oven. Following hybridization of AMP1-6, signal was detected using DAB substrate and tissues were counterstained with Gill’s hematoxylin and visualized using standard bright-field microscopy. On sections from the same liver lobes, immunohistochemistry was used to visualize F4/80 positive cells. Tissues were deparaffinized and target retrieval was performed by incubating slides in Citrate pH 6.1 Target Retrieval Solution (Dako Cat. No. S1699) in a Biocare Medical decloaking chamber at 110
 <bold>°</bold>C for 20 min. Tissues were then incubated with Dual Endogenous Enzyme Block (Dako Cat. No. S2000389) for 10 min at RT, followed by incubation with Protein Block (Dako Cat. No. X090930) for 10 min at RT. F4/80 antibody clone Cl:A3-1 (BioRad Cat. No. MCA497) was diluted 1:100 and added to tissues and incubated for 1 hr at RT, followed by biotinylated Anti-Rat IgG (Vector Laboratories BA-9401) for 30 min at RT. Tissues were then incubated with VECTASTAIN Elite ABS reagent (Vector Laboratories, PK-6100) at RT for 30 min, signal was detected using DAB substrate, and tissues were counterstained with Gill’s hematoxylin and imaged. To quantify F4/80 positive cells in WT and MARCO
 <sup>-/-</sup> livers, positively-stained cells in 10 randomly selected high power fields per section were counted in a blinded manner and used to calculate the average number of F4/80 positive cells per field.
</p>
