<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="czx132-T7" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Box 2.</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Details of the theoretical frameworks applied</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
     <hr/>
     <bold>Theoretical frameworks drawn upon to measure the extent of transfer and consider factors contributing to observations in country case studies</bold>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>Dolowitz and Marsh</bold> (
     <xref rid="czx132-B3" ref-type="bibr">
      <bold>1996</bold>
     </xref>) 
     <bold>framework</bold>
    </td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>Global health advocacy and policy project framework</bold>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comprised of six questions (A–F) to help examine all aspects of the policy transfer process</td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Three categories comprised of 10 factors that variously could influence effectiveness of global health networks in attracting attention, resources, and influencing policy outcomes.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Applied to enable examination of policy transfer process in both settings and thus compare differences between settings</td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Applied to gain insight into which factors facilitate transfer and explain observed differences between settings</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
     <hr/>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="alpha-upper">
      <list-item>
       <p>A. What is transferred and how is transfer demonstrated?</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>B. What are the degrees of transfer?</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>C. What restricts or facilitates transfer?</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>D. From where are lessons drawn?</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>E. Who are key actors involved in the transfer process?</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>F. Why do actors engage in transfer?</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="order">
      <list-item>
       <p>Network and actor features: factors internal to the network (1) leadership, (2) governance, (3) composition, (4) framing strategies utilized</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Policy environment: factors external to the network (5) allies and opponents, (6) funding availability, (7) norms.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Issue characteristics: features of the problem the network seeks to address (8) severity, (9) tractability, (10) affected groups.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
