<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="czx132-T5" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Table 5.</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Alignment of national HIV programme activities with recommendations by UNAIDS in 90–90–90 strategy document</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th rowspan="2" colspan="1">UNAIDS 90–90–90 Strategy: policy content for each target</th>
    <th colspan="2" rowspan="1">National-level adoption of 90–90–90: policy and programme activities planned and actual
     <hr/>
    </th>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ghana</th>
    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uganda</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="3" rowspan="1">
     <bold>First 90: 90% of PLHIV to know their status</bold>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>More frequent testing/increase demand for testing.</bold>
    </td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Nationwide ‘Know Your HIV Status’ campaign with special focus on high yield geographic locations and population groups.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>HIV-related stigma and discrimination reduction campaign.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Provide HIV testing services at multiple service delivery points—health facilities including clinics, community and outreach services delivery points, special events etc.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Expand cadre of service providers for outreach testing services.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Nationwide testing campaigns. Numerous campaigns for adolescents: peer-to-peer engagement, social media campaigns.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>Strategic, focused testing to key population groups and/or geographies.</bold>
    </td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Increase testing in four regions with antenatal clinic prevalence &gt;2%.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Improve targeted testing of key populations starting with the four priority regions (Ashanti, Eastern, Greater Accra and Western) and Brong Ahafo (facility-based and outreach).</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Pregnant women and TB patients</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Outreach testing in the general population will not be done because of low yield but will continue for key populations.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Discontinue low-yield HIV testing service activities and concentrate on high-yield activities.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>27 PEPFAR focus testing districts with regular monitoring to assess yield. High yield areas, e.g. fishing communities where HIV prevalence ranges between 14.9% and 35% around the shores of Lake Victoria, other lake systems throughout the country, and on the border with the Democratic Republic of the Congo.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Deliver HIV testing services in male dominated work settings and areas where male access to services is poor.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Test and start will minimize number of repeat tests required.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>Make available a broader number of HIV testing and counselling approaches, e.g. self-testing, provider initiated counselling and testing and community-based approaches.</bold>
    </td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Reactivate provider-initiated testing services (PITC) to include testing of children on admission, emergency room testing, increased testing in DOTS corners, blood donor testing and diagnostic testing to include all Hepatitis B and C positive clients.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Not doing nationwide PITC
        <sup>a</sup>
       </p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>To improve access and efficiency of HIV testing services a mix of health facility and community-based approaches to be utilized.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Differentiated models of HIV testing services have been developed: 
        <list list-type="bullet">
         <list-item>
          <p>Facility based approaches: routine PITC that is ‘opt out’ and client initiated testing and counselling.</p>
         </list-item>
         <list-item>
          <p>Community based approaches: Index client testing—HBCT or snowball, outreach HIV testing services in hotspots and workplaces.</p>
         </list-item>
         <list-item>
          <p>Pilot studies for HIV self-test are underway and pending attainment of supporting evidence, guidelines on roll out will be developed by MOH.</p>
         </list-item>
         <list-item>
          <p>Increase partner notification strategies.</p>
         </list-item>
        </list>
       </p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="3" rowspan="1">
     <bold>Second 90: 90% of those diagnosed to be on treatment</bold>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>Recommend antiretroviral therapy to all people with diagnosed HIV infection, without the requirement of a prior CD4 test.</bold>
    </td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Yes, but in a more staggered way as nationwide scale up of test and treat too expensive.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>‘Test and treat’ rolled out in four regions 1 October 2016: 
        <list list-type="bullet">
         <list-item>
          <p>Fast track enrolment of clients including key populations receiving clinical care</p>
         </list-item>
         <list-item>
          <p>Intensify current enrolment of HIV positive pregnant women, children, TB clients, hepatitis B and C clients, key populations and serodiscordant clients.</p>
         </list-item>
         <list-item>
          <p>Scale-up ART in TB DOTS sites and PMTCT sites</p>
         </list-item>
        </list>
       </p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>From January 2017 implement ‘test and treat’ to remaining 6 other regions.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>The Government of Uganda provided commitment to begin ‘test and treat’ in October 2016 pending reforms of the supply chain – to be conducted by PEPFAR and the MOH.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>‘Test and treat’ was rolled out January 2017.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>Use of preferred, optimized regimens.</bold>
    </td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Preferred first line regimens: tenofovir+emtricitabine or tenofovir+lamivudine+an NNRTI such as efavirenz.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Recommended first line regimen in accordance with WHO recommendations: tenofovir+lamivudine+efavirenz. All HIV-infected adults and adolescents aged 10 years and above should be initiated on tenofovir + lamivudine and efavirenz as a once-daily fixed dose combination.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>Make HIV treatment and care, including diagnostic tests and other treatment-related items, free to the individual.</bold>
    </td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Not discussed in interviews or identified in documents reviewed.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Not discussed in interviews and not identified in documents, but HIV testing and treatment is thought to be free to the individual in Uganda.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>Address implementation issues that have often slowed scale-up, e.g. frequent drug stock outs, barriers to procurement of optimally affordable medicines and diagnostics, and inadequate availability of second- and third-line regimens.</bold>
    </td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Reviews being undertaken. Consideration given to how to manage stock outs and high demand for treatment.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>In the event of deep and prolonged periods of ART stock outs, priority will be given to PLHIV with CD4 of less than 500.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Reviews being undertaken to streamline pipeline.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Differentiated service delivery being implemented.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Guidelines for reallocation of commodities between facilities and improvements in communication developed.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="3" rowspan="1">
     <bold>Third 90: 90% of those on treatment to achieve viral suppression</bold>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>Sustained use of HIV treatment and ongoing virologic monitoring to verify treatment success and to intervene to support treatment adherence and re-engage those who fall out of care.</bold>
    </td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Ghana's focus for the first half of the 90–90–90 time period is to focus on the first two 90s and then gradually draw focus on scale up of viral load. More efforts instead on adherence of patients on ART.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>PEPFAR will support MOH’s transition to viral load testing for ART monitoring.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>Every person starting HIV treatment will need to have access to viral load testing.</bold>
    </td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Current utilization of viral load machines considered to be &lt; 10%.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>NACP in collaboration with PEPFAR and CDC will review laboratory policy and strategic plan, develop guidelines and scale up plans for viral load testing and train all laboratory staff on these documents. These guidelines would support an increase in the uptake of viral load.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Implementation of the plan is scheduled to begin in the third quarter of 2017 supported by reprogrammed funds from The Global Fund (if awarded). The plan is to scale this up in 2018–20.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>A plan was devised to increase the viral load tests from 100 000 in 2014 to 1.2 million tests per year in 2018.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <fn id="tblfn11">
   <label>a</label>
   <p>One informant reported routine PITC was not to be rolled out nationally due to limited resources.</p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
