<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4">The influenza A viruses contain a significant number of Zn
 <sup>2+</sup> ion
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup>. The Zn
 <sup>2+</sup> is shown to bind to M1 protein with a tetrahedral coordination with two Cys and two His residues, where the Zn
 <sup>2+</sup> ion may play a structural role
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>. Cu
 <sup>2+</sup> and Zn
 <sup>2+</sup> ions, albeit less effective in the latter, significantly reduced the influenza viral titers in MDCK cells and on a copper surface
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup>. Zn
 <sup>2+</sup> is also an important cofactor of many viral proteins, including nucleocapsid protein 7 of HIV-1, NS3 of hepatitis C virus, VP30 of Ebola virus, E7 of human papilloma virus, VP6 of rotavirus, and E protein of Semliki Forest virus
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup>, mainly showing a structural role in zinc binding motifs. However, our understanding of the molecular mechanisms of divalent cation-mediated antiviral activities is far from complete. In this study, solving the crystal structure of HA derived from A/Thailand/CU44/2006 (CU44) led to a surprising finding of a divalent cation Zn
 <sup>2+</sup> bound to the head regions of two neighboring trimers. The divalent cation in the crystal structure appeared to enhance the stability of HA, but significantly decreased the melting temperature T
 <sub>m</sub> of the CU44 HA, depending on the Zn
 <sup>2+</sup> concentrations. The acid-induced conformational change of HA occurred even at neutral pH in the presence of Zn
 <sup>2+</sup>. Therefore, our results suggest that binding of Zn
 <sup>2+</sup> may facilitate the conformational change of HA, analogous to that induced by acidic pH. Here, we report the structure of HA bound to Zn
 <sup>2+</sup> ions and the effects of the divalent cation on pH-dependent conformational changes of HA.
</p>
