<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par48">Nitric oxide (NO) is a gaseous free radical with accessible vasodilatory and microbicidal functions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR144">144</xref>]. However, the antiviral effect of NO has also been documented, leading to reduced viral load and more efficient clearance of infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR145">145</xref>]. Nitrosylation of viral molecules has been offered as an antiviral mechanism employed by NO [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR146">146</xref>]. Also, NO synthase-mediated generation of NO leads to the depletion of L-arginine, thereby reducing the level of polyamines. Thus, IFN-induced NOS2 represents antiviral activities, and this, in turn, may exhibit another mechanism through which IFNs hinder viral infections such as influenza [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Despite existing data regarding the antiviral activity of NO, many studies have considered NO as a double-edged sword with both pathogenic and viricidal effects. The role of NO in the pathogenesis of pneumonia caused by influenza virus infection has been described in mice. The IFNγ response induces greatly increased levels of iNOS in the lungs of infected mice, leading to the production of a significant amount of NO and peroxynitrite species, which are among the most important pathogenic factors in influenza virus-induced pneumonia in mice [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR147">147</xref>]. Uetani et al. also observed overexpression of the iNOS gene in human airway epithelial cells induced by influenza A virus infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR148">148</xref>]. In addition, NO produced by phagocytic cells has antiviral activity that is simultaneous with nonspecific damage of host cells and viral pathogenesis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR149">149</xref>]. In a survey by Nin et al. on pandemic A/H1N1 influenza infection, all cases showed increased levels of iNOS protein, tyrosine nitration, and oxygen free radicals, indicating the production of peroxynitrite. Their results revealed the involvement of oxidative and nitrative stress in the pathogenesis of H1N1 influenza virus-induced acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Influenza-induced cytokines such as IFNγ stimulate NO release from human airway epithelial cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR150">150</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR152">152</xref>]. As mentioned previously, the influenza infection induces upregulation of HIF-1α.
</p>
