<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8">In contrast to pandemic flu, it is highlighted that angiotensin converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) of the lung type 2 alveolar epithelial cell acts as a non-catalytic receptor for SARS-CoV-1 and presumably for SARS-CoV-2 to infect the cell [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. ACE2 is reported to be predominantly localized on endothelial cells. Its mRNA is reported to be most highly expressed in testis, kidney, and, heart and also expressed in brain, intestine, and lungs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Thus, there have been growing concerns about hypertension being a risk factor for severe COVID-19 and the possibility of RAS inhibitors being an aggravating factor of severe COVID-19 due to the theoretical increase in the expression of systemic ACE2 with its use. The pandemic of SARS-CoV-2 which began in Wuhan, China from December 2019, has spread rapidly around the world. Severe lung damage and high mortality rates have been reported, particularly in the elderly and those with comorbidities. In particular, the high prevalence of hypertension and diabetes suggests that they maybe risk factors for severe COVID-19. The prevalence of hypertension is apparently high in patients with severe COVID-19, however, considering the age of those patients, the actual prevalence of hypertension does not seem to be higher. Zhou et al. analyzed the clinical characteristics of 191 patients diagnosed in Wuhan. Among them, the average age of deaths (
 <italic>n</italic> = 54) was 69 years, and the prevalence of hypertension was 48%, which is quite comparable to the prevalence of hypertension in the representative population of those ages [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Until now, none of the papers published through multivariate analysis indicated that hypertension was an independent risk factor for severe COVID-19. In the study by Guan et al., reporting the clinical features of 1099 COVID-19 patients diagnosed in Wuhan, the prevalence of hypertension was higher in severe patients (
 <italic>N</italic> = 173, mean age 52 years) than in mild patients (mean age 45 years)(23.7% vs. 13.4%), but it was not particularly higher when considering the prevalence of hypertension in that age group [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Therefore, there is no scientific evidence to suggest that hypertension itself is an independent risk factor for severe infection or mortality by COVID-19. The higher prevalence of hypertension in patients with COVID-19 is more likely due to the fact that the age of severe patients was significantly older and because major complications of hypertension such as chronic heart failure, cerebral infarction, and chronic renal failure make the patient much more vulnerable to progression to severe infection or death.
</p>
