<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Native to the Paleotropics (but see [
 <xref rid="B13-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]), the yellow crazy ant, 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>gracilipes,</italic> was introduced into many islands in the Indian and Pacific Oceans and had destructive impacts on the native ecosystems on these islands [
 <xref rid="B14-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Despite the presence of supercolonies in most of these island populations, previous studies have shown that populations of 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>gracilipes</italic> in Christmas Island [
 <xref rid="B14-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] and Taiwan (Lee, unpublished data) generally comprise of colonies that display limited aggression toward each other, while those in Penang, Malaysia, harbor a high proportion of mutually aggressive colonies [
 <xref rid="B16-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. These behavioral observations suggest that population structure may vary across where this ant is distributed. Coupled with the recent discovery of the TR44839 virus in the yellow crazy ant [
 <xref rid="B17-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], such differences in intercolonial aggression behavior provide an excellent opportunity to test whether viral prevalence is associated with the social interactions of populations. The TR44839 virus was discovered in a confirmed invasive population of 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>gracilipes</italic> in Australia and appears to be a member of the 
 <italic>Dicistroviridae</italic> viral family based on phylogenetic analysis [
 <xref rid="B17-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Despite no detailed fundamental information reported from the same study [
 <xref rid="B17-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], viruses in this family are generally characterized as positive-sense, single-stranded RNA genomes, and usually persist in hosts asymptomatically, yet sometimes cause illness in their arthropod hosts [
 <xref rid="B18-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].
</p>
