<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par10">Variola virus (smallpox virus), a member of the orthopoxvirus (OPV) genus of the family 
 <italic>poxviridae</italic>, was used in the 18th century as a biological warfare agent by British and American forces in North America [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>], and remains on the top of the list of biological threat agents for warfare or bioterrorism [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref>]. Effective vaccines and FDA-approved antivirals exist and could be used to control a deliberate release. Variola virus (VariolaV), which only infects humans, was declared eradicated in 1980, after a global vaccination campaign. Handling of VariolaV requires BSL-4 containment. Virus stocks are officially kept in only two designated laboratories in Russia and the US. Monkeypox virus (BSL-3), a zoonotic agent causing sequelae similar to smallpox but less fatal, is endemic in central Africa (Democratic Republic of Congo; DRC); recent introductions to the UK were travel-related. Poxviruses are transmitted by contact infection and via the respiratory tract, causing a systemic infection in humans and animals. Smallpox virus infection leads to a fatal multiorgan failure syndrome within 7–14 days, in complicated cases with a hemorrhagic syndrome and CNS involvement. Smallpox has played a role in large-scale epidemics in history and its causative agent continues to be considered a potential biological warfare agent [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Orthopoxviruses (OPV) are ovoid-shaped enveloped viruses with Group I double-stranded (ds) DNA genomes, replicating via a virus-encoded DNA polymerase, an antivirals target, in the cytoplasm of infected cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Poxviruses enter cells by macropinocytosis, but a poxvirus-specific receptor is still elusive [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>]. 
 <italic>Anti-poxvirus drugs</italic>. One of the first effective drugs in clinical use as a parenteral treatment in severe OPV infections was cidofovir, a bisphosphonate developed at REGA, in Belgium [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]) and FDA approved against human cytomegalovirus (HCMV). The ether lipid analogue 
 <bold>brincidofovir</bold> (CMX001), a prodrug of cidofovir, has shown efficacy in small animal models and is awaiting FDA approval [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115">115</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR116">116</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118">118</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR139">139</xref>]. The F13L virus egress inhibitor 
 <bold>tecovirimat</bold> (ST-246, TPOXX®) has been independently developed to treat smallpox infections and has been FDA approved since 2018. Tecovirimat has recently been used to treat non-human primates infected with variola, and humans exposed to OPV [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118">118</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR146">146</xref>]. Tecovirimat (TPOXX®) is currently stockpiled in the US and production for similar stockpiles in Europe is planned. Anti-poxvirus drugs effective in animal models are reviewed in more detail elsewhere [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR133">133</xref>]. Further candidate anti-poxvirus drugs include kinase inhibitors imatinib (Gleevec/STI-571; [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122">122</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR123">123</xref>]) and olomoucine [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>], terameprocol [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119">119</xref>], mitoxandrone [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], the membrane targeting ddBCNA cf2642 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>], bisbenzimide derivatives [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR151">151</xref>], FC-6407, a OPV D4 processivity factor mimic [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111">111</xref>], and a number of natural extracts that have shown interesting antiviral activity against OPV in in vitro infection models [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR153">153</xref>] (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).
</p>
