<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In China, the first outbreak of DF was reported in Guangdong province in 1978 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005354.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Since then DF cases have been reported in 26 provinces of China [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005354.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Guangdong province is the most affected areas in mainland China. In 2014, this province experienced a large outbreak resulting in 45, 224 DF cases [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005354.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005354.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Since there is no specific treatment for DF and vector control remains the most effective way to prevent and control it [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005354.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Early warning systems are considered as one of the prerequisites for adequate preparedness and response to DF epidemics [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005354.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Several previous studies have reported meteorological factors that were associated with DF outbreaks through early warning models [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005354.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0005354.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Among various meteorological factors, temperature and rainfall contribute the most to dengue epidemics [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005354.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In Singapore, Yien et al. [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005354.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] developed a weather-based dengue-forecasting model that allows warning 16 weeks in advance of dengue epidemics with high sensitivity and specificity. However, the dengue epidemics in Guangzhou are generally characterized by low level epidemic caused by imported cases, followed by a sudden and rapid transmission [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005354.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. They have varied greatly in size from year to year [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005354.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], which poses a different challenge for prediction than in the more stable and endemic regions. Although a study conducted by Sang 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005354.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] attempted to develop a model based on imported cases, minimum temperature and precipitation to predict the dengue incidence in Guangzhou, DF forecasting systems still face many difficulties due to the complexity of factors influencing DF outbreaks [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005354.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].
</p>
