<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>SARS-CoV-2 infection can also be confirmed by isolation and culturing. The human airway epithelial cell culture was found to be useful in isolating SARS-CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). The efficient control of an outbreak depends on the rapid diagnosis of the disease. Recently, in response to the COVID-19 outbreak, 1-step quantitative real-time reverse transcription-PCR assays were developed that detect the ORF1b and N regions of the SARS-CoV-2 genome (
 <xref rid="B156" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>). That assay was found to achieve the rapid detection of SARS-CoV-2. Nucleic acid-based assays offer high accuracy in the diagnosis of SARS-CoV-2, but the current rate of spread limits its use due to the lack of diagnostic assay kits. This will further result in the extensive transmission of COVID-19, since only a portion of suspected cases can be diagnosed. In such situations, conventional serological assays, like enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA), that are specific to COVID-19 IgM and IgG antibodies can be used as a high-throughput alternative (
 <xref rid="B149" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>). At present, there is no diagnostic kit available for detecting the SARS-CoV-2 antibody (
 <xref rid="B150" ref-type="bibr">150</xref>). The specific antibody profiles of COVID-19 patients were analyzed, and it was found that the IgM level lasted more than 1 month, indicating a prolonged stage of virus replication in SARS-CoV-2-infected patients. The IgG levels were found to increase only in the later stages of the disease. These findings indicate that the specific antibody profiles of SARS-CoV-2 and SARS-CoV were similar (
 <xref rid="B325" ref-type="bibr">325</xref>). These findings can be utilized for the development of specific diagnostic tests against COVID-19 and can be used for rapid screening. Even though diagnostic test kits are already available that can detect the genetic sequences of SARS-CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>), their availability is a concern, as the number of COVID-19 cases is skyrocketing (
 <xref rid="B155" ref-type="bibr">155</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B157" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>). A major problem associated with this diagnostic kit is that it works only when the test subject has an active infection, limiting its use to the earlier stages of infection. Several laboratories around the world are currently developing antibody-based diagnostic tests against SARS-CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="B157" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>).
</p>
