<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para20">There is an increasing focus on the human-animal-environment disease interface, as encompassed in the One Health concept. Mortalities, disability-adjusted life-years, and billions of dollars of economic losses from these infections demand action and investment in prevention to face novel challenges to human and animal health. Research has led to better understanding of the nature and drivers of cross-species viral jumps, but the detail is still elusive. No reservoir population of bats for SARS and MERS-CoV or Ebola virus have been definitively identified, despite considerable searching, possibly because of the source virus circulating in small and isolated populations. Forensic examination has clarified the human infection sources and multispecies involvement in these diseases, with some species confirmed as competent hosts (eg, camels for MERS-CoV
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref>), bridge (or amplifying) hosts (eg, pigs for Nipah virus, non-human primates for Ebola virus
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref>), or dead-end hosts. The crucial checkpoint is the jump and bridging of the viruses to humans, which occurs most frequently through animal-based food systems. In the case of SARS, markets with live and dead animals of wild and domestic origins were the crucible for virus evolution and emergence in the human population. Once the viruses' functional proteins enabled cell entry in civets (
 <italic>Paguma larvata</italic>) and racoon dogs (
 <italic>Nyctereutes procyonoides</italic>), the bridge was established and it was only a matter of time before the jump to humans occurred.
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref> Sequence comparison of civet viruses suggested evolution was ongoing; this was further supported by high seroprevalence of antibodies against SARS-CoV among civet sellers, suggesting previous cross-species transmission events without necessarily human-to-human transmission.
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Similarly, early Ebola virus was mostly associated with bushmeat and its consumption in Africa; Nipah virus is associated with date palm sap, fruit, and domestic pig farms; MERS is associated with the camel livestock industry; and H5N1 arose from viral evolution in domestic and wild birds, to ultimately bring all these cases to humans. The 2019-nCoV is another virus in the pipeline that originated from contact with animals, in this case a seafood and animal market in Wuhan, China.
</p>
