<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par29">The 254 nm UVC light adopted in conventional infection control products can disinfect the illuminated objects since the 254 nm radiation can disrupt the genetic materials of airborne pathogens and render them inviable [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].VUV has an even stronger ionizing power than UVC light and can generate high concentration reactive species such as ozone and OH radicals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. In other words, apart from direct illumination, VUV can inactivate bacterial growth by the radicals generated during VUV irradiation. Therefore, adopting VUV lamps can enhance the air disinfection capability of air cleaning systems. A previous study [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] conducted by Huang et al. demonstrated that 64% toluene removal with VUV irradiation alone and the use of photocatalyst enhanced the toluene removal from 64 to 82%. The experiment adopting UVC lamps and the use of photocatalyst removed only 14% of toluene. The result demonstrated that VUV light could be an effective measure for chemical degradation in ventilation systems. When it comes to disinfection, extensive research has been carried out on UVC light and effective destruction of both airborne [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] and other human pathogens [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] has been shown. Nevertheless, disinfection using VUV light has attracted very little attention. This would be caused by the relative low prevalence of VUV light sources. Kim et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] found that the disinfection time required to attain the same extent of inactivation of aerosolized MS2 bacteriophage, using low pressure mercury vapor lamps with both 254 nm UVC and 185 nm VUV output was much shorter than the lamps with 254 nm UVC only. The disinfection time of ozone only (without UV) process at ozone concentrations equivalent to the ozone level generated by the mercury vapor lamps was also significantly faster than using lamps with 254 nm emission only. Besides, Huang et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] reported the inactivation of 
 <italic>E coli</italic> by low pressure mercury vapor lamps. Additionally, some researchers tested the disinfection of water with VUV light and it was reported that the efficiency was quite low compared to disinfection with UVC light [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. The reason is due to the low penetration power of VUV light in water [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Moreover, the disinfection of human pathogens by VUV light was rarely reported. In our opinion, only Christofi et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>] reported the disinfection of the microbial films of 3 types of pathogenic bacteria using ozone producing low-pressure Hg vapor lamps. Therefore, the effect of VUV light against human pathogens is yet to be elucidated. In this study, we evaluated the germicidal effect of VUV light on common bacteria including 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> ATCC25922 (
 <italic>E. coli</italic>), Extended Spectrum Beta-Lactamase-producing 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> (ESBL), Methicillin-resistant 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA) and 
 <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> (MTB), and that on influenza viruses H1N1 and H3N2. Influenza viruses and MTB are inherent airborne pathogens while 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> ATCC25922 is always the first indicator organism to monitor disinfection efficacy. The more drug resistant ESBL and MRSA were chosen as examples to monitor disinfection efficacy on human pathogens. Some suspensions of these bacteria and viruses were absorbed into nitrocellulose filter papers during the experiments and the disinfection under the environment with a moderate barrier to light was evaluated.
</p>
