<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="ppat.1007938.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1007938.g005</object-id>
 <label>Fig 5</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Addition of clathrin-mediated endocytosis inhibitors prevents EGL disruption and endothelial hyperpermeability triggered by DENV NS1.</title>
  <p>
   <bold>(A)</bold> The integrity of the EGL on HPMEC was assessed by the presence of heparan sulfate [
   <xref rid="ppat.1007938.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] surface expression (green, bottom row), as well as cathepsin L (CTSL) activity (red, top row), at 6 hpt with DENV NS1 (5 μg/ml) in the presence or absence of Pitstop 2 (12.5 μM), or Pitstop 2 alone, at 37°C, as visualized via IFA. Nuclei were stained with Hoechst (blue). Images (20X; scale bars, 50 μm) are representative of 3 independent experiments. 
   <bold>(B)</bold> Quantification of MFI in 
   <bold>(A)</bold> from 3 independent experiments expressed as either fold change of cathepsin L activity from Pitstop 2 control values (left) or normalized percentage of heparan sulfate from Pitstop 2 control values [
   <xref rid="ppat.1007938.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Error bars indicate SEM. **, p&lt;0.01; ***, p&lt;0.001. 
   <bold>(C)</bold> HPMEC were grown on Transwell semi-permeable membranes (0.4 μm pore size), and the apical chamber was treated with either DENV NS1+ (5 μg/ml) and DMSO (blue squares); the dynamin inhibitor Dynasore (25 μM) alone (purple diamonds) or Dynasore and NS1 (orange triangles); or the clathrin-mediated endocytosis inhibitor Pitstop 2 (12.5 μM) alone (light green triangles) or Pitstop 2 and NS1 (pink circles). A TEER assay was used to evaluate the effect of NS1 and inhibitors on endothelial permeability at indicated time-points over 48 hours. (^) represents change of medium. Relative TEER values from 2 independent experiments performed in duplicate are plotted. Error bars indicate standard error of the mean (SEM).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1007938.g005" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
