<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="ppat.1007938.g007" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1007938.g007</object-id>
 <label>Fig 7</label>
 <caption>
  <title>DENV2 NS1-triggered vascular leak in the dorsal dermis of mice is prevented by clathrin-mediated endocytosis inhibitors.</title>
  <p>Hair was removed from the dorsal dermis of mice, and mice were allowed to recover for 3 days. On the day of the assay, retro-orbital injections of Alexa Fluor 680-conjugated dextran were administered, followed by intradermal injections of PBS plus vehicle (DMSO, top left circle), PBS plus inhibitor cocktail (top right circle), 15 μg DENV2 NS1 plus the DMSO vehicle (bottom left circle), and 15 μg DENV2 NS1 plus inhibitors (bottom right circle). The dermis from each mouse was collected and processed two hours post-injection. 
   <bold>(A)</bold> Representative image of the dorsal dermis from 2 mice following the fluorescent dextran assay. 
   <bold>(B)</bold> Dermises were scanned using a fluorescent detection system (LI-COR Odyssey CLx Imaging System) at a wavelength of 700 nm, and extravasated fluorescent dextran was quantified in tissue using Image Studio software (LI-COR Biosciences). Data represent the quantification of mean fluorescent intensity from mice in (A): PBS plus DMSO vehicle (closed black circles, n = 8); PBS plus inhibitors (open black circles, n = 4); DENV2 NS1–15 μg plus DMSO vehicle (closed blue diamonds, n = 8); and DENV2 NS1–15 μg plus inhibitors (open blue diamonds, n = 8). Data in (B) represent mean +/- SD and were collected from two independent experiments. All DENV NS1 proteins used in this experiment were purchased from the Native Antigen Company. A nonparametric Mann-Whitney U test was used to determine significance between treatment groups. ns = not significant, *, p &lt; 0.05; **, p &lt; 0.01. The cocktail of inhibitors was composed of Pitstop 2 (0.25 mg/ml) and Dynasore (0.5 mg/ml) to antagonize local clathrin-mediated endocytosis.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1007938.g007" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
