<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Globalisation, increased urbanisation resulting in large vastly populated and overcrowded cities, and the development of fast mass transit networks and consequent ease of travelling means that a virus can spread across a country or a continent in just a few hours. In the absence of a vaccine or an effective treatment, the tools to control a new viral infection have remained the same as during the 1918 influenza pandemic, 
 <italic>i.e.</italic> early public health interventions designed to reduce the risk of transmission and spread of infection such as increased respiratory hygiene, cough etiquette and hand washing, voluntary isolation of infected individuals or households as well as quarantine of their contacts, followed by voluntary or mandatory physical distancing measures, restrictions on travel and transportation, and dissemination of basic infection prevention and control messages and advice to the general population [
 <xref rid="C93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. National lockdown is an extreme measure that, while potentially reducing transmission, may also result in the collapse of the economy of a country. These nonpharmaceutical countermeasures aim at reducing the impact of COVID-19 by minimising the number of contacts that result in disease transmission and, thus, reducing the effective reproduction number R
 <sub>0</sub> to below 1. The reduction of the number of cases during the epidemic peak is crucial to reduce the burden on the healthcare services and other related sectors, and aims to flatten the curve by spreading cases over a longer period of time. This approach, while not necessarily reducing the total number of cases, gains time necessary for the development, production and distribution of effective and safe pharmaceuticals (
 <italic>i.e.</italic> vaccines and antiviral drugs), implementation of adequate hospital response and obtaining necessary ICU equipment as well as more sensitive diagnostic tests.
</p>
