<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Subunit-based vaccines are a preferred option in terms of safety and their ability to induce immune responses producing neutralizing antibodies without risk of using infectious viruses [
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. The genetic sequence of coronaviral S protein has been determined and recombinant proteins have been developed using a baculovirus expression system [
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>,
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Coronaviral S protein, either at full-length or in fragments (such as S1 subunit [
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>], RBD [
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>,
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>], N-terminal domain [
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>,
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>] or fusion peptide [
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]), is considered an attractive candidate for vaccine development against SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV because of its ability to stimulate the immune response and release neutralizing antibodies [
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>,
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. Currently, S protein-based vaccines are the most promising therapeutic approach against COVID-19 and so far, several institutions and companies are actively involved in this field. One of these vaccine candidates was generated by fusion of MERS-CoV-S1 or SARS-CoV-2-S1 segments with S-foldon trimerization domain (27-amino acid sequence) to mimic the native nature of virus structure in the presence or absence of immunostimulatory TLR ligand sequence [
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Subcutaneous delivery via microneedle arrays, which can provide high vaccine concentration and prolonged exposure, elicits humoral immunity stronger than traditional needle injection [
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Using its patented Trimer-Tag
 <sup>©</sup> technology, Clover Biopharmaceuticals Inc. has constructed a vaccine using trimeric S protein, which is similar to native trimeric spike of SARS-CoV-2. Moreover, Dynavax Inc. has conducted a preclinical study using its US FDA-approved CpG 1018 adjuvant to rapidly develop a COVID-19 Trimeric S protein vaccine [
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. Furthermore, molecular clamp-based technology [
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>] has been used by Queensland University to develop a subunit vaccine against COVID-19. Some researchers have been working on epitope vaccines using B- and T-cell epitopes from SARS-CoV S and N proteins, which are highly conserved epitopes in SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>], however, this type of vaccine needs adjuvants due to low-molecular-weight-related low immunogenicity [
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. Despite its abundance in CoVs, N protein immunization does not produce the expected protection 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> [
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. However, M protein is able to produce neutralizing antibodies against SARS-CoVs due to its highly conservative nature. Accordingly, it could be used as a candidate vaccine against SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>,
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>].
</p>
