<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4">How diabetes increases severity of COVID-19 is unclear, though several factors may be responsible (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Poor glycaemic control impairs several aspects of the innate and adaptive immune response to viral infections and to the potential secondary bacterial infection in the lungs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Defects in immunity namely inappropriate T-cell action, impaired natural killer cell activity and defects in complement action could reduce viral clearance [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Interestingly, ARDS in patients with COVID-19 is driven by severe hypoxaemia despite relatively well-preserved lung mechanics. Pre-existing proinflammatory state could accentuate the cytokine storm, which is believed to be responsible for ARDS as well as multi-organ dysfunction in COVID-19 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. In this context, it is important to note that there is strong association between type 2 diabetes, obesity and abnormal secretion of adipokines and cytokines like TNF-alfa and interferon, which may further impair immunity and predispose to severe infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Further, diabetes is associated with increased plasminogen levels which has been postulated to increase the virulence of SARS CoV-2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Presence of these inflammation and prothrombotic factors has been shown in a study in 174 patients hospitalised with COVID-19 in Wuhan, China; significantly higher serum levels of interleukein 6, erythrocyte sedimentation rate, C‐reactive protein, ferritin, fibrinogen and D‐dimer were reported in patients with diabetes compared with those without diabetes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Increased viral replication in diabetes may also due to an increase in furin, which is a type‐1 membrane‐bound protease involved in the entry of coronaviruses into the cell [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. In addition, pre-existing comorbidities associated with diabetes like hypertension, coronary artery disease and chronic kidney disease further worsen the prognosis. Lastly, hypoglycaemia which could occur during treatment of diabetes may additionally worsen the clinical outcomes.
</p>
