<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0240">
 <bold>Jordi Figuerola</bold> (
 <italic>Estación Biológica de Doñana</italic> – CSIC, Spain), 
 <bold>Albert Osterhaus</bold> (Research Center for Emerging Infections and Zoonoses (RIZ), University of Veterinary Medicine Hannover, Germany) and 
 <bold>Amelia Nieto</bold> (
 <italic>Centro Nacional de Biotecnología</italic> – CSIC, Spain) presented their views on the One Health concept, taking into account the fields of wildlife, ecology, as well as, veterinary and medical infectious disease disciplines. Figuerola highlighted the fundamental contribution of wildlife and environment (including climate change) to emerging and re-emerging zoonotic diseases, including some examples on mosquito borne flaviviruses like West Nile virus (
 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Rizzoli et al., 2015</xref>), as well as, non-infectious diseases. He emphasized the need to further research on how organisms interact and how they interact with their environment as a cornerstone to understand infectious disease dynamics. Osterhaus covered aspects of emerging diseases in wildlife, livestock and companion animals, and the role they play in emerging human infections. Subsequently he highlighted the need to prioritize syndrome surveillance and diagnostic platforms in humans and animals, as well as, the increasing role of novel molecular technologies in pathogen discovery (
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Kruppa et al., 2018</xref>). In addition, he stressed that these priorities must be coupled with platforms offering mathematical modelling capacity, animal models and pathogenesis studies for new infections. Moreover, all these aspects should be accompanied by investment in therapeutics discovery and preventive intervention strategies. He finally emphasized a key point of the One Health concept, which is communication among experts, politicians, stakeholders and society (
 <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Reperant et al., 2015</xref>). Nieto focused specifically on one of the most devastating zoonoses in human history: influenza. She presented recent results showing that the heart should be considered a new target of influenza A viruses in addition to lung, especially by strains of high pathogenicity. In addition, she discussed the need for novel developments of most effective, ideally universal, influenza vaccines, as well as, more effective antivirals with low escape potential.
</p>
