<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>MS-based lipidomics analyzes the targeted or global lipid profile (e.g., fatty acids, glycerophospholipids, sphingolipids, glycerolipids, glycolipids, and steroids) and its perturbation with disease or infection.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref51">51</xref>
 </sup> Lipidomics has had a tremendous impact in emerging pathogen studies. Lipids play important roles at various stages of host–pathogen interactions and pathogenesis.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref52">52</xref>
 </sup> For example, MS-based lipidomics revealed that arbovirus which is transmitted by 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> mosquitoes leading to dengue, Zika, chikungunya, and yellow fever, utilizes increased levels of glycerophospholipids, sphingolipids, and fatty acids for viral replication.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref53">53</xref>
 </sup> Studies based on electron tomography identified that significant rearrangements of the host cell membrane architecture occur upon infection.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref54">54</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref55">55</xref>
 </sup> As the host cell membrane is enriched with lipid molecules, viral entry into the host requires direct or indirect association or modulations of host membrane lipids. Evidently, lipids play multifaceted roles in viral entry into the host cell.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref56">56</xref>
 </sup> Glycosphingolipids composed of a lipid and carbohydrate moiety have been shown as receptors for members of the nonenveloped viruses such as calicivirus (it includes genera of norovirus, sapovirus, vesivirus, lagovirus, nebovirus, and recovirus), rotavirus, polyomavirus, and parovirus families.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref57">57</xref>
 </sup> The carbohydrate moiety of host cell membrane glycosphingolipids helps to direct the interaction between a host cell and the nonenveloped virus protein coat. This interaction leads to the virus internalization and initiation of infection.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref56">56</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref58">58</xref>
 </sup> Lipid receptors such as LDLR (low density lipoprotein receptor) act as an indirect receptor for hepatitis C virus (HCV) and bovine viral diarrheal virus (BVDV) where these viruses initially interact with LDL (low density lipoprotein) lipid in the bloodstream and then the virus is transported to the proximity of the target cell that will be infected via the association with the LDL–LDLR complex and eventually facilitates infection.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref59">59</xref>
 </sup> In the case of dengue, bis(monoacylglycero)phosphate (BMP) and phosphatidylserine (PS) act as viral fusion cofactors for endosomal acidification-dependent fusion machinery.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref60">60</xref>
 </sup> After initial receptor interactions, several viruses such as influenza, HIV, and Ebola use lipid microdomains, known as membrane rafts and made by sphingolipids and cholesterol, as cofactors for entry into the host cell, assembly, and budding.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref56">56</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref61">61</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
