<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par36">Although it is now established that the pathogenicity of PVB19 is not restricted to the erythroid progenitor cells, the mechanisms of PVB19-related renal lesions are still poorly understood. The proposed mechanisms include cytopathic effects on glomerular endothelial cells, glomerular deposition of immune complexes resulting from the infection, or the development of immune disorders after PVB19 infection. The direct infection of glomerular epithelial cells could be the mechanism of kidney injury in cases of FSGS, including collapsing glomerulopathy [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Indeed, PVB19 viral DNA was detected in kidney biopsies of patients with non-HIV-related collapsing FSGS, and was precisely located in visceral and parietal epithelial cells. However, viral DNA was also detected in control samples and in other glomerular lesions, which questions the specificity of this finding [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. In cases of TMA and vasculitis, the direct infection of glomerular endothelial cells has also been proposed as the trigger of endothelial activation and lesion, leading to the subsequent thrombotic and inflammatory response with complement activation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Indeed, the endocytosis of PVB19 by endothelial cells is enhanced by the presence of anti-PVB19 antibodies and their linkage to the C1q receptor [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. The glomerular deposition of circulating immune complexes, comprising viral antigens and host antiviral antibodies, could also lead to a post-infectious glomerulonephritis, which is the pathological lesion most frequently described in the literature [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. In addition, PVB19 could be implicated in the activation of complement alternative pathway (CAP), since C3 level is often decreased in PVB19 infection with kidney involvement [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Here, the case report n°4, showing MPGN with C3 deposits following a PVB19 infection in a patient with sickle cell disease, is particularly original and illustrates this possible link between PVB19 and CAP activation.
</p>
