<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par44">Currently, several biological functions of M2 protein are known. The first and most important is as a proton-selective channel or so-called viroporin [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>], which is formed by four fragments of H37xxxW41 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118">118</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125">125</xref>]. Shortly after the influenza virus enters a cell as part of the endosome [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132">132</xref>], M2 goes into an activated state triggered by the acidic environment inside the endosomes. Using the M2 protein, H
 <sup>+</sup> ions are transferred through the viral membrane into the virion (proton transfer occurs through the formation of the protonated state of His37 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125">125</xref>] and rotation of the indole of Trp41 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118">118</xref>]). The influx of protons also leads to an influx of potassium and sodium ions (K
 <sup>+</sup> and Na
 <sup>+</sup>), which in turn lead to a change in the M1 conformation, and the viral RNA goes into a relaxed state [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">112</xref>]. The low endosomal pH leads to conformational changes in the HA molecule, which in turn triggers the fusion of the virion membrane with the endosomal membrane. Further, the interaction between M1 and the ribonucleoprotein complex is weakened, which leads to the release of viral RNA into the cytosol [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. It has also been shown that the ionic imbalance in the cell, resulting from the operation of the M2 protein, is a signal for the formation of inflammatory activity in myeloid cells such as macrophages and dendritic cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>].
</p>
