<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Parida et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122">2004</xref>) developed real-time reverse transcription LAMP method for rapid detection of West Nile virus by using envelope gene of West Nile (WN) virus. Suebsing et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR162">2011</xref>) developed reverse transcription LAMP method for detection of infectious hematopoietic necrosis virus in 
 <italic>Oncorhynchus keta</italic>. The limit of detection was 0.01 fg of RNA extracted from IHNV-infected CHSE-214 cells, compared with 1.0 fg for nested RT-PCR. Ren and Li (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR142">2011</xref>) developed reverse transcription loop-mediated isothermal amplification for rapid detection of porcine epidemic diarrhea virus. Six primers were designed to amplify the nucleocapsid (N) gene of PEDV. The optimal reaction condition for RT-LAMP amplifying PEDV N gene was achieved at 63 °C for 50 min. It was found that RT-LAMP assay was more sensitive than gel-based RT-PCR and enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay. It was capable of detecting PEDV from clinical samples and differentiating PEDV from porcine transmissible gastroenteritis virus, porcine rotavirus, porcine pseudorabies virus, porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome virus, and avian infectious bronchitis virus. Taura syndrome virus (TSV) was first discovered in Ecuador in 1992 (Jimenez 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">1992</xref>). Kiatpathomchai et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">2007</xref>) developed a rapid and sensitive detection of Taura syndrome virus by reverse transcription loop-mediated isothermal amplification. The detection of TSV using RT-LAMP was ten times more sensitive than the RT-PCR, but less sensitive than nested RT-PCR. Sappat et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR148">2011</xref>) detected the shrimp Taura syndrome virus by loop-mediated isothermal amplification using a designed portable multichannel turbidimeter. When using the same TSV-RNA template sets, the results revealed the same detection limit of 10
 <sup>−6</sup> dilution for RT-LAMP when performed using a commercial heating block (Major Science, Taiwan) and the designed turbidimeter. When RT-LAMP reactions were carried out at 63 °C for 30 min using 2 μl of the ten-fold serially diluted RNA template extracted from TSV-infected shrimp, the turbidity measurement was able to detect 100 fg of total RNA. This detection limit was equivalent to that of RT-LAMP-AGE and nested RT-PCR. When the RNA 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> transcript was used as the template, the detection limit by both of turbidity measurement and AGE was ten copies. A prior study indicated that the LAMP method was capable of amplification starting with only six copies of template (Nagamine et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">2002</xref>).
</p>
