<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Coronaviruses are positive-strand, enveloped RNA viruses. Viruses in this group are important pathogens of mammals and birds. They cause enteric or respiratory tract infections in a variety of animals including humans, livestock, and pets. Severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) is caused by a coronavirus called SARS-CoV. CoV-based vectors have potential in vaccine development and for gene therapy (Theil 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR0040">2007</xref>). Severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) first spread in Guangdong Province, China in November 2002 (Zhong et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR186">2003</xref>). SARS is diagnosed by two major approaches: first, detection of antibodies against SARS-CoV was a sensitive and specific diagnostic approach, but seroconversion can be detected only around after day 10 of illness (Peiris et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129">2003a</xref>). In contrast, PCR-based tests have been shown to be useful for early SARS diagnosis (Berger et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2004</xref>). Quantitative PCR approaches are a powerful tool for identifying SARS-CoV early after disease onset (Drosten et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2003</xref>; Poon et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR136">2003</xref>; Ng et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115">2003</xref>; Grant et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2003</xref>). Because of the requirement of sophisticated instrumentation and expensive reagents, these rapid molecular tests might not be the method of choice in field situations. The detection limit of the assay was 10 copies/reaction, and positive signals were consistently observed in reactions containing ~50 copies of the target sequence. Quantitative PCR method was used for SARS diagnosis (Poon et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR136">2003</xref>). Thai et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR163">2004</xref>) developed a one-step, single-tube, accelerated, real-time, quantitative RT-LAMP assay for the early and rapid diagnosis of SARS-CoV. The sensitivity and specificity of RT-LAMP assay for detecting viral RNA in clinical specimens with regard to RT-PCR were 100 and 87 %, respectively. The RT-LAMP assay was found to be 100-fold more sensitive than RT-PCR, with a detection limit of 0.01 PFU in clinical samples. In addition, by using a real-time RT-LAMP assay, the quantitation of virus concentration in the clinical sample is possible, which will indicate the early stage of the virus infection as well as potential source transmitters. However, the detection rates for SARS in the LAMP assay are similar to those with our conventional PCR-based assays (Chan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2004</xref>). Rapid detection of the severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) coronavirus by a loop-mediated isothermal amplification assay was developed by Poon et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR0037">2004</xref>). The detection limit of the assay was 10 copies/reaction reactions containing ~50 copies of the target sequence. Viral load peaks in the second week of infection in SARS patients due to which its detection is difficult. LAMP assay is an inexpensive and accurate alternative method for detection of virus at the end of first week of infection (Peiris et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR130">2003b</xref>).
</p>
