<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Porcine circoviruses (PCV) are the smallest autonomously replicating viruses in eukaryotic cells. Among known two types of PCV, porcine circovirus type 1 (PCV1) does not cause disease, but porcine circovirus type 2 (PCV2) causes a new emerging and multifactorial disease in swine known as postweaning multisystemic wasting syndrome (PMWS) (Bolin et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2001</xref>) and porcine dermatitis and nephropathy syndrome (PDNS). Porcine circovirus type 2 (PCV2) syndrome is responsible for great losses to the pig industry. PCV2 is a non-enveloped, circular, single-stranded DNA virus. Presence of PCR inhibitors (including organic and inorganic substances such as detergents, antibiotics, phenolic compounds, enzymes, polysaccharides, fats, proteins, and salts) in the analysis of real biological samples limits the usefulness of PCR. These inhibitors reduce the amplification efficiency (Darwich et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2002</xref>; Guo et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2010</xref>). PCV2 was detected by reverse transcription LAMP using membrane protein M gene for primers with a detection limit ten fold greater than conventional PCR (Chen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2009</xref>). Chen et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2008</xref>) detected PCV2 by LAMP by using only four primers, while Zhao et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR185">2011</xref>) detected same virus by efficient LAMP assay using six primers including two loop primers for detection of target ORF2 gene in PCV2 (which encodes Rep protein that is involved in virus replication) with a detection limit of 10 copies, whereas the limit by conventional PCR was 1,000 copies. LAMP assay had advantages in specificity, selectivity, and rapidity over other nucleic acid amplification methods (Mori et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">2006</xref>). LAMP had been further advanced by using forward loop primers (Nagamine et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">2002</xref>). The LAMP assay developed had a detection limit of ten copies for PCV2, which was 100-fold more sensitive than conventional PCR.
</p>
