<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A final consideration of topical interest involves data collection on ASF at the European level. Linking outbreak information with surveillance and laboratory data, with the pathogen characteristics, would help in understanding the disease and its genetic dynamics in the spatial and temporal context and allow improvement of control and eradication strategies. At present, these data, if available, are usually collected at country level, with several information systems in place even in different regions of the same country, having different aims, and owned by different organizations. At EU level, data on the outbreaks of notifiable animal disease are currently registered into the Animal Diseases Notification System (ADNS) (
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>). However, the quality of data concerning each outbreak is currently poor, especially for data indispensable for evaluating the progression of the disease. Moreover, the information is often not linked to surveillance and laboratory data. The collection of data and information on ASF surveillance is fragmented even within a given country; this does not support the progression of control and eradication of the disease. Moreover, while data on farmed susceptible species and information on herds, densities, and locations (geographical coordinates) are stored in well-structured databases and information systems (
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>), densities and geographical distribution of wild susceptible animals are collected by the EU countries with different systems, each having their own specific characteristics with respect to the methodology used, the type of data acquired, the repository implemented, and data accessibility. This is of particular concern given the spread of ASF from Eastern Europe areas. In this framework, the ENETWILD EFSA funded project is attempting to develop standards for data collection, validation, and to create a data repository (
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>). Moreover, starting from 2019, EFSA has conducted a project with the support of volunteers EU Member States, aimed at building a harmonized and coherent platform for exchange of surveillance and laboratory information on ASF, lumpy skin disease, and Avian influenza (
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>). A coherent and harmonized data collection system would allow EFSA to perform proper risk analysis, with the aim of improving surveillance systems, and achieving eradication of the diseases.
</p>
