<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>HSV-1 and HSV-2 can cause severe disease in immunocompetent adults and newborns, such as life-threatening encephalitis with sequelae, despite antiviral treatment (
 <xref rid="B197" ref-type="bibr">Whitley et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B204" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Dinh et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Handel et al., 2011</xref>). These viruses can also produce eye infections leading to visual impairment: currently, HSV-1 is the main cause of infectious blindness in developed countries (
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Farooq and Shukla, 2012</xref>). However, the most common clinical manifestations associated to HSV-1 and HSV-2 infections are 
 <italic>herpes labialis</italic> and 
 <italic>herpes genitalis</italic> (
 <xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr">Lafferty et al., 1987</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B131" ref-type="bibr">Mertz et al., 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">Kaye and Choudhary, 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B143" ref-type="bibr">Paz-Bailey et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Farooq and Shukla, 2012</xref>), which are characterized by the appearance of vesicular ulcers in the oro-facial and genital areas that gradually dry out into crusts and may last up to 14 days during primary infections and approximately 10 days during recurrences if no treatment is undertaken (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Arduino and Porter, 2007</xref>). Lesion development is sequential and begins with a prodrome displaying erythema, then papules emerge which may progress into vesicles that break up giving way to the formation of ulcers. Finally, these ulcers dry out forming scabs, which are accompanied by residual swelling and finally healing (
 <xref rid="B178" ref-type="bibr">Spruance et al., 1977</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Corey et al., 1983</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Fatahzadeh and Schwartz, 2007</xref>). The lesions contain high amounts of virions and infiltrating leukocytes and may be painful with a burning sensation, ultimately impacting the quality of life of the affected individuals (
 <xref rid="B178" ref-type="bibr">Spruance et al., 1977</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Dreno et al., 2012</xref>).
</p>
