<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par40">Gene polymorphisms of opioid (
 <italic>OPRM1</italic> and 
 <italic>OPRK1</italic>) and non-opioid (e.g., 
 <italic>DRD1</italic> and 
 <italic>DRD2</italic>) drug/neurotransmitter receptor genes are associated with altered HIV infectivity, viral loads and CD4+ cell counts (Proudnikov et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR406">2012</xref>; Regan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR423">2012</xref>; Jacobs et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR223">2013</xref>; Proudnikov et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR407">2013</xref>; Dever et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115">2014</xref>). Not only do MORs mediate the behavioral consequences of opiate abuse (Bond et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">1998</xref>; Szeto et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR499">2001</xref>; Ikeda et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR219">2005</xref>; Kreek et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR260">2005</xref>; Xu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR552">2014b</xref>), but the ability of MOR to modulate HIV chemokine co-receptor signaling through cross desensitization or through direct molecular interactions suggest MOR may influence HIV infectivity at multiple levels. The unique ability of MOR to modulate HIV co-receptor function, prompted inquiry regarding whether variants of the 
 <italic>OPRM1</italic> gene (polymorphisms or splicing variants) might differentially effect HIV infectivity and/or opiate addictive behaviors. In a sample of 1031 HIV-1-infected women, 18 
 <italic>OPRM1</italic> polymorphisms were significantly associated with decreases or increases in HIV infectivity and responsiveness to cART (Proudnikov et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR406">2012</xref>). Other gene polymorphisms, such as enzymes affecting drug metabolism (Meyer and Zanger 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR335">1997</xref>; Benowitz et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2006</xref>) and other neurochemical systems (Herman and Balogh 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR210">2012</xref>; Koob and Volkow 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR250">2016</xref>) can also affect drug dependence. The A118G variant of 
 <italic>OPRM1</italic> alters the regulation of proinflammatory cytokine secretion (i.e., TNF-α, IL-10, IFN-γ) from peripheral immune cells (Matsunaga et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR318">2009</xref>). Overall, these findings suggest that polymorphisms in MOR ligands/genes (
 <italic>OPRM1</italic>) can influence the pathophysiology of HIV-1.
</p>
