<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The past 30 years have seen rapid development of genetic sequencing technologies for RNA and DNA.
 <xref rid="b58-rmmj-11-3-e0027" ref-type="bibr">58</xref> From the beginning, RNA/DNA research has been characterized by both exaggerated promises and inflated expectations regarding the importance of human genetic traits that predispose for both infectious and non-infectious diseases.
 <xref rid="b59-rmmj-11-3-e0027" ref-type="bibr">59</xref> Unfortunately, to date, no human genetic markers predisposing to SARS-CoV-2 infection, nor the severity of COVID-19, have been found—although recent isolated exceptions to this statement can be found. For example, there may be a predisposition to COVID-19 among humans with blood group A as opposed to other blood groups.
 <xref rid="b60-rmmj-11-3-e0027" ref-type="bibr">60</xref> In sharp contrast to human genomics, mapping viral RNA mutations of SARS-CoV-2 has enabled a fairly accurate reconstruction of its transmission (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3-rmmj-11-3-e0027">Figure 3B</xref>) and helped to determine its phylogenetic origins (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1-rmmj-11-3-e0027">Figure 1</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3-rmmj-11-3-e0027">Figure 3A</xref>).
 <xref rid="b1-rmmj-11-3-e0027" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="b61-rmmj-11-3-e0027" ref-type="bibr">61</xref> Viral sequencing of samples obtained from COVID-19 patients, and being able to mark its different mutations, has provided a much clearer and more accurate picture of viral transmission as opposed to results obtained by contact tracing. For example, a study of disease importation to continents, countries, or regions has surprisingly uncovered several shuffled patterns in the genomic data. When considering importation of the first COVID-19 cases to the Western United States, the initial investigation based on contact tracing indicated that those cases were epidemiologically unrelated. However, after sequencing multiple virus isolates, the researchers concluded that they were not only closely related, but probably also began with one patient of origin.
 <xref rid="b62-rmmj-11-3-e0027" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>
</p>
