<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Zika virus (ZIKV) is a mosquito-borne flavivirus virus that belongs to the family 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic> [
 <xref rid="B1-pathogens-08-00216" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. After its first discovery in 1947 from a sentinel rhesus monkey in Uganda, ZIKV caused sporadic outbreaks in Africa and South Asia until the occurrence of major outbreaks in Micronesia in 2007 and French Polynesia in 2013 [
 <xref rid="B2-pathogens-08-00216" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-pathogens-08-00216" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. ZIKV has spread rapidly throughout the Americas since its first report in Brazil in 2015 [
 <xref rid="B4-pathogens-08-00216" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], affecting more than 70 countries worldwide [
 <xref rid="B5-pathogens-08-00216" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. ZIKV is classified into two lineages: African (AF) and Asian (AS) [
 <xref rid="B6-pathogens-08-00216" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The Asian lineage is causing the current outbreaks occurring worldwide. The main vector for urban transmission of ZIKV is the 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> mosquito, although sexual contact and vertical transmission are also responsible for the virus dissemination [
 <xref rid="B7-pathogens-08-00216" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Infection by ZIKV is associated with neurological complications, such as microcephaly in foetuses and Guillain–Barré syndrome (GBS) in adults, now considered congenital zika syndrome (CZS) [
 <xref rid="B8-pathogens-08-00216" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-pathogens-08-00216" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-pathogens-08-00216" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. There has been considerable progress in the research of vaccines or therapeutics against ZIKV, however, no licensed vaccines are yet available against ZIKV. There are many ZIKV vaccine candidates, such as inactivated virus, based on DNA, mRNA, and recombinant viral vectors encoding the precursor membrane (prM) and the envelope (E) ZIKV proteins, which are currently in phase I or II clinical trials [
 <xref rid="B11-pathogens-08-00216" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The modified vaccinia virus Ankara (MVA) has been extensively studied as a vectored-vaccine against various infectious diseases, reaching clinical trials, where it has been regarded as a safe, cost effective, and efficacious vaccine vector [
 <xref rid="B12-pathogens-08-00216" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-pathogens-08-00216" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-pathogens-08-00216" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-pathogens-08-00216" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-pathogens-08-00216" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. We have previously reported the development of four ChAdOx1 ZIKV vaccine candidates and their protective efficacy in a homologous ZIKV challenge model [
 <xref rid="B17-pathogens-08-00216" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. All four ChAdOx1 ZIKV vaccine candidates (prME, prME ΔTM, Env, and Env ΔTM) were shown to stimulate the production of anti-E ZIKV antibodies and demonstrated protective efficacy in a homologous ZIKV-lineage challenge model. The vaccine candidate that contains prME and has a deletion (Δ) in the transmembrane domain (prME ΔTM) induced the highest titres of anti-envelope ZIKV antibodies that provided 100% efficacy against ZIKV infection, with only a single and non-adjuvanted vaccination. Here, we describe the development of MVA-ZIKV vaccine candidates based on the same Asian lineage sequence as our previous ChAdOx1-ZIKV vaccine candidates. All the MVA-ZIKV vaccines induced modest levels of anti-ZIKV envelope antibodies measured at 4 weeks and 12 weeks post-immunisation. In a ZIKV mice challenge model, two MVA-ZIKV vaccine candidates (Env ΔTM and prME) provided the best, yet partial protection against ZIKV, as shown by the reduction in levels of viraemia in all BALB/c mice, while the rest of the MVA candidates offered a lower degree of reduction in viral load in mice. This study reports that MVA ZIKV vaccine candidates may be a limited candidate for further clinical assessment, if used as a single-vaccination approach.
</p>
