<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>According to the general model developed here, population clustering is an important determinant for the effect of travel restrictions. For high levels of clustering, internal travel restrictions decrease the final size of the epidemic, and this is most prominent in the rural areas. There is no large effect on the peak date for the high clustering levels. For the lower clustering levels, there is less of a benefit in terms of final size reduction. However, for lower clustering levels, the peak date is delayed when implementing internal travel restrictions. That means more time to plan and implement interventions and preventive measures. Internal travel restrictions reduce the peak prevalence for all the clustering levels, reducing the stress on the health care systems. In addition, we found that the higher clustering levels have larger spatial clustering in peak dates. The more spatial clustering in peak dates, the more stress on the health care systems. Whether it is more attractive to delay an epidemic or decrease the final size, depends on the specific influenza strain. If there is high morbidity, such that the patients require more and/or longer health care, it might be of importance to delay the epidemic, to prepare the health care system for the peak period. In addition, if there exists vaccines or other interventions, a delay in the epidemic can be of key importance for the effectiveness of the vaccination programme, since there is more time to distribute (and develop/improve) the vaccine or implement other interventions. The impact of vaccines depends on how early they are introduced (see for instance [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006879.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]). For the European countries we considered (by visual inspection), the minimum clustering level was around 
 <italic>κ</italic> = 0.5, and the highest around 
 <italic>κ</italic> = 3.0, and they will likely become even more clustered in the future. This means that according to our model, internal travel restrictions are likely to be less and less effective in delaying epidemics, while they will be more effective in decreasing final sizes (especially in rural areas). In addition, proximate regions will, to an even higher extent than today, experience their peak simultaneously. Hence, it will be even more important to be able to predict the peak timing, in order to prepare the health care system for the peak period. In addition, in order to minimise the final sizes of the epidemic, it is important not to neglect the urban locations for vaccination, and thus specific vaccination sentiment campaigns might target urban locations.
</p>
