<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The 
 <bold>2016/17 influenza</bold> season differed from the other two seasons by the absolute dominance of one specific influenza A subtype and its evolving subclades (
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Such dominance of a single subtype is only very rarely observed. Sequence analyses revealed substantial heterogeneity in the circulating influenza viruses and showed the emergence of the A(H3N2) genetic subclade 3C.2a1 and its drift variants, not only in Europe (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) but worldwide (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>), revealing an antigenic mismatch to the vaccine strain. The proportion of this newly evolved subclade of the circulating viruses showed regional differences, depending on the start of the influenza season in the different European regions. In the northern parts of Europe, in Sweden and Finland, the influenza season 2016/17 started early in weeks 47/2016 to 49/2016 and peaked already in week 52/2016 (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). In these countries the genetic influenza surveillance revealed the presence of the genetic A(H3N2) subclade 3C.2a1 in 24% of the samples already at the beginning of the season, with an increase to 75% of the circulating viruses in the final weeks 52/2016 to 02/2017 (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). This circulation pattern is in contrast to that observed in Austria, where the influenza season started several weeks later with its peak in week 02/2017. The time dependent spread of the influenza virus activity throughout Europe may explain the differences in the proportion of circulating A(H3N2) genetic subclades in different regions. In Austria 3C.2a1 subclade accounted already for 71% of the circulating influenza viruses at the beginning of the season. This may also partly explain the absence of influenza vaccine protection in Austria, where negative IVEs throughout the season were observed. This differs to data from other countries, where overall IVE's for this season of around 40% have been described (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>–
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Beyond viral genomic variation, birth cohort effects, prior vaccination in addition to the epidemic period may account for regional differences in IVE estimates (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). In this context, the low vaccine coverage in Austria in contrast to that of the other European countries has to be taken into consideration. Nevertheless, detailed analyses of IVEs in Finland and Sweden during the season showed a clear decline in IVEs with increasing proportion of circulating 3C.2a1 viruses [IVE 50% at the start of the season with a drop to 30% at the end (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>)], indicating a correlation between viral changes and the observed decline of IVE estimates. This also demonstrates the strong influence of the antigenic match on the IVE and argues, at least in this case, against waning of vaccine induced immunity.
</p>
