<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Molluscum contagiosum is a viral infection that affects the skin and is caused by the dermatotropic poxvirus molluscum contagiosum virus (MCV) [
 <xref rid="B237-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">237</xref>,
 <xref rid="B238-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">238</xref>]. Unlike smallpox and human monkeypox diseases, MCV is nonlethal, mostly common in children and young adults and present worldwide [
 <xref rid="B237-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">237</xref>,
 <xref rid="B238-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">238</xref>]. However, MCV causes severe skin infections in immunosuppressed adults [
 <xref rid="B237-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">237</xref>,
 <xref rid="B238-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">238</xref>]. A typical feature is the apparition of single or multiple papules on the skin, which may persist for a few years. Most cases resolve in six to nine months without specific treatments [
 <xref rid="B237-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">237</xref>,
 <xref rid="B238-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">238</xref>]. Such a prolonged infection implies that MCV successfully manipulates the host environment. In 1998, the analysis of the MCV genome sequence predicted the presence of a candidate selenoprotein, homologous to mammalian GPX, with 75% amino acid sequence identity with human GPX1 [
 <xref rid="B175-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">175</xref>], see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="nutrients-11-02101-f005">Figure 5</xref>A,B. This viral GPX protein is encoded by 
 <italic>MC066L</italic> gene that presents every features of a selenoprotein gene, i.e., an in-frame UGA codon, a stop codon different from an UGA (in this case UAG), and a SECIS element in the 3’UTR of the mRNA (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="nutrients-11-02101-f005">Figure 5</xref>A). The absence of homologs of this gene in vaccinia and variola viruses suggests that the GPX-like gene was acquired by the MCV after the divergence of the 
 <italic>Molluscipoxvirus</italic> and 
 <italic>Orthopoxvirus</italic> genera. The expression of this predicted selenoprotein was tested experimentally in mammalian cells. Indeed, when a plasmid containing the 
 <italic>MC066L</italic> gene was transfected in human skin cell lines, many evidences supported the insertion of a selenocysteine residue at the UGA codon in the full-length protein, the functionality of the SECIS elements and the cellular antioxidant activity of the MC066L protein [
 <xref rid="B175-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">175</xref>,
 <xref rid="B239-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">239</xref>]. Remarkably, this viral selenoprotein has been shown to be protective for human keratinocytes against cytotoxic effects of UV-irradiation and hydrogen peroxides [
 <xref rid="B175-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">175</xref>,
 <xref rid="B239-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">239</xref>], suggesting an important function for the virus in defending itself against environmental stress and inflammation. How and when this selenoprotein is expressed in the context of viral infection remains poorly investigated. The first transcription map of the MCV genome was provided by the transcriptome sequencing (RNA-seq) of the RNAs synthesized in abortively infected cultured cells and human skin lesions [
 <xref rid="B240-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">240</xref>]. These next generation sequencing experiments showed that MC066L mRNA was only detected in cutaneous lesions, but not in MRC-5, Huh7.5.1 and Vero cells infected 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> by the MCV virus isolated from these same skin lesions. 
</p>
