<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Concerning the three HLA alleles previously reported only in HIV patients other than LTNP, the effect of HLA-B39, which is identified here as a protective allele for the Spanish LTNP cohort, to our knowledge for the first time in association with LTNP, appears to depend on the study, the geographical area or the HIV-infected population. HLA-B39 was described as a risk allele in smaller populations of Argentinian HIV
 <sup>+</sup> subjects [
 <xref rid="pone.0220459.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] and of Indian serodiscordant couples [
 <xref rid="pone.0220459.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], while, more in line with our results, as an allele associated with lower VL in Zambian HIV infected patients [
 <xref rid="pone.0220459.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. The second allele associated in this cohort for the first time with LTNP, HLA-A24, is described here as an unfavorable allele for the LTNP condition, and it was also early associated with rapid CD4 T lymphocyte decline [
 <xref rid="pone.0220459.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] and with susceptibility in adults [
 <xref rid="pone.0220459.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], promoting selection of cytotoxic T-lymphocyte escape variants in Japan [
 <xref rid="pone.0220459.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0220459.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Whether the detrimental role of HLA-A24 for LTNP described here in the Spanish population is related to T-lymphocyte escape also in LTNP patients is currently unknown and warrants investigation. Finally, HLA-B18 was the strongest and most significant detrimental factor for the Spanish LTNP population. This HLA allele has been widely studied in HIV infected populations other than LTNP, and its favorable [
 <xref rid="pone.0220459.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0220459.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] or risk [
 <xref rid="pone.0220459.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0220459.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] contribution to diverse aspects of HIV disease is variable and at least seems to depend on the virus clade.
</p>
