<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par31">The high mortality of males due to COVID-19 raises the question whether males are more vulnerable than females. Males show higher mortality from diseases including heart disease, diabetes, liver disease, and cancer [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Since these diseases are known to show sex-specific occurrence [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>], they could be contributing factors for the sex-biased mortality from COVID-19. For instance, the male mortality in Italy was reported to be high compared to China and this is suggested to be due to a higher prevalence of cardiovascular diseases in Italian men [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. The differences between males and females are observed not only in disease susceptibility but also in early development during infancy, endurance towards stress conditions, and overall life expectancy [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Sex differences are observed in life expectancy, with females outliving males by almost 7 years in some countries [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. This difference in life expectancy may be due to sex-related differences including hormonal milieu, genetics, and other physiological traits. Pieces of evidence indicate that females can outlive males even in harsh climate including famine [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. The 1772–1773 famine in Sweden dropped the life expectancy of males to 17.15 years while it was 18.79 years for females. The Irish famine (1845–1849) dropped life expectancy to 18.7 years for men and 22.4 years for women. The Ukrainian famine in 1993 dropped the life expectancy of males from 41.58 to 7.3 years and 45.93 to 10.9 for females [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Other historical events also suggest that endurance levels to cope up with stressful conditions are low in males compared to females. The freed American slaves’ journey back to Africa in 1820–1843 resulted in high mortality with 43% death rate in the first year. The life expectancy at birth was 1.68 years for males and 2.23 years for females [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. The measles outbreak in Iceland (1845–1849) also showed sex-specific mortality. The average life expectancy dropped from 37.62 years to 16.76 for males and 43.99 years to 18.83 years for females [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>].
</p>
