<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0020">The pathology of SARS-CoV-2 is not yet completely understood; most of our knowledge has been based on research into SARS-CoV and MERS, which previously caused epidemics of acute respiratory syndromes. In this short duration of the present pandemic, studies have shown that SARS-CoV-2 has several defense mechanisms, which makes its eradication more difficult. The SARS-CoV-2 envelope includes attached proteins like M (membrane), S (spike), E (envelope), and N (nucleocapsid). Similar to other coronaviruses, the N protein of SARS-CoV-2 inhibits IFN1 by regulating IFN-β synthesis and signaling. On the other hand, the effectiveness of the innate immune response against viral infection depends mainly on IFN1 production and its downstream signaling that results in controlling viral replication and induction of an adequate adaptive immune response [
 <xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. However the virus could avoid this attack due to the complex immune dysregulation caused by this infection. Chronic stimulation of T cells, resulting in a cytokine storm and T cell exhaustion, weakens the overall body defenses and puts the patient in a dangerous situation. High-grade chronic viral infections result in CD8+ T cell exhaustion (Tex) leading to a decreased effector function and lower proliferative capacity. Tex leads to over-expression of inhibitory receptors, including CD279 (PD-1), a lymphoid cell surface protein of the Ig superfamily, and a member of the extended CD28/CTLA-4 family of T cell regulators, which act as a mature T cell checkpoint for the modulation of apoptosis. PD-1 can bind to either of its ligands (PD-L1[CD274] and PD-L2[CD273]) both members of B7 family of T cell co-receptors. This binding causes significant suppression of the immune system by affecting T cells, as well as B cells and NK cells [
 <xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Another important observation is the strong correlation between inflammatory markers, including ESR, CRP and IL-6, and the relevant subset of lymphocytes [
 <xref rid="bb0130" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Overall, general lymphopenia is seen in COVID-19 patients, especially in severe cases [
 <xref rid="bb0135" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0140" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].
</p>
