<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Experimental evidence of the role of these infection traits in virus seed transmission is scarce. Plant genes involved in the efficiency of virus seed transmission have been identified only in soybean (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). In this host, 
 <italic>Soybean mosaic virus</italic> seed transmission is controlled by plant gene homologs of 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">Arabidopsis thaliana</named-content>
 <italic>DCL3</italic> and 
 <italic>RDR6</italic>, which are involved in small RNA-mediated gene silencing (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Similarly, virus seed transmission determinants have been analyzed in only a few species. Genetic variation in 
 <italic>Barley stripe mosaic virus</italic> (BSMV), 
 <italic>Cucumber mosaic virus</italic> (CMV), and 
 <italic>Pea seed-borne mosaic virus</italic> genes encoding the replicase and movement proteins has been associated with the efficiency of seed transmission (
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). This would be compatible with a role of virus multiplication, virulence, and movement. However, whether (and how) infection traits affect the efficiency of seed transmission has been seldom analyzed, and with contradictory results. Pagán et al. (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) showed that reduced CMV virulence and within-host multiplication were associated with an increased efficiency of seed transmission in 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">Arabidopsis thaliana</named-content>. Stewart et al. (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) also reported a negative correlation between BSMV virulence and the efficiency of virus seed transmission in barley, but no link to virus multiplication was detected. These works studied the effect of infection traits on the efficiency of seed transmission using univariate analyses. However, during infection, virus multiplication, movement, and reduction of plant fitness occur simultaneously, such that the efficiency of seed transmission would be determined by their combined (and not necessarily equally important) effects (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). To date, such multivariate effects have not been analyzed, and the infection traits associated with virus seed transmission (and their relative importance) are still poorly understood (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>).
</p>
