<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Selenium is an essential trace element for mammalian redox biology. Numerous epidemiological studies have revealed an association between selenium deficiencies and the increased risks of developing several pathologies, including cancers, neurogenerative diseases, cardiovascular disorders and infectious diseases [
 <xref rid="B1-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The ability of selenium supplementation to reverse or reduce these risks has been reported in many human or animal models although it remains controversial [
 <xref rid="B14-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Unlike other trace elements that act as cofactors, selenium is covalently bound to organic molecules. Most of the beneficial effects of selenium is due to its incorporation in the form of selenocysteine into an essential group of proteins that are called selenoproteins. Selenocysteine is the 21st proteinogenic amino acid and is encoded by an UGA codon which is normally the signal for termination of protein synthesis [
 <xref rid="B15-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Selenocysteine is a structural and functional analog of cysteine in which a selenium atom replaces sulfur to confer an enhanced catalytic activity. Amongst the twenty-five selenoprotein genes identified to date, several have important cellular functions in antioxidant defense, cell signaling and redox homeostasis [
 <xref rid="B24-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Within the well characterized selenoproteins we find the following sub-families: Glutathione peroxidase (GPX1–GPX4 and GPX6) that reduce hydrogen and lipid peroxides [
 <xref rid="B25-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], thioredoxin reductases (TXNRD1–TXNRD3) which are essentials in the homeostasis of thiol systems [
 <xref rid="B26-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], methionine sulfoxide reductase (MSRB1) [
 <xref rid="B30-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] and selenoproteins located in the endoplasmic reticulum (DIO2, SELENOF, SELENOK, SELENOM, SELENON, SELENOS and SELENOT) exhibit important functions in protein folding and in the endoplasmic reticulum stress response [
 <xref rid="B31-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The other half of the selenoproteome remains without a, yet, defined function. Selenoproteins are present in many organelles or cellular compartments, with a specific tissue distribution and sensitivity to selenium level changes. Selenoproteins are therefore important components of antioxidant defense systems maintaining redox homeostasis, which also include catalase (CAT), superoxide dismutase (SOD), glutathione (GSH), vitamin E, carotenoids, and ascorbic acid.
</p>
