<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="pone.0239899.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0239899.g003</object-id>
 <label>Fig 3</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Effect of PB2 variants on RNP activity and NP-binding.</title>
  <p>(A) Polymerase activity measured by luciferase reporter assay. Plasmids encoding wild-type or mutant PB2, PA, PB1, NP (ie. pcDNA-PA, pcDNA-PB1, pcDNA-PB2 and pcDNA-NP) were co-transfected with a plasmid expressing luciferase reporter gene under viral promoter control, pPOLI-Luc-RT and a plasmid expressing GFP, pEGFP were transfected to HEK 293T, pcDNA3 was used to replace pcDNA-PB2 as negative control. The overall polymerase activity is represented by a ratio of luminescence signal to GFP signal. The activity of polymerase with wild-type PB2 was set to 1. The bar represents the mean ratio ± standard errors from three independent experiments. *The p-values are smaller or equal to 0.05 in two-tailed Student’s 
   <italic>t</italic>-test. (B) Protein expression of PB2 and mutants. Level of PB2 expression of each mutant was detected by anti-PB2 polyclonal antibodies in Western blotting with ß-actin as loading control. (C) Co-immunoprecipitation of NP and cap-binding domain. Myc-tagged PB2 cap-binding domain and variants were co-transfected and expressed with NP in HEK 293 cells. Myc-tagged empty vector was used as negative control. Co-immunoprecipitation was performed after 48-hour incubation, cell lysates were incubated overnight with or without anti-myc antibody. Expression levels of myc-tagged PB2 cap-binding domain and variants were detected by anti-myc antibody, while anti-NP serum was used to detect NP expression level in the cells. Amounts of NP precipitated by cap-binding domain variants in Co-immunoprecipitation were compared to that precipitated from the wild-type. The bar represents the mean ratio ± standard errors from three independent experiments. *The p-values are smaller or equal to 0.05 in two-tailed Student’s 
   <italic>t</italic>-test.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="pone.0239899.g003" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
