<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract abstract-type="executive-summary">
 <title>eLife digest</title>
 <p>Mosquitoes can transmit viruses that cause Zika, dengue and several other tropical diseases that affect humans. Zika virus usually causes mild symptoms, but it is thought that infection during pregnancy can lead to brain abnormalities, including microcephaly, where babies are born with an abnormally small head. Recent studies have shed light on how the Zika virus spread from Africa to reach South America, the Caribbean and North America. However, much less is known about the ecological factors that contribute to the spread of the virus within towns, cities and other local areas.</p>
 <p>In 2015, Brazil was struck by an outbreak of the Zika virus that led to an international public health emergency. Lourenço et al. used a mathematical model to explore the local conditions within Feira de Santana (a major urban center in Brazil) that contributed to the outbreak. The model took into account numerous factors, including temperature, humidity, rainfall and the mosquito life-cycle, which made it possible to reconstruct the history of the virus over the past three years and to make projections for the next decades.</p>
 <p>It revealed that most of the infections occured during 2015, with approximately 65% of the population infected. The incidences of new infections declined in 2016, as increasing numbers of local people had already been exposed to the virus and became immune. Temperature and humidity appeared to have played a critical role in sustaining the mosquito population carrying the Zika virus.</p>
 <p>Further analysis suggests that the risk of Zika virus causing microcephaly is very low – only 0.3–0.5% of the pregnant women in Feira de Santana who were infected with Zika gave birth to a baby with the condition. What therefore makes Zika a public health concern is the combination of a low risk with very high infection rates, which can affect a large number of pregnancies.</p>
 <p>This study will help researchers and policy makers to predict how the Zika virus will behave in the coming years. It also highlights the limitations and successes of the current system of surveillance. Moreover, it will help to identify critical time periods in the year when mosquito control strategies should be implemented to limit the spread of this virus. In future, this could help shape new local strategies to control Zika virus, dengue and other diseases carried by mosquitoes.</p>
</abstract>
