<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>All data were analyzed using R version 3.3.2, and PAST 3.20 statistical packages. There were marked variations in the number of bacterial sequences between mosquito samples (Mean ± SE = 27,796.01 ± 2,229.73 per mosquito, minimum = 5, maximum = 164,228). Only samples with at least 900 sequences (n = 143) were used for downstream analysis in R. Rarefaction curves for entire dataset were generated using “
 <italic>phyloseq</italic>” [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007361.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. For additional analysis, OTUs accounting for less than 0.005% of the total sequences were discarded. Venn diagrams to visualize the OTUs that were shared between mosquito species and study sites were created using “
 <italic>limma</italic>” [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007361.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The difference in 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>mcintoshi</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>ochraceus</italic> OTUs that were shared across study sites were compared using Fisher’s exact test implemented in the package 
 <italic>RVAideMemoire</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007361.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Alpha diversity metrics for each sample including Shannon diversity index, observed OTUs (richness) and Chao1 were computed using 
 <italic>vegan</italic> package after rarefying all samples to an even depth of 900 sequences [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007361.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. We compared the relative OTU abundances across sites for each species using chi square good-ness-of-fit test implemented in the package 
 <italic>RVAideMemoire</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007361.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Multiple pairwise comparisons across sites was performed using adjusted 
 <italic>P</italic> after 
 <italic>false discovery rate</italic> (
 <italic>fdr</italic>) correction [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007361.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Non-parametric Scheirer-Ray-Hare test was used to test for statistical significance and Wilcoxon rank sum test with Bonferroni correction for multiple comparisons was used to establish treatments that were significantly different. For beta diversity, we used unrarefied data as suggested by [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007361.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. To minimize sampling bias, we transformed the raw dataset into proportion representing relative contribution of each OTU. This simple normalization provides a simple representation of the count data as a relative abundance measure [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007361.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Non-metric multidimensional scaling (NMDS) with Bray-Curtis dissimilarity metric was then performed in R package “
 <italic>phyloseq</italic>” [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007361.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] to visualize the effect of site and mosquito species on bacterial communities [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007361.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Results of NMDS were confirmed using analysis of similarities test (ANOSIM) with 9,999 permutations using PAST. Indicator species analysis was conducted using the R package ‘
 <italic>labdsv</italic>’ [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007361.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] to identify the bacterial OTUs that characterized each mosquito species based on fidelity and specificity [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007361.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Only OTUs with an indicator value ≥ 60% were considered significant.
</p>
