<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is well known that IgG subclasses (IgG1, IgG2, IgG3, and IgG4) present varied affinities to different FcγR, resulting in different immune responses. In this context, experimental results with SARS‐CoV suggest that FcγRIIa and FcγRIIb, but not FcγRI and FcγRIII, promote ADE (
 <xref rid="cytoa24047-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="cytoa24047-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">34</xref>). Moreover, polymorphisms in FcγRIIa correlated with SARS‐CoV severity (
 <xref rid="cytoa24047-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">35</xref>). The allelic polymorphism, in a single G or A nucleotide, results in an arginine (R) or histidine (H) at residue 131 of the Ig binding domain of FcγRIIa. This polymorphism modifies receptor affinity and specificity to the binding of different IgG subclasses. It has been demonstrated that this polymorphism affects susceptibility or severity of several infections, including 
 <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> infections, dengue fever, HIV infection, and SARS infection (
 <xref rid="cytoa24047-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">35</xref>, 
 <xref rid="cytoa24047-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">36</xref>, 
 <xref rid="cytoa24047-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">37</xref>, 
 <xref rid="cytoa24047-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">38</xref>). In fact, FcγRIIa‐R131 polymorphism seems to have clinical implication in SARS‐CoV pathology and possibly ADE. Yuan and co‐workers availed 180 infected patients and 200 controls and observed a correlation between the FcγRIIa‐R/R131 (homozygotes) and severe SARS‐CoV (patients requiring treatment in an intensive care unit) (
 <xref rid="cytoa24047-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">35</xref>). Thus, individual composition of cellular expression of polymorphic variants of FcγRII, which can vary with geographic region and ethnicity (
 <xref rid="cytoa24047-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">39</xref>), could define susceptibility to SARS‐CoV, COVID‐19 severity, and ADE (
 <xref rid="cytoa24047-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">34</xref>, 
 <xref rid="cytoa24047-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">35</xref>).
</p>
