<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0335">Reverse genetic systems or minigenome assays have proven to be valuable models to study RNA virus replication and transcription. This model system is used to screen and identify antivirals 
 <xref rid="bib0285" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0290" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>. Replication competent minigenome systems wherein some of the viral open reading frame is replaced with a reporter gene (GFP or luciferase) and the cDNA copy cloned into a plasmid is cotransfected into mammalian cells with individual plasmids each containing a viral ribonucleoprotein (RNP). The target genes in the expression vectors are under the control of either a mammalian RNA polymerase I or II or T7 RNA polymerase (which will require transfection of a plasmid containing the T7 RNA polymerase) promoters. Following transcription, the resulting viral RNA is complexed with the RNP components and there is subsequent replication of the virus genome and expression of the reporter protein. Minigenome systems have been developed for several biothreat pathogens, including filoviruses, arenaviruses, and bunyaviruses, and have been used to screen and identify small molecule inhibitors of filovirus and arenavirus replication 
 <xref rid="bib0285" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0290" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0295" ref-type="bibr">[58]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0300" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0305" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>. To study the viral assembly and budding, another surrogate model that can be used is based on virus-like particles (VLPs) that are mimics of viral protein assemblies made by reconstituting the viral recombinant structural proteins. VLPs are noninfectious as they do not contain any viral genome, but are intrinsically immunogenic, and hence are being extensively investigated as potential vaccine candidates 
 <xref rid="bib0310" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>. In the case of the EBOV VLP-based assay, cotransfection of plasmids encoding the viral GP and the matrix protein (VP40) results in spontaneous formation of filamentous VLPs that are released into the medium and can be quantitated by ELISA 
 <xref rid="bib0315" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>; thus this model can be useful in drug discovery research 
 <xref rid="bib0320" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref>. 
</p>
