<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since the discovery of broadly neutralizing Abs against HA stem [
 <xref rid="pone.0204776.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] a number of attempts have been performed to construct universal stem-based influenza vaccines. One direction of investigations is targeted to design the trimeric mini-stem constructs being able to bind conformational Abs and protect mice from lethal influenza virus challenge [
 <xref rid="pone.0204776.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0204776.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The constructs described are notably longer than tri-stalk protein and contain either intermolecular disulfide bridge, or trimerization (foldon) motif to stabilize the structure. At this stage, our aim was not to outperform these proteins in terms of protection, but to produce an alternative variant in a cost-effective way to be applied in several immune assays for evaluating the future universal vaccine-induced response. While tri-stalk protein is only 72 aa long, it is promising candidate for exposition on the surface of VLPs which is a highly powerful platform for vaccine construction. Incorporation of the LAH within the major immunodominant loop of the hepatitis B core protein allows formation of chimeric VLPs [
 <xref rid="pone.0204776.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0204776.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], however, anchoring of both LAH ends prevents folding of native trimeric conformation. Nevertheless, this strategy led to strong seroconversion to both HA group antigens in mice [
 <xref rid="pone.0204776.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] while immunization with tri-stalk protein alone generated Abs only against homologous group HA antigen (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0204776.s004">S4 Fig</xref>). Ideally, both approaches should be combined to obtain possible synergistic effect. Genetic fusion of LAH-encoding sequence with N- or C-termini of a carrier protein gene would theoretically allow such assembly. Among large variety of carriers coat proteins of small RNA phages organized in simple 
 <italic>T</italic> = 3 symmetry particles offer an attractive scaffold for exposition of trimeric proteins in their native form, since N- and C- terminal ends of the phage coat protein are arranged closely around quasi-threefold axis of 
 <italic>T</italic> = 3 particle. Although we failed to expose LAH peptide on the surface of PP7 VLPs (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0204776.s001">S1 Fig</xref>), it could be speculated that this chimeric protein at least partially assembles in trimeric structures capable to elicit potent immune responses (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0204776.s002">S2 Fig</xref>). This assembly is, however, hard to prove due to irregularity of LAH-VLP aggregates (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0204776.s001">S1 Fig</xref>).
</p>
