<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015">A 9-year-old male patient was hospitalized due to having had a fever for three days. The child had no obvious inducement of fever three days before this. His temperature was as high as 38.9 °C, and he presented no chill or shivering, cough, sputum or sore throat, chest tightness or chest pain, acid reflux, nausea, abdominal pain or diarrhea, dizziness or headaches, or breathing cyanosis, and no weakness or muscle ache. The patient had lived in Wuhan for a long time. There was also no clear history of exposure to patients infected with SARS-CoV-2. He was in good health and denied a history of food and drug allergies. Routine blood examination in the external hospital showed: leukocyte 13.07 × 10
 <sup>9</sup>/L, erythrocyte 4.25 × 10
 <sup>12</sup>/L, neutrophil ratio 72.71%, lymphocyte ratio 16.12%, absolute value of lymphocyte 2.1 × 10
 <sup>9</sup>/L, influenza A and B pathogen detection were negative. A chest X-ray did not find any obvious abnormality in either lung. The patient was given "oral administration of cattilan and intravenous drip of lysine acetylsalicylate injection" for one day (the specific dosage is unknown), and no fever occurred. The child was sent to hospital by his parents for further diagnosis and treatment. Because the child had lived in Wuhan two weeks before the onset of the disease and had a fever, SARS-CoV-2 infection was not excluded. During patient admission examination: T 36.6 °C, P 100 times/min, R 20 times/min, BP 100/65 mmHg, no congestion in the pharynx, no swelling of the tonsils, clear breath sounds in either lung, and no obvious dry and wet rales were recorded. Routine blood examination after admission was conducted with the following results: white blood cell 4.22 × 10
 <sup>9</sup>/L, red blood cell 3.80 × 10
 <sup>12</sup>/L, hemoglobin 118.00 g/L, platelet 363.00 × 10
 <sup>9</sup>/L, neutrophil percentage 37.40%, lymphocyte percentage 53.80%. Novel coronavirus nucleic acids testing was positive. Results for biochemical examination are: lactate dehydrogenase 69U/L↑, α-hydroxybutyrate dehydrogenase 258U/L↑, creatine kinase 139U/L, creatine kinase isoenzyme 41U/L, C- reactive protein 15.2 mg/L↑, serum amyloid &gt;300 mg/L↑, procalcitonin 0.28 ng/mL (see 
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> ).
</p>
