<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0085">For viruses, one of the key steps in the emergence process is the jump between one host species and humans. (For other kinds of pathogens, there may be other sources of human exposure, notably environmental sources or the normally commensal skin or gut flora.) Various factors have been examined in terms of their relationship with a pathogen’s ability to jump into a new host species; these include taxonomic relatedness of the hosts, geographical overlap, and host range. The roles of both host relatedness and geographical proximity have been clearly established. Experimentally associations between the degree of cross-species transmission of bat lyssaviruses and both the geographical overlap between bat populations across the United States and the phylogenetically relatedness of the bat species involved have been established. Primate species tended to share more parasitic species if they were both more closely related and had sympatric distributions. A broad host range is also associated with the likelihood of a pathogen emerging or reemerging in human populations. An illustrative case study is bovine spongiform encephalopathy (BSE). After BSE’s emergence in the 1980s, well before it was found to infect humans as Variant Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (vCJD), it rapidly became apparent that it could infect a wide range of hosts, including carnivores. This was in marked contrast to a much more familiar prion disease, scrapie, which was naturally restricted to sheep and goats. With hindsight, this observation might have led to public health concerns about BSE being raised earlier than they were. Host range is a highly variable trait among viruses: some, such as rabies, can infect a very wide range of mammals; others, such as mumps, specialize on a single species (humans). Moreover, for pathogens generally, host range seems to be phylogenetically labile, with even closely related species having very different host ranges. Hence, the biological basis of host range is relevant to understanding pathogen emergence (
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Jones et al., 2008</xref>).
</p>
