<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20">Interferons (IFNs) are a multigene family of inducible cytokines that possess antiviral activity. The IFN system comprises the cells synthesizing IFN in response to an external stimulus, such as viral infection, and cells that respond to IFN by establishing the antiviral state. They represent an early host defence, the one that occurs prior to the immune response onset. IFNs are classified as IFN-α and IFN-β, which are produced by the cell in response to virus infection, and IFN-γ, synthetized upon antigen or mitogen stimulation (Samuel 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">2001</xref>). Their activity has been reported against a number of feline viruses, including feline calicivirus (FCV), where they act by stimulating downstream genes such as 2′-5′oligoadenylate-dependent ribonuclease L (RNase L), which degrades single-stranded viral RNAs. Also, feline IRF-1, shown to be reduced upon FCV infection, has been reported to positively regulate IFN signalling by triggering the production of endogenous IFN and the expression of downstream targeted genes (Liu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2018</xref>). As mentioned before, another feline virus reported for IFN therapeutic solutions is FIV. The best known among them, recombinant RFeIFN-ω, is the first interferon compound that has been licensed for use in veterinary medicine, shown to significantly increase levels of acute phase proteins (APPs) (Doménech et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2011</xref>). RFeIFN-ω has also been reported for anti-inflammatory properties, exerted via interleukin-6 (IL-6) (Leal et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2015</xref>). Recombinant human interferon alpha-2b (rHuIFN-alpha2b) and recombinant feline interferon omega (RFeIFN-omega) have also exhibited an antiviral effect against feline herpesvirus (FHV)-1 in in vitro settings, as evidenced by significant reduction in plaque size (Siebeck et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">2006</xref>). Interferons also showed therapeutic potential against feline leukaemia virus (FeLV), with recombinant feline interferon RFeIFN-omega, resulting in improvement of clinical signs and survival of infected cats (de Mari et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2004</xref>).
</p>
