<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par10">Altogether in the African lineage eight mosquitoes were isolated, while P6-740 was the only mosquito isolated in the Asian lineage (Malaysia/1966). In 2007, ZIKV was identified in patients infected with 
 <italic>Aedes aldopictus</italic> mosquitoes from West Africa [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. However, the 
 <italic>Aedes (stregomyia) hensilli</italic> identified as the probable principal vector that cause Micronesia outbreak [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Later on, in 2013, the ZIKV spread out to French Polynesia, with consequent extent to Oceanian islands (New Caledonia, Cook islands, and Easter island), was mostly related with 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Aedes aldopictus</italic> species [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. The major symptoms such as rash, low-grade fever, arthralgia, conjunctivitis and GBS (Guillain–Barré syndrome) were observed in 11% of the total population [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Furthermore, in Central-South America, 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> is considered as the utmost common vector for DENV [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Later on in 2006, Chouin-Carneiro reported that the New World strains of 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> which found to be poor transmitters of ZIKV results in continuous divergence of the Asian lineage [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. These strains adopted alternative mode of transmission i.e. direct human to human transmission without the involvement of a vector. Indeed, while 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> is widely accepted as the vector for ZIKV [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>], Guedes et al. has revealed that ZIKV can infect and replicate in the salivary glands, midgut, and was also spotted in saliva of 
 <italic>Culex</italic> species [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Altogether this work suggests that the transmission vector range for ZIKV may be larger than foreseen (although still a debatable topic demanding more exploration).
</p>
