<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0039">Midwives and nurses in this review reported heightened levels of stress and tension amid the epidemics and pandemics. A review that analyzed 30 studies reported that midwives and midwifery students are at high risks of feeling stressed due to occupational and organizational sources (
 <xref rid="bib0302" ref-type="bibr">Pezaro, 2016</xref>). Hence, midwives and nurses from maternity units may experience exponential stress levels during public health emergencies. Future studies from different geographical regions should examine this phenomenon to present a global representation of midwives’ and nurses’ psychosocial needs. As occupational stress has been found to be detrimental to both physical and mental health (
 <xref rid="bib0302" ref-type="bibr">Pezaro, 2016</xref>), necessary initiatives need to be implemented to support midwives and nurses in maternity units. The focus of the interventions should be on prioritizing self-care and emotional wellbeing, providing psychologically safe working cultures, and promoting interprofessional support (
 <xref rid="bib0302" ref-type="bibr">Pezaro, 2016</xref>). Especially during epidemics and pandemics, interventions such as mindfulness-based therapy, resilience workshops, and provisions of clinical supervision and support may be beneficial and should be evaluated further. As time is of essence during epidemics and pandemics, short interventions maybe more practical and useful. Brief mindfulness exercises (i.e. five-minute sessions) for healthcare providers have shown effectiveness in instilling positive changes in levels of stress, resiliency, burnout symptoms, anxiety, and mindfulness (
 <xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">Gilmartin et al., 2017</xref>). Hence, brief mindfulness exercises can be integrated into workflows for midwives and nurses and even for other healthcare professionals of maternity units to benefit from these quick exercises and to calibrate their minds to maintain their psychological wellbeing during public health crises.
</p>
