<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0041">Families can be educated through online materials that are made readily available and accessible by healthcare leaders (e.g. WHO) on pregnancy-related topics during COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="bib0054" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2020</xref>d). These online materials can also be accessed by spouses and extended families who may be stranded in different parts of the world to help them to understand the situations better and enable them to empathize with and support pregnant women during crises. Future studies can evaluate telecommunicating platforms to cater to the needs of pregnant women and their families during and beyond public health crises. Awareness within a community and relevant support such as financial support to the needy are also essential to maintain the cohesiveness of the community. 
 <xref rid="bib0303" ref-type="bibr">Zuo and Liu (2014)</xref> analyzed an epidemic model in which the effect of awareness programs that were driven by media on the prevalence of an infectious disease was examined. The results revealed that increasing the dissemination rate of information and the implementation rate of safety measures, such as safe distancing and providing economic support where needed, can reduce proportions of infective populations and enhance compliance rates with safety measures, hence controlling the widespread of outbreaks (
 <xref rid="bib0303" ref-type="bibr">Zuo and Liu, 2014</xref>). Therefore, policy makers and health systems can collaborate to create awareness programs and educational programs, monitor the disseminations and implementations of various programmes to inform pregnant women, their families, and the population. For developing countries, these resources may be limited, and consensus and mutual support within families through shared experiences and open communications is encouraged to help pregnant women through epidemics and pandemics. Trained paraprofessionals such as community volunteers can also reach out to pregnant women and their families to provide easy-to-understand information and emotional support by simply being there as listening buddies (
 <xref rid="bib0305" ref-type="bibr">Shorey et al., 2019</xref>).
</p>
