<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<contrib-group>
 <contrib contrib-type="author">
  <name>
   <surname>Perez-Guzman</surname>
   <given-names>Pablo Noel</given-names>
  </name>
  <aff>Department of Global Health and Tropical Medicine, University of Oxford, UK; Department of Infectious Disease Epidemiology, Imperial College, London, UK</aff>
 </contrib>
 <contrib contrib-type="author">
  <name>
   <surname>Carlos Junior Alcantara</surname>
   <given-names>Luiz</given-names>
  </name>
  <aff>Laboratory of Haematology, Genetics and Computational Biology, FIOCRUZ, Brazil</aff>
 </contrib>
 <contrib contrib-type="author">
  <name>
   <surname>Obolski</surname>
   <given-names>Uri</given-names>
  </name>
  <aff>Department of Zoology, University of Oxford, UK</aff>
 </contrib>
 <contrib contrib-type="author">
  <name>
   <surname>de Lima</surname>
   <given-names>Maricelia M.</given-names>
  </name>
  <aff>Laboratory of Haematology, Genetics and Computational Biology, FIOCRUZ, Brazil</aff>
 </contrib>
 <contrib contrib-type="author">
  <name>
   <surname>Ashley</surname>
   <given-names>Elizabeth A.</given-names>
  </name>
  <aff>Myanmar-Oxford Clinical Research Unit, Yangon; Centre for Tropical Medicine and Global Health, Nuffield Department of Medicine, University of Oxford, UK</aff>
 </contrib>
 <contrib contrib-type="author">
  <name>
   <surname>Smithuis</surname>
   <given-names>Frank</given-names>
  </name>
  <aff>Myanmar-Oxford Clinical Research Unit, Yangon; Nuffield Department of Medicine, University of Oxford, UK; Centre for Tropical Medicine and Global Health, Nuffield Department of Medicine, University of Oxford, UK</aff>
 </contrib>
 <contrib contrib-type="author">
  <name>
   <surname>Horby</surname>
   <given-names>Peter</given-names>
  </name>
  <aff>Nuffield Department of Medicine, University of Oxford, UK</aff>
 </contrib>
 <contrib contrib-type="author">
  <name>
   <surname>Maude</surname>
   <given-names>Richard J.</given-names>
  </name>
  <aff>Nuffield Department of Medicine, University of Oxford, UK; Centre for Tropical Medicine and Global Health, Nuffield Department of Medicine, University of Oxford, UK; Mahidol-Oxford Tropical Medicine Research Unit, Faculty of Tropical Medicine, Mahidol University,Thailand; Harvard TH Chan School of Public Health, Harvard University, Boston, USA</aff>
 </contrib>
 <contrib contrib-type="author">
  <name>
   <surname>Lin</surname>
   <given-names>Zaw</given-names>
  </name>
  <aff>Myanmar Ministry of Health and Sports, Naypyidaw, Myanmar</aff>
 </contrib>
 <contrib contrib-type="author">
  <name>
   <surname>Kyaw</surname>
   <given-names>Aye Mon Mon</given-names>
  </name>
  <aff>Myanmar Ministry of Health and Sports, Naypyidaw, Myanmar</aff>
 </contrib>
 <contrib contrib-type="author">
  <name>
   <surname>Lourenço</surname>
   <given-names>José</given-names>
  </name>
  <aff>Department of Zoology, University of Oxford, Oxford, UK</aff>
 </contrib>
</contrib-group>
