<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Pedestrian crowds are commonly observed in all public locations offering entertainment, transportation, social or religious activities. The mass gathering of people congregated in limited space often elevates the risk of infectious disease spread due to the increased contacts between susceptible and infectious individuals. Further, individuals with different levels of vulnerability and receptivity due to variations in genetic background and intervention usage often congregate in touristic sites [
 <xref rid="pone.0235891.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. There is direct evidence for the occurrence of multiple epidemic outbreaks in high pedestrian density locations such as transportation hubs, entertainment venues, (e.g. theme parks, stadiums) and mass gatherings [
 <xref rid="pone.0235891.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0235891.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Gautret and Steffen [
 <xref rid="pone.0235891.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] report that sixty-eight cited instances of outbreaks among crowds occurred between 1980 and 2016. Numerous reports deal with the spread of diseases like influenza, SARS, and measles during air travel [
 <xref rid="pone.0235891.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0235891.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Examples of epidemics in entertainment venues include the influenza outbreak in 2002 during the winter Olympiad [
 <xref rid="pone.0235891.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] and the measles outbreak in Disney World in 2016 resulting in 125 cases [
 <xref rid="pone.0235891.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Several outbreaks of directly transmitted gastrointestinal and respiratory diseases have been reported in religious and social outdoor mass gatherings [
 <xref rid="pone.0235891.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0235891.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], international meetings [
 <xref rid="pone.0235891.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0235891.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] and concert halls [
 <xref rid="pone.0235891.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].
</p>
