<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0210">Rolf Hilgenfeld et al. previously revealed that the peptidomimetic α-ketoamide inhibitor 
 <bold>24</bold> serves as a broad-spectrum inhibitor of the 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup>s of β-coronaviruses, α-coronaviruses and enteroviruses [
 <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Compound 
 <bold>24</bold> exhibits a low EC
 <sub>50</sub> for SARS-CoV and a number of enteroviruses in different cell lines (EC
 <sub>50</sub> &lt; 5 μM); notably, the EC
 <sub>50</sub> of MERS-CoV in Huh7 cells is 400 pM. The lead 
 <bold>24</bold> has been subjected to various structural modifications [
 <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. To improve its half-life in plasma, compound 
 <bold>24</bold> was modified by hiding the P3–P2 amide bond on the pyridone ring (
 <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> , green circle), which is expected to prevent off-target contacts and the cleavage of this bond by other cellular proteases. In addition, to enhance the solubility of 
 <bold>24</bold> in plasma, the hydrophobic cinnamyl was replaced by a low-hydrophobic Boc group (
 <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, red circle), which produced 
 <bold>25</bold>. Moreover, the cyclohexyl at P2 of 
 <bold>25</bold> was substituted for the smaller cyclopropyl (
 <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, blue circle) to render 
 <bold>26</bold>, which might show enhanced antiviral activity against the β-coronaviruses of clade b (SARS-CoV-2 and SARS-CoV). However, compound 
 <bold>27</bold>, which was obtained by removal of the Boc group of 
 <bold>26</bold>, was almost inactive (
 <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, purple circle), which indicated that the hydrophobic group is necessary for crossing the cell membrane and binding to viral 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup>. A pharmacokinetics study demonstrated that 4 h after its subcutaneous administration, the lung tissue concentration of 
 <bold>26</bold> is approximately 13 ng/g. The lung tropism of 
 <bold>26</bold> was a favourable target organ aggregation characteristic because COVID-19 and other coronaviruses mostly affect lung tissue. As a complementary route of administration, 
 <bold>26</bold> can also be nebulized with an inhalation device at 3 mg/kg. Even 24 h after its administration, the concentration of 
 <bold>26</bold> in lung tissue remains at 33 ng/g. A mouse lung drug inhalation model showed that 
 <bold>26</bold> is well tolerated without adverse reactions, which indicates that inhalers might be a suitable method for the administration of 
 <bold>26</bold>. The other peptidomimetic inhibitors shown in 
 <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> and 
 <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> were described in detail in a previous review by Thanigaimalai Pillaiyar et al. [
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>].
</p>
