<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our model suggests a significantly stronger advantage to youth-focused TasP than what one might infer from previous modeling studies by Alsallaq 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007561.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] and Bershteyn 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007561.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. This is due to several factors. First, we included age-related risk factors (declines in coital frequency and per-act transmission rates with age) that were not included in these previous models. It may also be explained, in part, by differences in the groups being modeled. Alsallaq 
 <italic>et al</italic>. modeled the effects of prioritizing people under the age of 25. In the absence of other age-related risks, our "under age 30" and "under age 35" strategies outperform our "under age 25" strategy (
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007561.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, perturbation 14). We speculate Alsallaq 
 <italic>et al</italic>. would have seen larger benefits had they extended their target age to 30. Bershteyn 
 <italic>et al</italic>. focused on a strategy that targets those between ages 20 and 30. Although this strategy avoids the costs of testing a group with low prevalence (i.e., adolescents), it does not protect adolescents from getting infected by other adolescents. While the “ring of protection” imposed by their “ages 20 to 30” strategy is very likely to reduce the number of adolescents who get infected in the first place, the age-based strategies considered here are more robust to the risk of HIV spreading between adolescents. In addition, Bershteyn 
 <italic>et al</italic>. compared their “ages 20–30” strategy to a cohort-based strategy in which a defined cohort (i.e., people entering the sexually active population during the first 10 years of the treatment campaign) was prioritized for treatment for the rest of their lives to the exclusion of others. While useful for determining what kinds of age-based strategies are likely to be the most effective, this cohort-based comparator is not so helpful for our purposes because it enhances treatment of young people during the critical early years of the treatment campaign (though, admittedly, not during the later years).
</p>
