<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We previously identified 
 <italic>A. aegypti</italic> as the principal vector during a 2015 ZIKV outbreak in Chiapas State, Mexico by testing mosquito pools derived from collections in and around homes of febrile, tentatively diagnosed patients [
 <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. 
 <italic>C. quinquefasciatus</italic> collected in similar numbers, as well as 
 <italic>A. (Stegomyia) albopictus</italic>, were not found to be infected. To further assess the principal vector role of 
 <italic>A. aegypti</italic>, we performed real time RT–PCR assays on the mosquito pools described previously and Ct- values were extrapolated to focus-forming unit equivalents per mL (FFUe/mL) via a standard virus titration curve (equation: Titre in FFUe/mL = 2E + 10e
 <sup>-.696(Ct)</sup>, 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sup>2 </sup>= .988 using ZIKV reference strain Mex1-44, isolated from one of these pools) (
 <xref rid="T0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Of the 155 mosquito pools tested, 15 were found to be unambiguously positive (Ct values of 14.1–26.6) giving a range of 2.2–6.0 log
 <sub>10</sub> FFUe/pool. All six pools found to be unambiguously positive and consistent with disseminated, transmission-competence (&gt;10
 <sup>5</sup> FFUe/pool) were comprised of 
 <italic>A. aegypti</italic> females only. Four pools were found to be marginally positive at Ct values between 33 and 37, three of which were comprised of 
 <italic>C. quinquefasciatus</italic>, and a single positive pool of 
 <italic>Mansonia titillans</italic> also fell into this ambiguous range. Based on our standard curve, these Ct values correspond to ≈1 FFUe/pool or lower, indicating the amount of virus present was inconsistent with transmission-competence. Although in our experience ZIKV titres extrapolated from real-time PCR Ct values can vary by up to ≈2 fold, depending on the virus strain and infection conditions, in general experimental studies show a typical range of 3.7–5.7 log
 <sub>10</sub> FFU/mosquito in the midguts and/or bodies of transmission-competent 
 <italic>A. aegypti</italic> [
 <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. 
</p>
