<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="viruses-12-00167-f001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Production and characterization of the KPF1-Antx hMAb. (
   <bold>A</bold>) Schematic representation of KPF1-Antx hMAb production using the 
   <italic>vivo</italic>XPRESS
   <sup>®</sup> platform. Four week old plants were vacuum-infiltrated with a solution containing 
   <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic>. The Agrobacteria contained binary vectors for the co-expression of KPF1 or isotype control heavy- and light-chain genes, STT3D, and a system for enhancing protein expression. The infiltrated plants were returned to the greenhouse for 7 days, after which all foliage was harvested and processed to purify KPF1 hMAb using a standard antibody process. (
   <bold>B</bold>) KPF1-Antx hMAb purification process and analysis: Samples from the KPF1-Antx hMAb purification process: Protein A load (1), protein A flow through (2), protein A elution (3), CaptoQ FT (4), and final purified KPF1-Antx hMAb (5) were analyzed under non-reducing (left) and reducing (right) conditions using standard SDS-PAGE electrophoresis and Coomassie blue staining. Mobility of the molecular marker (MW) in kDa is shown on the left. (
   <bold>C</bold>) Size-exclusion high performance liquid chromatography: Purified hMAbs (10 µg) were injected into a TSKgel G3000SWXL column equipped with a TSKgel guard column SWXL (Tosoh Biosciences) using an Agilent 1100 Series HPLC. Agilent LC/MSD ChemStation Edition software was used for integration of data. (
   <bold>D</bold>) N-glycan analysis of KPF1-Antx and KPF1-HEK hMAbs, and plant-produced isotype control: Glycans were prepared using the GlykoPrep
   <sup>®</sup> Rapid N-Glycan Preparation kit (PROzyme) and separated by hydrophilic-interaction liquid chromatography (HILIC) using a TSKgel Amide-80 column (Tosoh Bioscience). Glycan species were identified by relative retention time and quantified using auto-integration of each glycan species peak.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="viruses-12-00167-g001" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
