<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Pain Symptom Manage</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Pain Symptom Manage</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Pain and Symptom Management</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0885-3924</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1873-6513</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Published by Elsevier Inc. on behalf of American Academy of Hospice and Palliative Medicine.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7141635</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S0885-3924(20)30182-2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2020.03.029</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Role and Response of Palliative Care and Hospice Services in Epidemics and Pandemics: A Rapid Review to Inform Practice During the COVID-19 Pandemic</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Etkind</surname><given-names>Simon N.</given-names></name><degrees>MB BChir, BA, MRCP, DTMH, PhD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Bone</surname><given-names>Anna E.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD, MPH, BA</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Lovell</surname><given-names>Natasha</given-names></name><degrees>MBChB, BSc, MRCP</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Cripps</surname><given-names>Rachel L.</given-names></name><degrees>MSc, BSc</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name><surname>Harding</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name><degrees>PhD, MSc, BSc, DipSW</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name><surname>Higginson</surname><given-names>Irene J.</given-names></name><degrees>OBE, BMedSci, BMBS, PhD, FMedSci, FRCP, FFPHM</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name><surname>Sleeman</surname><given-names>Katherine E.</given-names></name><degrees>PhD, BSc, MBBS, MRCP</degrees><email>Katherine.Sleeman@kcl.ac.uk</email><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1">King's College London, Cicely Saunders Institute, London, United Kingdom</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label><italic>Address correspondence to:</italic> Katherine E. Sleeman, PhD, BSc, MBBS, MRCP, King's College London, Cicely Saunders Institute, Bessemer Road, London SE5 9PJ, United Kingdom. <email>Katherine.Sleeman@kcl.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>8</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>7</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>60</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e31</fpage><lpage>e40</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Published by Elsevier Inc. on behalf of American Academy of Hospice and Palliative Medicine.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><p>Cases of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) are escalating rapidly across the globe, with the mortality risk being especially high among those with existing illness and multimorbidity. This study aimed to synthesize evidence for the role and response of palliative care and hospice teams to viral epidemics/pandemics and inform the COVID-19 pandemic response. We conducted a rapid systematic review according to the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses guidelines in five databases. Of 3094 articles identified, 10 were included in this narrative synthesis. Included studies were from West Africa, Taiwan, Hong Kong, Singapore, the U.S., and Italy. All had an observational design. Findings were synthesized using a previously proposed framework according to systems (policies, training and protocols, communication and coordination, and data), staff (deployment, skill mix, and resilience), space (community provision and use of technology), and stuff (medicines and equipment as well as personal protective equipment). We conclude that hospice and palliative services have an essential role in the response to COVID-19 by responding rapidly and flexibly; ensuring protocols for symptom management are available, and training nonspecialists in their use; being involved in triage; considering shifting resources into the community; considering redeploying volunteers to provide psychosocial and bereavement care; facilitating camaraderie among staff and adopting measures to deal with stress; using technology to communicate with patients and carers; and adopting standardized data collection systems to inform operational changes and improve care.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Key Words</title><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>coronavirus</kwd><kwd>pandemic</kwd><kwd>palliative care</kwd><kwd>hospice</kwd><kwd>end of life</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>Key Message</title><p id="p0010">An evidence synthesis on the role and response of hospice and palliative care in epidemics/pandemics to inform response to coronavirus disease 2019. Hospice and palliative care services should respond rapidly and flexibly, produce protocols, shift resources to the community, redeploy volunteers, facilitate staff camaraderie, communicate with patients/carers via technology, and standardize data collection.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0015">The relief of suffering, supporting complex decision making, and managing clinical uncertainty are key attributes of palliative care and essential components of the response to epidemics and pandemics.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> The coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic is escalating rapidly across the globe. Those affected experience symptoms including breathlessness, cough, myalgia, and fever. The mortality risk is especially high among those with existing illness and multimorbidity.</p><p id="p0020">Pandemics such as that caused by COVID-19 can lead to a surge in demand for health care services, including palliative and end-of-life care.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> These services must respond rapidly, adopting new ways of working as resources are suddenly stretched beyond their normal bounds. Globally, palliative care is now seen as an essential part of universal health coverage. To inform the palliative care response to the COVID-19 pandemic, we aimed to rapidly synthesize evidence on the role and response of palliative care and hospice services to viral epidemics/pandemics.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec3.1"><title>Design</title><p id="p0025">Rapid systematic review according to Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses guidelines.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><title>Inclusion/Exclusion Criteria</title><p id="p0030">
<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0010"><list-item id="u0010"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0035">Population&#x02014;patients, carers, health care professionals, other experts, wards, units, and services</p></list-item><list-item id="u0015"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0040">Intervention&#x02014;palliative care, hospice care, end-of-life care, and supportive care</p></list-item><list-item id="u0020"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0045">Context&#x02014;viral epidemics or pandemics characterized by rapid transmission through the population and requiring a rapid response from the health system, including Ebola, severe acute respiratory syndrome, Middle East respiratory syndrome, avian influenza, and COVID-19. HIV was excluded because of its slower transmission through the population.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0025"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0050">Findings&#x02014;role and/or response of palliative care and hospice services</p></list-item><list-item id="u0030"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0055">Study design&#x02014;case studies, cross-sectional studies, cohort studies, and intervention studies (opinion pieces and editorials excluded)</p></list-item><list-item id="u0035"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0060">Language&#x02014;no limits</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><title>Search Strategy</title><p id="p0065">We searched five databases (MEDLINE [1966&#x02013;2019], Embase [1980&#x02013;2019], PsycINFO [1967&#x02013;2019], CINAHL [1982&#x02013;2019], and Web of Science [1970&#x02013;2019]). The search strategy comprised terms for palliative care, hospice care, and end-of-life care as well as terms for pandemics and epidemics including specific named pandemics (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix</xref>). We identified and screened the reference lists of relevant systematic reviews, government and nongovernmental organization reports, opinion pieces, and included articles.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><title>Study Selection</title><p id="p0070">One researcher (S. N. E.) completed all searches and removed duplicate records. Articles were screened in EndNote (version X9, Clarivate Analytics, Philadelphia, PA) using titles and abstracts by R. L. C., K. E. S., and S. N. E. Full texts were screened by K. E. S. and N. L.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><title>Data Extraction</title><p id="p0075">A bespoke data extraction form was created in Excel (Microsoft Corporation, Redmond, WA). Data were extracted by two researchers (K. E. S. and N. L.) and checked by a third researcher (A. E. B.). We did not appraise the quality of included studies.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.6"><title>Analysis</title><p id="p0080">We conducted narrative synthesis and used the framework proposed by Downar and Seccareccia<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> to group recommendations. This framework, based on an established model of intensive care surge capacity, suggests that a palliative pandemic plan should include focus on systems, space, staff, and stuff.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Results</title><p id="p0085">We identified 3088 articles from database searches (search date: March 18, 2020) and identified six additional articles through screening the reference lists of relevant articles and reports. After removing duplicates, 2207 articles remained. Thirty six articles underwent full-text review, and 10 articles were included in the analysis (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>
; <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>
).<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses flowchart.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Description of Included Studies</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Authors, yr</th><th>Context</th><th>Study Aim</th><th>Study Design</th><th>Setting/Participants</th><th>Findings and Author Recommendations</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Costantini et&#x000a0;al., 2020<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref></td><td>Italy, coronavirus (COVID-19)</td><td>To examine the preparedness for and impact of COVID-19 on hospices in Italy to help inform the responses of other countries</td><td>Cross-sectional telephone survey</td><td>16 hospices</td><td>Hospice response to COVID-19:<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0015"><list-item id="u0040"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0185">All hospices had rapidly implemented changes in practice, including transfer of staff to community settings, changes in admission criteria, and daily telephone support for families</p></list-item><list-item id="u0045"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0190">Lack of PPE</p></list-item><list-item id="u0050"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0195">Lack of hospice-specific guidance</p></list-item><list-item id="u0055"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0200">Assessments of risk and potential impact on staff varied greatly</p></list-item></list>Authors recommended that governments urgently recognize the essential contribution of hospice and palliative care to the COVID-19 pandemic and ensure these services are integrated into the health care system response. Availability of PPE and setting-specific guidance is essential</td></tr><tr><td>Battista et&#x000a0;al., 2019<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref></td><td>West Africa, EVD</td><td>To identify care measures and barriers and facilitators to their implementation for patients with EVD</td><td>Cross-sectional online survey</td><td>29 clinicians and decision makers (24 physicians, three nurses, and two involved in project management and coordination)</td><td>Barriers to the provision of supportive care:<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0020"><list-item id="u0060"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0205">Insufficient numbers of health workers (maintenance, surveillance, and laboratory professionals)</p></list-item><list-item id="u0065"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0210">Improper tools to document clinical data</p></list-item><list-item id="u0070"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0215">Insufficient material resources (drug supplies, intravenous catheters, and lines)</p></list-item><list-item id="u0075"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0220">Unadapted PPE</p></list-item><list-item id="u0080"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0225">Limited sharing of protocols, advice, and standards of care within organizations</p></list-item></list>Facilitators to the provision of supportive care:<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0025"><list-item id="u0085"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0230">Team camaraderie</p></list-item><list-item id="u0090"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0235">Ability to speak the local language</p></list-item><list-item id="u0095"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0240">Treatment protocols in place</p></list-item></list>Authors recommended that these areas of consensus are incorporated into guidelines to ensure standards of care are met</td></tr><tr><td>Loignon et&#x000a0;al., 2018<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref></td><td>West Africa, EVD</td><td>To document barriers to supportive care in Ebola treatment units</td><td>Qualitative telephone interviews</td><td>29 clinicians and decision makers, comprising 25 physicians, three nurses, and one other</td><td>Barriers to the provision of supportive care:<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0030"><list-item id="u0100"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0245">Lack of material and human resources (access to diagnostic and monitoring equipment)</p></list-item><list-item id="u0105"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0250">Organizational structure limited the provision of clinical care (lack of protocols and deficient management structures)</p></list-item><list-item id="u0110"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0255">Delayed and poorly coordinated policies limited the effectiveness of global and national response (insufficient political leadership and early epidemiological surveillance)</p></list-item></list>Authors recommended that relevant protocols are available, and organizational structures are improved to provide supportive care in future outbreaks</td></tr><tr><td>Dhillon et&#x000a0;al., 2015<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref></td><td>West Africa, EVD</td><td>To describe the treatment course of a man admitted to an Ebola treatment center and to describe some of the challenges identified</td><td>Case report</td><td>One 33-yr-old man admitted to an Ebola treatment center who died from Ebola-related complications 18&#x000a0;days later</td><td>Challenges identified in providing care for an Ebola patient:<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0035"><list-item id="u0115"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0260">Lack of consistency/continuity of staff</p></list-item><list-item id="u0120"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0265">A decision maker was not identified</p></list-item><list-item id="u0125"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0270">No recognition that the patient was dying</p></list-item><list-item id="u0130"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0275">There was emphasis on saving life, and any protocols specific to palliative care were not implemented</p></list-item></list>Authors recommend that communication is paramount in an environment where there are multiple caregivers, identification of a lead decision maker is helpful, and knowledge of the basics of palliative is essential, particularly in low-resource settings</td></tr><tr><td>Michaels-Strasser et&#x000a0;al., 2015<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref></td><td>Sierra Leone, EVD</td><td>To assess the outcome or effectiveness of community care centers for rapid isolation and palliative care of people with suspected Ebola disease</td><td>Cross-sectional assessment using direct observation, a site assessment survey, and staff interviews</td><td>11 community care centers and 58 key informants</td><td>Description and assessment of community care centers:<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0040"><list-item id="u0135"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0280">Centers ranged from tents to repurposed hospital wards and schools and were set up swiftly (median 10&#x000a0;days)</p></list-item><list-item id="u0140"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0285">Common features were proximity to community, small size (8&#x02013;28 beds), ability to triage and isolate cases, and transport to Ebola treatment units when beds became available</p></list-item><list-item id="u0145"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0290">Community care centers engaged and supported communities and fostered trust</p></list-item><list-item id="u0150"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0295">Limited data to assess effectiveness, with registers and forms not standardized</p></list-item></list>Authors recommended that the creation of community care centers could be an effective and scalable response, if they have standardized design, include monitoring and evaluation instruments, and training and supervision manuals</td></tr><tr><td>Cheng et&#x000a0;al., 2014<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref></td><td>Hong Kong, avian influenza</td><td>To explain measures taken by palliative care services in Hong Kong during the H7N9 influenza</td><td>Case study of a service</td><td>The first confirmed case of human avian influenza A (H7N9)</td><td>Response to avian influenza within a palliative care unit:<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0045"><list-item id="u0155"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0300">Visiting hours for palliative units were limited to less than four hours per day, with not more than two visitors per visit</p></list-item><list-item id="u0160"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0305">Visitors to public hospitals were required to put on surgical masks and perform hand hygiene before and after visiting patient areas</p></list-item><list-item id="u0165"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0310">Volunteer services and clinical attachment in public hospitals were suspended</p></list-item><list-item id="u0170"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0315">The palliative unit handled the restriction on family visits on compassionate grounds</p></list-item></list>Authors highlight the ethical dilemma that arises between dual need for infection control and comprehensive psychosocial care, with volunteers being integral to the interdisciplinary model of palliative care</td></tr><tr><td>Matzo et&#x000a0;al., 2009<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref></td><td>Hypothetical mass casualty event from an influenza pandemic or other event</td><td>To understand the role of palliative care in mass casualty events and to make recommendations</td><td>Qualitative telephone interviews and group meeting with experts</td><td>10 disaster management and public health experts</td><td>Issues for palliative care in mass casualty event:<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0050"><list-item id="u0175"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0320">Role of palliative care with scarce resources</p></list-item><list-item id="u0180"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0325">Treatment decisions of those likely to die</p></list-item><list-item id="u0185"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0330">Knowing what palliative care services to provide, along with personnel and settings</p></list-item><list-item id="u0190"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0335">Ensuring training, supplies, and organisational or jurisdictional arrangements</p></list-item></list>Authors recommended:<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0055"><list-item id="u0195"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0340">Training for nonpalliative care professionals in management of symptoms and psychological support</p></list-item><list-item id="u0200"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0345">Plan for management of specific populations (elderly at home, those with learning disabilities)</p></list-item><list-item id="u0205"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0350">Planning for and ensuring ethical allocation of scarce resources</p></list-item><list-item id="u0210"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0355">Ensuring provision of palliative care at all medical care sites</p></list-item></list>Planning to provide palliative care during mass casualty events should be part of the current national and local disaster planning for training guidelines, protocols, and activities</td></tr><tr><td>Cinti et&#x000a0;al., 2008<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref></td><td>U.S., simulation exercise</td><td>To describe learning after simulation exercises for pandemic events</td><td>Simulation exercises with recommendations</td><td>A large tertiary care center with 913 beds</td><td>An ACC was described as four pods accommodating a total of 250 patients, providing limited supportive care for noncritical pandemic influenza patients and some who would require palliative care<break/>Authors concluded that: more attention was needed on palliative care and fatality management; plans should include involvement of clergy; palliative care protocols are essential, and there should be training for site leads in their use; and palliation medications should be included on the formulary</td></tr><tr><td>Chen et&#x000a0;al., 2006<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref></td><td>Taiwan, SARS</td><td>To describe changes in hospice inpatient utilization during and after the SARS epidemic in 2003 in Taiwan</td><td>Retrospective study using administrative data</td><td>Hospice wards within 15 hospitals</td><td>Changes in hospice inpatient utilization during SARS epidemic:<break/>During the peak SARS period, the number of admissions to the 15 hospice wards decreased to 69% of those in the previous year, and inpatient day units reduced to 54%. It was not known whether the decrease in utilization was due to patients' voluntary decisions or hospital policies, and the study could not determine whether the needs of patients with terminal illnesses were met during the epidemic<break/>The authors concluded that the ability to shift resources from inpatient to community settings would improve care and that seamless continuity of care between facilities and settings should be ensured at all times</td></tr><tr><td>Leong et&#x000a0;al., 2004<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref></td><td>Singapore, SARS</td><td>To describe the psychosocial impact of providing holistic care in an epidemic</td><td>Qualitative interviews</td><td>Eight health care professionals (doctors, nurses, social workers, and pharmacists) in a palliative care unit</td><td>Psychosocial impact of providing holistic care in an epidemic:<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0060"><list-item id="u0215"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0360">Consequences of isolation</p></list-item><list-item id="u0220"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0365">Impact of uncertainty creating difficulties for patients, families, and staff in preparing for death</p></list-item><list-item id="u0225"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0370">Impact for health care workers (risk of contracting disease and not being able to grieve)</p></list-item><list-item id="u0230"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0375">Disruption of bereavement for families (management of bodies after deaths)</p></list-item></list>Authors recommend that in an epidemic palliative care should include measures to improve connectedness, training in communication and bereavement counseling, and measures to help health care workers deal with stress</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>COVID-19&#x000a0;= coronavirus disease 2019; PPE&#x000a0;= personal protective equipment; EVD&#x000a0;= Ebola virus disease; ACC&#x000a0;= alternative care center; SARS&#x000a0;= severe acute respiratory syndrome.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0090">The 10 articles were published between 2004 and 2020. Two articles concerned planning for pandemics,<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> seven articles described data collected during epidemics/pandemics,<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> and one article studied an epidemic retrospectively.<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p0095">The settings included West Africa,<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Taiwan,<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> Hong Kong,<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> Singapore,<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> the U.S.,<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> and Italy.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> One article had no defined setting.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> Eight of the articles concerned specific epidemics/pandemics (including Ebola,<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> severe acute respiratory syndrome,<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> influenza,<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> and one on COVID-19<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>).</p><p id="p0100">We synthesized findings according to Downar and Seccareccia model of systems, staff, space, and stuff (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>
).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Synthesis of Evidence and Recommendations for the Palliative Care Response to COVID-19</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td>Systems</td><td><list list-type="simple" id="olist0010"><list-item id="u0235"><p id="p0380">Policies<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0065"><list-item id="u0240"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0385">Require flexibility and rapid changes to systems and policies<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0245"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0390">Limiting visitor hours/numbers<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0250"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0395">Change in admission criteria<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0255"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0400">Systems of daily telephone support for families<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0260"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0405">Stopping volunteer services<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0265"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0410">Palliative care and hospice care should be part of the national and Local epidemic/pandemic planning<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>
</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0270"><p id="p0415">Training and protocols<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0070"><list-item id="u0275"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0420">Palliative care protocols for nonspecialist staff on management of symptoms and psychological support are essential<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0280"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0425">Training for site leads in the use of the protocols<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0285"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0430">Education and training for nonspecialist staff in basics of palliative care,<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> including in communication and bereavement counseling<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0290"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0435">Consider separate guidelines for specific populations such as people in care homes and those with intellectual disabilities<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0295"><p id="p0440">Communication and coordination<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0075"><list-item id="u0300"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0445">Sharing of protocols, advice, and standards of care within organizations<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0305"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0450">Identification of a decision maker to improve communication, particularly where multiple health professionals may be involved outside their usual practice<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0310"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0455">Rapid triage to assess likelihood of response to treatment<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> and recognition of dying<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>
</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0315"><p id="p0460">Data<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0080"><list-item id="u0320"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0465">Standardized information collection<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0325"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0470">Continuous monitoring and evaluation to inform operational changes or quality of services<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>
</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td>Staff</td><td><list list-type="simple" id="olist0015"><list-item id="u0330"><p id="p0475">Deployment of staff<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0085"><list-item id="u0335"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0480">Flexibility of deployment, such as moving staff from acute setting to the community<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0340"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0485">Sufficient staff numbers<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0345"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0490">Restricting contact with volunteers for infection control,<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> whereas acknowledging volunteers are integral to the interdisciplinary model in palliative care and can make important contributions to psychosocial and bereavement care<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref>
</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0350"><p id="p0495">Skill mix of staff<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0090"><list-item id="u0355"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0500">Involving spiritual care and chaplains in the pandemic response<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0360"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0505">Involving psychologists with expertise in palliative care<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0365"><p id="p0510">Ensuring resilience of staff<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0095"><list-item id="u0370"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0515">Facilitating camaraderie among staff important to minimize negative psychosocial effects on staff, which include distress about risks of contracting the disease, grieving relatives, or friends while working<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0375"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0520">Measures to improve connectedness among staff<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0380"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0525">Training in communication and bereavement counseling<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0385"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0530">Measures to help health care workers deal with stress<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref>
</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td>Space</td><td><list list-type="simple" id="olist0020"><list-item id="u0390"><p id="p0535">Moving to community provision<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0100"><list-item id="u0395"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0540">Consider shifting resources from inpatient to community settings where demand may be higher<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0400"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0545">Consider the setup of community care centers to expand outside hospital with standardized designs, include monitoring and evaluation instruments, and make use of training and supervision manuals. Community engagement to foster trust is important<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>
</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0405"><p id="p0550">Use of technology<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0105"><list-item id="u0410"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0555">The role for virtual technology to enable communication, where visiting is restricted, for example, providing a daily update for families<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref>
</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td>Stuff</td><td><list list-type="simple" id="olist0025"><list-item id="u0415"><p id="p0560">Medicines and equipment<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0110"><list-item id="u0420"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0565">Relevant symptom medications should be included in formularies,<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> in the case of COVID-19&#x02014;breathlessness, cough, fever, delirium, anxiety, as well as pain</p></list-item><list-item id="u0425"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0570">Basic supplies of medications, intravenous catheters, and lines<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0430"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0575">Access to diagnostic and monitoring equipment<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref>
</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0435"><p id="p0580">PPE<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0115"><list-item id="u0440"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0585">Sufficient supplies of PPE that are adaptable to the person<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref>
</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item></list></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>COVID-19&#x000a0;= coronavirus disease 2019; PPE&#x000a0;= personal protective equipment.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0105">We provide the first evidence synthesis to guide hospice and palliative care teams in their response to the COVID-19 pandemic. Key findings were the need for teams to be flexible and rapidly redeploy resources in the face of changing need. For hospital teams, this involves putting in place protocols for symptom control and training nonspecialists in their use. Hospice services may see a shift in need and should be prepared to focus their resources on community provision.</p><p id="p0110">This was a rapid review, and we did not assess quality of studies or grade our recommendations. We found existing evidence to be limited. All identified studies were observational, quantitative data were rare, and there were no studies with an experimental design. Most studies were from Asia or Africa, with one study from Europe, and one from the U.S. This reflects the fact that Europe and the U.S. are less experienced at responding to pandemics than other regions, and this may in turn result in a lack of preparedness to respond to COVID-19. Although the importance of palliative care in response to pandemics has been well documented,<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> this is not reflected in pandemic plans or in palliative care training, and the research literature is sparse.</p><p id="p0115">There were gaps in evidence, particularly around the role of palliative care teams in acute hospitals. There was also relatively little data on provision of palliative care in community settings, although in two studies, a reduction in demand for inpatient care was seen and led to the suggestion to shift resources into the community.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> Community palliative care can facilitate advance care planning and symptom control and helps prevent hospital admissions among people near the end of life.<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> It is likely that community palliative care may help prevent hospital admissions among people dying from COVID-19 who would prefer to remain at home or in their care home, although this has not been tested. However, the rapid escalation of breathlessness in patients with COVID-19 who develop acute respiratory distress syndrome may make this challenging.<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> Severe breathlessness and respiratory disease are both known to be associated with increased hospital admissions at the end of life.<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> Therefore, rapid community response may be needed to manage advanced disease in COVID-19 if people are to remain at home.</p><p id="p0120">Two studies reported cessation of hospice volunteer services in response to pandemics.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> An alternative role for volunteers may be in provision of psychological support for patients and carers, which could occur by using digital technology or telephones. In light of the social distancing measures being widely used in response to COVID-19, volunteers may have a wider role in supporting communities, for example, helping the most vulnerable with shopping for food and medicines.</p><p id="p0125">Providing palliative care in pandemics can be compromised by the hostile environment, infection control mechanisms, and extreme pressure on services.<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> In addition, the family unit of care may be disrupted. Even so, provision of palliative care is an ethical imperative for those unlikely to survive and may have the advantage of diverting dying people away from overburdened hospitals as well as providing the care that people want.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> Pandemic situations introduce complex ethical challenges concerning allocation of scarce resources, and palliative care teams are well placed to help patients and carers discuss preferences and make advance care plans.</p><p id="p0130">Data collection systems to understand outcomes and share learning are important in a palliative pandemic response. However, these are frequently lacking.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> Such data should ideally include numbers of patients seen, as well as their main symptoms and concerns, treatments, effectiveness of treatment and outcomes. There is also a need to understand the prevalence of palliative care needs that are not met by palliative and hospice services. In a pandemic expected to last for several months such as COVID-19, implementing systems of data collection early would help services to plan for and improve care and could be used to project future needs.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0135">Providing holistic care in a pandemic can be compromised by extreme pressure on services. Hospice and palliative care services can mitigate against this by maintaining the ability to respond rapidly and flexibly; ensuring protocols for symptom management and psychological support are available, and nonspecialists are trained in their use; being involved in triage; considering shifting resources from inpatient to community settings; considering redeploying volunteers to provide psychosocial and bereavement care; facilitating camaraderie among staff and adopting measures to deal with stress; use of technology to communicate with patients and carers; and adopting standardized data collection systems to inform operational changes and improve care. Long-term priorities should include ensuring palliative and hospice care are integrated into pandemic plans.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nouvet</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Palliative care in humanitarian crisis: always something to offer</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>389</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>1498</fpage><lpage>1499</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28422014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Downar</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seccareccia</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Palliating a pandemic: &#x0201c;all patients must be cared for&#x0201d;</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Pain Symptom Manage</source><volume>39</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20152591</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matzo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynn</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatto</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Palliative care considerations in mass casualty events with scarce resources</article-title><source>Biosecur Bioterror</source><volume>7</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19635004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cinti</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkerson</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>J.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pandemic influenza and acute care centres: taking care of sick patients in a nonhospital setting</article-title><source>Biosecur Bioterror</source><volume>6</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19117432</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costantini</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sleeman</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peruselli</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Higginson</surname><given-names>I.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Response and role of palliative care during the COVID-19 pandemic: a national telephone survey of hospices in Italy</article-title><source>Palliat Med</source><year>2020</year><comment>(in press)</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Battista</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Loignon</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benhadi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Priorities, barriers, and facilitators towards international guidelines for the delivery of supportive clinical care during an ebola outbreak: a cross-sectional survey</article-title><source>Viruses</source><volume>11</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>194</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loignon</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nouvet</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Couturier</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Barriers to supportive care during the Ebola virus disease outbreak in West Africa: results of a qualitative study</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>13</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>e0201091</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30183718</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dhillon</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sue</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Palliative care conundrums in an Ebola treatment centre</article-title><source>BMJ Case Rep</source><volume>2015</volume><year>2015</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michaels-Strasser</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabkin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lahuerta</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Innovation to confront Ebola in Sierra Leone: the community-care-centre model</article-title><source>Lancet Glob Health</source><volume>3</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>e361</fpage><lpage>e362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26087982</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>H.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>K.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sham</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The first confirmed case of human avian influenza A(H7N9) in Hong Kong and the suspension of volunteer services: impact on palliative care</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Pain Symptom Manage</source><volume>47</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>e5</fpage><lpage>e7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leong</surname><given-names>I.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>A.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>T.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The challenge of providing holistic care in a viral epidemic: opportunities for palliative care</article-title><source>Palliat Med</source><volume>18</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14982202</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hospice utilization during the SARS outbreak in Taiwan</article-title><source>BMC Health Serv Res</source><volume>6</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>94</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16889656</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosoff</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A&#x000a0;central role for palliative care in an influenza pandemic</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Palliat Med</source><volume>9</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>1051</fpage><lpage>1053</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17040141</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Calanzani</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Curiale</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCrone</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Higginson</surname><given-names>I.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of home palliative care services for adults with advanced illness and their caregivers</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><year>2013</year><fpage>CD007760</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23744578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk factors associated with acute respiratory distress syndrome and death in patients with coronavirus disease 2019 pneumonia in Wuhan, China</article-title><source>JAMA Intern Med</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2020.0994</pub-id><comment>[Epub ahead of print]</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bone</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors associated with transition from community settings to hospital as place of death for adults aged 75 and older: a population-based mortality follow-back survey</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Am Geriatr Soc</source><volume>64</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>2210</fpage><lpage>2217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27610598</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Data</title><p id="p0145">
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ec1"><caption><p>COVID PRISMA 2009 Checklist</p></caption><media xlink:href="mmc1.doc"/></supplementary-material>
</p><p id="p0145aa">
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ec2"><caption><p>Supplementary Material</p></caption><media xlink:href="mmc2.pdf"/></supplementary-material>
</p></sec><sec id="appsec3"><title>Appendix</title><sec id="appsec3.1"><label>Appendix</label><title>Search Strategy</title><p id="p0155">There were no restrictions for language or publication date. Searches were completed on March 18,&#x000a0;2020.</p></sec><sec id="appsec3.2"><title>MEDLINE and Embase</title><p id="p0160">(palliative care/OR palliative medicine/OR palliate$.mp. OR hospices/OR terminally ill/OR terminal care/OR hospice$.mp. OR end of life.mp. OR EOL.mp.) AND (exp pandemics/OR pandemic$.mp. OR epidemic$.mp. OR epidemics/OR exp disease outbreaks/OR disease outbreaks.mp. OR SARS.mp. OR SARS virus/OR Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome/OR coronavirus/OR coronavirus.mp. OR exp coronavirus infections/OR ebolavirus/OR influenza, human/OR influenza.mp. OR hemorrhagic fever, ebola/OR mers.mp. OR flu.mp. OR Middle East Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus/OR Tuberculosis/OR Pulmonary tuberculosis/OR Tuberculosis, multi-drug resistant/OR Extensively drug resistant tuberculosis/OR TB.mp.)</p></sec><sec id="appsec3.3"><title>PsycINFO</title><p id="p0165">(palliative care/OR palliate$.mp. OR hospice/OR terminally ill patient/OR terminal care.mp. OR hospice$.mp. OR end of life.mp. OR EOL.mp.) AND (exp pandemics/OR pandemic$.mp. OR epidemic$.mp. OR exp epidemics/OR disease outbreaks.mp. OR SARS.mp. OR Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome.mp. OR coronavirus.mp. OR influenza/OR swine influenza OR ebola.mp. OR ebolavirus.mp. OR influenza.mp. OR mers.mp. OR flu.mp. OR Middle East Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus.mp. OR Tuberculosis/OR Pulmonary tuberculosis/OR multi-drug resistant tuberculosis.mp. OR extensively drug resistant tuberculosis.mp. OR TB.mp.)</p></sec><sec id="appsec3.4"><title>CINAHL</title><p id="p0170">Searched for the below as title, abstract, and keywords.</p><p id="p0175">(Palliative care OR palliative medicine OR palliat&#x02217; OR hospice&#x02217; OR terminally ill OR terminal care OR end of life OR eol) AND (pandemic&#x02217; OR epidemic&#x02217; OR disease outbreak OR SARS OR Severe acute respiratory syndrome OR SARS virus OR coronavirus OR coronavirus infections OR influenza OR flu OR MERS OR middle east respiratory syndrome OR ebola virus OR ebola OR Tuberculosis OR multidrug-resistant tuberculosis)</p></sec><sec id="appsec3.5"><title>Web of Science</title><p id="p0180">TS=((palliative care OR palliative medicine OR palliat&#x02217; OR hospice&#x02217; OR terminally ill OR terminal care OR eol) AND (pandemic&#x02217; OR epidemic&#x02217; OR disease outbreak OR SARS OR Severe acute respiratory syndrome OR SARS virus OR coronavirus OR coronavirus infections OR influenza OR flu OR MERS OR middle east respiratory syndrome OR ebola virus OR ebola OR Tuberculosis OR multidrug-resistant tuberculosis))</p></sec></sec><ack id="ack0010"><title>Disclosures and Acknowledgments</title><p>This research received no specific funding/grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors. K. E. S. is funded by a UK <funding-source id="gs12"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100000272</institution-id><institution>National Institute for Health Research</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (NIHR) clinician scientist fellowship (CS-2015-15-005); I. J. H. is an NIHR senior investigator emeritus and is supported by the <funding-source id="gs13"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100000272</institution-id><institution>NIHR</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> Applied Research Collaboration South London at King's College Hospital National Health Service Foundation Trust. I. J. H. leads the Palliative and End of Life Care theme of the NIHR Applied Research Collaboration South London and coleads the national theme in this. R. L. C. is funded by <funding-source id="gs14">Marie Curie and Cicely Saunders International</funding-source>; A. E. B. is funded by <funding-source id="gs15">Cicely Saunders International</funding-source> and the <funding-source id="gs16"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100000377</institution-id><institution>Dunhill Medical Trust</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>. S. N. E., N. L., and A. E. B. are previous Cicely Saunders International PhD training fellows. The views expressed are those of the authors and not necessarily those of the National Health Service, the NIHR, the Department of Health and Social Care, or the funding charities. The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="appsec2" fn-type="supplementary-material"><p id="p0150">Supplementary data related to this article can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2020.03.029" id="intref0010">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2020.03.029</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>