<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Immunomics can aid in identifying optimal B-cell and T-cell epitopes directly from the pathogen proteomes, while the literature suggested that T-cell predictions are more advanced and reliable than that of B-cell epitope predictions [
 <xref rid="B57-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="B58-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. A workshop on the B-cell epitope prediction tools reported that the prediction performance of B-cell tools is still far from reality due to a lack of high-quality experimental datasets [
 <xref rid="B57-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Detailed description on the existing epitope mapping tools, and challenges have been discussed in the cited review articles [
 <xref rid="B55-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B58-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="B59-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Key limitations include: (1) the availability of experimental datasets essential in training and developing any epitope prediction tool; (2) selection of epitope prediction tools may also introduce discrepancy in the identification of potential T-cell epitopes due to methodological differences. T-cell epitope prediction tools that include sequence- and structure-based methods are reviewed in Patronov et al. [
 <xref rid="B56-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>] and Luo et al. [
 <xref rid="B63-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]); (3) the availability of high-quality datasets on the binding affinity of epitope-MHC, which directs the development and success of T-cell epitope prediction tools. A prediction of strong binding affinity suggests that an epitope will be presented to T-cells. But this requires an experimental assessment; and (4) The population coverage of an epitope is related to MHC polymorphism that exists in humans. The efficacy of epitope-based vaccine(s) can be limited due to variability of MHC alleles among different ethnicities. This may reduce the maximum population coverage of epitope-based vaccine leading to the failure of the vaccine to elicit T-cell immune responses. The current tools, IEDB population coverage [
 <xref rid="B64-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>] and EPISOPT [
 <xref rid="B65-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], that are used to predict the population coverage are based on the limited experimental HLA frequency data from world-wide MHC allele frequency database (
 <uri xlink:href="http://www.allelefrequencies.net/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.allelefrequencies.net/</uri>).
</p>
