<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>ZIKV primarily transmits and spreads by the biting of infected female 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> mosquito, primarily by 
 <italic>A. aegypti and Aedes albopictus.</italic> The virus can also be transmitted by other species of mosquitoes such as 
 <italic>Anopheles</italic>, 
 <italic>Culex</italic>, 
 <italic>Eretmapodites</italic>, and 
 <italic>Mansonia</italic> [
 <xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]
 <italic>.</italic> This virus can also be transmitted by sexual intercourse, blood transfusion, saliva, urine, and from infected pregnant women to her babies (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="figure2">Fig. 2</xref>) [
 <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>–
 <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Though ZIKV infections might be asymptomatic, the infected patients may have fever, red eyes, joint pain, headache, conjunctivitis, retro-orbital pain, fatigue, and maculopapular rashes which are similar to that of Dengue and Chikungunya, but may cure within a week [
 <xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. However, it may cause severe diseases such as multi-organs failure, thrombocytopenia and thrombocytopenic purpura, meningitis, encephalitis, and Guillain-Barre syndrome [
 <xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Miscarriage and stillbirth may found if the ZIKV infection happens during pregnancy [
 <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The most dangerous effects are microcephaly, neurodevelopmental injuries of fetus, and the congenitally infected baby may show hypoplasia of the cerebellum and brainstem, ventriculomegaly, delayed myelination, enlarged cisterna magna, abnormalities of the corpus callosum, calcifications, and cortical malformations [
 <xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. However, ZIKV infected patient may also show local hyperemia and petechiae on the hard palate [
 <xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>].
</p>
