<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23">Despite growing evidence on how opiates and HIV interact to impact the neuropathology of HIV, little is known about their interactive effects on the blood-brain barrier (BBB). BBB integrity and function are critical for maintaining CNS homeostasis, and mediating neuroimmune interactions with the periphery and drug delivery into the CNS. HIV and many individual HIV proteins can breakdown the BBB disrupting tight junction proteins (Dallasta et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">1999</xref>; Boven et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2000</xref>; Andras et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2003</xref>; Mahajan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR303">2008</xref>; Banerjee et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2010</xref>; Gandhi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR172">2010</xref>; Xu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR550">2012</xref>; Patel et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR383">2017</xref>) and decreasing transendothelial electrical resistance (TEER) (an in vitro measure of barrier integrity) (Mahajan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR303">2008</xref>; Gandhi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR172">2010</xref>; Mishra and Singh 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR340">2014</xref>; Patel et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR383">2017</xref>), with resultant paracellular “leakage” of compounds/current between compromised barrier endothelial cells (Mahajan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR303">2008</xref>; Gandhi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR172">2010</xref>; Wen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR537">2011</xref>; McLane et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR327">2014</xref>; Leibrand et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR273">2017</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR274">2019</xref>). Although opioids can also impair the BBB through alterations in tight junction proteins and/or increased paracellular flux (Baba et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">1988</xref>; Mahajan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR303">2008</xref>; Wen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR537">2011</xref>; Leibrand et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR274">2019</xref>), others have found that it is morphine withdrawal, not the continued exposure to morphine, that most greatly disrupts BBB integrity (Sharma and Ali 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR461">2006</xref>). In addition to perturbing paracellular dynamics, morphine may also alter the expression and/or function of drug efflux proteins, such as P-glycoprotein (P-gp). Sub-chronic and chronic morphine exposure is reported to increase P-gp expression and/or function (Aquilante et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2000</xref>; Mahajan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR303">2008</xref>; Yousif et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR555">2008</xref>; Leibrand et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR274">2019</xref>). Alternatively, other investigators report no changes in P-gp with chronic exposure (Chaves et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">2016</xref>), while some see increases upon morphine withdrawal (Yousif et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR556">2012</xref>; Chaves et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">2016</xref>). Alterations in drug transport proteins would impact the central accumulation and efficacy of therapeutic drugs that are their substrates.
</p>
