<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P30">NS1 sequences from different virus isolates were selected from the Influenza Research Database (IRD) based on different structural and functional Sequence Feature Variant Types (SFVT) (
 <xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">Noronha et al., 2012</xref>). To obtain a robust diversity within the different NS1 variants, two different strains were selected for each sequence feature (SF): the first included in variant 1 (VT1), that uses A/Udorn/1972 as strain reference, and the second one corresponded to a different VT containing a relevant number of amino acid variation for that specific SF. The strain selection was refined after multiple alignments, discarding NS1 sequences that were identical and only considering the strains whose genome was fully sequenced and represented multiple times in the database. In addition, other parameters, such as the country of origin, host and year were also considered. Following this approach, a list of the most representative NS1 was created. As an internal control, each NS1 recombinant virus was rescued in duplicates and associated to a different and unique 22-nucleotide barcode. Barcodes were designed using a specific software (Barcode generator) and they were all GC content matched as previously reported (
 <xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">Varble et al., 2014</xref>). A total of 107 viruses out of 112 were rescued, plaque purified, titered and combined in equal amounts (100 pfu per virus) to constitute the final library (
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Only few NS1 recombinant viruses were more difficult to rescue, thus resulting in ~4% of viruses in the library that are not paired to a second barcode. This was likely due to variable rescue efficiencies when different plasmid preparations were used. Nevertheless, these few viruses represented by a single barcode were included as part of the final library since no major differences in barcode relative abundance were detected between viral pairs containing different barcodes. Viruses represented only with a single barcode are A/Auckland/599/2000, A/Malaysia/1954, A/Hong Kong/97/98, A/Mallard/Nova Scotia/00088/2010 and A/Mallard/Sweden/79367/2008. Barcode read ratios obtained for each recombinant virus within the original library mix (input) were close to 1:1:1, thus minimizing any amplification bias within the library construction. A small library containing 4 recombinant viruses (A/Shanghai/02/2013, A/Udorn/1972, A/Puerto Rico/8/1934 and A/Puerto Rico/8/1934-R38A/K41A) was used as a proof of principle to our strategy (
 <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S1</xref>), before assembling the final viral library.
</p>
