<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Common clinical signs and symptoms in pediatric LRTIs include coryza, apnea, rapid shallow breaths, head bobbing, tracheal tug, chest wall hyperinflation, and intercostal retractions (Fitzgerald 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2011</xref>). In addition to small airway inflammation, peripheral hyperinflation within the lung parenchyma contributes to symptoms (Tregoning and Schwarze 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2010</xref>). Severe symptoms are commonly characterized by oxygen saturation less than 92–93 % (Hammond et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2007</xref>; Chang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2009</xref>; Fitzgerald 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2011</xref>; Thomson and Harris 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2011</xref>). Atypical clinical presentations of viruses can be difficult to distinguish from bacterial etiologies. Typically, chest radiographs demonstrate diffuse airspace shadowing and/or dispersed areas of consolidation in bacterial pneumonia, whereas viral pneumonias more often produce hyperinflated lung parenchyma with patchy infiltrates and peribronchial cuffing (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">17.1</xref>) (Coffin 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2005</xref>; Chong et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2009</xref>). However there has been much debate about the reproducibility in the radiographic diagnosis of pneumonias, with a 48 % concordance with the WHO radiographic classification and relatively poor clinical utility in distinguishing bacterial versus viral etiologies (Thomson and Harris 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2011</xref>). One study suggests that a specific infectious agent is not identified in more than 50 % of LRTIs, leaving clinicians to empirically treat with antibiotics, a potentially unnecessary drug exposure with increased risk of developing drug resistance in bacteria (Tregoning and Schwarze 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2010</xref>; Marcos et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2009</xref>). 
</p>
