<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0170">The HA of IBV is synthesized in the ER as a HA
 <sub>0</sub> precursor of approx. 63 kDa with a predicted leader peptide of 15 amino acids that needs to be proteolytically cleaved by the cellular signal peptidase. HA
 <sub>0</sub> precursor is cleaved by trypsin-like proteases into HA
 <sub>1</sub> (approx. 346 amino acids) and HA
 <sub>2</sub> subunits (approx. 223 amino acids) to become biologically active. HA has an essential role in the viral life cycle as it mediates binding of the virion to host cell surface receptors as well as promoting the release of the viral genome from the late endosome. The HA of IBV is heavily glycosylated containing 10–12 N-linked glycosylation sites and it is assembled into homotrimers. The high number of glycan attachment sites may reflect the prolonged circulation of IBV in humans as glycosylation is believed to be a strategy, by which influenza viruses mask antigenic sites. Cleavage activation of the HA occurs within a motif that is highly conserved among viruses of the Yamagata and Victoria lineages (PAKLLKER↓GFFGAIAGFLE), which liberates the hydrophobic fusion peptide at the N-terminal end of HA
 <sub>2</sub>. Trypsin and the serine proteases TMPRSS2 and TMPRSS11d were shown to execute HA cleavage activation in vitro. TMPRSS2 knock out mice were shown susceptible to IBV infection suggesting the existence of additional proteases that can activate the HA. Several X ray structures have been reported for the neutral pH form of HA expressed by the divergent IBV lineages (
 <xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> ). Despite a low degree of sequence identity of approx. 25% to IAV HA these studies revealed an overall conserved fold of the trimeric HA ectodomain composed of a membrane-distal globular head domain (mainly located on HA
 <sub>1</sub>) and an elongated stem (mainly located on HA
 <sub>2</sub>) formed by each monomer. Each head domain carries a receptor binding pocket that is built by the 190 helix (aa 193–202) on the top, the 240 loop (aa 237–242) as the left boundary and the 140 loop (aa 136–143) as the right edge with additional contributions by the conserved Phe 95, Trp 158 and Tyr 202 residues. The principal receptor determinants of IBV HA are sialic acid (SA) conjugated to cellular surfaces. An interesting variation among clinical IBV isolates has been noted in terms of their receptor specificity by glycan array analysis. 19 of 21 Yamagata-like viruses isolated between 2001 and 2006 in Taiwan preferentially bound to α-2,6 linked sialic acid that is also the major receptor determinant for IAV in the human upper respiratory tract. In contrast, 12 of 23 Victoria-like viruses additionally bound α-2,3 linked sialic acid, which is the receptor for avian IAV and can be found in humans mainly in the lower respiratory tract (LRT). 6 of 23 Victoria-like IBV recognized specifically sulfated glycans. Receptor specificity is considered an important determinant of influenza virus pathogenesis, but it remains to be established whether IBV strains with dual receptor specificity are more prone to infect the LRT which is usually associated with more severe symptoms.
</p>
