<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14">Human pathogenic bunyaviruses, particularly Hantaviruses and Crimean-Congo Hemorrhagic Fever Virus (CCHFV), can cause hemorrhagic fevers, and CCHFV is on the list of potential biological threat agents (NATO AMed P-6 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref>]. Handling of these viruses requires BSL-3/BSL-4 containment. Bunyaviruses have a wide host range, including plants, ticks (Hyalomma ticks—CCHFV), insects (Culex—Rift Valley fever virus) and rodents (Hantaviruses), which also serve as transmission vectors. Humans are dead-end hosts, suffering fatal outcomes in the case of Crimean-Congo hemorrhagic fever (CCHF), as well as in hemorrhagic fever with renal syndrome (HFRS; Europe—South-East Asia; Puumala/Hantaan-type viruses) and hantavirus pulmonary syndrome (HPS; Americas; Sin Nombre-type viruses). The clinical outcome is linked to geographical context and the typical animal vector. While high case fatality rates were described with the Korean hantavirus types and with Sin Nombre-type viruses causing HPS in the Americas, the European situation indicates a high case load with HFRS, but less severe clinical outcomes (nephropathia epidemica), caused mainly by Puumala-type viruses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR127">127</xref>] as reported by the European Center for Disease Control [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Bunyavirus infections are endemic, vector-borne infections. Normally they do not cause epidemics, with the exception of nosocomially transmitted CCHF. Thousands of cases usually occur only in hyperendemic situations over a longer period of time. Beginning with an initial generalized flu-like illness and fever which lasts for about 3 days, these infections can end in fatal hemorrhagic fever (CCHF, HFRS), and pulmonary syndrome (HPS) with a 1–40% case fatality rate depending on virus strain [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. Bunyaviruses are enveloped viruses with bi- and tri-segmented ambisense ss-RNA Group IV genomes. Human cellular receptors include human beta 3 integrins, the main human cellular targets are macrophages and endothelial cells, and bunyaviruses replicate in the cytoplasm. No vaccines or licensed treatments are currently available. 
 <italic>Anti-bunyavirus drugs</italic>. The focus towards the identification of antiviral agents has mostly been on CCHFV infections, which are common in endemic areas, but are either asymptomatic or cause a non-specific febrile illness that does not require hospitalization or specific treatment. Few patients develop hypotension and hemorrhage, and medical management is then largely supportive, with volume replacement, and prevention of edema and inflammation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. Ribavirin has been used to treat CCHF patients under compassionate use protocols with some success since 1985 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR140">140</xref>], especially if given early in the course of the infection, but many studies with apparently beneficial results lack controls. Recent randomized clinical trials were unable to show significant beneficial effects of ribavirin versus CCHFV [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>]. Further interesting candidates for virus-specific treatment (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) include favipiravir (T-705), which has been evaluated against a number of phleboviruses (PhleboV) and to treat CCHFV infection in rodent models [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>], galidesivir (BCX4430), effective against Rift Valley fever virus (RVFV) infection in a hamster model and investigated for use by the FDA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR145">145</xref>], 2′-fluoro-2′-deoxycytidine (2FdC), which showed protective effects against infections with PhleboV in a rodent model [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR134">134</xref>], and the FGI-106 entry inhibitor [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR135">135</xref>].
</p>
