<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Host-pathogen studies encompass an extraordinary variety of temporal and spatial scales, including wide ranges of ecological settings and pathogen complexities—such as experimental versus field studies or single versus multiple pathogens—as well as genomic complexities, ranging from candidate gene studies to whole genome scans (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1A</xref>). Any single study can be classified according to these scales, with concomitant benefits and deficiencies in capturing the details of host-pathogen interactions in the real world. For example, studies aiming to link the evolution of host and pathogen genomes and to detect genomic signatures of host-pathogen interactions have arisen from searches for associations with single host candidate genes, such as genes of the major histocompatibility complex (MHC) (
 <xref rid="ref-66" ref-type="bibr">Hill et al., 1991</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-75" ref-type="bibr">Kaslow et al., 1996</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-174" ref-type="bibr">Wegner, Reusch &amp; Kalbe, 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-101" ref-type="bibr">Meyer-Lucht &amp; Sommer, 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-138" ref-type="bibr">Savage &amp; Zamudio, 2011</xref>), to genome-wide scans for associations with resistance or susceptibility (e.g., 
 <xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Fumagalli et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Bartha et al., 2013</xref>). We now have genomic insights into host-pathogen interactions that stem from field studies investigating temporal and spatial patterns (
 <xref rid="ref-66" ref-type="bibr">Hill et al., 1991</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-138" ref-type="bibr">Savage &amp; Zamudio, 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-117" ref-type="bibr">Penczykowski, Laine &amp; Koskella, 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Bourgeois et al., 2017</xref>); to experimentally evolving populations or ancient DNA studies encompassing hundreds or thousands of host generations (
 <xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Bos et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Cairns et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-163" ref-type="bibr">Tso et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-151" ref-type="bibr">Spyrou et al., 2019</xref>); to phylogenetic and comparative studies spanning tens of millions of years (
 <xref rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr">Enard et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-78" ref-type="bibr">Koonin, Makarova &amp; Wolf, 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-145" ref-type="bibr">Shultz &amp; Sackton, 2019</xref>). This variety makes it challenging to draw broad generalizations linking processes on different scales and, to date, few syntheses have attempted to bridge the many temporal and spatial scales on which host-pathogen studies take place. This represents an important deficit, as generalizability is key to identifying fundamental principles in the field of host-pathogen interactions and enables accurate predictions to be made about host-pathogen interactions in new study systems.
</p>
