<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this perspective, we aim to address the complexities and commonalities of diverse studies of host-pathogen interactions through the lens of evolutionary genomics. We emphasize the wide range of approaches used recently and focus primarily on evolutionary responses of hosts to pathogens (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1</xref>). We first document the diversity of recent studies of host-pathogen interactions through a comprehensive analysis of the recent literature on the subject. This survey documents the sheer diversity of temporal and spatial scales on which host-pathogen studies are conducted, but also reveals that the heterogeneity of results across studies, from laboratory to field to experimental settings, poses a challenge for synthesis. Our survey identifies gaps in emphasis on research on host-pathogen interactions, but also reveals opportunities for discovering common principles and methodologies that are likely to drive the research field forward. We then review major themes in the study of interactions between hosts and pathogens in the wild. While daunting in terms of confounding variables, such studies provide opportunities for studying the synergistic effects of anthropogenic change and the evolutionary response to epizootics. At the same time, an increasing number of experimental studies that examine the effects of multiple interacting pathogens on their hosts, or of host microbiome on infection outcome, capture some of the reality of epizootics in nature. We conclude that the full promise of genomic and other -omics approaches to further our understanding of host-pathogen interactions will not be realized until these data are thoroughly and consistently embedded in high quality, consistent, and reproducible ecological and environmental metadata. Increased resolution of ecological metadata, smart databases that facilitate collaboration and comparisons across studies, and deposition of voucher specimens associated with specific studies in museum collections are just some of the ways in which genomic data can realize their full potential. These new tools will facilitate the application of knowledge of basic principles of host-pathogen interactions to real world problems affecting wildlife, endangered species, and ultimately human welfare.
</p>
