<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Some of the protein cargoes delivered by EVs from hepatocytes are implicated in various pathways, including those involving detoxification, endosomes, cytosolic proteins, apolipoproteins, and coagulation-associated proteins. MPs/MVs have been found to contain typical markers such as actinin-4, mitofilin, and phosphatidylserine. Exosomes contain a rich variety of components, such as heat shock proteins (HSP60, HSP70, HSP90), tetraspanins (CD9, CD10, CD26, CD63, CD81, CD82), and integrins [
 <xref rid="B8-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Sphingosine kinase 2 (SK2) is delivered by exosomes that are formed by hepatocytes and target other hepatocytes; it catalyzes the formation of sphingosine-1-phosphate (S1P), implying that it is a disease-specific cargo of hepatocyte-derived exosomes [
 <xref rid="B13-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. EVs are formed by various types of liver cells, such as hepatocytes, hepatic stellate cells (HSCs), endothelial cells, Kupffer cells, and natural killer cells. They act as essential intracellular communication regulators, and are associated with various vital biological processes, including inflammation and tissue remodeling. EVs are expelled into the extracellular space by various types of liver cells and are thereby introduced into the circulation. Long non-coding RNAs (lncRNAs)—which regulate biological and genetic functions—have been identified in EVs. lncRNAs have been implicated in numerous biological disorders because they regulate developmental processes. As wells as secreting the components described above into the circulating blood, cells can also export the precursors produced by pathogens such as viruses during their replication. One example of this phenomenon is provided by the detection of covalently closed circular DNA (cccDNA) and pre-genomic RNA (pgRNA) formed during the replication of hepatitis B virus (HBV). The assembly of proteins and nucleic acids originating from EVs also can change in response to various stimulations. Therefore, EVs derived from cells or organs under stress or affected by disease are potential biomarkers as they are different from those secreted during healthy homeostasis [
 <xref rid="B12-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Liquid biopsy methods are now used widely to detect many aspects of chronic liver diseases. They are informative and provide in-depth information about the diverse spectrum of disease progression.
</p>
