<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Similar to the approach in the previous study [
 <xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], the association between the state rainfall level and LASV transmissibility are modelled by a linear mixed-effect regression (LMER) model in Eqn (
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eqn3">3</xref>), 
 <disp-formula id="eqn3">
  <label>3</label>
  <graphic xlink:href="S0950268819002267_eqn3.jpg" mime-subtype="png" position="float" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </disp-formula>Here, 
 <bold>E</bold>(·) represents the expectation function and 
 <italic>j</italic> is the region index corresponding to different regions (states). Term 
 <italic>c</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>j</italic>
 </sub> is the interception term of the 
 <italic>j</italic>-th region to be estimated and it is variable from different regions, serving as the baseline scale of transmissibility in different states. The term 
 <italic>t</italic> denotes the cumulative lag in the model and 〈rainfall
 <sub>
  <italic>j,t</italic>
 </sub>〉 represents the average monthly rainfall of the previous 
 <italic>t</italic> months from the turning point, 
 <italic>τ</italic>, of the 
 <italic>j</italic>-th region. The range of lag term, 
 <italic>t</italic>, will be considered from 4 to 9 months, which is explained by the time interval between the peak of the rainfall and the peak of rodent population [
 <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. As illustrated in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Figure 3</xref>, the reproduction numbers, 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>j</italic>
 </sub>s, are estimated for different epidemics from the selected growth models. The regression coefficient, 
 <italic>β</italic>, is to be estimated. Hence, the term (
 <italic>e
  <sup>β</sup>
 </italic> – 1) × 100% is the percentage changing rate (of 
 <italic>R</italic>), which can be interpreted as the percentage change in transmissibility due to a one-unit (mm) increase in the average of the monthly rainfall level over the past 7 months. The framework of the regression is based on the exponential form of the predictor to model the expectation of transmissibility (e.g. 
 <italic>R</italic>); this framework is inspired by previous work [
 <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>–
 <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. To quantify the impacts of state rainfall, we calculate the percentage changing rate with different cumulative lags (
 <italic>t</italic>) from 4 to 9 months and estimate their significant levels. Only the lag terms (
 <italic>t</italic>) with significant estimates are presented in this work. 
</p>
