<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>After virus entry, the polyproteins pp1a and pp1ab are processed into 16 nsps by the viral proteases 3CLpro and PLpro. These cleavage events play a key role in the virus life cycle because they lead to the generation, among others, of the RNA‐dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp) required for viral RNA replication and transcription. Due to the high conservation of the cleavage sites and of the protease structures, these proteases are an optimal antiviral target. A recent study described the X‐ray structures of SARS‐CoV‐2 3CLpro alone and in the presence of an α‐ketoamide inhibitor.
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>55</sup>
 </xref> Based on these findings, the α‐ketoamide inhibitor was optimized and showed antiviral activity against SARS‐CoV‐2 at concentrations lower than 10 μM in Calu3 lung cells. Protease inhibitors used in human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) therapy, such as lopinavir/ritonavir (a combination known as Kaletra), nelfinavir, also limit SARS‐CoV‐2 propagation in infected cells,
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>39</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0057" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>57</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0064" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>64</sup>
 </xref> and they are being tested in several ongoing clinical trials.
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0056" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>56</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>60</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>61</sup>
 </xref> However, the molecular basis of their inhibition mechanism has not been elucidated yet due to the fact that HIV and CoV proteases belong to different protease classes. Unfortunately, the first clinical trials reported that lopinavir, combined with the ritonavir that boosts lopinavir levels by interfering with cytochrome P450 metabolism, does not have any significant effect on SARS‐CoV‐2 infection.
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0058" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>58</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
