<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Eco-friendly biological control measures, such as genetically modified mosquitoes artificially infected with Wolbachia - a bacterium that stops dengue - placed in large water-storage reservoirs/tanks and rain fall streams were deployed successfully in 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> vector control in China, Brazil, Singapore, and parts of America. Another biological control measure is the use of fish/copepod predators, which can prey upon, parasitize, and compete with the wild vector and reduce the target vector populations.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
  <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>-
  <xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
 </sup> Deployment of genetically engineered mosquitoes, sugar toxic baits, and biologically new larvicide or adulticide agents' complements are crucial tools in improving biocontrol approaches and strategies and should be used in parallel with insecticide resistance monitoring and development of appropriate countermeasures.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>-
  <xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
 </sup> Strengthening local-tailored and proven effective communities' preventive and resilience methods coupled with educative approaches are needed in delivering vulnerable populations coverage against re/emerging public health threats (particularly maternal-child healthcare).
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
  <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
 </sup> Furthermore, adoption and adaptation of the CDC Pregnancy Risk Assessment Monitoring System to improve tracking and monitoring of Zika-related fetal development and birth defects, Guillain-Barre syndrome, and related motherhood and childhood complications in all endemic countries are highly recommended among the local population and expatriate workers. There is also need to establish green space to mitigate climate change as well as to develop a biodiversity conservation culture, which incorporates improved sanitation and drainage systems and mosquito repellants plants and waste management to develop a healthier environment. When introducing Wolbachia into urban or rural communities, it is important to understand mosquito host fitness and coexistence, the influence of biological competition outcomes, and the impact of vector competence as well as the ecological and bacterial profile in control and elimination.
</p>
