<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0120">Animal models play a crucial role in uncovering the mechanisms of viral pathogenicity from the entrance to transmission and in the scheming of therapeutic strategies. Previously, various animal models were used for examining replication of SARS-CoV which showed the symptoms of severe infection [
 <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. In case MERS-CoV no pathogenesis was observed in small animals as against seen in case of SARS-CoV. Mice was found not susceptible to MERS-coronavirus infection because of noncompatibility of the DPP
 <sub>4</sub> receptor [
 <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. As the entire genome of COVID-19 is more than 80% similar previous human SARS-like bat CoV, hence animal models previously used for SARS-CoV may be useful to study the pathogenicity of COVID-19. Novel coronaviruses and SARS both recognize human ACE
 <sub>2</sub> cell receptor. Conclusively TALEN or CRISPR-mediated genetically modified hamsters or other small animals may be used to test the pathogenicity of novel coronaviruses. It was observed that SARS-CoV having a mutation for spike glycoprotein, replicate and cause severe disease in Rats (F344) [
 <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. Thus spike glycoprotein targeting therapeutics is a suitable option against coronaviruses. In recent studies to formulate some therapeutic strategy against COVID-19 clinical isolates and mice models were used [
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Artificial intelligence prediction were also used in similar studies to investigate the inhibitory role of the drug against SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Randomized clinical trials were also used in COVID-19 patients [
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. It is now essential for scientists worldwide to collaborate on the design of an effective model and to investigate the in vivo mechanisms associated with COVID-19 pathogenesis.
</p>
