<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8">As first described by Witkowski et al. in 1972, ribavirin (1-β-D-ribofuranosyl-1,2,4-triazole-3-carboxamide) is a triazole nucleoside analogue that inhibits replication of both DNA and RNA viruses by interfering with viral mRNA synthesis (Witkowski et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117">1973</xref>). It is active against a wide range of viruses including adenoviruses, arenaviruses, bunyaviruses, herpesviruses, orthomyxoviruses, paramyxoviruses, picornaviruses, poxviruses, retroviruses, rhabdoviruses and rotaviruses, but the strongest effect exhibits against influenza viruses and, in combination with interferon, against hepatitis C virus (Dolin 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">1985</xref>; Gustafson 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">1986</xref>; Te et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">2007</xref>). It has several possible mechanisms of action. Firstly, as ribavirin monophosphate, generated by adenosine kinase-mediated phosphorylation, it can indirectly inhibit the synthesis of guanine nucleotides. Further, the phosphorylated triphosphate form competitively inhibits binding of ATP and GTP to RNA polymerase (Riviere and Papich 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">2013</xref>). Orally administered ribavirin has been shown to worsen the condition of cats experimentally infected with calicivirus. Toxic effects mainly resulted from drug-induced thrombocytopenia and include depression of red and white blood cells, increased alanine aminotransferase activity, icterus and body weight loss. However, observed clinical symptoms withdrew within one week after treatment discontinuation (Riviere and Papich 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">2013</xref>; Povey 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">1978</xref>). Interestingly, these side effects were not observed in dogs treated for 2 weeks with 60 mg/kg of the drug (Canonico 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">1985</xref>). In kittens experimentally infected with feline infectious peritonitis virus (FIPV), treatment with neither free nor liposomal ribavirin improved survival rate and, similarly to animals infected with calicivirus, resulted in intrinsic toxicity (Riviere and Papich 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">2013</xref>; Weiss et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114">1993</xref>). Activity of ribavirin has also been demonstrated against bovine viral diarrhoea virus, bovine herpes virus-1 and parrot bornavirus 4 in cell culture models (Glotov et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2004</xref>; Musser et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">2015</xref>).
</p>
