<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Others have also addressed how the immune response to influenza infection can be altered in an allergic setting. Using an 
 <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic> model of asthma Samarasinghe 
 <italic>et al</italic> showed that infection during the acute phase of asthma leads to protection from influenza virus induced weight loss and disease. However, infection during chronic asthma led to the loss of this protective effect and mice were found to develop lung pathology comparable to that of infected PBS treated mice. They believed the protective effect seen in acute asthmatic mice was due to the maintenance of an intact epithelium, reduced interferon responses and increased production of insulin-like growth factor-1 [
 <xref rid="pone.0190063.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. In a more recent study Furuya 
 <italic>et al</italic> concluded that influenza induced pathology can be prevented by the transient increase in production of TGF-β during allergic asthma. They show that asthmatic mice infected with influenza displayed a reduced cytokine storm and cytotoxicity in the airways and that by deleting TGF-β receptor II they abrogated the resistance of asthmatic mice to influenza [
 <xref rid="pone.0190063.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. From the data presented here we suggest that CD11b+ DCs play an important role in the protective effects seen in BTE sensitised mice infected with influenza. We show that low dose sensitisation with BTE led to the increase in CD11b+ and CD103+ DCs in the MLN and the lungs. Although both DC populations were found to increase, the magnitude of the increase in CD11b+ DCs was significantly larger. This is perhaps not surprising as CD11b+ DCs have been shown to rapidly translocate to the MLN following allergen exposure. It has also been demonstrated that in the presence of low allergen dose, conventional CD11b+ DCs and not monocyte-derived DCs are the main DCs to migrate to the MLN and present to CD4 T cells priming for a Th2 immune response [
 <xref rid="pone.0190063.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0190063.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. In contrast, during a primary influenza infection both CD11b+ and CD103+ DCs have been shown to capture viral antigen and transport it to the lung draining lymph nodes. However, in this situation only the CD103+ DCs present viral antigen to naïve CD8 T cells [
 <xref rid="pone.0190063.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0190063.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0190063.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. We propose that prior exposure to BTE, before influenza infection, leads to lung inflammation, activation and recruitment of DCs and the disruption of the airway epithelium, which exposes lung CD11b+ DCs normally located in the submucosa and lung parenchyma [
 <xref rid="pone.0190063.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] to viral antigen, which they capture and then carry to lung draining lymph nodes where they cross-present to CD8 T cells. In support of this we have shown that influenza infection following sensitisation resulted in a significant increase in CD11b+ DCs in the MLN, compared to infected PBS treated mice. In contrast, numbers of CD103+ DCs in the MLN were found to be similar in both infected PBS and BTE treated mice, with both higher than in non-infected BTE treated mice. In addition, we also found that the 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> proliferation of transferred naive OT-1 CD8 T cells within the MLN was greater in infected BTE sensitised mice compared to infected PBS treated mice, suggesting that there was a significant increase in antigen presentation to CD8 T cells in these mice. To identify which DC population was responsible for this increased proliferation we sorted CD103+ and CD11b+ DCs from infected PBS treated or BTE sensitised mice and co-cultured them with naïve OT-1 CD8 T cells. To our surprise, we found that in infected BTE sensitised mice the enhanced T cell proliferation came from T cells co-cultured with CD11b+ DCs and not CD103+ DCs. The idea that CD11b+ DCs are able to acquire and present influenza antigen is not new. Several groups have shown that CD11b+ DCs are more efficient in viral antigen uptake in the lung, compared to CD103+ DCs they migrate poorly to the lung draining lymph nodes during the early stages of the immune response to primary influenza infection [
 <xref rid="pone.0190063.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0190063.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0190063.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0190063.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. However, Ballesteros-Tato 
 <italic>et al</italic> have demonstrated that during the peak of the T cell response to influenza infection (day 5–10 p.i.), lung CD11b+ DCs are able to capture viral antigen, process the antigen into the MHC class I pathway and migrate to the lung draining lymph nodes where they cross-present to naïve CD8 T cells [
 <xref rid="pone.0190063.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Although both CD103+ and CD11b+ DCs can be infected by influenza, a number of groups have shown that the virus is only able to propagate in the CD103+DCs and this is thought to be due to the inhibition of viral replication by type I interferons in CD11b+ DCs [
 <xref rid="pone.0190063.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Whilst not investigated in these experiments, it is possible that following BTE sensitisation CD11b+ DCs no longer produce type I interferons, allowing them to become permissive to viral replication.
</p>
