<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition to altered DC migration and function, a subsequent effect was also seen on the CD8 T cell populations in the lungs. Sensitisation prior to infection led to an earlier increase in CD8 T cells and virus specific CD8 T cells in the lungs, which peaked at day 8 p.i., earlier that the peak seen in the PBS infected mice. Not only was the peak earlier, but the magnitude of this increase was also much greater in infected BTE sensitised mice and these T cells were also found to produce more IFN-γ. Interestingly, at later time points after infection (day 14 p.i.) there was a significant decrease in the number of T cells and those producing IFN-γ in the lungs of BTE sensitised and infected mice compared to PBS infected mice, indicating there was faster resolution of influenza virus induced disease and reduced lung damage. In supported of this, we also found a reduction in the amount of albumin leakage in the airways of influenza infected BTE sensitised mice compared to PBS infected mice at day 14 p.i. In contrast to the data shown by Furuya 
 <italic>et al</italic>, we find that T cells play a key role in the enhanced protection to influenza in asthmatic mice. These differences could be due to the use of a different asthma model. In their studies the majority of the experiments were performed using an OVA sensitisation and challenge model, and the time between the last challenge and infection was also much longer compared to our study, where infection was given twenty-four hours after the last allergen challenge. Interestingly, even though they saw a reduction in immunopathology in infected asthmatic mice, they did not see a difference in viral clearance [
 <xref rid="pone.0190063.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. This again is in contrast to our findings where we show that BTE sensitisation prior to infection had no effect on the replication of the virus in the lung, but did in fact enhance the clearance of the virus, presumably through the increased number and activity of virus specific CD8 T cells.
</p>
