<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The value of genomic data cannot be understated and has yet to reach its full potential for RABV. While the emphasis of this paper is on the application of the workflow and not phylogenetic analysis, the genomic data has already provided new insights. For example, uncovering the presence of two RABV subclades in Kenya, including one that is closely related to the lineage found in Tanzania. The extent of cross-border transmission and the scale over which persisting RABV lineages circulate in East Africa will have important implications for national and regional control efforts. In 
 <xref ref-type="boxed-text" rid="B1">Box 1</xref>, we suggest how genetic data can inform control measures at different stages in the pathway to elimination. In addition, during the application of our workflow in Tanzania we were able to show directly how genomic data enhanced an investigation of a rabies outbreak on the island of Pemba (K. Lushasi, Ifakara Health Institute, unpublished report). Pemba is a small island (988 km 
 <sup>2</sup>) off the coast of Tanzania. After four years of sustained vaccination campaigns, rabies appeared to have been eliminated from Pemba, with the last case detected mid-2014. However, after a lapse in vaccination efforts there was a rabies outbreak in 2016–2017. Samples collected in the early stages of the outbreak were exported to the UK as a priority for sequencing but still experienced a lag time of around three months. During our first field trip to validate in-country MinION sequencing in Tanzania (2017), we had the opportunity to sequence more samples from the outbreak. Eight samples were sequenced with a turnaround of two days, yielding whole genome consensus sequences that provided evidence of multiple incursions from mainland Tanzania (see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f7">Figure 7</xref>). This emphasises the importance of maintaining vaccination coverage and continued surveillance on Pemba to contain incursions and sustain freedom from rabies.
</p>
