<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4">The novel coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) has been documented to have an efficient human to human transmission process via airborne, droplet and contact routes. Unlike the SARS-CoV, patients of SARS-CoV-2 can transmit the infection during the incubation period as well [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. The age group with the highest risk for acquiring primary and secondary cases of infection is 50–65 years (most cancers are found in the same age group). About 50% of patients have a subclinical infection, 30% have mild to moderate symptoms and 20% can develop severe symptoms with 5–10% requiring ICU care and ventilatory requirement. Symptoms common to most coronavirus infections are fever, chills, generalized myalgia, drowsiness, cough, shortness of breath, abdominal pain, nausea, vomiting and diarrhoea. The median duration of viral shedding is about 20 days and longest known to be 37 days, with continue shedding until death, unaltered by the administration of antiviral drugs such as Ritonavir and Lopinavir [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The median time of requirement of invasive mechanical ventilation reported is 14.5 days, and the median time to death being 18.5 days [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Sepsis, followed by respiratory failure, adult respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), heart failure, acute kidney injury, shock and secondary infections (including ventilator-associated pneumonia) are the common complications with severe infections [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The virus can be isolated from oropharyngeal and respiratory secretions and also in stool samples of affected individuals. However, the virus has not been isolated in the blood or urine [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. The World Health Organization (WHO) and Centre for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) recommend RT-PCR for laboratory diagnosis of SAR-CoV-2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. China, where the pandemic started, has now entered the post pandemic or the transitional phase, and clinical epidemiological data from China can prove to be a guiding light for the management of cases. So far social distancing, a modern form of quarantine, has proven to be the most effective preventive strategy for containment of this pandemic. Two drugs, remdesivir and hydroxychloroquine, have shown in vitro efficacy against SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Further population studies with these drugs are awaited, and it will take another few months till we have a vaccine for SARS-CoV-2.
</p>
