<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par29">Temporal patterns of disease outbreaks were decomposed into long-term (secular), cyclical and seasonal trends. The decomposed temporal patterns demonstrated statistically significant seasonality for FMD outbreaks, which is in line with Nejash’s [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] findings who pointed out season as risk factors for FMD outbreak. In contrast to our result, Jemberu et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] reported that FMD outbreak incidence has neither long-term nor seasonal trend in Ethiopia. In the present study, the peak FMD outbreaks were recorded in March (the dry season) and the low in August (the rainy season). The variation of FMD outbreak in season might be related to the variation in animal movements. Outbreak numbers increased during December, January, February and March (reaching peak in March). This might be coinciding with the increased animal transports due to the increased meat demand during the impending Christmas (at the end of December) and Easter festival (March–April) celebrations of the Christian population in the Amhara region, which are the two big religious festivals for Orthodox Christians in Amhara region in particular and in Ethiopia in general. Similarly, peak FMD outbreaks coinciding or following special holidays have been observed in endemic countries such as Sri Lanka. This has been related to animal transports in response to the increased demand of meat for the impending Milad-Un-Nabi (March) and Ramadan festival of the Muslim population as well as the ‘cattle salvage’ practice associated with the two Buddhist festivals Vesak (May) and Poson (June) celebrations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. On the other hand, in most midland and highland parts of Amhara region, during the rainy season of the years wide areas of farmland are planted with crops, as a result the movement of domestic animals is restricted and kept confined on small plots of grazing lands, which could be the reason for low incidence of FMD outbreaks in this season.
</p>
