<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several nasal formulations have been studied in order to induce the uptake of zidovudine (AZT) in the central nervous system. It is well-known that AZT penetration in the CNS is poor because it is a substrate of AET systems expressed by both the BBB and BCSFB [
 <xref rid="B107-pharmaceutics-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>,
 <xref rid="B108-pharmaceutics-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>,
 <xref rid="B109-pharmaceutics-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. The AET systems induce, in vivo, an asymmetric transport of AZT across these barriers, where the rate of AZT efflux from the CNS to blood is greater than its influx rate [
 <xref rid="B110-pharmaceutics-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>], resulting in a poor CNS/plasma ratio (about 0.1) of zidovudine [
 <xref rid="B111-pharmaceutics-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]. It is important to underline that AZT activity in the CNS is of great importance in those CSF subarachnoid spaces that contain macrophages constituting the only site of HIV replication in the brain [
 <xref rid="B112-pharmaceutics-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>,
 <xref rid="B113-pharmaceutics-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>]. The presence of AET systems in macrophage membranes [
 <xref rid="B25-pharmaceutics-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] can constitute a further obstacle for AZT penetration in these cells. Significantly high concentrations of AZT therefore appear necessary in the bloodstream in order to allow the drug to reach and maintain a minimum effective concentration in the CNS. The intravenous administration of high doses of AZT allowed its detection in the CSF of rats [
 <xref rid="B114-pharmaceutics-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>], a phenomenon probably due to the saturation of AET systems. Indeed, the AZT amounts detected in the CSF increased when AZT was intravenously co-administered with probenecid [
 <xref rid="B114-pharmaceutics-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>], even if it is known that the concomitant presence of high hematic AZT and AET inhibitor concentrations cause severe unwanted effects [
 <xref rid="B27-pharmaceutics-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B115-pharmaceutics-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>].
</p>
