<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0030">Discovery by zur Hausen and his colleagues of a virus causally connected to cervical cancer laid the foundation for the development of HPV vaccines to prevent this disease, especially once it was established that HPV infection was common, and progression to cancer slow and not particularly common. The then conventional approaches to the development of a new vaccine were precluded because HPV could not be grown in the lab, which would be necessary to enable development of an attenuated virus vaccine or a killed virus vaccine. However, technological developments enabled progress on HPV vaccines. The then newly achieved ability to express genes in cell culture enabled laboratory production of HPV proteins. Prokaryotic expression systems were initially used to produce virus-encoded proteins, but the proteins produced lacked the three-dimensional conformation of the proteins as assembled in the native virus, and the antibodies they induced in animals were ineffective at binding and neutralizing HPV. When eukaryotic expression systems were developed, my Chinese colleague in virology, Dr. Jian Zhou, whom I met while on sabbatical in Cambridge, England, agreed with me to try to assemble the HPV shell when he came to work in my lab in Brisbane, Australia, in 1990. Eukaryotic cell expression of virus genes cloned from a clinical specimen into a vaccinia expression vector, with gene translation initiated from an appropriate start codon, turned out to be successful in producing assembled capsid proteins in monkey kidney cells,
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref> whereas virus genes cloned from a cancer had sequence errors that precluded efficient capsid assembly even in a eukaryotic expression system.
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>10</sup>
 </xref> Over the next few years, we and other researchers used more efficient gene expression systems (baculovirus, yeast)
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> to produce larger quantities of correctly conformed viral capsid proteins, and these, when used as the basis of a vaccine, induced an antibody that bound to the HPV capsid. These vaccines were shown to prevent papilloma virus infection in animal models, and then to prevent papilloma virus infection and cervical precancer in humans, first in commercially funded clinical trials, and subsequently in epidemiological studies in countries where vaccination had been routinely introduced.
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
