<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The Rockborn vaccine was supposedly withdrawn from markets after the mid-1990s. However, Demeter et al. and Martella identified Rockborn-like viruses in vaccines currently on the market [
 <xref rid="B61-viruses-11-00944" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-viruses-11-00944" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Vaccine X (also called Vaccine D and Vanguard), a Rockborn-based vaccine, has been used in recent years in Africa. Isolates from vaccinated dogs with distemper in Africa were investigated [
 <xref rid="B63-viruses-11-00944" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-viruses-11-00944" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. The isolates were only distantly related to Ondersteport- and Snyder Hill-derived vaccines based on phylogenetic analysis of the H gene of CDV. Vaccine D was more closely related to the isolates, but could still be distinguished from them and showed 99% nucleotide identity to a Hungarian vaccine strain (EF095750) and to a Chinese CDV isolate from a lesser panda (red panda— 
 <italic>Ailurus fulgens</italic>) (AF178039) [
 <xref rid="B64-viruses-11-00944" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Disease in the lesser panda had previously been demonstrated to be vaccine-induced [
 <xref rid="B65-viruses-11-00944" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Pardu et al. [
 <xref rid="B66-viruses-11-00944" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>] also reported a North American isolate from a vaccinated dog with distemper which was related to the lesser panda strain. Vaccine D also grouped in lineage America 2 with many CDVs of wildlife species [
 <xref rid="B64-viruses-11-00944" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>], raising the possibility of a vaccine-derived virus in these species. An alternative explanation is that the virulent Rockborn parent virus infected wildlife in Africa and on other continents. However, the occurrence of highly related viruses in such diverse locations would be consistent with vaccine distribution worldwide, and could account for the wide geographical spread of Rockborn-like viruses, their reversion, and cases of disease in vaccinated animals. 
</p>
