<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>   
 <list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
   <p>Methods/design description 
    <bold>:</bold> some elements related to this part of the manuscript should be further expanded and detailed for a better understanding and accuracy of the manuscript. Especially, the authors should consider:
   </p>
   <p> - Improving the description of the YFV infection assays in mosquitoes. For example, it is not clear the number of mosquitoes and replicates used to determine the viral load in the body of WT or wMel mosquitoes. </p>
   <p> - Similarly, it is important to clarify the design and data presentation of the transmission assays in mosquitoes. For example, it is not clear if each bar on Figure 4 represents the data combination of 8 mosquitoes injected with the same saliva of a given mosquito (1 x 8 x 8) or if it is the data collected from an individual mosquito injected with the saliva of a given individual mosquito (1 x 1 x 8). This may also cause confusion when interpreting this figure as the Y-axis labels refer to “infected mosquitoes per saliva” while the subtitles refer to “the number of YFV copies…per mosquito”. Additionally, the authors should check the position of the graphs on the right (A and C) and left (B and D) panels as they seem not to match their respective description in the subtitles.</p>
   <p> - An important question that was raised is why the authors have chosen to inject mosquito saliva into mice instead of feeding such mosquitoes on mice in order to test transmission directly.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Results/hypothesis/conclusions:</p>
   <p> - The leukocyte counts are significantly high in mice inoculated with the saliva of wMel mosquitoes orally exposed to YFV (Figures 5C and 5D). Do the authors have any hypothesis to explain why this is happening?</p>
   <p> - Because the WT mosquito population used in this work presented a relatively low vector competence to YFV, on page 10 (Discussion, second column) the authors infer this phenotype as a representation of Brazilian  
    <italic>Ae. aegypti </italic>populations. While this is a plausible hypothesis, I would suggest the authors to be more cautious with this statement as vector competence to YFV of many other  
    <italic>Ae. aegypti </italic>populations must be tested before one assumes this fact.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
