<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Indeed, to effectively prevent and control this epidemic, one of the most critical tasks is to clearly and comprehensively understand the epidemic from different perspectives. Currently, a large body of research has been accomplished, especially in the field of medicine. Mainly, these investigations focus on the genomic characterization of the novel coronavirus [
 <xref rid="B3-ijerph-17-02563" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-ijerph-17-02563" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], the clinical characterization of the infected patients [
 <xref rid="B5-ijerph-17-02563" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-ijerph-17-02563" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], and the medical diagnosis and treatment of the infected cases [
 <xref rid="B7-ijerph-17-02563" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-ijerph-17-02563" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The medical research immensely contributes to the recognition of the virus’ characteristics and to obtaining the cure. However, no study has discussed the spatio-temporal patterns of the 2019-nCoV epidemic. Mainly, the spatio-temporal patterns describe the epidemical characteristics, including spatio-temporal distribution (regular, clustered, or random), spatio-temporal association, and spatio-temporal evolution [
 <xref rid="B9-ijerph-17-02563" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. This is beneficial for enhancing the understanding of this epidemic in the spatio-temporal dimension and providing reliable information for decision-making. For example, Liu et al. [
 <xref rid="B10-ijerph-17-02563" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] and Dong et al. [
 <xref rid="B11-ijerph-17-02563" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] analyzed the spatial and temporal characteristics of human infection of avian influenza A(H7N9) in mainland China in 2013. Their results showed that there existed spatially clustered characteristics. Meanwhile, the research by Qiu et al. [
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-17-02563" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] identified additional risk factors. To understand the dynamic spread of porcine epidemic diarrhea in 2013 in the US, global and local analysis methods uncovered the spatio-temporal patterns of this epidemic [
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-17-02563" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The spatio-temporal distribution and diffusion pattern of the dengue outbreak in Swat, Pakistan, in 2013, was also discovered based on the spatio-temporal analysis method, and the implications were assessed and recommendations were made [
 <xref rid="B14-ijerph-17-02563" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Spatio-temporal patterns (i.e., trends and clusters) of influenza in 2005–2018, in China, were detected by spatio-temporal analysis where high-risk areas and the corresponding reasons were identified [
 <xref rid="B15-ijerph-17-02563" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].
</p>
