<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Previous studies have reported the association between HFRS epidemics and temperature in many areas of China.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>–
  <xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]
 </sup> These studies have indicated that temperature is an important factor for HFRS epidemics in China. On the one hand, temperature affects the incidence of HFRS by influencing rodent pregnancy rate, litter size, birth rate, and survival rate. On the other hand, temperature may affect the spread of HV among humans and the incidence of hemorrhagic fever in the population.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
  <xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]
 </sup> The results of the present study showed that MT
 <sub>2</sub>, MT
 <sub>3</sub>, MT
 <sub>4</sub>, MT
 <sub>5</sub>, MinT
 <sub>2</sub>, MinT
 <sub>3</sub>, MinT
 <sub>4</sub>, MinT
 <sub>5</sub>, MaxT
 <sub>2</sub>, MaxT
 <sub>3</sub>, MaxT
 <sub>4</sub>, and MaxT
 <sub>5</sub> were negatively associated with the monthly HFRS cases in Changchun. Thus, effective surveillance of HFRS epidemics can be conducted by monitoring the fluctuations of these parameters in the area so that targeted countermeasures can be taken in advance. Liu et al have applied a case-crossover design and conditional logistic regression to analyze the relationship between the incidence rates of HFRS and meteorological variables in one national surveillance area for HFRS in Shandong Province.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]
 </sup> They have found that the MWV was positively associated with HFRS incidence. We found that MWV
 <sub>1</sub> had positive effects on the monthly HFRS cases in a cross-correlation analysis, which was consistent with the previous studies in Shandong Province. However, no study has yet been published revealing the underlying mechanism. A possible explanation might be that high wind velocity is conducive to the spread of virus particles. Higher levels of humidity may affect the survival of rodent hosts but are also known to influence the infectivity and stability of the virus in the ex vivo environment.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
  <xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]
 </sup> Some studies also found that HV is limited in their spread to high humidity environments for extended ex vivo stability. The present study found that relative humidity factors, including RH
 <sub>0</sub>, RH
 <sub>1</sub>, and RH
 <sub>2</sub>, affected HFRS negatively, which is consistent with the findings of previous studies in China.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
  <xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]
 </sup> Appropriate precipitation not only stimulates plant growth but also improves the bioenergy and infection rate of the HV, which eventually increases HFRS incidence. However, excessive precipitation could have reduced the rodent population by destroying their habitats in Eastern China.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
  <xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]
 </sup> By reducing the possibility of human contact with rodents, the likelihood of transmission of the virus reduces as well. Our data indicate that AP
 <sub>2</sub>, AP
 <sub>3</sub>, and AP
 <sub>4</sub> were negatively associated with the incidence of HFRS, which is consistent with the findings of most of previous studies.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
  <xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
  <xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
  <xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]
 </sup> HV is easily inactivated by heat and ultraviolet radiation, which destroys the viral nucleic acid and reduces its infectivity.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
  <xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]
 </sup> A key finding of this study was that SD
 <sub>3</sub>, SD
 <sub>4</sub>, SD
 <sub>5</sub>, and SD
 <sub>6</sub> were negatively associated with HFRS incidence, possibly because increased solar radiation may reduce virus survival outside the host and reduce the risk of disease in humans.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]
 </sup> In the present study, multiple regression was applied to determine the relationship between HFRS epidemics and climate factors in Changchun, by incorporating climate factors of the previous months based on a PCA. This model was reliable and had a better fit (adjusted R
 <sup>2</sup> = 0.456) than that in the general multiple regression model (adjusted R
 <sup>2</sup> = 0.397).
</p>
