<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>C57BL/6 WT mice were obtained from the Animal Resources Center (Perth, Australia). AG129 mice were bred in-house. Twenty-eight-day-old male and female mice, in equal distribution, were inoculated with viable virus or vaccine particles (10
 <sup>4</sup> pfu CHIKV-WT or CHIKV-NoLS), liposome-delivered RNA (2 μg of CHIKV-WT or CHIKV-NoLS RNA complexed with 0.3 mg of CAF01) or RNA alone (2 μg of CHIKV-WT or CHIKV-NoLS RNA) subcutaneously in a 20-μl volume in the ventral/lateral side of the right foot. The immunologically competent C57BL/6 mouse footpad model of acute CHIKV disease recapitulates the arthritis, tenosynovitis, and myositis associated with mononuclear cell infiltration seen in CHIKV-infected patients. Mock-inoculated mice received 20 μl of VP-SFM media alone or VP-SFM media containing 0.3 mg of CAF01. Mice were monitored for changes in weight and the development of disease signs every 24 h. CHIKV-induced footpad swelling was assessed by measuring the height and width of the perimetatarsal area of the hind foot, using Kincrome digital vernier calipers. Disease signs in inoculated AG129 mice were scored on a scale of 0–4 where 4 is immediate humane endpoint. Clinical scores were assessed as follows: 0 = no disease; 1 = hunched, ruffled fur; 2 = a score of 1 in addition to dehydration, lethargy, ocular exudates, and diarrhea; 3 = a score of 1 and/or 2 in addition to vocalization, modified gait, hind limb weakness, and being emaciated; 4 = neurological disease signs (tremors/seizures), splayed legs, circling, hyperexcitability, weight loss ≥15%, and dragging limbs. Mice were sacrificed by CO
 <sub>2</sub> asphyxiation at endpoints. Mice were challenged with 10
 <sup>4</sup> pfu CHIKV-WT subcutaneously in the ventral/lateral side of the right (ipsilateral) or left (contralateral) foot 30 days after immunization. All animal procedures and experiments were performed in accordance with the guidelines set out by the Griffith University Animal Ethics Committee.
</p>
