<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Previous time-series analyses have demonstrated viral interference after accounting for seasonal factors, suggesting that epidemics of influenza virus and rhinovirus infection tend to shift the timing of epidemics for other viruses [
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Others have used case-control–type analyses of codetection data to demonstrate that rhinovirus infection, as an exposure, was inversely associated with the probability of observing adenovirus [
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] and influenza virus infections, with the latter 2 viral infections framed as the outcomes of interest [
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. However, in a study of military recruits in which adenovirus was the dominant FRI agent, Wang et al used a case-control analysis to demonstrate the reverse phenomenon—that adenovirus infection as an exposure reduced the odds of rhinovirus infection as the outcome of interest [
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. However, they noted how another interpretation of their results is that rhinovirus infection reduced the risk of subsequent adenovirus infection. The opposing framing of outcomes and exposures in these codetection studies highlights issues in interpreting results from such cross-sectional and case-control designs, in which the sequence of infections cannot be ascertained. What distinguishes this work is our use of a cohort study design by which we can identify the temporality and sequence of initial and subsequent FRI episodes, which the previous studies could not do. Observations positive for a specific virus group are essentially being compared against those negative for all viruses we tested for. Therefore, this analyses does not assess whether, for example, infections by the ERV group confers any protection relative to individuals who did not recently have any viral infection. 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup5">Supplementary Tables 1 and 2</xref> suggest that, relative to enlisted recruits for the main BMT intake types, incidence rates for subsequent FRI episodes were higher over the full course duration and for 19-week BMT intake types, respectively. This applied to all virus groups except AdV and FluV groups and was possibly due to confounding by common risk factors for repeated FRIs at the individual level [
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. However, in the shortest, 9-week BMT type and when censoring the data at shorter periods after enlistment, incidence rates were reduced for most virus groups relative to the average rates for recruits following enlistment. For FRI episodes as a whole, incidence rate ratios were 0.49 (95% CI, .29–.77; 
 <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001) in the data censored 4 weeks after enlistment (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup5">Supplementary Table 1</xref>). These observations therefore suggest that viral causes of FRI other than AdV and FluV may also confer short, time-limited protection. They also corroborate findings from 
 <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> on how a reduced hazard of a subsequent FRI episode occurs in the first 4 weeks following the initial FRI episode, relative to latter periods, and how FluV is more strongly protective during the former period. The difference between the viruses may thus be one of degree, with most viruses conferring some weak, time-limited protection, with the stronger effects from adenovirus and influenza virus becoming apparent when aggregating data over the full course duration. One mechanism consistent with such short-lived cross-protection is the triggering of interferon-stimulated genes and cytokines, causing nearby cells in the respiratory tract to enter an antiviral state [
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Alternatively, transient cross-protection could result from infection-induced behavioral changes, such as improved hand hygiene following an FRI and a short duration of reduced exposure to new pathogens while being furloughed on home leave. However, this on its own is likely inadequate to explain the extent of cross-protection observed with adenovirus and influenza virus infections relative to other FRI episodes. Other proposed mechanisms, such as competition for the same receptor-binding sites and intracellular host machinery for replication [
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], and an unfavorable physiological state of the host, such as high body temperatures upon an initial infection [
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], are more applicable to protection against coinfections but not, as demonstrated here, against sequential infection.
</p>
