<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>During the study period, different patterns of Victoria and Yamagata-lineage B viruses were observed. Regarding the distribution of the different lineages in relation to the age groups of the population studied, our study showed that both the Victoria and Yamagata viruses were more likely to infect patients aged between five and 14 years, which had also been observed in previous studies [
 <xref rid="B32-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Moreover, it can be observed that Victoria lineage viruses tend to be distributed according to age with a peak in children under 10 years. Meanwhile, Yamagata lineage viruses frequently show two peaks (in children younger than 10 years and a significant predominance towards individuals over 25 years, preferentially adults over 64 years), as in other countries [
 <xref rid="B12-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Interestingly, Vijaykrishna and colleagues [
 <xref rid="B12-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] proposed that age difference between Victoria and Yamagata-lineage infections is thought to be due to differences in the molecular aspects of cellular dynamics, which help the viruses to infect the epithelium of the respiratory tract, while Orsi and colleagues [
 <xref rid="B45-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] proposed a higher reproductive number (Ro) of the Victoria-lineage viruses, which might reduce the mean age of lineage-specific infections. More studies are required to determine whether there is indeed any difference with either of the B lineages in different age groups. Regarding the distribution of influenza B viruses in relation to the surveillance type, the highest proportion of young children (&lt; 4 years) within SARI patients could be due to different behaviors when a child is found to be sick. Children are more likely to be taken to hospital, especially for SARI cases. It is well known that SARI cases in children could lead to respiratory failure. Respiratory Sincitial Virus (RSV) and human Metapneumovirus (hMPV) significantly increase the risk of SARI, especially in children younger than 24 months. [
 <xref rid="B46-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Similar results have been obtained from other countries [
 <xref rid="B47-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. The finding from ILI sentinel sites revealed that the influenza positivity rate was high among children aged 5–9 years and became practically null in ages &gt;39 years. Interestingly, and even though ILI surveillance was only done during three of the eight years of the study, the proportion of influenza B found was significantly higher than the observed among SARI cases across different groups of age. Some studies have demonstrated that influenza played an important role in the viral aetiologies of ILI cases [
 <xref rid="B49-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>], while other respiratory viruses were essential for the cause of SARI, especially in children [
 <xref rid="B46-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>].
</p>
