<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <bold>What are the situations promoting oxidative stress?</bold> about our subject, it is known that oxidative stress is triggered by a wide variety of viral infections [
 <xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] including HIV 1, viral hepatitis B,C,D viruses, herpes viruses, respiratory viruses, most of the RNA viruses [
 <xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] probably also corona viruses belonging to this family. Let us remind that corona viruses are encapsulated RNA viruses with different types: the classic coronaviruses, responsible for moderate respiratory infections in general, the SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV involved in epidemics of more severe respiratory infections [
 <xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] and the new coronavirus (SARS-CoV2) discovered in January 2020 responsible for infectious disease called COVID-19 which is currently experiencing a worldwide outbreak [
 <xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Generally, viral infections lead to an increase in production of free radicals and a depletion of antioxidants [
 <xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The mode of action varies according to the viruses as demonstrated by the analysis of the oxidative stress induced by different viruses of the flaviviridae family [
 <xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] but we find these two phenomena increasing the oxidative stress in these RNA viruses infections and for Ivanov [
 <xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] one of the sources of production of these ROS could be the mitochondrial dysfunction caused by the penetration of the virus into the cell. A “cytokine storm” with release of Il-2, Il-6, Il-7, TNF α etc. as been described in COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. These authors described a cytokine shock with hyperinflammation accompanied by cytopenia, hyperferritinemia, [
 <xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] which is known to generate by the Fenton reaction (Fe²+ + H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>→ Fe³+ + HO‾ + HO‾) the production of ROS [
 <xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In addition, cytokines and endotoxins will stimulate one of the isoforms of nitric oxide synthetase (NOs), the inducible isoform iNOs, which will stimulate the production of nitric oxide NO which will react with the superoxide ion to give the powerful oxidizing peroxynitrite radical (ONOO‾) [
 <xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Other factors can promote the endogenous production of free radicals, such as intense physical activity, high blood pressure, tissue ischemia, the action of certain metals (lead, arsenic, cesium, mercury) counteracting the co-factors of antioxidant enzymes, notably superoxide dismutase, NADPH oxidase, myeloperoxidase which will lead to the production of the superoxide radical. Physical agents (ionizing radiation, UV), solvents, various pollutants, an anesthetic agent halotane and even paracetamol have also been incriminated in this genesis of free radicals [
 <xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Several techniques can be used to evaluate the state of oxidative stress such as electron paramagnetic resonance, direct evaluation of oxidative stress markers such as oxidized glutathione, malonyl aldehyde, quantification of total antioxidant status etc [
 <xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].
</p>
