<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0085">Viruses are the most abundant and diverse microbes on our planet. They have inhabited the Earth for billions of years [
 <xref rid="bb0005" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], have adapted to various environments, and are now found across all ecosystems. Viruses have contributed to the evolution of life on Earth, and can be beneficial for preserving ecosystems and important natural Earth cycles such as the carbon cycle in the sea [
 <xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. On the other hand, pathogenic viruses cause tens to hundreds of millions of plant, animal, and human infections annually, which result in high crop losses and numerous deaths (
 <xref rid="b0005" ref-type="boxed-text">Box 1</xref> ). Therefore, inactivating harmful viruses is crucial for better quality of life.
 <boxed-text id="b0005">
  <label>Box 1</label>
  <caption>
   <title>Viruses and Methods for Their Disinfection</title>
  </caption>
  <p id="p0005">Viruses are microscopic agents that can infect all forms of cellular life. Their classification as living organisms has historically been a question of philosophical debate, but they are unquestionably one of the most powerful engines of evolution on the planet [
   <xref rid="bb0255" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Most viruses are not harmful, and some are even beneficial for their hosts [
   <xref rid="bb0260" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. In recent years viruses have been increasingly used to promote human wellbeing. For example, lentiviruses [
   <xref rid="bb0265" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] and adeno-associated viruses [
   <xref rid="bb0270" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>] are being genetically engineered to formulate state-of-the-art gene therapies. Nevertheless, viruses have a bad reputation as causative agents of various human, animal, and plant diseases. This is no surprise because they have been the main players in numerous epidemics and pandemics throughout history (
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/managing-epidemics/en/" id="ir0005" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/managing-epidemics/en/</ext-link>). Several viral agents have contributed to the well-deserved ‘biohazard’ fame of viruses, including influenza, Ebola, HIV ,and coronavirus SARS-CoV-2. Despite not being such ‘viral celebrities’, waterborne viruses pose increasingly serious health and economic burdens in the present era that is threatened by climate change and the scarcity of potable water.
  </p>
  <p id="p0010">Different physical and chemical treatments have traditionally been applied for inactivation of viruses. Chlorine, alcohols, acids, alkalis, and bleach are examples of chemical disinfectants, whereas UV irradiation, filtration, pressure, and temperature are physical treatments [
   <xref rid="bb0275" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. The method of choice depends on the matrix to be disinfected and on the virus targeted for inactivation. Waterborne viruses, including enteric viruses [
   <xref rid="bb0280" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>] and plant tobamoviruses [
   <xref rid="bb0285" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>], are among the most stable of all viruses. To inactivate such stable viruses in a delicate matrix, the disinfection method needs to be strong enough to inactivate the virus but at the same time it needs to be nontoxic to maintain the quality and properties of the water. It is now known that chlorination, a traditionally used method for water disinfection, does not efficiently inactivate some viruses, and in the long term can pose a risk to human health through release of toxic byproducts [
   <xref rid="bb0290" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. In recent years novel waterborne virus inactivation technologies have been developed, such as membrane filtration, reverse osmosis, UV and ozone treatments, and hydrodynamic cavitation, each of which has their own pros and cons. The frequent disadvantages of these technologies are cost inefficiency, scalability problems, and unsustainable power usage. Laboratory-scale studies suggest that CP has potential to overcome these problems, but confirmation will require studies focused on pilot or industrial scale deployment of plasma-based disinfection devices.
  </p>
  <notes notes-type="alt-text" specific-use="for-accessibility" id="al0020">
   <p>Alt-text: Box 1</p>
  </notes>
 </boxed-text>
</p>
