<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22">Our study has several weaknesses. First, sequence sampling of the infected population in RCCS communities remained incomplete. Phylogenetic inferences are expected to improve with higher sampling fraction
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup>, though in practice, complete sequence sampling is hard to achieve. This study enrolled participants before immediate provision of ART was recommended in national guidelines, so that a relatively large proportion of infected individuals did not report ART use at first study visit, and could be sequenced. To perform similar phylogenetic analyses of ongoing viral spread in sub-Saharan Africa in the future, it is thus important to collect and store samples prior to ART initiation, and to investigate alternative sequencing protocols
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>
 </sup>. Second, relatively modest deep-sequencing quality compromised the length of deep-sequence reads
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup>. Analyses were based on relatively short read alignments of 250 bp that primarily covered the 
 <italic>gag</italic> gene, rather than the whole genome (Supplementary Figure 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). It is thus plausible that deep-sequence phylogenetic analyses may be more accurate than reported in this study as deep-sequence output with longer reads and greater coverage is becoming available
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>
 </sup>. Third, we found that inferring the direction of transmission became more challenging as the virus was increasingly closely related within individuals. We thus predict that the direction of transmission may be less frequently inferable in situations when the virus spreads more rapidly between persons, as in high-risk sexual networks among men having sex with men
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>, or among injecting drug users
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup>. For the same reason, sources of infections may be less accurately and/or less frequently inferable for pathogens that generate within-host viral diversity at a slower pace than HIV-1 
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
