<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This study has a number of limitations. First, HIV clustering and network inferences are directly affected by the sampling density [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]: studies with low sampling density showed minimal HIV clustering [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>], while in depth sampling allows more accurate characterization of HIV transmission network [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. In these deeper sampling density studies, the proportion of clustering sequences varied between 28 and 41%, though these studies were performed in heterogeneous population, in other countries and with various methods. While the number of individuals in our dataset is smaller than other studies, we reported an overall clustering proportion of 28.5% and up to 52.5% (332 out of 636) among MSM, consistent with previous reports. This overall clustering rate is also consistent with previous reports where interventions have been deemed useful [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] and allowed the characterization of the dynamics of HIV transmission [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. We have also estimated that the PRIMO ANRS Cohort is well representative of new HIV infections occurring in France. Indeed, based on the data recorded through the mandatory notification of new HIV infections, 12% of new HIV diagnoses are done at time of primary infection, corresponding to 600–700 cases each year [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. Therefore, the cases included in the PRIMO ANRS cohort represent approximately 15% of all primary infections diagnosed in the country. In addition, the proportion of MSM included in our study (71.4%) is similar to that observed at the national level (73.6%) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. Altogether, while our dataset is not ideal and that we could have missed a number of HIV infected individuals in the local network due to the lack of diagnosis of all PHI, it is sufficient to use the presented techniques to understand the transmission dynamics underlying the sampled epidemic.
</p>
