<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>When 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic>-infected mosquitoes are introduced in a wild population of uninfected mosquitoes, the infection is quickly wiped out unless the fraction of infected mosquitoes exceeds a threshold 
 <italic>θ</italic> of the total population. Recent mathematical models have established these threshold conditions as 
 <italic>θ</italic> = 0.15, 0.24, and 0.6 for wAlbB-, wMel-, and wMelPop-infected mosquitoes to establish a stable population, respectively [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006666.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Note that these threshold estimates are for an ideally controlled situation where mosquitoes do not mix with surrounding uninfected mosquitoes. The thresholds could be much higher for a release in the wild. Recent studies have found that maintaining a sustained wMelPop-infection requires continually introducing new wMelPop-infected mosquitoes into the wild population [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006666.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. A recent research has reported that large-scale releases of 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic>-infected 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> in the city of Cairns, Australia, invaded and spread through the populations, while 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic> infection at a smaller release site collapsed due to the immigration of 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic>-free mosquitoes from surrounding areas [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006666.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Population cage experiments indicated that the wAlbB strain can be successfully introduced into populations, and subsequently persist and spread [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006666.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Ndii et al. analyzed a first-order differential equation and found that a significant reduction in human dengue cases can be obtained by releasing wMel-infected mosquitoes, instead of wMelPop-infected mosquitoes due to the greatly reduced lifespans [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006666.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Ferguson et al. developed a mathematical model of DENV transmission incorporating the dynamics of viral infection in humans and mosquitoes, and predicted that wMel-infected 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> mosquitoes have a substantial effect on transmission [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006666.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Ross et al. found that, in most situations, it was easier to establish wMel than wAlbB in mosquito populations, except when the conditions were particularly hot [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006666.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. They also observed that the wMel infected larvae survived better than wAlbB infected larvae under starvation conditions [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006666.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].
</p>
