<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Like HIV, other RNA viruses can also evade antiviral treatments, including influenza virus, HCV, and HBV. HBV is a DNA virus, but its DNA replicates through a genomic RNA intermediate and utilizes a virally encoded reverse transcriptase. Consequently, a significant amount of diversity, similar to that seen in RNA viruses, occurs in the sequences of HBV isolates. Until recently, monotherapies or sequential treatments with nucleoside analogues were widely used to treat chronic HBV infection. Not surprisingly, this approach has resulted in the generation of multidrug-resistant viruses (Locarnini and Warner 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2007</xref>). Current treatment of chronic HCV infection is based on the combination of pegylated interferon-α and ribavirin; this regimen eradicates the virus in up to 80% of patients infected with genotypes 2 or 3, but in only 40–50% of patients infected with HCV genotype 1 (Pawlotsky 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">2011</xref>). Studies of recently developed direct-acting antiviral molecules against HCV have shown that administration of these drugs alone may lead to the selection of resistant viruses, raising concerns that resistance may undermine therapy based on direct-acting antivirals (Pawlotsky 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">2011</xref>). Two HCV NS3 protease inhibitors, telaprevir and boceprevir, have already been approved for HCV infection treatment, and several other drugs that are directed against different HCV proteins are in phase II and III of clinical development. As expected, resistant mutants to telaprevir and boceprevir preexist in HCV populations before they have been exposed to the inhibitors (Bartels et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2008</xref>; Cubero et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2008</xref>; Franco et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2011</xref>). Mathematical modeling suggests that at least three direct-acting antiviral molecules should be used (Rong et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">2010</xref>), but the final number will depend on their modes of action and the likelihood that HCV variants bearing substitutions in different regions of the genome conferring resistance to the different classes of drugs are present in the same strain (Pawlotsky 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">2011</xref>). HCV shares many properties with HIV; both are highly variable viruses with quasispecies distribution, large viral populations, and very rapid turnover in the individual patient. Fortunately, unlike HIV, the HCV replicative cycle is exclusively cytoplasmic, with no host genome integration or episomal persistence in infected cells; therefore, HCV infection is intrinsically curable, but the development of antiviral resistance in chronic viral infections like HIV, HCV, or HBV can thwart the success of future treatments. For instance, the development of resistances to first generation HCV NS3 protease inhibitors, boceprevir and telaprevir, may compromise the treatment success of the next generation of NS3 inhibitors, now in clinical development. Moreover, resistant viruses can be transmitted, compromising the efficacy of new antivirals at the population level. Viral quasispecies are endowed with memory of their past intra-host evolutionary history, maintained in the form of minority variants (Briones et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2006</xref>; Briones and Domingo 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2008</xref>). These variants can reemerge and become a major quasispecies variant if the quasispecies is subjected to selective pressures. This is particularly relevant in antiviral treatment because minority memory drug-resistant variants can quickly expand under drug selection pressure. One example of the key role of minority HIV-1 variants is the fact that women who receive intrapartum nevirapine monotherapy are less likely to exhibit virologic suppression after 6 months of postpartum treatment with a nevirapine-containing regimen (Jourdain et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2004</xref>). RNA viruses can escape from antiviral activity through mutations in the target viral gene itself, causing decreased affinity to the inhibitor and leading to resistance. These changes also affect the phenotype of the targeted protein, and consequently decrease the replication capacity of the virus. Continuous replication of these viruses may result in the acquisition of compensatory changes, which can fixate the drug-resistant variant in the viral population and increase viral fitness (Martinez-Picado et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">1999</xref>; Nijhuis et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">1999</xref>). Therefore, since the frequency of a variant in a quasispecies depends on the relative fitness of that particular variant, memory genomes that are maintained after drug discontinuation will be present at a higher frequency than in the original population.
</p>
