<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In recent years, several cellular factors have been identified in some viruses (e.g., HIV, HCV, and HBV) that are closely involved with the virus replication cycle, and that can be targeted to prevent virus spread. The genetic barrier for viral escape may be much higher when cellular factors are targeted; virus adaptation to alternative cellular co-factors is expected to be more complicated or even impossible when no alternative cellular functions are available. Targeting cellular functions is obviously not without danger. The use of host gene targets requires careful selection; knock-down of cellular factors essential for virus replication may also be detrimental to the cell and the host. The recent availability of CCR5 antagonists has raised concern that genetic, biological, or chemical CCR5 knockout—although beneficial against some pathogens (e.g., HIV-1)—could be deleterious for host processes involved in pathogen response (Telenti 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121">2009</xref>). Targeting cellular factors requires extensive toxicity studies, but in the case of CCR5, we know that the protein does not fulfill an essential function in human physiology (Liu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">1996</xref>). Unfortunately, targeting cellular viral cofactors does not preclude the emergence of drug-resistant viruses. Viral resistance to CCR5 antagonists (maraviroc) has been extensively observed (Llibre et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2010</xref>). HIV-1 can selectively express variants of the envelope protein that either exhibit higher CD4 receptor affinity (Agrawal-Gamse et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2009</xref>) or recognize the inhibitor-bound CCR5 complex (Westby et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132">2007</xref>). Such drug pressure can also raise the possibility of viral escape by triggering a switch to CXCR4 as an alternative receptor; such CXCR4-using HIV-1 variants may be more pathogenic (Nedellec et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">2011</xref>). Likewise, cyclophylin inhibitors—promising potent HCV inhibitors that are now in late clinical trials, and that target a host protein (cyclophylin peptidyl-prolyl cis-trans isomerase activity)—can drive the selection of HCV resistant viruses with amino acid substitutions in the viral proteins NS2 and NS5 (Pawlotsky 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">2011</xref>).
</p>
