<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0065">SARS-CoV2 is transmitted from 1 individual to another predominantly via respiratory droplets through direct or indirect routes.
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref> Indirect transmission can occur through contact with inanimate objects (fomite) contaminated by the droplets.
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>17</sup>
 </xref> Transmission through oral–fecal contamination has also been reported.
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Direct transmission occurs when respiratory droplets (&gt;5 μm in size) carrying the virus particles or pathogen spread from the infected host to the susceptible mucosal surface of the recipient. Studies have revealed that respiratory viruses enter via the nasal mucosa and conjunctiva and, less often, through the mouth. Droplets generated while talking, coughing, or sneezing are usually believed to travel up to a distance of 1 meter (3 ft) but the distance can be farther than 1 meter
 <italic>.</italic> Experience during the previous SARS outbreaks revealed that the droplets could travel up to 6 ft. Hence, the recommendation for the use of a face mask when within 6 to 10 feet of another person. Factors to consider include the droplet size, source, density of secretions, temperature, humidity, velocity, and mechanism by which the droplets were propelled. Procedures such as an injection of a local anesthetic or examination of the oropharynx can cause patients to cough or sneeze, propelling droplets 6 ft or more. In contrast, droplet nuclei (dried droplets containing the pathogen), which are 5 μm or less in size have been associated with airborne transmission that can remain in the air for long periods and be transmitted over greater distances.
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>22</sup>
 </xref> Airborne transmission is more likely to occur during aerosol-generating procedures (AGPs) with and without high-speed drills and during endoscopic airway manipulation, endotracheal intubation, and suctioning. The newer models of respiratory droplet transmission have been based on the concept of a high momentum turbulent puff or cloud that carries droplets for longer distances, as far as 7 to 8 meters or 23 to 27 ft. The current masks have not been tested for their ability to withstand such high-momentum, multiphase gas cloud ejections caused by a cough or sneeze.
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>23</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
