<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is noteworthy that four of the eight substitutions identified here were observed in the NS2A protein, indicating that this small transmembrane protein had the higher number of positions under selective pressure. ZIKV NS2A protein has been previously reported to play a role in the disruption of adherens junction formation, which has been associated with reduced proliferation, premature differentiation and the depletion of radial glial cells in the mouse cortex.
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>19</sup>
 </xref> A single mutation at ZIKV NS2A (A175V), which has been shown to decrease virus production and RNA synthesis 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>, was associated with an attenuated phenotype in a ZIKV mouse model.
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>20</sup>
 </xref> Based on a study by Xie et al.
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref> and on the transmembrane helices and protein topology prediction program HMMTOP (http://www.enzim.hu/hmmtop/), this mutation (A175V) maps to a transmembrane domain. The NS2A mutation M181V (between ZV BR 2015/15261 and ZV BR 2015/15098 or ZV BR 2016/16288 - 
 <xref rid="t3" ref-type="table">Table III</xref>) maps to this same domain. The nature of the mutation is also similar, resulting in just a small increase in the amino acid side chain. The amino acid polymorphism identified in ZV BR 2015/15098 NS2A
 <sub>117</sub> presents the same character as minor variants previously identified at this same position through next-generation sequencing.
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>22</sup>
 </xref> There are five other isolates (KX520666/BR/2015, KY648934/MX/2016, KX446951/MX/2016, MH900227/MX/2016 and KX377336/MY/1966) in our datasets that contain this same substitution (A117V). Based on the homology and the 
 <italic>in silico</italic> prediction, this mutation also maps to a transmembrane domain, and the only amino acids identified at this position are either alanine or valine. Additionally, when the UTRs of the three new ZIKV isolates were compared, one single nucleotide change downstream of the stop codon of the NS5 gene was detected in the ZIKV ZV BR 2015/15098 strain. This mutation was mapped to the highly variable proximal region 1 of the 3ʹUTR sequence (3ʹHVR), a region of the Flavivirus genome known for displaying large heterogeneity in both sequence and length.
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>23</sup>
 </xref> The flavivirus 3’UTR contains essential elements that function as important mediators to promote viral genome replication and translation. Despite this, the nucleotide change at 3’HVR of the ZV BR 2015/15098 does not seem to have any impact on the secondary structure, as shown in the RNA fold analysis (
 <inline-supplementary-material xlink:href="1678-8060-mioc-114-e190150-s.pdf" id="d35e1084" content-type="local-data" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Supplementary data</inline-supplementary-material>). Nevertheless, previous studies have demonstrated that sequence variability at 3’HVR of DENV-1 and DENV-2 are associated with DENV fitness gain or loss in mammalian and insect cells.
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>23</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
