<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Additionally, we observed that ZV BR 2016/16288, the isolate circulating in southern Brazil one year after the detection of the first case of ZIKV in Brazil, is less infective when compared with the ZIKV prototypes and the 2015 isolates in all cell lineages tested in this study, except in C6/36 cells. In this cell line, the low-passage strain ZV BR 2016/16288 showed very similar viral growth when compared with the other two recent ZIKV isolates. The ZIKV ZV BR 2016/16288 showed one nonconservative point mutation at residue 26 of the N-terminal region of the NS4B protein (
 <xref rid="t3" ref-type="table">Table III</xref>) and one point mutation at residue 349 of NS1 protein that should play an important role in ZIKV infectivity, live virus release and viral RNA replication. NS1 protein is a secreted glycoprotein involved in viral replication and immune evasion during flaviviral infection. Further, one non-synonymous mutation at NS1 associated with a single mutation at E protein in a ZIKV strain was found to alter viral fitness in cell culture and pathogenesis in mice.
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>26</sup>
 </xref> On the other hand, although the exact topology of flavivirus integral membrane-NS4B on the host membrane compartment is not totally clear, previous studies have shown that the 30 N-terminal residues of NS4B form a dynamic structure that is not associated with the endoplasmic reticulum (ER).
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>27</sup>
 </xref> Elazar et al.
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>28</sup>
 </xref> demonstrated that in HCV, the modifications of the amphipathic characteristics of NS4B’s N-terminal helix have critical implication for RNA replication. The presence of the threonine residue at NS4B
 <sub>26</sub> could disrupt the amphipathic nature of the NS4B helix and impact on NS4B functions in distinct cell lines [
 <inline-supplementary-material xlink:href="1678-8060-mioc-114-e190150-s.pdf" id="d35e1138" content-type="local-data" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Supplementary data</inline-supplementary-material>
 <bold>(Fig. 2)</bold>].
</p>
