<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="fig0007">
 <label>Fig. 7</label>
 <caption>
  <p>
   <bold>Evaluation of DENV infection-enhancement by anti-ZIKV-80E NP antiserum.</bold> (a) Each of the four DENV serotypes was separately pre-incubated with different amounts of mAb 4G2 (0.01–100 µg), and then allowed to infect K562 cells for 24 h. The percentage of DENV-infected cells was determined by flow cytometry using mAb 2H2-Alexa 488 conjugate. Data depict infection profiles of DENV-1 (magenta), DENV-2 (green), DENV-3 (blue) or DENV-4 (black), as functions of mAb 4G2 concentration. (b) Similar experiment as in panel ‘a’, except that DENV pre-incubations were performed with pooled, serially diluted (10
   <sup>−1</sup>–10
   <sup>−5</sup>) immune serum, obtained from BALB/c mice immunised with DENV-2 S16803 strain (α-DENV-2 antiserum). (c) 
   <italic>In vitro</italic> ADE experiment as in panel ‘b’, except that the murine polyclonal antiserum was from mock-immunised BALB/c mice (control serum); (d) Similar experiment as in panels ‘b’ and ‘c’, but using pooled immune serum from ZIKV-80E NP-immunised BALB/c mice (α-ZIKV-80E NP antiserum). (e) Schematic representation of the 
   <italic>in vivo</italic> DENV-2 ADE experiment in AG129 mice (abbreviations: IC: immune complex; FIU: FACS infectious unit). (f) Kaplan–Meier survival curves for groups (
   <italic>n</italic> = 6) of AG129 mice which were intravenously administered with a sub-lethal dose of DENV-2 S221 (pre-incubated with NMS, green curve) or with ICs generated 
   <italic>in vitro</italic> by pre-incubating the sub-lethal dose of DENV-2 S221 with mAb 4G2 (4G2, grey curve), murine anti-DENV-2 antiserum (α-DENV-2, black dashed curve) or with serum from BALB/c mice immunised with ZIKV-80E NPs (α-ZIKV-80E, purple curve). Survival was observed for 12 days post-challenge. Survival of mice in the α-ZIKV-80E and NMS groups were comparable to each other (
   <italic>p</italic> = 0.5282) and significantly higher (
   <italic>p</italic> = 0.0095) than that in the 4G2 or α-DENV-2 groups, based on the Log-Rank (Mantel–Cox) test. Statistical differences are indicated as not significant (ns) or as significant (twin star symbol).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <alt-text id="alt0007">Fig. 7</alt-text>
 <graphic xlink:href="gr7" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
