<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Concurrently with the rather practical benefits from developments in viral cultivation, interest in general biological issues became increasingly important. The crystallization of tobacco mosaic virus from liquid media by Wendell Stanley in California in 1935 stimulated discussions as to whether viruses are dead or living matter. The main question concerned, however, the nature and structure of the genetic material, which was found to be nucleic acid by the seminal experiments of Oswald T. Avery, Colin McLeod and Maclyn McCarty with pneumococci in 1944. In 1952, Alfred D. Hershey and Martha Chase proved that during bacteriophage T4 infections only DNA, but not the protein shell of the virus, penetrates into the bacterial cell. This demonstrated that nucleic acids are the carrier of genetic information. A few years later, in 1955, Gerhard Schramm and Heinz Fraenkel-Conrat showed independently in tobacco mosaic virus that RNA can also be infectious. Schramm and his colleagues had already described in Germany in 1944 that tobacco mosaic virus is composed of RNA and proteins; however, these findings attracted initially only little attention. The base ratios in DNA molecules (A = T and C = G) that were discovered and developed by Edwin Chargaff enabled James D. Watson and Francis H. Crick, in connection with the Rosalind Franklin’s X-ray structural analysis, to develop their model of the DNA double helix in 1953. In 1958, Matthew Meselson and Franklin W. Stahl demonstrated that DNA is replicated semiconservatively during cell division. These fundamental insights created the way for the elucidation of basic molecular biological processes which are nowadays generally familiar. The now common molecular genetic, biochemical and immunological methods allow the detection of viruses in the organs and the study of their spread in the organism. The function and effect of viral genes can be explored in isolation and in interaction with other viral or cellular components. Today, many viruses can be cultivated in large quantities in vitro in order to resolve their morphology and particle structure as well as to sequence their genetic information. In the case of non-cultivable viruses, modern molecular biological methods are available which make possible the investigation of the pathogens. Virus–cell interactions can be explored, and provide important insights into the mechanisms of viral replication. On the other hand, many of the molecular processes in eukaryotic cells have been elucidated by using viruses as cell research tools. In this way, the process of RNA splicing was originally described in adenoviruses, in which widely separated gene segments are assembled into single messenger RNA molecules after transcription. The fact that DNA is arranged with histone proteins into nucleosome structures within the nucleus was also first discovered in a virus, simian virus 40. In addition, even enhancers were originally described in viruses, i.e., the specific DNA regions that increase the expression of certain genes in a localization- and orientation-independent manner. Several of these viral regulatory elements have been used for alternative purposes: for example, the most frequently used promoter/enhancer sequences to control the expression of heterologous genes in commercially available vectors are derived from cytomegalovirus. This immediate-early promoter/enhancer region actually regulates the expression of early genes of the virus (see 10.1007/978-3-642-20718-1_19). Furthermore, the transfer of nucleic acid sequences and foreign genes by viral transduction, e.g., using vector systems based on the functions of adenoviruses or retroviruses, is today an indispensable constituent of molecular and cell biology, and has essentially contributed to the development of gene therapy procedures.</p>
