<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The NS segment has also been targeted by codon deoptimization for the generation of LAIV (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00190-f006">Figure 6</xref>A,B) [
 <xref rid="B178-viruses-11-00190" ref-type="bibr">178</xref>]. Three codon deoptimized recombinant PR8 viruses were generated containing silent mutations in the coding regions of NS1 (NS1
 <sub>CD</sub>), NEP (NEP
 <sub>CD</sub>), or both (NS
 <sub>CD</sub>) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00190-f006">Figure 6</xref>B). Although the three viruses grew to similar levels as WT PR8 virus in MDCK cells, the replication capabilities of NS
 <sub>CD</sub> and NS1
 <sub>CD</sub> were impaired in human lungs epithelia carcinoma A549 cells, which was likely due to differences in the IFN responses between the A549 and MDCK cells [
 <xref rid="B181-viruses-11-00190" ref-type="bibr">181</xref>]. In fact, bioassays to evaluate the production of IFN showed that NS
 <sub>CD</sub> and NS1
 <sub>CD</sub> viruses (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00190-f006">Figure 6</xref>B) counteracted the IFN response to a lesser extent than the WT PR8 virus (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00190-f006">Figure 6</xref>A). Likewise, NS
 <sub>CD</sub> and NS1
 <sub>CD</sub> viruses were significantly attenuated in mice when compared to the WT virus, while NEP
 <sub>CD</sub> similarly replicated WT PR8. Those data suggested that a correlation exists between the extent of deoptimization and levels of viral attenuation, since the viruses with more codon deoptimized substitutions were more attenuated (NS
 <sub>CD</sub> &gt; NS1
 <sub>CD</sub> &gt; NEP
 <sub>CD</sub>). The authors also showed that a single-dose intranasal immunization with NS
 <sub>CD</sub> was sufficient to induce a strong humoral response in mice and to protect animals against homologous and heterologous lethal challenges, providing an effective viral segment target for codon deoptimization to develop LAIV candidates.
</p>
