<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14">Oropouche virus (OROV) stands out as the utmost prevalent 
 <italic>Orthobunyavirus</italic> contagion in some northern South American countries and specially in the Amazon region. In these areas, OROV is endemic, nonetheless scarce information exists about the inflammatory response induced by OROV fever. The present study is the first comprehensive investigation on the chemokine and cytokine profile in early and late seroconverters with OROV fever. In regard to the initial responses triggered by OROV, the innate antiviral response induced by OROV is mediated by induction of type I IFN pathway through Interferon Regulatory Transcription Factors (IRF3 and IRF7), as well as interferon-α/β receptor, and Mitochondrial Antiviral Signaling Protein (MAVS), as evidenced in animal model-based studies
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup>. The OROV fever pathogenesis was in fact described as restricted by the IFN pathway-related signaling molecules MAVS, IRF-3, IRF-7 in non-myeloid cells
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup>. In line with these findings, a very elegant study demostrated that several 
 <italic>Orthobunyaviruses</italic>, including: 
 <italic>Tacaiuma (TCMV), Guama (GMAV), Guaroa (GROV) and Caraparu (CARV)</italic> viruses in addition to OROV are vulnerable to the antiviral attack mediated by Interferon-α in time and dose-dependent fashion
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup>. In fact, OROV fever is restrained by the IFN pathway in wild-type mice. This is exemplified by the fact that IFN-α knockout mice display increased hepatic injury, significantly superior mortality and rapid progress of the disease
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup>, as similar as previously observed into immunocompetent Syrian golden hamsters
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>
 </sup>. It is important to underscore that although IFN-α is a useful universal biomarker for OROV fever, it should be considered together with other clinical and laboratorial records since several other viruses can also elicit IFN-α production.
</p>
