<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0145">Human-infecting HEV strains are genetically heterogeneous and display distinct epidemiologic patterns, but all belong the 
 <italic>Orthohepevirus A</italic> species. Orthohepeviruses A account for a minority of the overall diversity of hepeviruses that infect vertebrates and their closest relative is a presently unclassified virus detected in a Swedish moose (
 <xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>A) 
 <xref rid="b0545" ref-type="bibr">[109]</xref>. Field surveys revealed a high prevalence of HEV in moose populations from Sweden and other Baltic Regions 
 <xref rid="b0550" ref-type="bibr">[110]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0555" ref-type="bibr">[111]</xref>. In general, ungulates represent major Orthohepeviruses A reservoirs. At present, eight Orthohepevirus A genotypes are recognized (HEV-1 to -8) (
 <xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>A). HEV-1 and HEV-2 infect only humans and cause waterborne outbreaks mainly in tropical and subtropical regions (
 <xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>B). Conversely, genotypes 3 and 4 account for the majority of hepatitis E human cases in industrialized countries. HEV-3 and HEV-4 also infect several other domestic (mainly pigs) and wild (e.g., ungulates and small carnivores) animals, their transmission to humans being usually zoonotic 
 <xref rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref> (
 <xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>A). Phylogenetic analyses showed that HEV-3 and HEV-4 sequences derived from human cases are interspersed within those isolated from swine, indicating that pig-infecting HEV-3 and HEV-4 can easily cross the species barrier and infect humans 
 <xref rid="b0560" ref-type="bibr">[112]</xref>. Notably, though, evolutionary rates are higher for genotypes 3 and 4 than for the human-specific genotypes, suggesting cyclical adaptation to different mammalian hosts 
 <xref rid="b0565" ref-type="bibr">[113]</xref>. A distinct HEV-3 clade, mainly detected in rabbits (HEV-3ra), can also cause human hepatitis E 
 <xref rid="b0570" ref-type="bibr">[114]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0575" ref-type="bibr">[115]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0580" ref-type="bibr">[116]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0585" ref-type="bibr">[117]</xref> (
 <xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>A). The remaining genotypes HEV-5/HEV-6 and HEV-7/HEV-8 have been detected in boars and camels, respectively 
 <xref rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref> (
 <xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>A). However, they are also thought to have zoonotic potential, as HEV-5 and HEV-7 can infect cynomolgus monkeys 
 <xref rid="b0590" ref-type="bibr">[118]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0595" ref-type="bibr">[119]</xref> and HEV-7 was detected in a patient who consumed camel meat and milk 
 <xref rid="b0600" ref-type="bibr">[120]</xref>. Thus, viruses belonging to all HEV genotypes seem to be transmissible to humans. Conversely, experimental infection with HEV-1 and HEV-2 indicated that these viruses have a host range restricted to primates 
 <xref rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. HEV genotypes are therefore usually referred to as enzootic (HEV-3 and −4) or human-restricted/anthropotropic (HEV-1 and -2).
</p>
