<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par28">In addition to addressing the important question of whether CRP can be prognostically useful as a dengue biomarker, our findings add to the existing evidence base for its use in differentiating dengue from non-dengue causes of fever [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. We found the median CRP level of approximately 30 mg/L among dengue cases within the first 3 days of illness. Other studies found similar levels with observed mean CRP levels of 19.0 mg/L on the first day of illness in dengue cases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. A number of previous studies have demonstrated the role of CRP in differentiating dengue from specifically bacterial [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] and malarial infections [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], although the most effective CRP thresholds for predicting underlying etiology remain difficult to define. Furthermore, the use of a CRP threshold of 20 mg/L has been demonstrated in simulation models to be successful and cost-effective in classifying patients into those that would and would not benefit from antibiotics in 80% of cases, regardless of baseline endemicity levels of different pathogens [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. In practice, the use of POC CRP assay has been shown to reduce antibiotic prescribing when implementing thresholds of significance of both 20 mg/L and 40 mg/L [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. However, our results highlight the risk of inadvertently increasing inappropriate antibiotic prescribing if dengue is not first considered in patients with CRP &gt; 20 mg/L during seasons of high incidence. Nevertheless, growing confidence in the diagnostic value of CRP makes POC CRP an increasingly relevant component of antimicrobial stewardship strategy in the present era of ever-growing antimicrobial resistance.
</p>
