<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Here, we identified 15 anti-EBOV compounds with selectivity indices higher than 10 by screening a chemical library of compounds tested for clinical trials. Based on their target analysis, we found that GPCRs were closely linked to the EBOV life cycle. Using the same trVLP system, N. Lee 
 <italic>et al</italic>. found GPCR modulators as antiviral hits, suggesting experimental reliability (
 <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). However, in contrast to the previous study, from a technical perspective, we adopted the dual luciferase assay to measure the antiviral activity and cytotoxicity simultaneously from the same sample, while the cytotoxicity was determined in an image-based manner via Hoechst staining. Second, we evaluated the antiviral activity of the selected compounds by using immunoblotting or genetic analysis alternatively, independent of the luciferase activity. It is not trivial, because hit compounds targeting the reporter protein, either FLuc or RLuc, were selected accidentally and frequently (
 <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). In addition, classification of the chemical structure facilitated the determination of structure-activity relationships (
 <xref rid="S1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 3</xref>). Diphenylmethane derivatives belong to group I, promazine derivatives to group II and other compounds to group III. Given that the histamine H1 receptor of GPCRs is rarely expressed in human embryonic kidney 293 (HEK293) cells (
 <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>), a parental cell line of HEK293T, and that groups I and II carry distinct chemical skeletons as diphenylmethane and promazine cores, respectively, these structural features might be preferred for the induction of antiviral activity. Furthermore, we tested the antiviral efficacy of the three active compounds including sertindole, raloxifene and ibutamoren against other human RNA viruses, such as dengue virus and rhinovirus (
 <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>-
 <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). We found no viral inhibition in cells, indicating that the hit compounds are EBOV-specific (data not shown).
</p>
