<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0100">As explained above, phylogenetic analyses of viral sequences may be able to detect parallel evolution, but are insufficient to establish whether a given trait has arisen repeatedly through adaptation. Experimental evidence, from molecular biology or animal challenge studies, is ultimately required to determine the functional consequences of parallel mutations. However, it may be possible to further refine candidate sites for experimental confirmation by undertaking 
 <italic>in silico</italic> analyses that combine structural and evolutionary information. This is especially true if virus proteins evolve the same structural change (e.g. a change in charge) via a variety of mutational paths. Mapping of virus mutations onto resolved protein structures can provide information about the functional effects of genetic changes, including thermodynamic stability, or interactions with other proteins or biologically important molecules [
 <xref rid="bib0180" ref-type="bibr">36
  <sup>•</sup>
 </xref>]. For example, a recent study of human influenza B virus genomes observed parallel amino acid changes occurring three times in the HA gene of the Yamagata lineage [
 <xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Computational structural analyses showed that these were located in a major antigenic epitope [
 <xref rid="bib0185" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. These approaches include structural alignment methods [
 <xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] that can compare divergent virus proteins that exhibit little homology at the sequence level, but which share homology at the structural level. Other combined phylogenetic approaches can estimate the effect of specific mutations on protein stability, as demonstrated in a functional analysis of influenza A virus hemagglutinin gene variation [
 <xref rid="bib0195" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. We envisage that structural analyses could form part of a phylogenetically informed workflow for investigating the significance of parallel evolutionary changes (
 <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> ), and for selecting appropriate candidates for experimental validation. The results obtained would also provide insights into the evolvability, mutability and robustness of virus proteins [
 <xref rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>].
</p>
