<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">Baricitinib (Olumiant
 <sup>®</sup>) is another JAK1 and JAK2 inhibitor that is predicted to have a dual effect of reducing both viral entry and inflammation in COVID-19 patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Baricitinib might be preferred over other JAK-STAT signaling inhibitors, given its once-daily dosing and acceptable adverse effect profile [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Additionally, its low plasma protein binding properties and minimal interaction with CYP enzymes and drug transporters allows for well-tolerated concomitant use of baricitinib with the direct-acting antivirals (e.g. remdesivir) and other drugs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. However, the use of baricitinib is associated with increased thromboembolic events, which is concerning given that COVID-19 patients are at risk of developing these events [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. In an Italian open-label study of 12 patients with moderate COVID-19 pneumonia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], baricitinib therapy combined with lopinavir/ritonavir was associated with significant improvement in clinical and laboratory parameters, and none of the patients required intensive care unit support, however, the study was limited by its small sample size and open-label design. An open-label, multicenter, adaptive phase II/III study to evaluate the safety and efficacy of baricitinib in hospitalized patients with COVID-19 has commenced (NCT04340232). Other clinical trials are evaluating baricitinib in combination with or without an antiviral agent for the treatment of COVID-19 (NCT04346147, NCT04320277, NCT04345289, NCT04321993). Notably, baricitinib is included as an arm in the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases’ (NIAID) phase III adaptive COVID-19 treatment trial [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Currently, the National Institutes of Health (NIH) COVID-19 Treatment Guidelines Panel recommends against the use of JAK inhibitors for the treatment of COVID19 except in the context of a clinical trial, in part because the broad immunosuppressive effect of JAK inhibitors outweighs the potential for benefit [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. An NIH-sponsored randomized, controlled trial (Adaptive COVID-19 Treatment Trial 2) combining the investigational antiviral remdesivir plus the anti-inflammatory drug baricitinib is currently underway and will investigate whether adding an anti-inflammatory agent to remdesivir can provide additional benefit for patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Patients will receive either the combination or remdesivir alone, the latter of which was the focus of the Adaptive COVID-19 Treatment Trial. This combination may be able to control the viral infection as well as reduce the immune system reaction.
</p>
