<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The pathogenesis and the outcome of COVID-19 are closely related to the host immune response. The viral RNA recognition by the intracellular receptors activates IFN-I signalling pathways involved in the regulation of the inflammatory and antiviral response. A delayed or attenuated IFN-I response has been recorded in SARS-CoV-2 infections complicated with systemic inflammatory response and acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) (
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Jose and Manuel, 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Prompetchara et al., 2020</xref>). The induction of IFNs and the transcription of the interferon stimulated genes (ISGs) triggers specific antiviral pathways which directly target the viral transcriptome and proteome activity. The interaction between the ISGs and viral RNA has been better explored in other viral infections (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Goraya et al., 2020</xref>) but has been less documented in SARS-CoV-2 infection. Recently, Ziegler et al. proved that ACE2 SARS-CoV-2 receptor is an ISG found in human airway epithelial cells. The authors have thus identified a surprising alternative which allows the virus to hijack the innate immunity to attenuate the immune response and to entry the human cells (
 <xref rid="B121" ref-type="bibr">Ziegler et al., 2020</xref>). Currently, it is not well understood how the virus triggers an IFN-type I response, not how it influences the pathogenesis of COVID-19. In this respect, it is unclear whether is stimulates a protective response similar to MERS-CoV (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Fung et al., 2020</xref>) or an excessive inflammatory response (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Channappanavar et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Channappanavar et al., 2019</xref>) as seen in SARS-CoV-infected mice. It is possible that IFN-type I response plays a protective role in the initial phase of the infection but later contributes to the “cytokine storm’’ either directly or through the induction of other cytokines, as was proved during the MERS infection (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Channappanavar et al., 2019</xref>). Hence, IFN therapy could play a pivotal role in COVID-19 clinical improvement and viral load lasting according to a recent study (NCT04276688) (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Hung et al., 2020</xref>). Still, the previous study was disputed as a result of the patient selection criteria and the timing of IFN administration. Additionally, the control group received protease inhibitors, known to display a limited efficacy (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Gandhi, 2020</xref>). Another notable issue on the subject is the type of IFN which efficiently inhibits SARS-CoV-2. On this matter, even though IFNβ1 displays an anti-inflammatory role on the pulmonary endothelia, it does not appear to reduce the mortality of ARDS (
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">Ranieri et al., 2020</xref>).
</p>
