<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome-related Coronavirus (SARS) Co-V, was first report in Guangdong Province, China in November 2002. At its initial outbreak (until August 2003), 8,096 probable cases were reported with an ~10% fatality rate (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). Further sporadic cases were reported in November 2003 through April 2004 (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). The case studies showed the occurrence of bacterial co-infections in the large number of patients. These include infections by MRSA, 
 <italic>Klebsiella</italic> spp., 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> and 
 <italic>Streptococcus</italic> (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). The large multinucleated cells observed in the lungs of the SARS patients may be due to the underlining bacterial infections (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). The use of broad-spectrum antibiotics to cover the secondary bacterial infections is one of the supportive cares during SARS outbreak (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>) (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">Supplementary File</xref>). The case studies (
 <italic>n</italic> = 7) reported the disease progression of a total of 534 SARS-CoV patients (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>–
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>) (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">Supplementary File</xref>). Details about prophylactic antibiotic therapy was reported in five studies (patients 
 <italic>n</italic> = 385) and 100% patients were treated with prophylactic antibiotic therapy (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>–
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). The antibiotics used for prophylactic treatment were levofloxacin, clarithromycin, amoxicillin-clavulanic acid, piperacillin-tazobactum, maxipime, azithromycin, amoxicillin-clavulanate, cefoperazone/sulbactam, quinolone plus azithromycin, levofloxacin, moxifloxacin, and ceftriaxone plus azithromycin, and most commonly azithromycin (
 <italic>n</italic> = 206, 74.6%). Of the four studies that reported secondary bacterial infections, 35 of 306 patients (11.4%) became infected. The pathogens that caused the infections included 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>, MRSA, 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae, K. pneumoniae, Enterococci, Acinetobacter baumannii, Enterobacter, H. influenza, S. maltophilia</italic>, and 
 <italic>Serratia</italic> (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Despite the deployment of prophylactic antibiotics, the use of therapeutic antibiotics was reported in three studies, administering amoxicillin-clavulanate, clarithromycin, azithromycin, levofloxacin, moxifloxacin and ceftriaxone plus azithromycin (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). In total, 12 patients out of 23 (52%, described in two studies who provided the respective information) had complications due to secondary bacterial infections (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>).
</p>
