<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>HFMD and AM across Japan are part of the diseases under surveillance in the NESID (available at 
 <uri xlink:href="https://www.niid.go.jp/niid/en/iasr-e.html" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.niid.go.jp/niid/en/iasr-e.html</uri>), according to the Japanese Infectious Diseases Control Law, with more than 3000 fixed points in pediatric clinics and hospitals nationwide with weekly reports (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-05201-f001">Figure 1</xref>). Clinical samples are collected in ~10% of pediatric sites, and viruses are detected and identified by molecular methods in local health laboratories nationwide [
 <xref rid="B8-ijms-20-05201" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. As the main causative agents of HFMD, EV-A71 and CV-A16 have been monitored across Japan between 2012 and 2018 (
 <xref rid="ijms-20-05201-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>); it is noteworthy that every three years a rise in the number of cases has been noted and attributed to a three year cyclical component of EV-A71 [
 <xref rid="B44-ijms-20-05201" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], however, closer inspection to the distribution of etiologic agents also suggests that CV-A16 cases rise and fall periodically. Furthermore, EV-A71 was the main cause of epidemic outbreaks in 2000 and 2003 in Japan [
 <xref rid="B2-ijms-20-05201" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], while CV-A16 was reported as the cause of outbreaks in Japan and also in India [
 <xref rid="B45-ijms-20-05201" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. On the other hand, a variety of EVs were detected as a cause of AM in Japan between 2012 and 2018, among them types in Enterovirus A. It is noteworthy that the annual number of detected AM cases is on average 0.8% ± 0.6 of the total number of HFMD cases, which is remarkable considering the biannual rise in the number of cases in the latter. The number of recorded AM events, similar to the number of HFMD cases, peaks in summer. However, the causative EV pathogens associated with AM belong on average to Enterovirus B in 74% ± 15 of cases per year, with the mumps paramyxovirus (which is not part of the routine Japanese vaccination) the second most common cause in 16% ± 9 of cases (
 <xref rid="ijms-20-05201-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Therefore, factors common to Enterovirus A and B and the number of susceptible/previously exposed individuals in the population determine the number of cases, together with other factors, such as the average temperature and other prevailing weather conditions promoting the spread of these viruses in the summer months [
 <xref rid="B46-ijms-20-05201" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Nevertheless, EV-A71 was the etiologic agent in ~10% of AM cases in 2013 and 2017 coinciding with two peaks of infection reflecting the risks associated with outbreaks from this neurotropic EV. EV-induced meningitis has a fundamentally favorable prognosis (particularly in comparison to bacterial meningitis) so timely laboratory confirmation of aseptic meningitis is crucial for clinical care.
</p>
