<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although it is apparent that 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> feeds predominantly on mammals, the degree of mammalophagic or anthropophagic host feeding preferences of this species appear location specific. Because of the rapidly expanding range of 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>, its abundance in metropolitan centers, and its close association with humans in peridomestic habits, combined with the emergence and resurgence of exotic pathogens for which 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> is a capable vector, it is clear that assessing its host feeding preferences in newly invaded areas is critical to elucidate disease transmission cycles and develop strategies to reduce the local risk of an exotic arbovirus outbreak. However, the collection of 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> (
 <italic>Stegomyia</italic>) spp., such as 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>, has been difficult because standard vector surveillance traps are generally placed 1.5 m above the ground, are operated overnight, and utilize light as an attractant 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003037-Farajollahi2" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. Since 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> is diurnal and not attracted to light, host-seeks near the ground surface, and utilizes visual, in addition to olfactory cues for host location 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003037-Hawley1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003037-EstradaFranco1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003037-Kawada1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref> these traps are not an effective way to collect this species. Consequently, most blood meal analyses to date were performed on specimens collected from areas where their densities are very high, such as tire yards and tire dumps (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0003037-t001">Table 1</xref>). The creation of newly developed vector surveillance traps, such as the Biogents Sentinel (BGS) trap, have only recently allowed the collection of large number of 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> specimens from typical urban and suburban areas for ecological studies 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003037-Kroeckel1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. These traps simulate convection currents created by human body heat, utilize lures which mimic human odors, are operated during the day, placed at the ground level, and utilize contrasting black and white markings that provide additional visual cues that may be attractive to 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>
 <xref rid="pntd.0003037-Farajollahi2" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0003037-Crepeau1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>.
</p>
