<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>First, a major challenge is the ever-increasing size of data sets being analyzed, leading to difficulties with navigating through the resulting phylogenetic trees and to problems with interpreting the inferred dynamics, not only from a computational perspective (e.g., to render large images in a timely manner) but also from the human capability to deal with high levels of detail. Software packages that mainly aim to visualize phylogenetic trees as well as those that target more broad analyses have implemented various solutions to accommodate systematic exploration of large phylogenies. Dendroscope (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>) was one of the first visualization tools aimed at large phylogenies, with its own format to save and reopen trees that had been edited graphically, offering a magnifier functionality to focus on specific parts of the (large) phylogeny. Follow-up versions (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) focused on rooted phylogenetic trees and networks, and offered parallel implementations of demanding algorithms for computing consensus trees and consensus networks to increase responsiveness. Phylo.io (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>) improves the legibility of large trees by automatically collapsing nodes so that an overview of the tree remains visible at any given time. iTOL [(
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), but see below] and IcyTree (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>) also provide intuitive panning and zooming utilities that make exploring large phylogenetic trees of many thousands of taxa feasible. The PhyloGeoTool [(
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>); also see 
 <bold>Figure 4</bold>] eases navigation of large trees by performing an 
 <italic>a priori</italic> iterative clustering of subtrees according to a predefined diversity ratio, as well as pre-rendering the visualization of those subtrees enabling fluent navigation. PastML (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>) allows visualizing the tree annotated with reconstructed ancestral states as a zoomable HTML map based on the Cytoscape framework (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). PastView (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>) offers synthetic views such as transition maps, integrates comparative analysis methods to highlight agreements or discrepancies between methods of ancestral annotations inference, and is also available as a webserver instance. Grapetree (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>) initially collapses branches if there are more than 20,000 nodes in the tree and then uses a static layout that splits the tree layout task into a series of sequential node layout tasks. With the development of many packages targetting the visualization of large phylogenies in recent years, the question arises whether they will continue to be maintained and extended with novel features.
</p>
