<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fn-group id="heyj13570-ntgp-0001">
 <title>Notes</title>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1001">
  <label>1</label>
  <p>Coronaviridae Study Group of the International Committee on Taxomony of Viruses, “The Species Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome‐Related Coronovirus: Classifying 2019‐NCoV and Naming it SARS‐CoV‐2” 
   <italic>Nature Microbiology</italic> 2020; 5: 536‐544. Another area not addressed in this essay is the question about the inability of different scientific systems to intersect with one another. While the Coronaviridae Study Groug (CSG) calls for better and consistent taxonomic designations and better communication between the virologists of CSG and public health science and practitioners, in part we would argue that there is always slippage between different scientific construals even if taxonomy does the work that the CSG imagines it will do. After all, one could create a system of naming the viruses that fits within the nucleotide or proteonomics, or in terms of the infectious mechanism, or in terms of spread of the virus. There will always be varying degrees of overlap in the scientific taxonomies created.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1002">
  <label>2</label>
  <p>Jiabao Xu, Shizhe Zhao, Tiesahn Teng, et al. “Systematic Comparison of Two Animal‐to‐Human Transmitted Human Coronaviruses: SARS‐CoV‐2 and SARS‐CoV” 
   <italic>Viruses</italic> 2020; 12 244: 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3390/v12020244" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://doi.org/10.3390/v12020244</ext-link>.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1003">
  <label>3</label>
  <p>Xu, Zhao, Teng et al. 2020; CSG 2020.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1004">
  <label>4</label>
  <p>Experts question whether or not this is due to testing biases seeing as probably only the most severe cases sought hospitalization.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1005">
  <label>5</label>
  <p>Noah C Peeri, Nistha Shrestha, Md Siddikur Rahman, et al. “The SARS, MERS and novel coronavirus (COVID‐19) epidemics, the newest and biggest global health threats: what lessons have we learned?” International Journal of Epidemiology 2020, 1‐10; 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1093/ije/dyaa033" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://doi.org/10.1093/ije/dyaa033</ext-link>.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1006">
  <label>6</label>
  <p>Kayla M. Peck and Adam S. Lauring, “Complexities of Viral Mutation Rates,” 
   <italic>Journal of Virology</italic>, 2018; 92(14). 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1128/JVI.01031-17" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://doi.org/10.1128/JVI.01031-17</ext-link>.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1007">
  <label>7</label>
  <p>Xu, Zhao, Teng et al. 2020.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1008">
  <label>8</label>
  <p>Xu, Zhao, Teng, et al. 2020. We do not entertain the question about whether medicine and the use of ACE inhibitors or other medication might have also exerted some as yet unexplained evolutionary pressure on the CoVs, though an investigation of this question would fit nicely into the overall narrative we are trying to construct about how one ought to conceive of the origin / problematic of the COVID‐19 pandemic.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1009">
  <label>9</label>
  <p>Peck and Lauring 2018; Xu, Zhao, Teng et al. 2020.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1010">
  <label>10</label>
  <p>See, for example: Rob Wallace, 
   <italic>Big Farms Make Big Flu,</italic> (New York: Monthly Review Press, 2016).
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1011">
  <label>11</label>
  <p>Wu et. al. “The outbreak of COVID‐19: An overview,” 
   <italic>Journal of the Chinese Medical Association</italic> 83, no. 3 (2020): 217‐220.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1012">
  <label>12</label>
  <p>Sam Ellis, “Why new diseases keep appearing in China: Why COVID‐19 was bound to happen” Vox, March 6, 2020. See also, Sam Ellis’s Vox Atlas piece, “How wildlife trade is linked to coronavirus”, March 6, 2020. Accessed March 27, 2020. See also Julia Belluz, “Did China downplay the coronavirus outbreak early on?” Vox January 27, 2020. Accessed Mach 31, 2020.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1013">
  <label>13</label>
  <p>Therese Shaheen, “The Chinese Wild‐Animal Industry and wet markets must go” National Review, March 19.2020. Accessed March 25, 2020.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1014">
  <label>14</label>
  <p>Shaheen 2020.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1015">
  <label>15</label>
  <p>Perhaps even more provocatively, it is not clear why this problem isn’t conceived of as one of animal consumption generally. This is not to suggest that one of the conclusions of our paper is that we all ought to adopt a plant‐based diet per se, but it is an interesting illustration of the limits of imagination that one of the primarily takeaways of COVID‐19 in public discourse has been how to manage the vast amount of agricultural animals more safely rather than to suggest that there be fewer such animals in the first place.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1016">
  <label>16</label>
  <p>Shaheen 2020; Ellis “How wildlife” 2020.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1017">
  <label>17</label>
  <p>Shaheen 2020.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1018">
  <label>18</label>
  <p>Shaheen 2020.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1019">
  <label>19</label>
  <p>Shuru Zhong, Mike Crang, Guojun Zeng, “Constructing freshness: the vitality of wet markets in urban China,” 
   <italic>Agriculture and Human Values</italic>, 2020; 37:175‐185, 177. The paper was accepted in September 2019, and based on fieldwork done from May 2016‐July 2017 and in part of 2018.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1020">
  <label>20</label>
  <p>Zhong, Crang, and Zeng 2020, 178.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1021">
  <label>21</label>
  <p>Zong 2020, 178.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1022">
  <label>22</label>
  <p>Zhong et al., 176.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1023">
  <label>23</label>
  <p>S. Friedberg, 
   <italic>Fresh: A Perishable History</italic>, Cambridge, MA: Harvard, 2009.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1024">
  <label>24</label>
  <p>Zhong 2020, 179.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1025">
  <label>25</label>
  <p>Zhong 2020, 181.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1026">
  <label>26</label>
  <p>Zhong 2020, 180.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1027">
  <label>27</label>
  <p>H. Tristram Engelhardt, Jr. Bioethics and Secular Humanism: The Search for a Common Morality, Eugene, OR: Wipf and Stock, 2011, p. 38.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1028">
  <label>28</label>
  <p>For the way this felicitous vagueness plays itself out in medical educational arenas, see Jeffrey P. Bishop, “Rejecting Medical Humanism: Medical Humanities and the Metaphysics of Medicine,” Journal of Medical Humanities 2008; 29(1): 15‐25.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1029">
  <label>29</label>
  <p>Engelhardt 2011, 38.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1030">
  <label>30</label>
  <p>Alasdair MacIntyre, Whose Justice, Which Rationality? Notre Dame, IN: University of Notre Dame Press, 1988, 388.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1031">
  <label>31</label>
  <p>Marshall Berman, 
   <italic>All that is Solid Melts Into Air</italic>, New York: Simon and Schuster, 1982, 15.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1032">
  <label>32</label>
  <p>Donald Clark Hodges, “Marx’s Contribution to Humanism” 
   <italic>Science and Society</italic> 1965; 29(2): 173‐191, 177.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1033">
  <label>33</label>
  <p>Engelhardt 2011, p. 43. It should be noted that the liberalism that animates many Western governments and the socialism that animates communist governments (even in China) stem from Western humanist philosophy. See for example Hodges, “Marx’s Contribution,” 1965. See also Reobert E. Gahringer, “Liberalism and Humanism”, Ethics, 1955; 66(1): 36‐50; George Lichtheim, 
   <italic>Marxism: An Historical and Critical Study</italic>, New York: 1961.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1034">
  <label>34</label>
  <p>And, given what we currently know of the origins of this disease and of influenzas generally, this seems quite likely!</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1035">
  <label>35</label>
  <p>Rob Wallace, 
   <italic>Big Farms Make Big Flu,</italic> (New York: Monthly Review Press, 2016)
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1036">
  <label>36</label>
  <p>We will elaborate on this point later in the paper. But, in a word, what is meant here is that it is a mistake to use the cosmopolitical methods for arbitrating dispute, say in the context of a league of nations, as the primarily tool for analysis of a situation generally. In this case, the question of “what could China change in its domestic food regulation” is certainly a cosmopolitical question, but it loses sight of the complexity of the different systems functioning in the COVID‐19 pandemic.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1037">
  <label>37</label>
  <p>For an analysis of homo economicus see Jeffrey P. Bishop, M. Therese Lysaught, and Andrew A. Michel, 
   <italic>Chasing After Virtue: Nueroscience, Economics, and the Biopolitics of Morality</italic>… in progress.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1038">
  <label>38</label>
  <p>Andrea Haslanger, ‘The Cynic as Cosmopolitan Animal,’ in Nagai et. al. (eds.) Cosmopolitan Animals, (New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2015), 31.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1039">
  <label>39</label>
  <p>Samantha Hurn, “Baboon Cosmopolitanism: More‐Than‐Human Moralities in a Multispecies Community,” in Nagai et. al. (eds.) Cosmopolitan Animals, (New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2015), 158.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1040">
  <label>40</label>
  <p>Hurn, “Baboon Cosmopolitanism,” 160.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1041">
  <label>41</label>
  <p>Donna Haraway, 
   <italic>When Species Meet,</italic> (Minneapolis and London: University of Minnesota Press, 2008), 90.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1042">
  <label>42</label>
  <p>Eduardo Mendieta, “Interspecies Cosmpolitanism,” in Delanty (ed.) Routledge Handbook of Cosmopolitanism Studies, (New York: Routledge, 2012), 278‐279.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1043">
  <label>43</label>
  <p>Mendieta, “interspecies Cosmopolitanism,” 279; Mendieta is citing Haraway, 
   <italic>When Species Meet</italic>, 2008, 12.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1044">
  <label>44</label>
  <p>Mendieta, “Interspecies Cosmopolitanism,” 279.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1045">
  <label>45</label>
  <p>Although, as has been suggested here and will be demonstrated later, it is mistaken to think of “humans” as one thing over here and “technics” as another different thing over there. They are hopelessly entangled, though this observation ought not to be morally evaluated simply in terms of its ability to blur the line between what might traditionally have been thought as two different metaphysical species.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1046">
  <label>46</label>
  <p>Mendieta, “Interspecies Cosmopolitanism,” 282.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1047">
  <label>47</label>
  <p>Mendieta, “Interspecies Cosmopolitanism,” 279‐280.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1048">
  <label>48</label>
  <p>For the purpose of clarity, from here on out in this paper, “law” is reserved for the judicial law, except where noted.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1049">
  <label>49</label>
  <p>Hurn, 
   <italic>Baboon Cosmopolitanism,</italic> 160.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1050">
  <label>50</label>
  <p>Hurn, Baboon Cosmopolitanism, 161.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1051">
  <label>51</label>
  <p>Or at least not in the sense of having legal title over something.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1052">
  <label>52</label>
  <p>This is, in part, why a nation‐state refusing to abide by international regulation is such a puzzling problem for the international community writ large. Often the first response is something to the effect of “but wait, you can’t do that!”</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1053">
  <label>53</label>
  <p>Stiegler, 1998, 1.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1054">
  <label>54</label>
  <p>Bernard Stiegler, 
   <italic>Technics and Time</italic>, 1998, 1‐2.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1055">
  <label>55</label>
  <p>Stiegler, 1998, 2.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1056">
  <label>56</label>
  <p>Stiegler, 
   <italic>Technics and Time</italic> 1998, 32‐33.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1057">
  <label>57</label>
  <p>Stiegler, 
   <italic>Technics and Time</italic>, vol. 1 1998; 17‐19, 136‐145.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1058">
  <label>58</label>
  <p>Note that Stiegler uses terms that may have other meanings in the natural sciences. Their technical meanings are given here and ought to be carefully separated from their ordinary usage.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1059">
  <label>59</label>
  <p>Keith Ansell Pearson, 
   <italic>Viroid Life: Perspectives on Nietzsche and the Transhuman Condition</italic>, New York: Routledge, 1997, 124.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1060">
  <label>60</label>
  <p>Ansell Pearson 1997, 124. Italices in original.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1061">
  <label>61</label>
  <p>Ansell Person 1997, 133.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="heyj13570-note-1062">
  <label>62</label>
  <p>Ansell Pearson 1997, 133.</p>
 </fn>
</fn-group>
