<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>According to the Diagnosis and Treatment Scheme released by the National Health Commission,
 <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref> and after testing and evaluating the efficacy of various viral nucleic acid detection diagnostic kits, we propose the following interpretations (
 <xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>): 
 <list list-type="roman-lower">
  <list-item>
   <p>(i) The diagnosis is ‘Confirmed’ in patients with positive RT-PCR results for both 
    <italic>ORF1ab</italic> and 
    <italic>N</italic> gene/
    <italic>E</italic> gene amplification (
    <xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4a</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>(ii) The diagnosis is ‘Highly Suspected’ in patients with an RT-PCR result positive for 
    <italic>ORF1ab</italic> and negative for 
    <italic>N</italic> gene/
    <italic>E</italic> gene. The analyses should be repeated with a different RT-PCR kit or replicated with a nucleic acid test kit based on a different methodology (
    <xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4b</xref>) or further genomic sequencing should determine whether the virus has a potential mutation.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>(iii) The diagnosis is ‘Uncertain’ when 
    <italic>ORF1ab</italic> gene amplification is negative. In this case, regardless of the 
    <italic>N</italic> gene/
    <italic>E</italic> gene result, a replicate test should be done with another kit, or the process of sampling and testing should be repeated (
    <xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4c</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>(iv) The interpretations of 2019-nCoV RT-PCR results (
    <xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4d</xref>): a positive nucleic acid test result includes a cycle threshold (Ct) value less than 35 and a standard S-shaped amplification curve of 
    <italic>ORF1ab, N</italic> gene/
    <italic>E</italic> gene, and internal control (IC) on RT-PCR. A negative RT-PCR result is one with absence of amplification curve for 
    <italic>ORF1ab</italic> and 
    <italic>N</italic> gene/
    <italic>E</italic> gene and, at the same time, presence of an S-shaped amplification curve for IC (
    <xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4e</xref>). When the Ct value is between 35 and 40, the result is a suspected positive and should be reviewed before a diagnosis is done.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
