<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0220">The water soluble vitamin C (ascorbic acid) is profoundly available in lemon, oranges, amla, kiwi, guava, grapes, broccoli, cauliflower, and capsicum etc. Vitamin C is well-known as an antioxidant and inhibits the ageing process by enhancing the collagen expression, further, it involved in the wound healing process [
 <xref rid="bb0770" ref-type="bibr">154</xref>]. Apart from the antioxidant effects, Vitamin C involved in chemotaxis, phagocytosis and increases the reactive oxygen species to kill the microorganisms and also acts as an antibacterial agent. It also protects cells by clearing the non-functional organelles by apoptosis mechanisms. Also, it involved in proliferation and differentiation of B- and T-cells, which play a pivotal role in immune mediated reactions [
 <xref rid="bb0775" ref-type="bibr">155</xref>]. Recent scientific reports suggest that vitamin C inhibits the LPS induced TNF-α and IL-1β expression ad reduced the MDA levels and increased the GSH levels and acts as an anti-inflammatory agent [
 <xref rid="bb0780" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>]. Additionally, Vitamin C inhibits the lung fibrosis by reducing the IL-17 secretion and induced SOD levels [
 <xref rid="bb0785" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>]. Vitamin C also has a direct virucidal effect at higher concentrations and decreased the virus load of Ebstein-Barr virus (EBV) infected cells [
 <xref rid="bb0790" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0795" ref-type="bibr">159</xref>]. In general, vitamin C is considered as strong immune booster and must able to protect wide array of microbial infections. However, some reports suggest that ≥1 g per day vitamin C supplementation had no significant effect on common cold incidence. But, some evidence infers that vitamin C could have moderate preventive effects in low dietary intake groups or acute physical stress suffering people [
 <xref rid="bb0800" ref-type="bibr">160</xref>]. Based on the anti-inflammatory and antiviral properties, Vitamin C infusion was tried in SARS-CoV-2 infected pneumonia patients and numerous clinical trials (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="ClinicalTrials.gov" xlink:href="NCT04323514" id="ir0310" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NCT04323514</ext-link>, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="ClinicalTrials.gov" xlink:href="NCT04264533" id="ir0315" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NCT04264533</ext-link>, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="ClinicalTrials.gov" xlink:href="NCT03680274" id="ir0320" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NCT03680274</ext-link>, and 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="ClinicalTrials.gov" xlink:href="NCT04326725" id="ir0325" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NCT04326725</ext-link>) are ongoing for its therapeutic usage.
</p>
