<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par33">The majority of the human serine proteases belongs to the subfamily S1A, possessing a chymotrypsin-like folding pattern, and to the family S8 with the two subfamilies S8A and S8B exhibiting a subtilisin- or kexin-like folding (Rawlings et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR153">2014</xref>). First studies on the limited proteolysis and essential maturation of viral glycoproteins by host proteases were performed on influenza viruses. It could be demonstrated that the cleavage of the hemagglutinin (HA) precursor could be blocked by the broad-spectrum serine protease inhibitor diisopropylfluorophosphate (DFP) (Klenk and Rott 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">1973</xref>). It was found that the poor infectivity of influenza A viruses (IAV) grown in cultures of chick embryo cells could be strongly increased after treatment with exogenous trypsin, which cleaves substrates after basic residues like arginine or lysine (Klenk et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">1975</xref>). At the same time, comparable results were described for the trypsin-catalyzed activation of HA from influenza B viruses (Lazarowitz and Choppin 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">1975</xref>). Although the digestive protease trypsin is not found in the respiratory tract, these initial studies suggested that other trypsin-like airway proteases should be involved in HA maturation. For instance, plasmin efficiently activated the HA of the A/WSN virions but failed to cleave the influenza B HA (Lazarowitz and Choppin 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">1975</xref>). A detailed analysis of the substrate sequences revealed that HAs of human and other mammalian influenza viruses as well as HAs of low pathogenic avian influenza viruses (LPAIV) are cleaved after a single arginine residue before a constant P1′-P3′ Gly-Leu-Phe segment by trypsin-like serine proteases. In contrast, HAs of high pathogenic avian influenza viruses (HPAIV) are activated by furin-like proprotein convertases (PCs) at inserted multibasic sequences containing additional arginine or lysine residues in the adjacent non-primed positions (Garten and Klenk 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2008</xref>). In addition to the HA activation of HPAIV, many other viruses depend on the correct cleavage of their surface glycoproteins by furin-like PCs (basic PCs) or by the neutral PC SKI-1 (Klenk and Garten 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">1994</xref>; Pasquato et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR146">2013</xref>). Consequently, different inhibitor structures depending on the specific virus strains are required to target the appropriate activating protease.
</p>
