<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par35">Data from virus-infected cell cultures suggested that different secreted trypsin-like serine proteases are involved in the HA activation of human IAV and LPAIV depending on the host and specific virus strain. A protease named tryptase Clara was isolated from Clara cells of rat airway epithelium (Kido et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">1992</xref>). Furthermore, miniplasmin purified from rat lungs was described as potential HA activator (Murakami et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR136">2001</xref>). Miniplasmin is a degraded version of plasmin, only comprising the kringle 5 and protease domain and lacking the N-terminal kringle domains 1–4 (Al-Horani and Desai 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2014</xref>). However, plasmin cannot efficiently activate the HAs with monobasic cleavage sites found in the presently circulating influenza strains, because it prefers substrates with bulky P2 residues like Phe, Tyr, and Trp (Swedberg and Harris 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR186">2011</xref>). In embryonated chicken eggs, a blood clotting factor Xa-like protease was found to activate HA (Gotoh et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">1990</xref>). Again, it seems unlikely that human factor Xa could be involved, which is a very specific protease with a strong preference for substrates with glycine in P2 position due to the presence of a bulky Tyr99 on top of its S2 binding pocket. This special structural feature limits the access of substrates with larger P2 side chains. So far, only prothrombin and eventually the protease-activated receptor 2 (PAR-2) are known as well-cleavable natural factor Xa substrates (Oe et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR137">2016</xref>); both possess a glycine in P2 position. Moreover, in rats and mice, cellular ectopic trypsins due to severe influenza infections and cytokine storms were detected as HA-activating proteases (Kido et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">2012</xref>; Pan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR143">2011</xref>; Wang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR198">2010</xref>). An unusual extrapancreatic trypsin expression was also found in some human tumors (Paju et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR141">2001</xref>; Sorsa et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR178">1997</xref>), raising speculations that this could also happen as a consequence of excessive inflammation during viral infections. Porcine tryptases are additional candidates (Chen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2000</xref>; Sato et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR159">2003</xref>), although human lung tryptase has failed to activate the HA of the 1918 IAV (Stevens et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR181">2004</xref>). Among the 15 kallikrein-related peptidases (KLKs) (Goettig et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">2010</xref>), 12 of them possess a trypsin-like substrate specificity, and a potential HA activation of seasonal IAV was observed for KLK5 and KLK12 (Hamilton and Whittaker 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">2013</xref>).
</p>
