<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the 1950s, Tarshis
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr28-1178630220913365" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>
 </sup> provided a compelling evidence incriminating cockroaches as possible vectors of human infections, through a study that reported a correlation between the incidence of hepatitis A and the lack of cockroach control. From 1956 to 1959, the Carmelitos Housing Project had 20% to 39% of the hepatitis A cases in Los Angeles. However, through a concentrated pest control programme, there was a sharp decline in the incidence of endemic infectious hepatitis: in 1960, the hepatitis A incidence at the housing project reduced to 6.6%, then further to 3.6% in 1961, and to 0.0% in 1962. Meanwhile, around the same period, every other place in Los Angeles County that was not receiving the pest control service experienced increasing incidence of the infection. It was observed that the decline in hepatitis A incidence occurred simultaneously with a significant reduction (about 70%) in cockroach infestation due to the pest control programme. The hepatitis A virus occurs in the faeces of infected persons and is usually transmitted through consumption of contaminated water or food. The association of cockroaches with faeces and food makes their transmission of hepatitis A virus highly plausible. Although the study of Tarshis
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr28-1178630220913365" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>
 </sup> was not supported with experimental data, it provides evidence supporting the theory that cockroaches play a role in the transmission of food-borne pathogens. Experimental evidence supporting the possible role of cockroaches in the transmission of food-borne pathogens has been provided by several investigators. A study done by Ash and Greenberg
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr29-1178630220913365" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>
 </sup> in 1980 reported that exposure of cockroaches to 
 <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> subsp. 
 <italic>enterica</italic> serovar Typhimurium resulted in occurrence of the pathogen in the excreta of the cockroaches in a dose-related fashion with outputs of 8 × 10
 <sup>1</sup> to 2 × 10
 <sup>7</sup> cells/defecation over a range of 3 to 20 days. The investigators observed that 
 <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium was recoverable about 10 days longer in the cockroach gut compared with the faeces, and persistence of the organism occurred primarily in the hindgut. In another experiment by Kopanic et al
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr30-1178630220913365" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>
 </sup> in 1993, it was shown that cockroaches could be infected with a naladixic acid-resistant strain of 
 <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium from a contaminated food source. The investigators also showed that the infected cockroaches could transmit the naladixic acid-resistant strain of 
 <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium to uninfected cockroaches, food (eggs), and water. A study by Zurek and Schal
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr31-1178630220913365" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>
 </sup> in 2004 investigated the vectorial potential of German cockroaches for verotoxigenic 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> F18, an important porcine bacterial pathogen. Forty adult cockroaches were divided into 2 groups of 20 each; 1 group of cockroaches was exposed to 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> F18 (5.0 × 10
 <sup>5</sup> CFUs mL) in 10 mL of phosphate buffer solution (PBS), while the second group (control) received 10 mL of sterile PBS. After 5 hours, the PBS was replaced with sterile tap water, and sterile piglet feed ration (collected from the swine farm) was supplied to both cockroach groups. Viable and virulent 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> F18 cells were detectable in cockroach faeces for up to 8 days after the initial exposure, and the number of bacterial cells decreased over time. In the control group, no 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> F18 organisms were detected in cockroach faeces. The average number of faecal coliforms in cockroach faeces was high (4.4 × 10
 <sup>5</sup> g
 <sup>−
  <xref rid="bibr1-1178630220913365" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
 </sup>) and not significantly different from that found in piglet faeces (1.9 ± 0.8 × 10
 <sup>6</sup> g
 <sup>−
  <xref rid="bibr1-1178630220913365" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
 </sup>). Using non-food-borne pathogens such as 
 <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr32-1178630220913365" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>
 </sup> and 
 <italic>Mycobacterium avium</italic> subsp. 
 <italic>paratuberculosis</italic>,
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr33-1178630220913365" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>
 </sup> other investigators have also demonstrated the vectorial potential of cockroaches through controlled laboratory studies.
</p>
