<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As with many modeling studies, this study has several limitations. Many parameters, such as transmission probability and impact of NSPs on transmission, are difficult to identify, and must be estimated using fitting techniques that cannot always account for co-linearity. The data that we use for calibration are from a variety of sources with varying sample sizes and confidence. However, we perform sensitivity analyses (see Section 2 in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0177195.s001">S1 File</xref>) to demonstrate that our results are qualitatively robust across parameter sets. We also assume that treated individuals (except for those who have progressed to chronic liver disease) go back to being susceptible, when in reality it is likely that those with more severe liver damage still have increased morbidity. We tested the sensitivity of our model to this assumption by building in an additional compartment for treated individuals, in which they are cured but can be reinfected, and also have a shorter lifespan to account for this additional morbidity due to liver damage. We found that using this more complex model did not alter any results significantly, except for a cost analysis as described below and in Section 3 in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0177195.s001">S1 File</xref>. Our study also does not take into account other groups at high risk of HIV acquisition, e.g. female sex workers (FSW) and men who have sex with men (MSM). There would likely be spillover effects among FSW and MSM, as there is some interaction between PWID and these groups. The model accounts for this in having a force of infection for HIV that is not fully dependent on prevalence among PWID, but it is not able to measure changes in burden among these other groups. However, it seems likely that reducing the HIV burden among PWID would have positive indirect effects among FSW and MSM, for example among HIV-positive MSM who may be at risk of sexually transmitted HCV [
 <xref rid="pone.0177195.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>].
</p>
