<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20">AGAs have been found in a variety of disorders classically considered to be of exclusive neurological interest. Anti-GM1 AGAs have been found in Alzheimer’s disease (AD) patients.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup> AD has been also related to IgM anti-GD1b
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>
 </sup> and anti-GQ1bα antibodies, although the latter association has received discordant views in the literature.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>
 </sup> It appears that GM1-amyloid-beta protein complexes have the capacity to increase Aβ assembly.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>
 </sup> To further complicate the picture, Svennerholm et al in 2002, reported a slowing of the degenerative process in Alzheimer’s disease patients treated with exogenous GM1.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup> Similarly to AD, association to anti-GM1 antibodies has been found also in Parkinson disease
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>
 </sup> and GM1 supplementation has been studied as a possible treatment strategy
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>
 </sup>. The presence of AGA in amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) has been investigated, but recent studies found no differences between ALS patients and healthy controls.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>
 </sup> AGA were also sporadically identified in cases of myasthenia gravis and Lambert–Eaton syndrome
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>
 </sup> and in a single case of small fiber neuropathy
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>
 </sup>. Because of their ubiquitous nature in the neuronal system, it is not surprising that gangliosides have potentially multiple pathological roles in neurological diseases. Some of them play key roles in disease development, whereas in other cases ganglioside abnormalities are secondary to the actual disease process.
</p>
