<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0675">Considering the time necessary to develop a new medication, in a pandemic, such as the current one, repurposing drugs is useful, and a good part of the literature on the treatment of COVID-19 so far presents possible alternatives. Hence, this comprehensive review of the literature produced in the last six months on the repurposing of drugs for anti-SARS-CoV-2 therapy. Based on the evidences published through theoretical, 
 <italic>in-vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in-vivo</italic> investigations, several drugs from different classes were identified and considered promising candidates for repurposing against COVID-19. Among purine and pyrimidine derivatives, RDV is the most promising adenosine analogue for clinical trials, probably due to the importance of enzyme SARS-CoV-2 RdRp that is inhibited by its action, whereas SBV, structured as uridine analogue, is undergoing clinical trials at different stages of COVID-19. Analyses of carboxylic acids pointed Kaletra®, a combination of LPV/RTV, as the most effective drug after various studies, in isolation or combined therapy, with good results but without a clear mechanism of action against COVID-19. Data on the naphthalene derivative Dasabuvir are still inconclusive as 
 <italic>in-silico</italic> studies came to divergent data.
 <xref rid="b0885" ref-type="bibr">177</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0930" ref-type="bibr">186</xref> Its repurposing potential relies on the mechanism for other viruses, such as Hepatitis C, by inducing conformational changes that compromise RdRp activity. It was also possible to identify benzene derivatives used to treat cancer (Dasatinib and Imatinib) and one antiviral (Darunavir), but predominant 
 <italic>in-silico</italic> and some 
 <italic>in-vitro</italic> outcomes demand more conclusive studies. Representative of benzoic derivatives, NTZ displayed significant inhibitory activity against pro-inflammatory cytokines, which can benefit control of ARDS, in spite of an unclear mechanism against SARS-CoV-2.
</p>
