<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0023">We implemented a cost-effectiveness analysis to assess the economic cost of waiting time, if adhering to our modeling method and contrasting the proposed method to the WHO criteria. To do so, we calculated the cost of waiting for a certain length of time as well as the probability of reduced risk of observing additional cases due to the waiting time. First, let 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>c</sub> and 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>w</sub> be the number of weeks since the last case, as suggested by our computational method and the WHO, respectively. In many instances, 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>c</sub>-
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>w</sub> &gt; 0. We extracted the gross domestic product (GDP) due to Ebola epidemic per week, and fixed the cost, 
 <italic>c</italic>, as 14 million United States dollars (USD) per week (
 <xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr">Bambery et al., 2018</xref>). Second, let 
 <italic>Pr</italic>(
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>c</sub>) and 
 <italic>Pr</italic>(
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>w</sub>) as the probability of observing at least one additional case given the waiting time 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>c</sub> and 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>w</sub>. We converted the risk of recrudescence into the number of Ebola deaths by assuming that one epidemic induced 10,000 deaths as approximated by the 2014–16 epidemic, and thus, 1% risk of recrudescence is assumed to be equivalent to 100 deaths. To convert the number of deaths into the number of life years lost due to Ebola, we calculated the average age of fatal cases and subtracted the average age from the life expectancy at birth. Table S2 shows the life years lost due to Ebola, 
 <italic>y</italic>, in Guinea, Liberia and Sierra Leone. Accordingly, incremental cost-effectiveness ratio (ICER) was calculated as
 <disp-formula id="eqn0007">
  <label>(7)</label>
  <math id="M10" altimg="si10.gif" overflow="scroll">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mtext>ICER</mtext>
     <mspace width="0.33em"/>
    </mrow>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mfrac>
     <mrow>
      <mi>c</mi>
      <mo>(</mo>
      <msub>
       <mi>T</mi>
       <mi>c</mi>
      </msub>
      <mo>−</mo>
      <msub>
       <mi>T</mi>
       <mi>w</mi>
      </msub>
      <mo>)</mo>
     </mrow>
     <mrow>
      <mi>a</mi>
      <mi>y</mi>
      <mrow>
       <mo stretchy="true">|</mo>
       <mrow>
        <mi>P</mi>
        <mi>r</mi>
        <mrow>
         <mo stretchy="true">(</mo>
         <msub>
          <mi>T</mi>
          <mi>c</mi>
         </msub>
         <mo stretchy="true">)</mo>
        </mrow>
        <mo>−</mo>
        <mi>P</mi>
        <mi>r</mi>
        <mrow>
         <mo stretchy="true">(</mo>
         <msub>
          <mi>T</mi>
          <mi>w</mi>
         </msub>
         <mo stretchy="true">)</mo>
        </mrow>
       </mrow>
       <mo stretchy="true">|</mo>
      </mrow>
     </mrow>
    </mfrac>
    <mo>×</mo>
    <mn>100</mn>
    <mo>,</mo>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula>where 
 <italic>a</italic> is the conversion rate from the probability of recrudescence to the number of deaths (i.e., 
 <italic>a</italic> = 100 deaths per 1% risk of recrudescence). During the implementation, we accounted for the uncertainty with respect to the proportion of sexual transmissions among all secondary cases, 
 <italic>p</italic>. To address the uncertainty, we randomly sampled the value of 
 <italic>p</italic> for 1000 times from a triangular distribution with the peak 0.0012 and minimum and maximum values at 0 and 1, respectively. This illustration was made with application to Guinea data, but univariate sensitivity analysis using 
 <xref rid="eqn0007" ref-type="disp-formula">(7)</xref> was also conducted for all three countries.
</p>
