<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Guangdong Province is located in the southern mainland of China and experiences tropical and subtropical monsoon climates with a hot and rainy environment that supports breeding of mosquitos, leading to epidemics and very high incidences of DF.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
  <xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>
 </sup> The first outbreak of dengue in the Foshan city of Guangdong Province occurred in 1978, after which periodic infections and transmission of all four serotypes of dengue have occurred in the past 30 years.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>
 </sup> The DENV found in these areas may have different origins. There were two DENV2 outbreaks in Foshan in 1993 and 1998, respectively. Phylogenetic analysis revealed that isolates from the 1998 epidemic and DENV4 from the 1978 epidemic and the 1990 epidemic were closely related to those from the 1993 epidemic in Thailand, 1973 epidemic in Indonesia, and the 1984 epidemic in the Philippines, respectively. Since 1990, however, DENV1 has been mainly isolated from the infected cases, and its continued existence in Guangdong Province indicated that endemic infectious agents of dengue may be circulating locally. Sequence analysis of the viruses causing the epidemics at different time points revealed that the isolates were closely related to each other, implying that DENV1 had probably circulated locally and caused the epidemics.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
 </sup> Since 2009, all four serotypes were derived from autonomous patients from different outbreak localities in Guangdong Province.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
 </sup> In 2014, a total of 45,236 cases of dengue were reported, which exceeded the total number of cases reported over the previous 10 years. Although three serotypes of the DENV (DENV1, DENV2, and DENV3) were identified, DENV1 was found to be the major causative agent responsible for 98.72% of all 21,928 laboratory-confirmed cases diagnosed during this outbreak.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>
 </sup> A recent study revealed that the detected sequences belonged to viruses of multiple origins, but the strain isolated in 2014 possibly originated from the isolates of 2013.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>
 </sup> It can be reasonably speculated that the infectious agents of DENV1 from the endemic, which were circulating locally, played a crucial role in causing the dengue epidemic in Guangdong Province. However, the data mentioned previously are from the studies based on the outbreaks of the particular year and have the limitation of space and time. As a result, comprehensive evaluation of the epidemiological situation and molecular evolution of the viral agents is of significance to warn against their risks and establish preventive and control measures for DF.
</p>
