<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Here, we reviewed recent research efforts in the field of vaccine discovery, vaccine formulation development, and vaccine delivery device designs. Because of the deployment of various engineering technologies, it is expected that future vaccines will not only need to demonstrate safety and efficacy but also to be relatively convenient and simple to use for better coping with population-level vaccinations or sudden outbreaks worldwide. Nanoengineered formulations could enhance the immune response by delivering the required components together and maximizing their uptake by immunocompetent cells. To expedite the future preparedness of vaccines for the occurrence of a pandemic, synthetic vaccines have demonstrated great potential for rapid clinical applications because they are molecularly defined and independent of the time-consuming culture of viruses, which can accelerate the initial vaccine development. However, synthetic vaccines are also the ones that need to be formulated the most, which constitutes the major part of their time costs. To accelerate the development of synthetic vaccines, the nanoengineered formulations need to be simple and robust to manufacture in terms of chemistry or the selection of raw materials.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref165">165</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref166">166</xref>
 </sup> In terms of vaccine delivery devices, self-administrable vaccines, single-shot vaccines, and solid MN-based vaccines could further enhance the availability of vaccines to a broader population. For instance, self-administrable vaccines can be mailed to patients at home without the need of medical experts.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref165">165</xref>
 </sup> Single-shot vaccines can be much more convenient compared to the traditional immunization regimens that require multiple shots. Furthermore, solid MN-based vaccines that are cold chain free could simplify the vaccine transportation and distribution process. All of these aspects could be enabled by engineering approaches to accelerate the development of vaccines at a pandemic speed.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref165">165</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref166">166</xref>
 </sup> Although combining the advantages of vaccine formulations and vaccine delivery devices is promising, micro/macro-engineering still needs to develop solutions that do not require “harsh” conditions to be compatible with nanoengineered formulations.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref167">167</xref>
 </sup> Expectedly, platform technologies that can be quickly adapted to address emerging viral diseases could speed up the pace of vaccine development.
</p>
