<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The COVID-19 pandemic by coronavirus SARS-CoV-2, is a severe, complex, and multifactorial disease in which human genetics, due to inherited predispositions, could play a role together with pre-existing comorbidities and acquired risk conditions. Unmodifiable factors, such as age and sex, together with modifiable classical cardiovascular risk factors and comorbidities play crucial roles in tuning the fate of SARS-CoV-2 infection, worsening prognosis, and mortality rate. In turn, the mechanism of SARS-CoV-2 infection, due to ACE2 receptor entry, might be altered by individual genetic or developed susceptibility. An overly activated RAS-system, mainly due to local ACE1/ACE2 unbalancing, might be crucial in determining specific vulnerability/receptivity and in giving indicators of the local balanced inflammation, blood coagulation, and fibrinolysis. These evidences support the use of appropriate anticoagulant and anti-inflammatory therapies properly monitored by specific laboratory markers (as fibrin D-Dimer) or with a more refined approach by the dynamic assessing of residual FXIIIA levels, as recently suggested during any acute thrombotic event [
 <xref rid="B182-ijms-21-03474" ref-type="bibr">182</xref>,
 <xref rid="B183-ijms-21-03474" ref-type="bibr">183</xref>]. The unexpected reported higher expression of 
 <italic>ACE2</italic> in females, the inverse age-dependent 
 <italic>ACE2</italic> expression significantly reduced by the presence of diabetes, and the strong repression of 
 <italic>ACE2</italic> by inflammatory cytokines, confirm an inverse correlation between 
 <italic>ACE2</italic> levels and SARS-CoV-2 prognosis. Summarizing, this is in contrast with the assumption that “
 <italic>high ACE2 is a culprit in COVID-19 outcome, and on the contrary supports a protective role of high ACE2 expression against SARS-CoV2 fatality</italic>” [
 <xref rid="B131-ijms-21-03474" ref-type="bibr">131</xref>] also strengthened by the ACE2 intrinsic anticoagulant properties. Interestingly, SARS-CoV-2 mediated repression of ACE2 is counteracted by sex hormone inducible mechanisms (though unfortunately sex-hormones decrease with age) and exacerbated by systemic inflammation (which unfortunately increases with age and chronic diseases) [
 <xref rid="B131-ijms-21-03474" ref-type="bibr">131</xref>].
</p>
