<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There have been a number of structures of norovirus P domains complexed with simple saccharides [
 <xref rid="B15-viruses-11-00235" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-viruses-11-00235" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-viruses-11-00235" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Cloned, expressed P domains, separate from the full-length capsid protein, have been crystallized and diffract to high resolution and therefore more amenable for detailed studies of oligosaccharide—P domain interactions. Norwalk virus, the archetype genogroup I norovirus, recognizes A-type and H-type human blood group antigens while VA387, a genogroup II norovirus, recognizes a larger array of blood group antigens. In the first structure [
 <xref rid="B34-viruses-11-00235" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], the P domains from VA387 were crystallized in the presence of trisaccharides representing blood group antigens A and B. These glycans bind to essentially the same location; at the interface between the two subunits and at outer most tip of the P2 domain. The both types of glycans are able to bind likely due to the fact that most of the protein/ligand interactions are via the common fucose moiety. While the binding pocket lies at the P2 dimeric interface, the predominant interactions lie on one side of the dimer. Similar studies were performed on Norwalk P domains [
 <xref rid="B35-viruses-11-00235" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. One of the major differences between NV and VA387 is that VA387 can bind to both A and B blood group antigens while NV can only bind to A. This is well explained by the structure that shows that, while blood group antigen A binds to NV in approximately the same location as was observed in VA387, the majority of the interactions are formed between the α-GalNAc moiety and the P2 domain—the defining difference between the A and B blood group antigens. In a subsequent study [
 <xref rid="B15-viruses-11-00235" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] they determined the structure of both A and H blood group antigens complexed with NV P domains. The H blood group polysaccaride has a terminal α-fucose sugar being followed by a β-galactose. These two sugars together replaced the interactions made by the single α-GalNAc moiety in the A group antigen. Both glycans interact with a conserved tryptophan (375) and common hydrogen binding patterns with both glycans. It is therefore a very interesting case of where there is ligand specificity yet two quite different ligands bind to the same site. Similarly, the primary interactions between the HGBAs and GII.10 and GII.12 genotypes are with the terminal αfucose1-2 moiety of the HGBA at the dimer interface [
 <xref rid="B36-viruses-11-00235" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The remaining interactions with other HGBAs are variable with fewer hydrogen bonds.
</p>
