<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0490">VL is fatal if not treated, and is caused by 
 <italic>Leishmania donovani</italic>, 
 <italic>Leishmania infantum</italic>, and 
 <italic>Leishmania chagasi</italic>.
 <xref rid="bib129" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>129</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib130" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>130</sup>
 </xref> Immunity to leishmaniasis is mediated by the cellular and humoral arms of the mammalian immune system: the innate system (by neutrophils, macrophages, and dendritic cells) and by adaptive (T cells) responses.
 <xref rid="bib131" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>131</sup>
 </xref> Sand-fly bites cause minimal tissue damage, but the bite promotes neutrophil recruitment.
 <xref rid="bib132" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>132</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib133" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>133</sup>
 </xref> Parasites can survive for a time within neutrophils, and eventually they parasitize neutrophils. Viable parasites are engulfed by macrophages or dendritic cells. Inside the macrophages, promastigotes change into amastigotes and they reproduce by binary fission, ultimately rupturing the macrophage and releasing amastigotes into the blood. Leishmania modulates the normal antimicrobial mechanisms of the macrophages. They increase membrane fluidity and thereby disrupt lipid rafts and APC antigen presentation as well as lysosomal fusion.
 <xref rid="bib134" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>134</sup>
 </xref> Leishmania-infected APCs interact with T cells, and together they express cytokines and chemokines that begin to “hijack” the immune system, which enables these parasites to survive.
 <xref rid="bib135" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>135</sup>
 </xref> Cell-mediated immunity is the principle host defense against 
 <italic>leishmania</italic> species. T
 <sub>h</sub>1-like cells primed mainly by APCs and IL-12 expression are major effector responses to this microbe.
 <xref rid="bib136" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib137" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib138" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib139" ref-type="bibr">139</xref> The dichotomy between T
 <sub>h</sub>1-like protection (IFN-γ, IL-2, and TNF) and Th2-like disease progression (IL-10, IL-4) in mice has been shown to be essential in CL infection,
 <xref rid="bib140" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>140</sup>
 </xref> although this paradigm is less clear in humans infected with VL.
 <xref rid="bib141" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>141</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib142" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>142</sup>
 </xref> The immunopathology of VL is complex, and involves cellular and genetic factors that confer disease susceptibility, versus resistance to 
 <italic>Leishmania</italic> species.
 <xref rid="bib143" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>143</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
