<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0500">Resolution of human and murine VL depends on the production of Th1-like cytokines.
 <xref rid="bib139" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>139</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib140" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>140</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib147" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>147</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib157" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib158" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib159" ref-type="bibr">159</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib160" ref-type="bibr">160</xref> IL-12 and IFN-γ are crucial in controlling parasite growth and development.
 <xref rid="bib157" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>157</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib161" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>161</sup>
 </xref> While IL-10 suppresses host immunity and helps parasite survival, it is the antidote to inflammation that reduces tissue damage caused by exaggerated inflammation.
 <xref rid="bib162" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>162</sup>
 </xref> Since IFN-γ -producing cells can also produce small amounts of IL-10, this may act as a negative feedback in controlling tissue damage
 <xref rid="bib142" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>142</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib146" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>146</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib163" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>163</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib164" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>164</sup>
 </xref> and supporting immune memory. TNF stimulates IFN-γ -induced expression of nitric oxide by APCs that can kill VL parasites.
 <xref rid="bib165" ref-type="bibr">165</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib166" ref-type="bibr">166</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib167" ref-type="bibr">167</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib168" ref-type="bibr">168</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib169" ref-type="bibr">169</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib170" ref-type="bibr">170</xref> Th17-like cells that produce IL-17 are pro-inflammatory, and stimulate IL-6, TNF-α, and chemokine expression. However, 
 <italic>L. donovani</italic> strongly induces IL-17 and IL-22, and enhances the secretion of these cytokines that protect this parasite.
 <xref rid="bib171" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>171</sup>
 </xref> CD8
 <sup>+</sup> cytotoxic T cells are also important in controlling CL and VL.
 <xref rid="bib172" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>172</sup>
 </xref> CD4
 <sup>+</sup> and CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells, and their pro-inflammatory cytokines, are required to control VL parasite proliferation and leishmaniacidal activity.
 <xref rid="bib138" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>138</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib161" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>161</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib173" ref-type="bibr">173</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib174" ref-type="bibr">174</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib175" ref-type="bibr">175</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib176" ref-type="bibr">176</xref> However, in canine VL, antibodies are insufficient in providing protection in the absence of -pro-inflammatory T cell responses.
 <xref rid="bib132" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>132</sup>
 </xref> Thus, in addition to protective T cell responses, other T cell subsets, including Tregs and Th17 cells, confer either susceptibility or resistance to animal verses human VC. Other cells may also be important in the resolution of these infections, thus further investigation is required in designing vaccines or treatments for these diseases.
</p>
