<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18">Our current result indicates that the maintenance of a low ZIKV titer in sewage can cause the infection of adult mosquitoes through breeding. The infected mosquitoes derived from the infectious sewage can transmit ZIKV to a host by biting. In a disease-outbreak scenario, many infected individuals (with or without symptoms) may intensively discharge a large volume of infectious urine into a restricted aquatic habitat of mosquitoes. We therefore speculate a scenario during a Zika outbreak in which the accumulating ZIKV infectious particles discharged by patients might be sufficient to facilitate the acquisition of an infection by immature mosquitoes breeding in cesspit conditions, thereby establishing the host urination-mosquito breeding transmission cycle. Interestingly, the emerging evidence indicates that low-passage 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> field mosquitoes from the Americas have an unexpectedly low vector competence for ZIKV transmission by oral blood feeding
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup>. Compared to that of CHIKV and DENV, clinical surveillance has shown a relatively low ZIKV viremia (10
 <sup>2</sup>–10
 <sup>3</sup> pfu/ml) present in human serum samples
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup>. Intriguingly, the acquisition of human blood with 10
 <sup>3</sup>–10
 <sup>4</sup> pfu/ml ZIKV resulted in an inefficient infection and transmission by both the lab-adapted and field-derived 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> mosquitoes. Thus, ZIKV viremia alone might not account for its rapid spread, implicating that additional routes might contribute to the prevalence of mosquito infection in nature. Nonetheless, human viremia titers reported in the previous literature may reflect snapshot results of patients seeking treatment after symptom onset. It is possible that these results may actually reflect off-peak viremia.
</p>
