<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par34">Immunocompromised individuals tend to suffer from influenza longer with more serious complications than otherwise healthy patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR151">151</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR154">154</xref>]. Since immunocompromised patients are more likely to acquire influenza [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR155">155</xref>], showing relatively high influenza-associated mortality [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR153">153</xref>], effective antiviral is crucial for these patients. Like with influenza and young children, the higher level of replication with longer duration of virus shedding in immunocompromised patients increases the chance of developing antiviral resistance [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR156">156</xref>]. Several recent clinical studies have reported that the emergence of antiviral resistance among treated immunocompromised patients is not uncommon [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR151">151</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR157">157</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR158">158</xref>]. Recently, a prospective clinical study aimed to study antiviral resistance in immunocompromised patients (
 <italic>n</italic> = 24); a resistance prevalence of 17 % (4/24) was reported [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR158">158</xref>]. In all four cases the NA His275Tyr was detected by RT-PCR of 2009 influenza A/H1N1 virus-infected patients. In other retrospective studies, similar rates have been reported [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR151">151</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR157">157</xref>]. The NA His275Tyr amino acid change has been described frequently during the 2009 influenza A/H1N1 virus pandemic in case reports of antiviral-treated immunocompromised patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117">117</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR159">159</xref>]. Amino acid changes at position 223 have also been reported to cause increased levels of resistance (48-fold) to oseltamivir. The impact on therapy is unclear for such moderate increase in oseltamivir resistance; however viruses with the combination of Ile223Arg and His275Tyr are highly resistant to oseltamivir in vitro (1750-fold) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR160">160</xref>]. In the past, emergence of resistance in immunocompromised patients has been also described for influenza A/H3N2 and influenza B virus-infected patients treated with oseltamivir and zanamivir with mutations in both the viral HA and NA glycoproteins [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR161">161</xref>]. Most fatal cases during influenza pandemics and seasonal epidemics are patients belonging to the traditional high-risk groups for developing severe disease, including the very young children, elderly, and immunocompromised patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR162">162</xref>]. Given the high mortality and morbidity, the moderate effectiveness of current antivirals, and the relatively high prevalence of resistance in immunocompromised patient, better treatment strategies are clearly needed for these patients.
</p>
