<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par99">Plasma therapy is the process of extracting therapeutic molecules, such as antibodies and plasma, from the immunized or recovering individual and transferring the extracted molecule to ill individuals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>]. This type of regenerative medicine was first developed to battle the Spanish flu during the early 20th century [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>]. During the Spanish flu pandemic, transfusion of blood from influenza survivors significantly decreased mortality rates [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>]. Another notable discovery was made during a latter viral outbreak. During the arenavirus outbreak, victims often experienced severe hemorrhage [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>]. 
 <italic>In vivo</italic> studies during this outbreak highlighted the protective abilities of plasma therapy. Specifically, transfusing blood from immune species into healthy species decreased the severity of the symptoms. These discoveries opened the possibility of utilizing plasma therapy to battle against viral outbreaks. Tremendous advancements were made in the molecular techniques and production of human immunoglobin during the years after each subsequent pandemic or epidemic, including measles, HIV/AIDS, and 2003 SARS-CoV. After several past experiences with viral outbreaks worldwide, there was one constant observation: plasma therapy must be applied as soon as possible after the first onset of disease. Clinical trials have reported that healthy and infected patients who received plasma therapy early displayed a decrease in symptom severity and mortality rate [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>]. Based on previous pandemics and discoveries on plasma therapy, if plasma therapy became an available treatment option for COVID-19 patients, convalescent plasma therapy should be applied at the earliest, either as a preventive measure or early therapeutic option, to maximize the efficiency of the treatment.
</p>
