<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec id="sec001">
  <title>Purpose</title>
  <p>Quadrivalent influenza vaccine (QIV) includes the same strains as trivalent influenza vaccine (TIV) plus an additional B strain of the other B lineage. The aim of the study was to analyse the public health and economic impact of replacing TIV with QIV in different scenarios in Spain.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec002">
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>A dynamic transmission model was developed to estimate the number of influenza B cases prevented under TIV and QIV strategies (&lt;65 years (high risk) and ≥65 years). This model considers cross-protective immunity induced by different lineages of influenza B. The output of the transmission model was used as input for a decision tree model that estimated the economic impact of switching TIV to QIV. The models were populated with Spanish data whenever possible. Deterministic univariate and probabilistic multivariate sensitivity analyses were performed.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec003">
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>Replacing TIV with QIV in all eligible patients with current vaccine coverage in Spain may have prevented 138,707 influenza B cases per season and, therefore avoided 10,748 outpatient visits, 3,179 hospitalizations and 192 deaths. The replacement could save €532,768 in outpatient visit costs, €13 million in hospitalization costs, and €3 million in costs of influenza-related deaths per year. An additional €5 million costs associated with productivity loss could be saved per year, from the societal perspective. The budget impact from societal perspective would be €6.5 million, and the incremental cost-effectiveness ratio (ICER) €1,527 per quality-adjusted life year (QALY). Sensitivity analyses showed robust results. In additional scenarios, QIV also showed an impact at public health level reducing influenza B related cases, outpatient visits, hospitalizations and deaths.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec004">
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p>Our results show public health and economic benefits for influenza prevention with QIV. It would be an efficient intervention for the Spanish National Health Service with major health benefits especially in the population ≥65-year.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
