<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The results from our laboratory study of 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> mosquitoes at various physiological states confirmed what 
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">Costero et al. (1998b)</xref> suggested about background detection of sugar in blood-fed mosquitoes. While our mean fructose value for blood-feds was only 3.72 µg, adding two standard deviations to this would make it 7.41. However, it should be noted that we tested fully engorged mosquitoes for this lab analysis, while none of our field-collected mosquitoes appeared to be blood-fed at the time of analysis. The hot anthrone test, which detects all carbohydrates, had higher mean values for most of the laboratory-reared groups, as expected. Interestingly, the mean sugar content for both male and female starved 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> actually decreased slightly. It was also interesting to see higher values for females than males in both unfed and sugar-fed cohorts. In the unfed mosquitoes, perhaps body size difference (females are on average larger than males) was enough to give a higher reading, but with the mosquitoes that were analyzed 24-h after feeding on 10% sucrose, differences in rate of digestion and levels of activity may account for this distinction where females had four times the fructose and over twice as much total sugars compared to males. Perhaps males burn ingested sugars at a faster rate as they are seeking mates immediately after obtaining a sugar meal. Gravid females had a slightly lower mean fructose compared to blood-feds, but were higher than blood-feds with the hot anthrone test. Finally, post-oviposition females appeared to have slightly less fructose than blood-fed or gravid females, and less total sugars than gravid females, but slightly higher total sugar than blood-fed mosquitoes. Among females, the range of values was greatest in this physiological category. Further study of post-oviposition females would be useful to better understand why some show negligible sugar while others in this category appear to have significant sugar reserves.
</p>
