<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>"Zoonosis" is defined as a disease or infection that is naturally transmitted from vertebrate animals to humans [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Zoonotic diseases can be either transmitted via direct or indirect contact. Transmission of an infectious agent from a vertebrate animal to a human by an arthropod vector is an example of indirect transmission of zoonotic disease. Viruses that maintain transmission cycles between vertebrate animal reservoirs as main amplifying hosts and insects as primary vectors are known as arboviruses (arthropod-borne viruses). Arboviruses must replicate in the arthropod vectors, such as mosquitoes, ticks, midges or sandflies, prior to transmission. Female mosquitoes acquire virus during blood feeding of an infected animal and the virus replicates in the mesenteronal epithelial cells. The virus released from the mesenteronal epithelial cells infects salivary glands after secondary amplification in other cells and tissues. Some arboviruses can infect the salivary glands without secondary amplification in other cells and tissues. Subsequently, the virus released from salivary gland epithelium is transmitted during blood feeding of the vertebrate host. Arboviruses are included in different taxonomic families, including 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic> (genus 
 <italic>Flavivirus</italic>), 
 <italic>Bunyaviridae</italic> (genus 
 <italic>Nairovirus</italic>, 
 <italic>Orthobunyavirus</italic>, 
 <italic>Phlebovirus,</italic> and 
 <italic>Tospovirus</italic>), 
 <italic>Togaviridae</italic> (genus 
 <italic>Alphavirus</italic>), 
 <italic>Rhabdoviridae</italic> (genus 
 <italic>Vesiculovirus</italic>), 
 <italic>Orthomyxoviridae</italic> (genus 
 <italic>Thogotovirus</italic>), and 
 <italic>Reoviridae</italic> (genus 
 <italic>Orbivirus</italic> and 
 <italic>Coltivirus</italic>) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Many of the important zoonotic arboviruses belong to the families 
 <italic>Togaviridae</italic> and 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. However, there are many other clinically important human and animal arboviruses belonging to the 
 <italic>Bunyaviridae</italic> family, such as Crimean-Congo hemorrhagic fever virus (tick-borne) in the genus 
 <italic>Nairovirus</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] and Toscana virus (sandfly-borne) and Rift Valley fever virus (mosquito-borne) in the genus 
 <italic>Phlebovirus</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Colorado tick fever virus in the family 
 <italic>Reoviridae</italic> (genus 
 <italic>Coltivirus</italic>) is also an important human arbovirus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>-
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>].
</p>
