<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The heptad repeat (HR) regions in the S2 domain are crucial for the viral membrane fusion event.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref84">84</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref85">85</xref>
 </sup> HR1 and HR2 can interact with each other to form a 6-HB to bring viral and cellular membranes close (for exact location, see 
 <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>
 </xref>). On the basis of this requirement, Bosch et al. obtained peptides corresponding to region HR2 within the HR. HR2-8 displayed in an infection inhibition assay with pseudotyped SARS-CoV S protein in Vero cells an EC
 <sub>50</sub> value of 17 μM (
 <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>
 </xref> and 
 <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="other">Table 
  <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="other">2</xref>
 </xref>).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref84">84</xref>
 </sup> Moreover, HR2-8 demonstrated concentration-dependent inhibition of HCoV-NL63 infection with an IC
 <sub>50</sub> value of 0.5 μM and a CC
 <sub>50</sub> value of 20 μM.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref86">86</xref>
 </sup> On the basis of these initial results, further development of the HR2-8 peptide is necessary to develop a more potent human coronaviruse (HCoV) peptide inhibitor. Similarly, Ngai et al. obtained three HR derived peptides, including HR1-a, GST-removed-HR2, and HR2 peptide, with remarkable inhibitory activity against SARS-CoV (
 <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>
 </xref> and 
 <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="other">Table 
  <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="other">2</xref>
 </xref>). Virus entry inhibition studies suggested that HR1-A, derived from the HR1 region, had an EC
 <sub>50</sub> value of 1.61 μM. GST-removed-HR2 peptide and HR2 peptide, derived from the HR2 region, had EC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 2.15 and 0.34 μM, respectively.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref87">87</xref>
 </sup> HR2P, spanning residues 1251–1286 in HR2 domains, could effectively inhibit MERS-CoV infection and S protein-mediated membrane fusion (
 <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>
 </xref> and 
 <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="other">Table 
  <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="other">2</xref>
 </xref>). This study indicates that HR2P could specifically inhibit MERS-CoV in Vero cells, with an IC
 <sub>50</sub> value of ∼0.6 μM and a CC
 <sub>50</sub> value of &gt;1000 μM. HR2P also demonstrated high selectivity, as indicated by its high selectivity index (SI &gt; 1667). Importantly, the introduction of Arg, Lys, or Glu residues into the HR2P peptide increased stability, solubility, and anti-MERS-CoV activity.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref88">88</xref>
 </sup> To improve the stability, solubility, and antiviral activity of HR2P, Channappanavar et al. designed and synthesized an HR2P analogue named HR2P-M2. HR2P-M2 strongly blocked S protein-mediated cell–cell fusion in a dose-dependent manner at IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 0.55 μM in vitro. In vivo, HR2P-M2 intranasal administration to Ad5/hDPP4 transgenic mice protected them from MERS-CoV infection and reduced the lung viral titers by more than 1000-fold. Moreover, combination treatment with IFN-β was demonstrated to enhance the protective effect.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref89">89</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
