<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pntd.0006538.s003">
 <label>S3 Fig</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Phylogenetic analyses of Yellow fever virus (based on dataset 2).</title>
  <p>The maximum clade credibility tree inferred using 125 Yellow fever virus sequences (651 nt) from South America is shown. The posterior probabilities are represented by circles drawn in scale in the nodes. Clades containing Brazilian yellow fever virus from outbreaks 2000–01, 2008–09 and the current (2016–2018) are shown in green, blue and red, respectively. Terminal branches in orange represent sequences of Yellow fever virus from Venezuela, pink from Colombia, purple from Trinidad and Tobago, light green from Panama, light blue from Ecuador and black from Brazil. Sequences from South America, genotpe II and South African genotype are collapsed in grey. Horizontal branch lengths are drawn to a scale of years. The tree was reconstructed using the nucleotide substitution model HKY with gamma distribution (four categories), under the relaxed molecular clock and Bayesian skyline demographic model. The asterisk (*) denotes the cluster of 
   <italic>Yellow fever virus</italic> obtained from non-human primates which had two amino acid substitutions characterized as synapomorphies. ES: Espírito Santo state, MG: Minas Gerais state. Analyses were performed using programs from BEAST package v.1.8.4 [
   <xref rid="pntd.0006538.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], BEAUTi v.1.8.2 [
   <xref rid="pntd.0006538.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], Tracer v.1.5.0 [
   <xref rid="pntd.0006538.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], TreeAnotator v.1.8.2 [
   <xref rid="pntd.0006538.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] and FigTree v.1.4.3 [
   <xref rid="pntd.0006538.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]
  </p>
  <p>(TIF)</p>
 </caption>
 <media xlink:href="pntd.0006538.s003.tif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <caption>
   <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
  </caption>
 </media>
</supplementary-material>
