<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The role of DVGs in inducing the innate immune response has been demonstrated in cell culture [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006650.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and animal models [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006650.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Studies in several animal models have led to proposals for the use of DG molecules or viruses modified to generate them in large numbers as protective elements against influenza virus infection [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006650.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. It would be likely that the reduced activation of the antiviral state of cells infected with low DVGs producer viruses might induce an impaired immune response in infected animals or patients. The initially reduced antiviral state of the infected cells (Figs 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat.1006650.g003">3</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat.1006650.g006">6C</xref>) may allow the virus to grow uncontrolled for a short time and then this would induce an exacerbated immune response and inflammation which was described for severe IAV infected patients in the 2009 pandemic [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006650.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1006650.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. In viral infections, neutrophils and alveolar macrophages play a key role in clearance and control of viral growth in infected lungs, thus their substantial migration to the site of inflammation in infected tissue contributes to overall viral pathogenicity. Depletion of alveolar macrophages leads to an uncontrolled viral proliferation and fatal outcome in infected mice [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006650.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1006650.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] while high influx of neutrophils in lungs and excessive inflammation has been associated with severe illness and high mortality rate in influenza infection [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006650.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The depletion of alveolar macrophages perfectly correlates with increased viral titers in lung tissue of PA 
 <italic>mut</italic> and PB2/PA 
 <italic>mut</italic> infected animals (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat.1006650.g008">Fig 8A and 8C</xref>), emphasizing again the crucial role of these cells in viral clearance and control of viral growth. In addition, an increased influx of neutrophils, which is associated with lethal influenza virus infection [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006650.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], has been observed in recombinant viruses carrying a mutation (PA 
 <italic>mut</italic> and PB2/PA 
 <italic>mut</italic>) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat.1006650.g008">Fig 8B</xref>) present in a fatal-case virus, which produce reduced amount of DVGs (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat.1006650.g005">Fig 5A</xref>).
</p>
