<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The induction of the interferon system is a universal element in the activation of the host cell innate immune response against viruses. When cells sense viral components, interferons produced in infected cells are secreted to induce an antiviral state in surrounding cells, thus keeping viral spread at bay. Among the host cell proteins induced by interferon, IFITM3 is a potent antiviral factor that strongly restricts IAV (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). The antiviral activity of IFITM3 is mechanistically not fully resolved. IFITM3 is detected at LE/L (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) and was reported previously to induce the accumulation of LE/L cholesterol (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), possibly through interfering with ER-LE/L contact sites (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Although the impact of IFITM3 on membrane fusion has been observed by several studies (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>), the role of LE/L cholesterol accumulation as part of antiviral IFITM3 activity has been questioned (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). LE/L cholesterol accumulation has been observed in IFITM3-overexpressing cells (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>), but the issues of whether IFN treatment itself would also result in upregulation of LE/L cholesterol contents (via upregulation of IFITM3 or, rather, independently of IFITM3) and whether such IFN-driven increased LE/L cholesterol levels would restrict IAV endosomal escape had not been addressed previously (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Here, we report that IFN treatment indeed elevates the amounts of LE/L cholesterol. Interestingly, such an increase of the levels of LE/L cholesterol upon IFN treatment was suggested earlier but was not shown experimentally (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). The IFN-driven LE/L cholesterol increase appeared to depend on the upregulation of IFITM3, in line with previous data obtained from cells ectopically overexpressing IFITM3.
</p>
