<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Because the antiviral impact of LE/L cholesterol overload on IAV cell entry is heavily disputed (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), we utilized AnxA6 overexpression and the small-molecule inhibitor U18666A to interfere with the proper function of the endosomal cholesterol transporter NPC1. Both approaches represent alternative IFN-independent and well-established models used to induce LE/L cholesterol accumulation (reviewed in reference 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). We identified that the interferon-independent LE/L cholesterol accumulation was clearly antiviral and restricted early IAV infection in cells not exposed to IFN-β, thus supporting the idea that LE/L cholesterol is an element of the IFN response chain. NPC1 was discovered as an entry factor for filoviruses (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>) and in the case of the Ebola virus entry apparently acts in a cholesterol-independent fashion (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). Our findings indicating that NPC1 overexpression 
 <italic>per se</italic> did not increase the proportion of IFN-β-unprimed, IAV-infected cells argue, however, against a cholesterol-independent function for NPC1 in IAV entry. The significantly impaired number of NP-positive nuclei seen during infection of AnxA6-overexpressing A431 cells as well as A549 cells indicated that early IAV infection was affected. An earlier analysis by Ma et al. did not detect decreased NP staining using a similar cell system. However, it is not known whether the AnxA6-mediated LE/L cholesterol phenotype was apparent in their stable cell line (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). IFITM3-sensitive viruses, such as IAV, are still able to reach the acidic endosomes, the site where pH-dependent viral envelope/membrane fusion occurs (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). In agreement, we did not observe inhibition of IAV uptake (as judged by the presence of IAV M1 protein) and trafficking in U18666A-treated or AnxA6-overexpressing cells.
</p>
