<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The data presented in this study contradict previous studies that reported LE/L cholesterol accumulation and reduced IAV endosomal escape in IFITM3-overexpressing cells but did not detect an effect on virus-membrane hemifusion, leading to the assumption that excess LE/L cholesterol is not the mechanism by which IFITM3 inhibits the IAV fusion. Similarly, only a minor impact on lipid mixing was observed when the LE/L compartment was subjected to cholesterol loading using U18666A (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). However, in the study mentioned, pseudovirus infection was used. More importantly, our comparison of the different methods used to measure lipid mixing (single dye versus dual dyes) indicated that single-dye fusion assays might have reduced sensitivity. Consistently, we always detected a pronounced decrease in hemifusion in U18666A-treated cells, applying the well-established dual-dye assay (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Thus, our results point to an inhibitory effect of LE/L cholesterol on viral envelope/endosomal membrane fusion. Besides its activity with respect to LE/L cholesterol contents, IFITM3 was proposed to affect IAV endosomal escape at a step later than hemifusion, possibly by negatively affecting fusion pore formation and opening (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). We did not observe impaired membrane fusion in cells that had not been treated with interferon but that were downregulated for IFITM3, and yet the number of infected cells was increased. These observations suggest that IFITM3 has several roles in the complex process of IAV endosomal escape, in addition to cholesterol-mediated inhibition of hemifusion. In turn, this could explain the fact that no rescue due to overexpression of NPC1 in IFITM3 overexpressing cells was seen in earlier studies (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>).
</p>
