<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Landscape attributes might have a beneficiary effect on rodent host population dynamics. There exists excellent data on the influence of topography and soil properties on dynamics of common voles from almost 40 years collected in eastern Germany. The analyses showed for example that mean elevation, area-related percentage of Chernozem soils, and soil air capacity are variables that have an influence on the common vole outbreak risks at different sites (Blank et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">2011</xref>). The link to forest environments has been discussed in earlier chapters. More precisely, deadwood and denser ground vegetation, which are found both in forest reserves and managed forests to varying degrees, may serve as a microhabitat and deadwood is used by many species as a food resource, breeding habitat, and for shelter. Further, species richness correlates high with deadwood volume (Siitonen, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B150">2001</xref>; Maguire, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B97">2002</xref>). Deadwood thus represents an important feature and may therefore relate to higher bank vole population densities, which may increase the overall hantavirus prevalence in the rodent host, and provoke hantavirus epidemics (Rooney and Hayden, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B132">2002</xref>). Analogous to deadwood, dense ground vegetation may also serve as an ideal habitat for bank voles and has been associated with PUUV foci in other countries (Escutenaire et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">2002</xref>; Tersago et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B155">2008</xref>). In Lower Bavaria, increasing percent coverage of deadwood and dense ground vegetation significantly increases the probability of PUUV prevalence in 
 <italic>M. glareolus</italic> (Thoma, personal communication). In conclusion, despite the important aspects of deadwood for a healthy ecosystem and the tendency to launch such traditional and untouched forests enhanced deadwood may be one factor to increase a risk for PUUV infections.
</p>
