<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To mitigate these concerns, there is a strong public health interest to develop a broadly protective or universal influenza virus vaccine to induce durable and broadly cross-reactive antibody responses, which would confer cross-protection against all influenza viruses and would alleviate potential disease burden once a pandemic influenza virus strain emerges (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Designing immunogens and vaccination strategies that focus the humoral immune response on the highly conserved HA stalk region is regarded as a promising strategy to achieve this goal. Compared to current, licensed seasonal influenza virus vaccines which predominately induce potent strain-specific antibodies against the immunodominant HA head domain (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>–
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), several innovative vaccine candidates were proven to induce protective antibody responses against the immuno-subdominant HA stalk domain (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) and confer heterosubtypic protection in mice (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) and ferrets (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>–
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Toward the goal of a universal influenza virus vaccine, we have developed group 1 hemagglutinin-specific influenza virus vaccines based on chimeric HAs (cHAs) composed of a stalk domain derived from a circulating influenza virus strain and head domains from “exotic” subtypes of influenza viruses that do not circulate in humans. Through sequential immunizations, repeated exposure to these cHAs redirects antibody responses toward the conserved stalk domain (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>–
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Importantly, most adults have pre-existing stalk antibodies from prior influenza virus infection or vaccination so it is expected that our immunization approach will boost anti-stalk antibody responses after one or two vaccinations with cHAs (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Recent reports also indicated that LAIV could successfully prime immune responses against infection by exotic viruses (
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>–
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). Our recent study demonstrated that a cHA-based vaccination regimen with a prime immunization with LAIV followed by booster immunization with Adjuvant System 03 (AS03)-adjuvanted inactivated split influenza virus (LAIV-IIV) vaccine conferred superior protection against 2009 pandemic H1N1 (pH1N1) infection compared to two doses of AS03-adjuvanted split influenza virus (IIV-IIV) vaccine in the preclinical ferret model (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Due to comparable antibody responses between LAIV-IIV and IIV-IIV regimens, we hypothesized that cell-mediated immunity may also contribute to protection. The vaccination regimens that we selected from our previous study, i.e., cH8/1N1 LAIV followed by cH5/1N1 IIV w/or w/o AS03 adjuvant and cH8/1N1 IIV followed by cH5/1N1 IIV w/ AS03 adjuvant, have advanced to a human Phase I trial (
 <italic>ClinicalTrials.gov</italic> # NCT03300050).
</p>
