<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
   <p>Unplanned urbanization: The main factor in dengue resurgence is unplanned urbanization with the overcrowded population, which is characterized by lack of basic infrastructures, substandard housing conditions, deficiencies in water supply, and sewage management.[
    <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] Improper water supply which has resulted from rapid urbanization contributes to the habitat expansion of the vector, Aedes Aegypti as the residents have to reserve water in vessels, which promotes mosquitoes breeding. Evidence from research stated that low-income groups with no air-conditioning and poor street drainage are most likely to be infected.[
    <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] Furthermore, inappropriate disposal of nonbiodegradable materials like plastic containers and old tires are potential breeding sites for mosquitoes due to the ability to serve as water reservoirs. The main effective measure to control vector is source reduction and it is crucial to be able to distinguish and address not only outdoor but also indoor wastes as a study reported that 79% of the total breeding sites was indoor in Singapore.[
    <xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Transportation and migration: Rapid global migration with the aid of modern transport system creates an extensive urban network which increases the potential for vector and virus dissemination to new a territory. Global transmission and spread of virus leads to genetic expansion of virus which makes it more difficult to control the infection spread. Hence, tourism and immigration are risk factors of dengue transmission.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Usage of insecticides: The extensive and indiscriminate use of insecticides worldwide is one of the main challenges in eradication of vector due to global pandemic of insecticide resistance. The ability of larvicides to control vectors also limited as it has low coverage in term of the large pool of breeding sites present in any urban environment. In Asia and America, studies show that after application of the ultralow volume, the population of adult mosquitoes returned to the pretreatment level within 2 weeks and even with multiple applications, the impact resulted was minimal.[
    <xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Public perception: Although community participation in disease control is crucial, but often public perceives that dengue control is solely a responsibility of governmental agencies. Several studies revealed that people from dengue endemic countries understand the disease and its transmission, but the control practices are not equivalent to the knowledge about the disease. There is no sense of urgency within the population even though the incidence of dengue has increased at an alarming rate. Education is important, but solely dependent on the interventions that rely on education strategies shown to have less impact on behavioral and entomologic indices</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Limited infrastructure and resources: National Vector Borne Disease Control Program (NVBDCP) covers malaria, dengue, Chikungunya, and Japanese encephalitis, and also works for the elimination of Kala-azar and Lymphatic Filariasis. The allocation to the program has seen a 3% decline, from INR 482 crore in 2011-12 to INR 463 crore in 2015-16.[
    <xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] Also, the field workers involved are less motivated and poorly supervised as they are under paid and lack communication skills. Most participants involved lose interest in vector control during the low transmission period; thus, resulting in subsequent increase in vector's population. Other factors include limited infrastructure and resources in control and surveillance, limited quality of diagnosis, and clinical care and the need of more advance entomological tools to standardize and classify the vectors.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
