<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study we observed a significant increase in viral titers upon spautin-1 and torin-1 treatment in Aag2 cells; however, we observed no effect in another mosquito cell line, C6/36 cells. While both are mosquito cell lines, there are significant differences that could affect the chemical-arbovirus-cell interface. Aag2 cells are derived from 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> mosquitoes whereas C6/36 cells originate from 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> mosquitoes; however, due to the evolutionary conservation of autophagy it is unlikely that there are significant species-level differences in autophagic activity. A potentially more important factor could be the tissue source of the cells [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007754.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Mosquito cell culture is generally initiated by grinding up larvae (C6/36 cells) or embryos (Aag2 cells) and recovering cells amenable to growth in culture. Consequently, the specific cell type of the cells in culture is unknown. It could be that the differences arise because they are derived from different tissues and therefore respond differently to DENV-2 in the presence of chemicals. In addition, previous reports have demonstrated that Aag2 cells are persistently infected with multiple insect-specific viruses while C6/36 cells are not [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007754.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. It is possible that additional viruses in the system could alter how the cells respond to both chemicals and arboviruses. Finally, the primary antiviral immune response, RNAi, is functionally impaired in C6/36 cells [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007754.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. How this would impact the host cells’ response to chemicals targeting the autophagy pathway during viral infection is unclear; however, previous studies have demonstrated that autophagy can selectively degrade components of the RNAi pathway [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007754.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007754.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. If RNAi is actively targeting viruses during infection, than induction with torin-1 could lead to increased viral replication in Aag2 cells but not C6/36 cells. Conversely, suppression of autophagy with spautin-1 would in theory increase available RNAi machinery thereby enabling a more potent RNAi response and reduction of viral titers; however, this is not what was observed. This may reflect the fact that RNAi genes are not significantly upregulated during arbovirus infection so suppression of autophagy has little effect on the normal levels of RNAi while increased autophagic activity could reduce activity allowing the viruses to replicate to higher titers [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007754.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Further research will be needed to fully elucidate autophagy-RNAi interactions and how they impact arbovirus infection of mosquitoes.
</p>
