<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0016">The serological assays were performed at the Joint Institute of Virology (Shantou University-The University of Hong Kong). The antigens used were reverse genetically reconstructed viruses, including low pathogenic A(H7N9) virus strains A/Anhui/1/2013 (all genes derived from wild-type virus) and A/Hong Kong/125/2017 (YRD lineage, hemagglutinin and neuraminidase genes from wild-type virus, and six internal genes from A/Puerto Rico/8/1934) and highly pathogenic A(H7N9) virus strain A/Guangdong/17SF003/2016 (YRD lineage, with removal of the multiple basic amino acid motif at the hemagglutinin cleavage site). All three viruses are A(H7N9) candidate vaccine viruses proposed by WHO.
 <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref> Samples from patients from the 2013 and 2013–2014 epidemics were tested against A/Anhui/1/2013 virus, which represented A(H7N9) viruses isolated from humans during these epidemics.
 <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>25</sup>
 </xref> A(H7N9) viruses isolated from humans in Jiangxi province in the 2016–2017 epidemic belong to clade C1,
 <xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>26</sup>
 </xref> and are antigenically similar to A/Hong Kong/125/2017 virus. To test the reactivity of human antiserum induced by A/Hong Kong/125/2017 virus to A/Anhui/1/2013 virus and A/Guangdong/17SF003/2016 virus, samples obtained from patients from the 2016–2017 epidemic were tested against the aforementioned three A(H7N9) virus strains. Hemagglutination inhibition (HAI) assay and neutralization (NT) assay were performed according to standard protocols.
 <xref rid="bib0027" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>27</sup>
 </xref> Seropositive threshold was defined as an HAI antibody titer of 40,
 <xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>28</sup>
 </xref> or a neutralizing antibody titer of 20.
 <xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>29</sup>
 </xref> A non-reactive titer was defined as a value of ≤10. See supplementary data for further details.
</p>
