<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig00141">
 <label>Fig. 14.1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>(
   <bold>a</bold>) Structure of a picornavirus particle. The positions of capsid proteins VP1, VP2 and VP3 are shown schematically. VP4 resides on the inner side of the capsid, and is not exposed on the surface. The location of the precursor product for VP1, VP2 and VP3, the protomer, is indicated by the 
   <italic>grey-shaded region</italic>. The so-called canyons, which as moat-like clefts or crevices surround the vertices of the icosahedron, are shown in 
   <italic>red</italic>. (
   <bold>b</bold>) Structure of poliovirus capsid proteins VP1, VP2 and VP3. Also shown is the RNA virus capsid domain (
   <italic>RVC</italic>) of the proteins, which represents the common wedge-shaped folding pattern consisting of eight antiparallel β-sheet structures. Single β-sheets are represented by 
   <italic>arrows</italic> and are indicated by 
   <italic>capital letters</italic> according to their sequential order within the proteins. The α-helical regions are represented by 
   <italic>cylinders</italic>. The structures of VP1, VP2 and VP3 are illustrated as ribbon models. The 
   <italic>numbers</italic> refer to the amino acid positions numbered from the amino terminus of the respective capsid protein. The α-helical structures are represented by the helical folding of the ribbons. The amino- and carboxy-terminal regions are not included in the illustration for better identification of the common structural motif. (
   <bold>c</bold>) The canyon structure of human rhinovirus 14 and its interaction with the cellular receptor intercellular adhesion molecule 1 (ICAM-1). The structures of capsid proteins VP1 (
   <italic>dark red</italic>) and VP2 (
   <italic>light red</italic>) are shown as ribbon models. The antiparallel β-sheets are represented by 
   <italic>arrows</italic> and are indicated by 
   <italic>capital letters</italic>. The crystal structure of the amino-terminal region of CD4 was used as a basis for structure modelling of receptor domain D1 of ICAM-1 (
   <italic>grey</italic>) because of their extensive reciprocal homology (
   <bold>b</bold> From Hellen and Wimmer 
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR00141">1995</xref>; 
   <bold>c</bold> after Olsen et al. 
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR00142">1993</xref>)
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="212870_1_En_14_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e1137" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 <graphic xlink:href="212870_1_En_14_Fig32_HTML" id="d29e1138" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
