<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite the success of genome-wide associations and selection scans to find genomic evidence of pathogen pressures on hosts, simultaneous genomic investigation of the co-evolutionary dynamics between host and pathogen within a single system remain rare (see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1</xref>). Indeed, today, few systems have the genomic resources available to truly interrogate ongoing genomic changes between pathogen and host in parallel. One such example is described in 
 <xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Bartha et al., 2013</xref>, who identified linked sequence variants between humans and HIV through genome-wide-association scans. This study highlighted both host and viral loci that are potentially involved in the co-evolutionary dynamics between host and pathogen. Additionally, emerging studies of experimental evolution in the field or laboratory, or multigenerational sampling of natural populations of hosts and pathogens, have successfully identified novel adaptive alleles in both hosts (
 <xref rid="ref-139" ref-type="bibr">Scanlan et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Cairns et al., 2017</xref>) and pathogens (
 <xref rid="ref-114" ref-type="bibr">Pal et al., 2007</xref>). The reciprocal nature of the interactions between host and pathogens over time naturally lead researchers to ask whether host and pathogen species co-diversify over evolutionary time and to what extent genomics can inform the underlying processes. Indeed, attempts to detect co-speciation among hosts and pathogens date back to the beginning of the 20th century (reviewed in 
 <xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Vienne et al., 2013</xref>). However, inferring co-evolutionary history through comparisons of host and pathogen phylogenies is challenging. For example, such comparisons can mistake a host shift followed by co-diversification as co-speciation (
 <xref rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr">Vienne, Giraud &amp; Shykoff, 2007</xref>). The former mechanism is more consistent with empirical data that suggests that the level of co-evolution necessary to drive co-speciation of host and pathogen is rarely encountered in nature (
 <xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Vienne et al., 2013</xref>). As models of molecular adaptation and gene tree evolution improve, we may be able to identify phylogenetic congruence at the gene-tree level or signatures of selection that co-vary among hosts and parasites with more confidence. In turn, we might be better able to interpret results in the light of co-diversification versus co-speciation of studies, such as by 
 <xref rid="ref-163" ref-type="bibr">Tso et al. (2018)</xref>, where a pathogenic strain of 
 <italic>Candida albicans</italic> evolved into a gut symbiont in mice in just ten weeks. Parallel genomic analyses of the pathogen showed that genes involved with an important virulence factor in 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic>, the hyphal morphogenesis program, had undergone rapid degeneration via both point mutations and deletions.
</p>
