<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Globally over 8000 cases and over 900 deaths due to SARS-CoV were reported, with a case-fatality ratio of approximately 11% (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/csr/sars/en/WHOconsensus.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.who.int/csr/sars/en/WHOconsensus.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 3 February 2020). Between September 2012 and November 2019, there were 2494 laboratory-confirmed cases of MERS, with 858 deaths (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/mers-cov/en/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.who.int/emergencies/mers-cov/en/</ext-link>. Accessed 4 February 2020). The MERS case-fatality rate of 34.4% is about triple that of SARS, and persons in the 50–59 year age group are at highest risk for primary cases. In the short time from its emergence in December 2019 to 15 March 2020, the SARS-CoV-2 has been reported in 134 countries. At the time of writing, the situation was evolving rapidly, with over 142,000 confirmed cases reported globally (over 81,000 in China) and 3194 deaths in China (3.9% case-fatality rate) and over 2100 deaths outside of China. Of countries and continents outside of China, South Korea, Iran, and Europe (particularly Italy) have experienced a high number of COVID-19 cases (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/situation-reports/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/situation-reports/</ext-link>. Accessed 15 March 2020). Mortality rates vary widely, and depend on the age of patients, underlying risk factors, and the denominator definition – hospitalized cases, all symptomatic cases, only moderate to severe cases, etc. In a study of adult patients (mean age 59.7 y; 40% with chronic illnesses) with SARS-CoV-2 pneumonia admitted to the intensive care unit (ICU), 61.5% died within 28 days [
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. In contrast, a study of hospitalized patients (median age 47.5 years) across Beijing showed 18% of cases to be severe and 73% mild, with a fatality rate of 0.9% [
 <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Mortality is highest in older persons, with a median age of 59–75 years [
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Treatment for all severe HCoV infections is supportive although a randomized, double-blinded, control clinical trial has been conducted on a Gilead drug Remdesivir [
 <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] Based on one study focused on children, a total of 28 children aged from 1 month to 17 years have been reported in China. All paediatric cases with laboratory-confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection were mild cases with no deaths reported [
 <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. During the first 2 months of the current outbreak, COVID-19 spread rapidly throughout China and caused varying degrees of illness with a death rate of 1.3%. Patients often presented without fever, and many did not have abnormal radiologic findings [
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].
</p>
