<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0195">A sample-to-answer system that runs an automated sample preparation and real-time RT-PCR in an all-in-one cartridge has been developed and tested for influenza (H1N1), achieving an LOD of 100 copies·mL
 <sup>−1</sup> [
 <xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. The cartridge was a three-dimensional acrylic block with chambers that extended between the top and bottom surfaces and featured millimeter-sized interconnecting channels (
 <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>B). One chamber contained a silica membrane for nucleic acid adsorption, while another was designated for waste storage. All the remaining chambers were preloaded with liquid reagents, and the cartridge was completely sealed to reduce the risk of viral exposure or sample-to-sample cross-contamination. A nasopharyngeal swab sample, diluted in viral transport media, was injected, together with a lysis buffer, into the silica membrane chamber from a syringe equipped with a needle by punching the seal. The sample and reagent liquids were pneumatically manipulated within the cartridge under pressure, and a vacuum was applied from syringe pumps through the seal-piercing connectors. Further fluidic control was provided by built-in surface tension valves. The amplification took place in three separate vials, each containing a frozen PCR master mix, which were inserted into the cartridge prior to the test. All the hardware was built in a desktop system that completed a fully automated test within 2.5 h. The test duration could be further shortened through miniaturization, which could also minimize the large dead volume introduced by the commercial silica membrane, as well as avoid diluting the viral RNA due to a large eluent volume for elution consistency. Moreover, the absence of mixing strategies implemented within the PCR vials led to a slightly lower PCR efficiency. Otherwise, the cartridge appears to be simple and amenable to injection molding for mass dissemination.
</p>
