<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The development of advanced, data-dense assessment techniques, including transcriptomics, proteomics, metabolomics has enhanced the opportunity to identify biosignatures of the progression of 
 <italic>Mtb</italic> infection to active TB disease. Transcriptomes, which require samples of whole blood, combined with computational modelling, currently represent the most widely studied biomarkers in TB. Taken together, small signatures, utilizing three to four transcripts and assessed via decision trees or other computational methods, have resulted in a biosignature which discriminates active TB disease from LTBI with 85–90% sensitivity and specificity 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-99" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>, 
  <xref rid="ref-100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>
 </sup>. Signatures comprising 16 transcripts have been shown to be associated with the future development of active TB in individuals with LTBI 6–12 months prior to a clinical diagnosis 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-101" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>
 </sup>. Further refinement of algorithms led to a predictive signature composed of only two transcript pairs which detect risk of active TB up to one year prior to clinical diagnosis of TB in different regions of the African continent 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>
 </sup>. Metabolomics represents an under-researched area, particularly given that such studies can be run utilizing serum or plasma rather than whole blood, reducing the complexity and cost of sample collection and storage. A prospective multisite study across sub-Saharan Africa analyzed metabolic profiles in serum and plasma from HIV-negative, TB-exposed individuals who either progressed to TB 3–24 months post-exposure (progressors) or remained healthy (controls) 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>
 </sup>. A metabolic biosignature of TB within months of diagnosis, with 69% sensitivity at 75% specificity, was found. These biosignatures are consistent with a state of subclinical disease prior to manifestation of active TB, potentially enabling interventions to prevent disease progression and transmission.
</p>
