<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There is strong evidence that rabies in the vampire bat moves in wave-like patterns through regions. This assertion is based on detailed studies of rabies outbreaks in Argentina [
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-06-01911" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Ahead of the wavefront, there is low seroprevalance and an absence of detectable virus [
 <xref rid="B25-viruses-06-01911" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The wavefront is characterized by detection of virus in vampire bats but with a low seroprevalence. As the wavefront moves on, the presence of virus declines and the remaining bats are predominantly seropositive bats. This type of “migratory epidemic” often follows the course of rivers because of the greater numbers of roosting sites and access to water that is necessary for cattle ranching. Retrospective analysis of the outbreak of rabies in Trinidad that began in 1923 has provided supportive evidence for this [
 <xref rid="B26-viruses-06-01911" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. The epidemic began in cattle in the north east of the island. This is the closest point to Venezuela on the South American mainland and easily crossed by flying animals. The outbreak spread to the south east by 1929. Then, for reasons that are not fully explained, cases in humans began in the same year. Incidence of human rabies cases suggested a northwards spread of the epidemic. Analysis of the case distribution and land use revealed an association with plantations that grew crops such as cocoa, coffee, banana and citrus fruits. Both examples are from regions on the edge of vampire bat distribution. Less structured temporal-special patterns of persistence could also occur and a recent longitudinal serology study suggests that rabies virus, once introduced into a bat population can persist for a number of years through interactions between colonies [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-06-01911" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Virus naïve juvenile bats appear to play a critical role in virus persistence. Vampire bat bites lead to rabies transmission although the observation of seropositive humans in areas of vampire bat activity without vaccination history against rabies virus suggests that biting, in some cases, does expose humans to sufficient virus to stimulate antibody production without progression to disease [
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-06-01911" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].
</p>
