<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our study elucidated the spatio-temporal dynamics of ZIKV in pregnant mice and its subsequent vertical spread to the fetuses. The placenta develops within days of conception and acts as an innate barrier to invading microorganisms 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>. Based on epidemiological data combined with the detection of proteins and nucleic acids, it has been previously suggested that ZIKV can cross the placental barrier, being directly associated with fetal death, microcephaly, and other fetal abnormalities during pregnancy 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>. However, the mechanism for the infection and dissemination of ZIKV at the different stages of gestation remains unknown. In this study, by infecting pregnant AG6 mice with ZIKV-Nluc, the virus was found to primarily target the local site of inoculation and peritoneal cavity, subsequently spreading to other organs. The fetus may be highly sensitive to ZIKV infection during the first trimester of pregnancy 
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>. However, devastating fetal outcomes, such as microcephaly, cerebral atrophy, ventricular enlargement, and cerebral calcifications, have also been found at other various gestational ages 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>. Our results clearly demonstrated that the virus crossed the maternal-fetal barrier and infected newborn pups when the pregnant AG6 mice were infected at E10, corresponding to the period of neurogenesis in mice 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>. Further longitudinal studies are needed in order to define the relationship between the severity of maternal infection and fetal consequences, as well as to determine the mechanism by which ZIKV crosses the placental barrier at the different stages of gestation.
</p>
